<caption>
	<formalpara>
		<title>Figure 1. Schematic Diagram of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Body-Wall Muscle Structure, and fluorescence microcopy of muscle attachments in embryos and adults</title>
		<para>(A) An adult worm with body-wall muscle quadrants visible (orange). (B) A body-wall cross-section with cuticle, hypodermis, and basal lamina peeled away to reveal the basal membrane of two body-wall muscle cells. (C) A longitudinal section through a body-wall muscle cell. Dense bodies and M-lines attach actin thin filaments and myosin thick filaments, respectively, to the basal sarcolemma. (D) Locations of several different muscle attachment proteins. Loss-of-function for proteins shown in red causes the Pat developmental arrest phenotype. (E-J). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink>/ILK and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-3</ulink> integrin colocalize at muscle attachments in embryos and adults. (E) A wild-type, 420 min. embryo. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink>::GFP localizes to body-wall muscle attachments (arrow). The scale bar represents 2 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03BC;</symbol>m. (F) The same embryo as that shown in (E) double stained with monoclonal antibodies MH25, recognizing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-3</ulink> integrin, and MH27, recognizing hypodermal-hypodermal cell junctions (included for developmental staging and orientation purposes). (G) An overlay of (E) and (F). Areas of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink>::GFP and integrin colocalization appear yellow. (H-J) Detail of body-wall muscle from a rescued p<emphasis>at-4(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=st551;class=Variation" role="_blank">st551</ulink>)</emphasis> adult hermaphrodite coexpressing (H) p<emphasis>at-4::yfp</emphasis> and (E) p<emphasis>at-3::cfp</emphasis>. Dense bodies (arrows), M-lines (arrowheads), and muscle-muscle adhesion plaques (brackets in H) are indicated. (J) An overlay of panels (H) and (I). Regions in which <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-3</ulink>::CFP and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink>::YFP colocalize appear white. The scale bar in (H) represents 5 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03BC;</symbol>m. Right-click or control-click for larger image.</para>
	</formalpara>
</caption>