<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'Musclefig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'Musclefig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'Musclefig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'Musclefig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'Musclefig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'Musclefig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'Musclefig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'Musclefig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'Musclefig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'Musclefig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'Musclefig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'Musclefig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig7 SYSTEM 'Musclefig7.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig7legend SYSTEM 'Musclefig7leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig8 SYSTEM 'Musclefig8.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig8legend SYSTEM 'Musclefig8leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY Muscle_Refs SYSTEM 'Musclerefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="Muscle_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Sarcomere assembly in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> muscle<footnote>
                <para>Edited by James M. Kramer and Donald G. Moerman. Last revised May 5, 2005. Published January 16, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Moerman, D. G. and Williams, B. D. Sarcomere assembly in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> muscle (January 16, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.81.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 Donald G. Moerman and Benjamin D. Williams. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
            </footnote>
        </title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 5/5/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
-->
        <author>
            <firstname>Donald G.</firstname>
            <surname>Moerman<remark>
				<footnote>
                        <para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:moerman@zoology.ubc.ca">moerman@zoology.ubc.ca</ulink> or <ulink url="mailto:bdwillms@life.uiuc.edu">bdwillms@life.uiuc.edu</ulink></para>
                    </footnote>
                </remark>
            </surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Department of Zoology, University of British Columbia, Vancouver, B.C., Canada V6T 1Z4</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
        <author>
            <firstname>Benjamin D.</firstname>
            <surname>Williams</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Department of Cell and Structural Biology, University of Illinois, Urbana, IL, 61801 USA</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Sarcomeres within body wall muscle in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">include attachments to the sarcolemma that are remarkably similar in structure to vertebrate adhesion complexes. Crucial early steps in muscle sarcomere assembly, a highly orchestrated affair involving many proteins, involve the assembly of these sarcomere attachments.  The steps involved in initiating the correct placement of these attachments and other sarcomere substructures are poorly understood. Using mutants in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">we are attempting to dissect the various steps in this process. We review what has been discovered to date and present a model of sarcomere assembly that initiates at the plasma membrane and involves proteins within muscle, the hypodermis and within the extracellular matrix.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
<?newpage?>
    <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>The nematode <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> has proven to be a useful
            system to study the development of muscle (<link linkend="bib53">Waterston, 1988</link>; <link linkend="bib38">Moerman and Fire, 1997</link>).
            Here we review sarcomere assembly, focusing specifically on the early events that occur
            at the muscle cell membrane. Myoblasts arise after the end of gastrulation (at 290 min.
            of embryonic development; <link linkend="bib60">Sulston et al., 1983</link>) and are defined by the accumulation of
            structural components such as myosin, actin, vinculin, and integrin (<link linkend="bib15">Epstein et al., 1993</link>; <link linkend="bib29">Hresko et al., 1994</link>). Myoblasts then migrate to their final positions in four
            longitudinal quadrants, each of which is a double row of muscle cells (<link linkend="bib29">Hresko et al.,
            1994</link>; <link linkend="bib49">Schnabel et al., 1997</link>). The myoblasts flatten basally against the hypodermis and
            laterally against the neighboring muscle cell. The result is a continuous muscle-muscle
            junction running down the center of the muscle quadrant that is flanked on either side
            by a muscle-hypodermal junction (<link linkend="bib29">Hresko et al., 1994</link>). In mid embryogenesis (450 min),
            the sarcomere components move to the muscle cell membrane where the muscle-muscle and
            muscle-hypoderm junctions converge at the center of the muscle quadrant, and then
            organize into sarcomeres. At this same time they form attachment structures that provide
            a physical linkage laterally between muscles cells and basally between muscle and
            hypodermis (<link linkend="bib29">Hresko et al., 1994</link>).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Muscle attachments</title>
        <para>There are three related attachment complexes formed, the muscle-muscle adhesion
            plaques, and two related muscle-hypodermal structures termed dense bodies and M-lines.
            Although the attachment plaques also contribute, the dense bodies and M-line are
            primarily responsible for translating the mechanical movement of myofibrillar components
            to motion of the whole animal (<link linkend="bib17">Francis and Waterston, 1985</link>).</para>
        <para>In adult muscle cells both dense bodies and M-lines are finger-like projections that
            extend from the muscle cell membrane into the cytoplasm where they ultimately attach to
            and organize the myofilaments within the contractile units. This arrangement is
            illustrated in <xref linkend="figure1"/>, which shows the overall distribution of
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> body wall muscle and the organization of sarcomeres
            within muscle. Dense bodies and M-lines attach to actin filaments and myosin filaments,
            respectively, and are homologs of the Z-lines and M-lines in vertebrate striated muscle.
            The attachment plaques at muscle-muscle junctions are most similar to dense bodies, and
            anchor the actin filaments of the last half-I-band to the cell membrane (<link linkend="bib17">Francis and
            Waterston, 1985</link>).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig1" align="center" width="7in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Schematic Diagram of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Body-Wall Muscle
                    Structure, and fluorescence microcopy of muscle attachments in embryos and
                    adults Figure 1</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>Here we discuss early events in the assembly of muscle attachments, so it is important
            to recognize that all three types of attachments appear as morphologically similar dense
            plaques when they are first formed in embryos (<link linkend="bib29">Hresko et al., 1994</link>). This is indicated
            for dense bodies and M-lines on the right of panel d in <xref linkend="figure1"/>. It
            is only during larval stages that the dense bodies and M-lines extend deeper into the
            cytoplasm and assume the shape of finger-like projections from the membrane (<link linkend="bib17">Francis and
            Waterston, 1985</link>). Interestingly, at least for the dense body, projection from the
            membrane corresponds with the addition of the membrane-distal component, alpha-actinin
            (<link linkend="bib17">Francis and Waterston, 1985</link>; <link linkend="bib1">Barstead and Waterston, 1991</link>).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Dissection of muscle attachment assembly</title>
        <para>The extracellular matrix (ECM) receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-2</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-3</ulink> integrin (<link linkend="bib20">Gettner et al., 1995</link>; B.
            Williams, unpublished results) is concentrated at the membrane of attachment plaques, as
            well as dense bodies and M-lines, allowing them to transmit mechanical force across the
            muscle cell membrane to the basal lamina. This force can be transmitted, either between
            adjacent muscle cells, or between muscle and hypodermis. Fibrous organelle (FO&apos;s)
            complexes in the hypodermis, which are similar to hemi-desmosomes, then complete the
            mechanical linkage to the cuticular exoskeleton (<link linkend="bib18">Francis and Waterston, 1991</link>).
            Patterning of the muscle to hypodermis linkage may involve the hypodermal transmembrane
            protein myotactin at the hypodermal/muscle interface (<link linkend="bib28">Hresko et al., 1999</link>). A major
            component of the hemidesmosome at hypodermal/muscle and hypodermal/cuticle interfaces is
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-10;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-10</ulink>/ spectroplakin (<link linkend="bib6">Bosher et al., 2003</link>). Also probably present at both sites is the
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-19;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-19</ulink>/Krank protein (<link linkend="bib14">Ding et al., 2003</link>). The linkage from the epidermis to the cuticle
            is through cytoplasmic intermediate filaments (e.g., <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mua-6" role="_blank">mua-6</ulink></emphasis>; <link linkend="bib24">Hapiak
            et al., 2003</link>). Present only at the hypodermal/cuticle interface are the transmembrane
            proteins, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MUA-3;class=protein" role="_blank">MUA-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MUP-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MUP-4</ulink> (<link linkend="bib4">Bercher et al., 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib27">Hong et al., 2001</link>), which mediate the
            final step in the mechanical linkage to the cuticle.</para>
        <para>Just as occurs in vertebrate integrin-mediated attachments between the ECM and the
            actin cytoskeleton, dense bodies contain cytoskeletal adaptor proteins such as vinculin,
            alpha-actinin, talin, PINCH, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MIG-2;class=protein" role="_blank">MIG-2</ulink>, integrin linked kinase (ILK), and actopaxin, which
            complete the linkage between the cytoplasmic domain of integrin and actin filaments (see
                <xref linkend="figure2"/>; <link linkend="bib17">Francis and Waterston, 1985</link>; <link linkend="bib1">Barstead and Waterston,
            1991</link>; <link linkend="bib40">Moulder et al., 1996</link>, <link linkend="bib26">Hobert et al., 1999</link>, <link linkend="bib46">Rogalski et al., 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib36">Mackinnon et al., 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib34">Lin et al., 2003</link>). The M-lines contain many of the same membrane-proximal adaptors,
            but lack vinculin. The membrane-distal region of the M-line lacks the dense body protein
            alpha-actinin, but does include the M-line specific protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-89;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-89</ulink> (<link linkend="bib3">Benian et al., 1996</link>).
            Given their protein composition and functions, dense bodies and M-lines are both
            analogous and homologous to vertebrate integrin mediated adhesion plaques, commonly
            called focal adhesions (FA&apos;s) in tissue culture cells (<xref linkend="figure2"/>; for
            review see <link linkend="bib9">Burridge and Chrzanowska-Wodnicka, 1996</link>; and <link linkend="bib19">Geiger and Bershadsky, 2001</link>). In
            effect, these attachment complexes and associated myofilaments can be thought of as a
            highly ordered set of focal adhesions that offer a unique opportunity for genetic
            analysis. The regulatory steps that coordinate the assembly of adherens junction
            components into functional attachment structures capable of enduring and transmitting
            mechanical stress are largely undefined. Genetic screens for mutants with defects in
            sarcomere assembly have proven a powerful aid in identifying novel focal adhesion
            proteins and for the investigation of their functions <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> (for
            example, see <link linkend="bib57">Williams and Waterston, 1994</link>). Mutants with early, severe defects in
            sarcomere assembly fail to begin normal embryonic movements at mid-embryogenesis, and
            soon after this point the morphogenetic process of elongation stops prematurely at the
            two fold length. This is referred to as the Pat developmental arrest phenotype (<emphasis role="underline">P</emphasis>aralyzed,
            <emphasis role="underline">A</emphasis>rrested elongation at <emphasis role="underline">T</emphasis>wo fold).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig2" width="5.5in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Comparison between vertebrate focal adhesions and <emphasis>C.
                    elegans</emphasis> dense bodies Figure 2</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Initiating a sarcomere leads to distinct assembly dependence pathways for dense
            bodies and M-lines</title>
        <para>Genetic dissection of muscle attachment assembly has allowed us to construct distinct
            "assembly dependence" pathways for dense body and M-lines (see <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> and <xref linkend="figure3"/>). These pathways differ in their membrane-distal components,
            probably reflecting the separate roles of dense bodies and M-lines in anchoring either
            thin or thick filaments to the cell membrane. Within each pathway, location of one
            protein above another with an intervening arrow means that the top protein is recruited
            to attachments independent of the protein below, or any of the other proteins further
            down the pathway. Reciprocally, the recruitment of the protein below is dependent upon
            the protein above. This diagram therefore shows the results of a genetic epistasis
            analysis of "assembly dependence". It is important to note that the arrows indicate
            specific requirements for protein recruitment <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>, rather than
            evidence of direct protein-protein binding in teractions. Proteins within parallel
            branches in the pathway are recruited independent of one another to attachments.
            Conversely, two proteins located at the same level in the pathway
            (i.e., not separated by an arrow) are mutually dependent on each other for recruitment.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig3" width="5in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>"Assembly dependence" pathways for dense bodies and M-lines</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<?newpage?>
 <table id="table1" frame="all">
            <title>Table 1. Muscle cell phenotype in Pat mutants</title>
				<tgroup cols="4">
				<colspec colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="3*"/>
				<colspec colname="c2" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c3" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c4" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Genes</entry>
                        <entry>Cell polarization</entry>
                        <entry>Myosin organization</entry>
                        <entry>Actin organization</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <simplelist>
                                <member><emphasis role="bold">Class I</emphasis></member>
                                <member><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-52" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> (perlecan)</member>
                                <member><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pat-2" role="_blank">pat-2</ulink></emphasis> (alpha-integrin)</member>
                                <member><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pat-3" role="_blank">pat-3</ulink></emphasis> (beta-integrin)</member>
                            </simplelist>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>No</entry>
                        <entry>No</entry>
                        <entry>No</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <simplelist>
                                <member><emphasis role="bold">Class II</emphasis></member>
                                <member><emphasis>pat-34</emphasis> (ILK)</member>
                                <member><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-97" role="_blank">unc-97</ulink></emphasis> (PINCH)</member>
                                <member><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-112" role="_blank">unc-112</ulink> </emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MIG-2;class=protein" role="_blank">MIG-2</ulink>)</member>
                                <member><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pat-6" role="_blank">pat-6</ulink></emphasis> (Actopaxin)</member>
                                <member><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pat-11" role="_blank">pat-11</ulink></emphasis></member>
                            </simplelist>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>No</entry>
                        <entry>No</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <simplelist>
                                <member><emphasis role="bold">Class III</emphasis></member>
                                <member><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=deb-1" role="_blank">deb-1</ulink></emphasis> (vinculin)</member>
                                <member><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pat-9" role="_blank">pat-9</ulink></emphasis></member>
                                <member><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pat-12" role="_blank">pat-12</ulink></emphasis></member>
                            </simplelist>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <simplelist>
                                <member><emphasis role="bold">Class IV</emphasis></member>
                                <member><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lev-11" role="_blank">lev-11</ulink></emphasis> (Tropomyosin)</member>
                                <member><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-19" role="_blank">egl-19</ulink></emphasis> (L-type calcium channel)</member>
                                <member><emphasis>tnc-1</emphasis> (troponin C)</member>
                                <member><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mup-2" role="_blank">mup-2</ulink></emphasis> (troponin T)</member>
                            </simplelist>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <simplelist>
                                <member><emphasis role="bold">Class V</emphasis></member>
                                <member><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=myo-3" role="_blank">myo-3</ulink></emphasis> (myosin heavy chain)</member>
                            </simplelist>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                        <entry>No</entry>
                        <entry>Yes</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
<para>Modified from <link linkend="bib57">Williams and Waterston (1994).</link></para>
        <para>We have also included one "counter current" dashed arrow in each of the pathways.
            These arrows indicate more subtle requirements for proper attachment assembly than gross
            recruitment, as we describe in more detail below. The first protein to consider is
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-52;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink>/perlecan, which is found in the basement membrane between the body wall muscle
            cells and the hypodermis, and is concentrated at muscle cell dense bodies and M-lines
            (<link linkend="bib18">Francis and Waterston, 1991</link>; <link linkend="bib47">Rogalski et al., 1993</link>; <link linkend="bib41">Mullen et al., 1999</link>).
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-52;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink>/perlcan is at the top of each pathway because protein-null mutations in the
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-52" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> gene block all subsequent steps in sarcomere development,
            including the next step, which is the polarization of integrin to the basal membrane and
            its subsequent aggregation, (for each of the four muscle quadrants) into a stripe of
            small, isotropically arranged focal contacts (<xref linkend="figure1"/>E&#x02013;G). At this
            stage, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-52;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink> is normally organized in a corresponding stripe within the adjacent basal
            lamina. (<link linkend="bib47">Rogalski et al., 1993</link>; <link linkend="bib29">Hresko et al., 1994</link>; <link linkend="bib57">Williams and Waterston, 1994</link>; <link linkend="bib41">Mullen et al., 1999</link>). The interaction of integrin and perlecan, either directly or
            indirectly, is a key early event in the assembly of these attachment structures. While
            there is no evidence in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> for a direct interaction of
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-52;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink> and integrin there is evidence for a direct protein-protein interaction between
            integrin and perlecan in vertebrates (<link linkend="bib25">Hayashi et al., 1992</link>; <link linkend="bib12">Chakravarti et al., 1995</link>; <link linkend="bib8">Brown et al., 1997</link>). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-2</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-3</ulink> integrin heterodimer is next in the pathway because
            removal of integrin does not block <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-52;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink>/perlecan deposition in the basal lamina, but
            does block the recruitment of all other attachment proteins and myofilaments to the
            muscle cell membrane (<link linkend="bib47">Rogalski et al., 1993</link>; <link linkend="bib29">Hresko et al., 1994</link>; <link linkend="bib57">Williams and Waterston, 1994</link>).</para>
        <para>During subsequent steps of normal attachment assembly, other components are recruited
            to the focal contacts, and as the nascent complexes mature, they enter into a highly
            ordered array of recognizable dense bodies and M-lines. We have shown that the
            recruitment of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-112;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-112</ulink>/Mig-2 (<link linkend="bib46">Rogalski et al., 2000</link>) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink>/ILK (<link linkend="bib36">Mackinnon et al.,
            2002</link>) are mutually dependent, but that both are required for the recruitment of
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-6</ulink>/actopaxin (<link linkend="bib34">Lin et al., 2003</link>). The three proteins form a complex, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-112;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-112</ulink>/Mig-2 and
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-6</ulink>/actopaxin binding to the amino portion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink>/ILK (<xref linkend="figure4"/>).
            Interestingly, we have found that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-6</ulink> protein is not detectable in
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pat-4" role="_blank">pat-4</ulink></emphasis> mutants, suggesting that the stability of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-6</ulink>/actopaxin may
            be dependent upon its entry into a complex with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink>/ILK (<link linkend="bib34">Lin et al., 2003</link>).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig4" width="3.5in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Interactions between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-112;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-112</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-97;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-97</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-6</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-98;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-98</ulink> as determined
                    by yeast two-hybrid Figure 4 analysis</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DEB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DEB-1</ulink>/vinculin is placed in a parallel branch because its recruitment to attachments
            is independent of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-112;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-112</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-6</ulink>, and reciprocally, the recruitment of
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-112;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-112</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-6</ulink> is not dependent upon <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DEB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DEB-1</ulink>/vinculin (<link linkend="bib46">Rogalski et al., 2000</link>;
            <link linkend="bib36">Mackinnon et al., 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib34">Lin et al., 2003</link>). This feature may reflect vinculin&apos;s involvement
            in the separate "classical" linkage between integrin and the cytoskeleton involving
            talin and <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>-actinin (illustrated in <xref linkend="figure5"/>). Actin filaments are placed at the convergence of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-112;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-112</ulink>,
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-6</ulink> and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DEB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DEB-1</ulink> branches because removal of any of these four proteins blocks
            the normal recruitment of actin filaments to the basal membrane. Similarly, myosin thick
            filaments are at the bottom of the M-line pathway because removal of any of the upstream
            components blocks thick filament recruitment to the cell membrane.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig5" width="3.5in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Two different linkage pathways between integrin and actin filaments Figure5</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>To this point we have indicated the assembly dependencies between proteins as revealed
            by substantial disruptions in protein recruitment to nascent attachments. Our genetic
            analysis has also revealed additional dependencies that are subtler, but nevertheless
            crucial for proper attachment formation. Although the removal of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-112;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-112</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-6</ulink>
            does not affect integrin&apos;s polarization to the basal membrane and entering nascent focal
            contacts, removing any of these members of the PAT-4 complex does disrupt the refinement
            of integrin patterning within the cell membrane. In these mutants integrin never enters
            the recognizable striated arrays that correspond to dense bodies and M-lines (<link linkend="bib46">Rogalski
            et al., 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib36">Mackinnon et al., 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib34">Lin et al., 2003</link>). We indicate this more subtle type
            of assembly dependence with a dashed arrow (<xref linkend="figure3"/>) in both the dense
            body and M-line pathways that extends from the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink> complex back to integrin. The
            relationships indicated by these counter-current arrows are perhaps not surprising. The
            complexity of these muscle attachments seem almost certain to have many such
            interdependencies that will preclude a simple linear pathway of assembly.</para>
        <para>At least three LIM domain proteins are also involved in adhesion complexes in
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-95;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-95</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-97;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-97</ulink>/PINCH and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-98;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-98</ulink> (<link linkend="bib7">Broday et al.,
            2004</link>; <link linkend="bib26">Hobert et al., 1999</link>, Norman et al., unpublished; <link linkend="bib37">Mercer et al., 2003</link>). Of these three genes
            only <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-97" role="_blank">unc-97</ulink></emphasis> has a Pat null phenotype suggesting that like
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-112" role="_blank">unc-112</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pat-4" role="_blank">pat-4</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pat-6" role="_blank">pat-6</ulink></emphasis>,
            it is involved with the very early stages of dense body and M-line organization (<link linkend="bib26">Hobert
            et al., 1999</link>; Norman et al., unpublished). Indeed, in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-97" role="_blank">unc-97</ulink></emphasis>,
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-112" role="_blank">unc-112</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pat-4" role="_blank">pat-4</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pat-6" role="_blank">pat-6</ulink></emphasis>
            mutants, integrin and vinculin are recruited to nascent attachments but myofilaments are
            not recruited, and the stalled complexes never form a striated array. Although
            additional experiments are needed to place <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-97;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-97</ulink> relative to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-112;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-112</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-6</ulink>
            on the assembly dependence pathway, the biochemical data support the notion that these
            proteins work together during attachment assembly. Similar to mammalian PINCH (<link linkend="bib51">Tu et al.,
            1999</link>), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-97;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-97</ulink> binds to the carboxy portion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink>/ILK and is found in dense bodes and
            M-lines (Norman et al., unpublished; <link linkend="bib26">Hobert et al., 1999</link>; <xref linkend="figure4"/>).</para>
        <para>Null alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-95" role="_blank">unc-95</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-98" role="_blank">unc-98</ulink></emphasis> affect
            myofilament organization and both proteins are located in dense bodies and M-lines
            (<link linkend="bib7">Broday et al., 2004</link>; <link linkend="bib37">Mercer et al., 2003</link>). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-95;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-95</ulink> is first detected in dense bodes and is
            only later found in M-lines as well, while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-98;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-98</ulink> is found initially in M-lines and only
            sporadically in dense bodies (there is some disagreement here between GFP fusion and
            antibody results). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-98;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-98</ulink> has been shown to bind to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-97;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-97</ulink>/PINCH, but no binding studies
            have yet been done with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-95;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-95</ulink> and members of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink>/ILK complex. Curiously, vinculin
            levels within the dense body are dependent on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-95;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-95</ulink>; loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-95;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-95</ulink> shows most vinculin
            located within the cytosol, not within the dense body. However the animals are not Pat,
            which suggests that some vinculin is present within the dense body as
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=deb-1" role="_blank">deb-1</ulink>/</emphasis>vinculin null animals are Pat (<link linkend="bib1">Barstead and Waterston, 1991</link>).
            In addition to their role as attachment proteins, all three LIM proteins are found
            within the nucleus throughout muscle development and growth (<xref linkend="figure6"/>).
            Whether any of these proteins shuttle between the nucleus and the plasma membrane as
            demonstrated for zyxin (<link linkend="bib42">Nix et al., 2001</link>) has not been tested. Their localization to both
            the nucleus and the cytoplasm does make them candidate biosensors (<link linkend="bib32">Kadrmas and Beckerle, 2004</link>).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig6" width="3.5in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-97;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-97</ulink>::GFP within muscle body wall muscle Figure 6</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig6legend;</mediaobject>
        <para><xref linkend="figure2"/>, <xref linkend="figure3"/>, and <xref linkend="figure5"/>
            suggest strong parallels between vertebrate and nematode attachment complexes, but there
            are some differences. The binding of the complex of talin, vinculin and alpha-actinin to
            integrin in vertebrates is through the FERM domain of talin (reviewed in <link linkend="bib10">Calderwood,
            2004</link>; <link linkend="bib11">Campbell and Ginsberg, 2004</link>). By analogy we suggest that <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> talin does the same. However, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink>/ILK complex behaves
            differently in vertebrates and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. In vertebrates ILK is
            the linker to integrin (Hannibal et al., 1996), but in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
            and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> it is not (<link linkend="bib36">Mackinnon et al., 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib59">Zervas et al.,
            2001</link>). We suggest that binding of this complex to integrin may be mediated through
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-112;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-112</ulink> since this protein when used as bait in a yeast two-hybrid assay identified
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-3</ulink> integrin as a binding partner (Hiroshi Qadota and DGM, unpublished results). No
            follow-up binding studies have yet been done to confirm these findings but we find it
            intriguing that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-112;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-112</ulink>, similar to talin, has a FERM domain that may bind integrin.</para>
        <para>The assembly pathway described here relies on epistasis analysis, which would not be
            possible without mutants in each of the key molecules involved. The subset of Pat
            mutants described above may offer an entry point into the spatial control of adhesion
            sites. ILK and its binding partners do not appear to interfere with the formation of the
            "classical" talin vinculin adhesion complex, but removal of any member of the ILK
            complex inhibits the formation of a functional sarcomere. Myosin and actin filament
            networks are not assembled into sarcomeres, but even earlier, correct organization of
            integrin within the membrane is perturbed. Perhaps the role of the ILK complex,
            including <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-112;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-112</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-97;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-97</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-6</ulink>, is to give definition to integrin spacing within
            the plane of the muscle plasma membrane. This spatial organization of integrin clusters
            may be achieved by linking the integrins to the underlying cytoskeleton which then
            "tows" the complex into position. Obviously, this is still a working hypothesis and
            needs to be verified through further experiments.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Distinguishing dense bodies from M-lines</title>
        <para>The pathway described above gives an order of events starting at the cell membrane and
            progressing deeper into the cell. At some point along this progression adhesion plaques
            are segregated into two pools, one destined to be dense bodies and the other destined to
            be M-lines. These nascent adhesion plaques have at least nine proteins in common
            including integrin, talin, the ILK complex and the various LIM proteins. Divergence into
            distinct actin and myosin filament anchorage sites occurs after the addition of the
            ILK-binding complex, but presumably before alpha-actinin is added to the dense body or
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-89;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-89</ulink> is added to the M-line. It is noteworthy in this regard that null mutations in
            alpha-actinin or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-89" role="_blank">unc-89</ulink></emphasis> do not lead to a Pat phenotype (R.
            Barstead, personal commun; <link linkend="bib3">Benian et al., 1996</link>). In fact, alpha-actinin is not even
            present at this stage of embryogenesis. Vinculin (possibly along with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-95;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-95</ulink>) is the
            first component that is unique to the dense body over the M-line and is the first
            protein that allows us to distinguish these two adhesion complexes. Is it the addition
            of vinculin that gives an adhesion complex its specific identity as a dense body, and is
            an adhesion complex without vinculin by default an M-line? Consider a model in which
            vinculin is the key factor capable of determining whether a developing complex becomes a
            dense body or an M-line. The key issue would seem to be controlling the binding of
            vinculin to talin, perhaps by regulating the accessibility of binding sites on these two
            molecules (<link linkend="bib31">Izard et al., 2004</link>; <link linkend="bib16">Fillingham et al., 2005</link>). As a mechanism phosphorylation is
            one possibility that comes to mind, but one is then still faced with the problem of how
            such a switch distinguishes the adhesion complex pools. More specifically, how might
            such a switch be controlled spatially to create the characteristic, regular striated
            pattern of dense bodies and M-lines?</para>
        <para>One idea that we explore further below in a speculative model is the possibility that
            the binary switch described above is simply stochastic. In other words, the initial
            isotropic fields of immature attachment complexes are randomly assigned either a dense
            body or M-line identity. How then is the ordered spatial array of dense bodies and
            M-lines established? The pattern could be established through the subsequent "pruning"
            of complexes that do not make productive transmembrane linkages. In our model a
            "productive" linkage is put under significant mechanical tension, which stabilizes it.
            In this view, nascent complexes formed "in the wrong place" fail and are disassembled,
            which frees their components to contribute to the continued growth of the appropriately
            positioned dense bodies and M-lines. The binary switch is not used to produce the
            pattern, but instead, patterning occurs after the switch has determined dense
            body/M-line fate. Below we speculate on mechanisms that might establish the patterned
            array of dense bodies and M-lines.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Spacing of the components</title>
        <para>While it may seem counter-intuitive, adhesion plaques are relatively dynamic
            structures within tissue culture cells since they are not only important for adherence
            but are also necessary for cell motility. During nematode body wall muscle development
            integrin clusters must also have some flexibility. This can be observed during muscle
            cell growth. A newly formed muscle cell is two sarcomeres wide and has filaments 5
                <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03BC;</symbol>m long. In an adult animal this same
            muscle cell will be 10 sarcomeres wide and have individual filaments as long as 10
                <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03BC;</symbol>m (<link linkend="bib55">Waterston and Francis, 1985</link>).
            Muscle cell mass increases greatly from an L1 lava to an adult so that individual dense
            bodies and M lines must also increase in size. A single A-band in an L1 larva has 100
            filaments while an adult A-band may have as many as 600 filaments (<link linkend="bib35">MacKenzie et al.,
            1978</link>). Increased filament length implies increased spacing between integrin clusters,
            and increased filament number implies larger integrin clusters. This latter point is
            important if the dense body is to increase in size, which it does. There is much in the
            literature on integrin clustering and on what some of the control elements may be
            (reviewed in <link linkend="bib21">Giancotti and Ruoslahti, 1999</link>) and there are inroads being made to explain
            mechanosensitivity of integrin sites and the dynamics of integrin turnover during cell
            migration (<link linkend="bib5">Bershadsky et al., 2003</link>; <link linkend="bib56">Wehrle-Haller and Imhof, 2002</link>). However, with the
            notable exception of Ingber&apos;s theories on tensegrity (<link linkend="bib30">Ingber, 1997</link>), there is little
            information available to explain how proper spacing of integrin within the plane of the
            membrane might be achieved.</para>
        <para>Our model for the initial patterning of integrin into a proper array of dense bodies
            and M-lines relies on tissue interaction between muscle and hypodermis, and requires
            tension produced by the developing myofilament lattice. Several lines of evidence
            suggest that cytoskeletal patterning in muscle and hypodermis are tightly coupled during
            sarcomere assembly. The first suggestive evidence comes from the observation that in
            adults the muscle adhesion complexes and fibrous organelles (FO&apos;s) of the hypodermis,
            while not precisely aligned, do exhibit a tantalizing similarity in spacing. Strong
            evidence that muscle may induce the underlying patterning of the hypodermis comes from
            laser ablation experiments. Laser ablation of muscle precursors in the developing embryo
            leave substantial gaps in the normally continuous muscle quadrants. Underneath the
            muscle gaps there is no perlecan in the basement membrane (<link linkend="bib39">Moerman et al., 1996</link>) and FO&apos;s
            fail to form in the underlying hypodermis (<link linkend="bib28">Hresko et al., 1999</link>). One interpretation of
            these observations is that body wall muscle cells provide a signal that positions FO&apos;s
            in the hypodermis, and perhaps also induces FO assembly at appropriate sub cellular
            sites. Genetic analysis demonstrates that the hypodermal transmembrane protein myotactin
            is a key component in this tissue interaction. In myotactin loss-of-function mutants the
            FO&apos;s spread out laterally (and abnormally) into regions of hypodermis that are not in
            contact with body wall muscle (<link linkend="bib28">Hresko et al., 1999</link>). What is particularly fascinating
            about myotactin is how it changes localization during the time of sarcomere assembly
            within body wall muscle. Initially myotactin is arranged in a pattern coinciding with
            the arrays of newly formed dense body and M-lines in the attached muscle cell just
            across the basement membrane, but at later stages of development myotactin moves from
            these nearly longitudinal lines into a series of circumferential lines as it joins the
            hypodermal FO&apos;s (<link linkend="bib28">Hresko et al., 1999</link>). Myotactin may therefore be initially patterned by the
            muscle cell cytoskeleton.</para>
        <para>There is also evidence that the hypodermis may influence muscle development and
            sarcomere assembly. Embryonic elongation is driven by circumferential actin cables
            assembled within the hypodermis (<link linkend="bib45">Priess and Hirsh, 1986</link>). Mutations in the only alpha
            spectrin gene in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spc-1" role="_blank">spc-1</ulink></emphasis>, disrupts
            the regular patterning of these cables, causing the mutant embryos to elongate more
            slowly than normal, and eventually arrest at the two-fold length (<link linkend="bib44">Norman and Moerman,
            2002</link>). Interestingly, the A-bands in the body wall muscles of these arrested
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spc-1" role="_blank">spc-1</ulink></emphasis> embryos are much wider than normal, and are oriented at ~20
            degrees to the longitudinal access instead of the normal ~6 degrees. This wider zone
            within muscle for myofilament organization correlates with wider than normal zones of
            both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-52;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink> depositions in the basement membrane and FO organization in the hypodermis.
            These changes in the muscle cytoskeleton are not simply due to a failure to complete
            elongation as several Pat mutants limited to expression in muscle (e.g.,
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-19" role="_blank">egl-19</ulink></emphasis>) exhibit normal myofilament orientation and A-band width
            (<link linkend="bib44">Norman and Moerman, 2002</link>). These effects on the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spc-1" role="_blank">spc-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant
            muscle cells are also not simply caused by the absence of alpha spectrin in the muscle
            cells. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-70" role="_blank">unc-70</ulink></emphasis> gene encodes beta-spectrin (<link linkend="bib22">Hammerlund et al.,
            2000</link>), and in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-70" role="_blank">unc-70</ulink></emphasis> mutants, alpha-spectrin remains cytoplasmic in
            body wall muscle cells, instead of localizing normally to the muscle cell membrane. The
            mutant <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-70" role="_blank">unc-70</ulink></emphasis> embryos have normal muscle structure, suggesting that
            it is the loss of spectrin activity in the hypodermis that is altering the patterning of
            muscle sarcomeres (<link linkend="bib44">Norman and Moerman, 2002</link>). Although the mechanism responsible for
            this effect remains to be elucidated, these results raise the interesting possibility that the contracting hypodermis affects the amount of muscle cell surface area that
            comes into contact with the hypodermis during the initial assembly of sarcomeres. This
            change in the basal surface of the muscle cell in turn has a direct effect on the
            spatial orientation of the incipient sarcomeres, the width of the basement membrane and,
            by extension, the width of FO&apos;s within the hypodermis.</para>
        <para>As well as hypodermal/muscle contact there is evidence that mechanical tension is
            needed for the proper formation of muscle-hypodermal cytoskeletal linkages. Body wall
            muscle cells never contract forcefully in Pat mutants, and it appears that the resulting
            lack of tension blocks the normal development muscle-hypodermal linkages. The
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=myo-3" role="_blank">myo-3</ulink></emphasis> Pat mutants provide the best example. The
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=myo-3" role="_blank">myo-3</ulink></emphasis> gene encodes myosin A protein, which is the central component
            of body wall muscle thick filaments (<link linkend="bib54">Waterston 1989</link>). Despite the fact that myosin A is
            not a structural component of muscle attachment complexes, linkages to the hypodermis
            are extremely weak in these animals. This is shown by the frequent detachment of their
            dorsal muscle quadrants from the body wall near the bend of the arrested two fold
            embryos. These detachments are a characteristic that is shared by a subset of Pat
            embryos able to weakly contract their body wall muscle cells . In the
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=myo-3" role="_blank">myo-3</ulink></emphasis> mutants, we speculate that these weak movements are powered
            by other myosin isoforms expressed by the muscle cells.</para>
        <para>Our model for how sarcomere spacing may be achieved is as follows. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-52;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink>/perlecan
            begins to accumulate in the extracellular space separating two longitudinal rows of
            muscle cells making up each quadrant (green, <xref linkend="figure7"/>A), and then
            initiates the assembly of muscle attachments in the basal membrane adjacent the
            centerline of the quadrant. The adhesions first appear as two parallel stripes closely
            flanking the quadrant centerline (black dots, <xref linkend="figure7"/>A, also <xref linkend="figure7"/>E&#x02013;G). The newly formed complexes are small and are randomly
            positioned within each of the stripes. Actin filaments organize next through their
            association with the attachment complexes, resulting in two large, longitudinally
            oriented bundles of actin filaments flanking the quadrant centerline (vertical red
            lines; <xref linkend="figure7"/>B; <xref linkend="figure8"/>). Myosin assembles into
            thick filaments and then forms larger aggregates (blue lines; <xref linkend="figure7"/>B-C) that are dispersed throughout the muscle cell cytoplasm (see
            <link linkend="bib15">Epstein et al., 1993</link>). The myosin aggregates interact with the bundled actin filaments,
            and are also recruited to the centerline. Actin and myosin filaments begin to
            interdigitate, and the resulting myofilament lattice begins to contract (<xref linkend="figure7"/>C). During the next phase of muscle development a subset of the
            attachment complexes continue to grow and form longitudinal rows of uniformly spaced
            dense bodies, while others are either disassembled or are repositioned to join the
            successful attachments. For a dense body to persist during this phase it must be under
            significant tension from the myofilament lattice and must also become mechanically
            linked to the actin cables in the adjacent hypodermis (<xref linkend="figure7"/>G). This
            process is illustrated at the bottom of <xref linkend="figure7"/>B-D, which shows the
            loss of small integrin clusters from sites not immediately adjacent to actin cables in the
            underlying hypodermis (black horizontal lines), and the simultaneous enlargement of the
            remaining muscle-muscle attachment complexes (black half-circles; <xref linkend="figure7"/>D). These combined constraints limit the locations where dense bodies
            can mature, and ultimately imposes the longitudinal spacing between these mature
            attachments. The M-line complexes require only linkage to the center of myosin thick
            filaments to persist, which permits the very close spacing that often appears as a
            continuous line (see <xref linkend="figure7"/>H-J). It is important to note that because
            each muscle cell is two sarcomeres "wide", one end of every sarcomere is precisely
            positioned by the intersecting "grid" of nearly longitudinal muscle-muscle junctions and
            the circumferential hypodermal actin cables (<xref linkend="figure7"/>D). Thus, it may
            be this intersection that initially determines the spacing of dense bodies and M-lines.
            In  <xref linkend="figure7"/>G, we diagram a hypothetical "linker" protein that
            binds <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-52;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink>, which in turn may be bound by integrin, thus establishing a mechanical
            linkage that stabilizes the nascent dense body or muscle attachment plaque.</para>
        <para>The idea that actin cytoskeleton in the hypodermis might establish the initial spacing
            of dense bodies is only one of many possible mechanisms that might bring this about. We
            raise this idea because the muscle and hypodermis are clearly interacting in important
            ways at this stage of development, and it is intriguing that the spacing between actin
            cables and newly formed dense bodies is of the same order of magnitude. It should be
            noted, however, that we are not aware of any data demonstrating that the position of
            actin cables and newly forming muscle attachments coincides precisely, as this model
            predicts and is indicated in <xref linkend="figure7"/>.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure7" xreflabel="Figure 7">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig7" align="center" width="5.5in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Model of sarcomere development showing several adjacent cells in one dorsal
                    muscle quadrant at several successive developmental stages Figure 7</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig7legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>Why are the dense body rows pitched ~6 degrees from the longitudinal axis? We propose
            that the angle is imposed by shape of the muscle cells at the time when dense bodies and
            the related adhesion plaques (hemi-dense bodies) become stabilized by linkage to the
            hypodermal cytoskeleton. The muscle cells have assumed a spindle shape by the
            one-and-three-quarter-fold stage, and muscle-muscle junctions between anterior-posterior
            neighbors are approximately 6 degrees from longitudinal. The intersections between these
            junctions and the nearly orthogonal pattern of actin hypodermal actin cables define a
            series of points where attachment plaques will persist and mature (unipolar dense
            bodies). Interestingly, in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spc-1" role="_blank">spc-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants elongation is much
            slower than normal, so dense bodies and attachment plaques are "selected" when the
            muscle cells are in the "wrong" shape. The cells are much wider than they should be for
            their chronological age, and the muscle-muscle junctions between anterior-posterior
            neighbors are closer to 20 than to 6 degrees (<xref linkend="figure7"/>E&#x02013;F). The
            A-bands, like the muscle cells, are too wide, and their angle to the longitudinal axis
            is 20 degrees.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure8" xreflabel="Figure 8">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig8" width="3.3in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>View of a phalloidin stained 1.5 fold wild type embryo figure 8</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig8legend;</mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Is sarcomere assembly in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> a general model of sarcomere assembly?</title>
        <para>A key question is whether these studies on sarcomere assembly in <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> have any relevance for mammalian muscle development. For several
            years those working on myogenesis in vertebrates largely ignored the work on
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> sarcomere assembly. At the same time those working
            on adhesion complexes have used observations in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and
                <emphasis>Drosophila melanogaster</emphasis> to advance our understanding of
            adhesion complexes in mammals (reviewed in <link linkend="bib33">Labouesse and Georges-Labouesse, 2003</link>). Three
            examples serve to illustrate this point. First, recent studies on flies and worms
            demonstrate that ILK is an adaptor molecule and all of its behavior can be explained as
            an adaptor molecule, not as a kinase (<link linkend="bib59">Zervas et al., 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib36">Mackinnon et al., 2002</link>;
            reviewed in <link linkend="bib58">Zervas and Brown, 2002</link>). These observations have been confirmed in mammals
            using an ILK knockout mouse (<link linkend="bib48">Sakai et al., 2003</link>). Second, it was the genetic analysis in
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> that first demonstrated the key roles of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-112;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-112</ulink>,
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-97;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-97</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-4</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAT-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAT-6</ulink> in the assembly of integrin attachment complexes. Third, the
            observation that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-112;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-112</ulink>/Mig-2 is localized to adhesion complexes, and binds ILK and
            PINCH, led <link linkend="bib52">Tu et al. (2003)</link> to recapitulate these results and do 2-hybrid screens for a
            novel Mig-2 binding partner. This led to the isolation of a protein with a proline rich
            amino terminus and three LIM domains, Migfilin, which they demonstrated binds to
            filamin. This is the first example linking filamin regulation of actin filaments to the
            integrin/vinculin pathway for actin filament assembly. Finally, and to come full circle,
            the critical role played by beta 1 integrin in early mouse myogenesis has recently been
            demonstrated. In a mouse mutant lacking beta 1 integrin, recruitment of talin and
            vinculin to costamers is inhibited and proper rcomeres are not formed (<link linkend="bib50">Schwander et al.,
            2003</link>). The phenotype observed is reminiscent of Pat mutants in <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> confirming the phylogenetic conservation of integrin complexes in
            sarcomere assembly.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Summary</title>
        <para>We, and others, have made significant inroads into how a muscle sarcomere is initiated
            and some progress on dissecting the assembly pathway that leads to this complex
            structure. However, there are several outstanding issues that remain including "</para>
        <para>1. How does the cell distinguish adhesion sites destined to be dense bodies from those
            destined to be M-lines?</para>
        <para>2. How is the precise spacing between sarcomere units generated and maintained
            throughout development?</para>
        <para>3. How are actin and myosin microfilaments inserted into the nascent sarcomere, and
            then how is filament length regulated as the animal grows?</para>
        <para>These are difficult questions, ones that we think go to the heart of a very difficult
            problem in cytoarchitecture. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> may offer the best
            opportunity to solve these challenging problems in macromolecular assembly and cellular organization.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Acknowledgements</title>
        <para>We thank Ken Norman for <xref linkend="figure8"/> and Hiroshi Qadota for permission to
            cite his data on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-112;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-112</ulink> binding to integrin. This review benefited greatly from the
            insightful comments of an anonymous reviewer. Research in the laboratory of DGM relevant
            to this review was supported by grants from the Canadian Institute for Health Research,
            the National Science and Engineering Research Council of Canada, the Heart and Stroke
            Foundation of Canada and the Health Research Foundation of British Columbia. Research in
            the laboratory of BDW relevant to this review was supported by grants from the National
            Institutes of Health (R01 HD38646) and the American Heart Association, Midwest Affiliate.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
		<para/>
		&Muscle_Refs; </sect1>
</article>