<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'insulingrowthsignal_fig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'insulingrowthsignal_fig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'insulingrowthsignal_fig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'insulingrowthsignal_fig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'insulingrowthsignal_fig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'insulingrowthsignal_fig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY insulingrowthsignal_ref SYSTEM 'insulingrowthsignal_ref.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="insulingrowthsignal">
<articleinfo>
<title>Insulin/insulin-like growth factor signaling in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis><footnote><para>Edited by Iva Greenwald Last revised July 11, 2013, Published December 26, 2013. This chapter should be cited as: Murphy C.T., Hu P.J. Insulin/insulin-like growth factor signaling in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (December 26, 2013), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.164.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2013 Coleen T. Murphy and Patrick J. Hu. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para></footnote></title>
<author><othername>Coleen T. Murphy<superscript>1&sect;</superscript> and Patrick J. Hu<superscript>2</superscript><remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:ctmurphy@princeton.edu">ctmurphy@princeton.edu</ulink>; <ulink url="mailto:pathu@umich.edu">pathu@umich.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></othername>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>1</superscript>Lewis-Sigler Institute for Integrative Genomics and Department of Molecular Biology, Princeton University, Princeton, NJ 08544 USA</orgname></affiliation>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>2</superscript>Institute of Gerontology and Departments of Internal Medicine and Cell and Developmental Biology, University of Michigan Medical School, Ann Arbor, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MI;class=Cell" role="_blank">MI</ulink> 48109 USA</orgname></affiliation>
</author>
</articleinfo>
<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> insulin/IGF-1 signaling (IIS) pathway connects nutrient levels to metabolism, growth, development, longevity, and behavior. This fundamental pathway is regulated by insulin-like peptide ligands that bind to the insulin/IGF-1 transmembrane receptor (IGFR) ortholog DAF-2. DAF-2/IGFR controls the activity of a conserved phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K)/Akt kinase cascade, culminating in the regulation of a FoxO transcription factor, DAF-16, that governs most of the functions of this pathway. In light of the evolutionary conservation of the IIS pathway, its study in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is likely to shed light on its functions and regulation in higher organisms, including humans. Originally identified based on its role in the regulation of larval development and aging, IIS also controls a host of other biological processes. Here we review what is currently known about the biological functions and the molecular components of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> IIS.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>Insulin and insulin-like growth factor-1 (IGF-1) exert their biological effects by binding to and activating cell surface transmembrane receptors with intrinsic tyrosine kinase activity (<link linkend="bib272">Ullrich et al., 1985</link><!--: PMID2983222-->; <link linkend="bib273">Ullrich et al., 1986</link><!--: PMID2877871-->). Activated insulin and IGF-1 receptors phosphorylate a variety of substrates, among which are the IRS (Insulin Receptor Substrate) family of scaffold proteins (<link linkend="bib287">White, 1998</link><!--: PMID9609109-->). Tyrosine-phosphorylated IRS proteins promote the recruitment and activation of components of downstream cascades such as the phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K)/Akt, Ras/MAPK (mitogen-activated protein kinase), and mTOR pathways (<link linkend="bib257">Taniguchi et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16493415-->). These and other insulin and IGF-1 signaling (IIS) pathway components are widely conserved in metazoans (<link linkend="bib225">Pinero Gonzalez et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID18616978-->). Moreover, the role of the IIS in connecting system-wide functions, such as growth, reproduction, and aging, to nutritional status is both conserved and universally important. The use of the genetically tractable system, <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> to study the function of IIS has been valuable, yielding many important insights into the functions, regulation, and outputs of IIS.</para>
<para>Here we review the discovery of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> IIS pathway and its components (<link linkend="sec2">Section 2</link>), phenotypes of IIS mutants (<link linkend="sec3">Section 3</link>), molecular characterization of IIS pathway components (<link linkend="sec4">Section 4</link>), the FoxO transcription factor DAF-16 (<link linkend="sec5">Section 5</link>), DAF-16/FoxO co-factors and regulators (<link linkend="sec6">Section 6</link>), other transcription factors regulated by IIS (<link linkend="sec7">Section 7</link>), components of IIS in other organisms that are conserved in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="sec8">Section 8</link>), and non-autonomous regulation and integration of insulin signaling (<link linkend="sec9">Section 9</link>). We conclude by exploring some prominent remaining questions in the field (<link linkend="sec10">Section 10</link>).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>The IIS pathway</title>
<sect2 id="sec2-1">
<title>Components of the IIS pathway</title>
<para>The main components of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> IIS pathway (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>) include insulin-like peptides (ILPs), at least one of which can bind to and activate the human insulin receptor (<link linkend="bib108">Hua et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12654724-->). DAF-2/IGFR activation results in recruitment and activation of the phosphoinositide 3-kinase AGE-1/PI3K. In turn, the serine/threonine kinases PDK-1, AKT-1, and AKT-2 are activated, resulting in phosphorylation of the DAF-16/FoxO transcription factor. Phosphorylation of DAF-16/FoxO regulates its interactions with the 14-3-3 proteins PAR-5 and FTT-2, which control DAF-16/FoxO subcellular localization. The DAF-18/PTEN lipid phosphatase and the serine/threonine phosphatase PPTR-1/PP2A counteract AGE-1/PI3K and AKT-1 signaling, respectively. These components will be described in detail below (<link linkend="sec4">Section 4</link>). DAF-16/FoxO interacts with additional factors in the nucleus, including SIR-2.1 and HCF-1 (<link linkend="sec6">Section 6</link>), as well as additional transcription factors, such as HSF-1 and SKN-1 (<link linkend="sec7">Section 7</link>).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-2">
<title>Discovery of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> IIS pathway</title>
<para>The discovery of the IIS pathway in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> emerged from converging lines of investigation in several laboratories studying dauer regulation and the genetic control of longevity.</para>
<para>In genetic screens pioneered by the Riddle lab and subsequently performed in the Thomas and Ruvkun labs, dauer-constitutive (Daf-c) and dauer-defective (Daf-d) mutants were isolated (<link linkend="bib229">Riddle et al., 1981</link><!--: PMID7219552-->; Dauer). Among these were mutants that defined the Daf-c genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-23</ulink></emphasis> and the Daf-d gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/gene/WBGene00000912?query=daf-16#0-9e-3" role="_blank">daf-16.</ulink></emphasis> The dauer-constitutive phenotype caused by mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-23</ulink></emphasis> required the activity of the dauer-defective genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000913;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-18</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib279">Vowels and Thomas, 1992</link><!--: PMID1732156-->; <link linkend="bib82">Gottlieb and Ruvkun, 1994</link><!--: PMID8056303-->; <link linkend="bib207">Ogg and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--: PMID9885576-->; <link linkend="bib81">Gil et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10077613-->; <link linkend="bib180">Mihaylova et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10377431-->; <link linkend="bib233">Rouault et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10209098-->), indicating that DAF-2 and DAF-23 act to prevent dauer arrest in non-dauer-inducing conditions by antagonizing DAF-16 and DAF-18. Genetic analysis indicated that DAF-2 and DAF-23 likely acted in a single pathway to inhibit DAF-16 activity.</para>
<para>In parallel, the labs of Klass and Johnson isolated and characterized the first long-lived <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> mutant, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>. age-1</emphasis> was first identified by Klass in a genetic screen for long-lived animals (<link linkend="bib131">Klass, 1983</link><!--: PMID6632998-->), and subsequent analysis by the Johnson lab suggested that the longevity phenotype in this mutant strain was due to a recessive mutation in a single gene (<link linkend="bib68">Friedman and Johnson, 1988b</link><!--: PMID3385139-->; <link linkend="bib67">Friedman and Johnson, 1988a</link><!--: PMID8608934-->; <link linkend="bib116">Johnson, 1990</link><!--: PMID2392681-->). Later, Kenyon, <emphasis>et al</emphasis>. found that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants also live twice as long as wild-type animals, and that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> is required for the extended longevity of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib124">Kenyon et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID8247153-->). Molecular analysis demonstrated that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-23</ulink></emphasis> are allelic and that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-23</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> encode components of a conserved insulin-like signaling pathway (<link linkend="bib184">Morris et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID8700226-->; <link linkend="bib129">Kimura et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9252323-->; <link linkend="bib155">Lin et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9360933-->; <link linkend="bib206">Ogg et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9353126-->). The extension of life span by mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink></emphasis> also required wild-type <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> function (<link linkend="bib190">Murakami and Johnson, 1996</link><!--: PMID8807294-->), and the discovery that the life span extension caused by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-23</ulink></emphasis> mutations also requires <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000913;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-18</ulink></emphasis> suggested that the DAF-2/AGE-1/DAF-23/DAF-16 pathway functioned at a crossroads between dauer regulation and longevity (<link linkend="bib54">Dorman et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID8601482-->; <link linkend="bib138">Larsen et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID7789761-->). Intriguingly, despite the natural link between dauer longevity (<link linkend="bib130">Klass and Hirsh, 1976</link><!--: PMID1264206-->) and adult longevity, the long lifespan of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants does not require passing through the dauer stage (<link linkend="bib124">Kenyon et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID8247153-->). Taken together, these results defined a genetic pathway in which DAF-2 and DAF-23/AGE-1 control dauer arrest and life span by acting in opposition to DAF-16 and DAF-18.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-3">
<title>Conservation of IIS components</title>
<para>Prior to the availability of genome sequences for multiple organisms, the discovery that the longevity and dauer formation mutants <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-23</ulink></emphasis> encode <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> orthologs of mammalian insulin/IGF-1 receptors (IGFRs) and PI 3-kinase (PI3K), respectively (<link linkend="bib184">Morris et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID8700226-->; <link linkend="bib129">Kimura et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9252323-->), established the evolutionary conservation of IIS in metazoans and provided seminal insights into the role of IIS in controlling dauer arrest and adult life span. Furthermore, this finding suggested that mobilizing the power of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as a experimental system to study IIS could lead to new discoveries that would inform investigations into mammalian IIS &#x2013; a prediction borne out shortly thereafter by the revelation that the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> FoxO transcription factor DAF-16 is a major target of IIS (<link linkend="bib155">Lin et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9360933-->; <link linkend="bib206">Ogg et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9353126-->). Subsequent studies have revealed new regulatory components and mechanisms involved in IIS regulation of a variety of biological processes. Moreover, many of the downstream transcriptional targets that control these processes have been identified.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>IIS pathway loss-of-function phenotypes</title>
<para>IIS mutants exhibit a wide array of phenotypes, including developmental, reproductive, life history, and behavioral changes, with varying penetrance and expressivity. While the vast majority of early studies on IIS in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> focused on its roles in the control of dauer arrest and aging, IIS has since been implicated in a wide variety of biological functions. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants, in addition to their dauer-constitutive and increased adult longevity (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0001171;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Age</ulink>) phenotypes, are more resistant to stress and exhibit increased intrinsic thermotolerance (Itt) (<link linkend="bib157">Lithgow et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID7963273-->). Some alleles exhibit additional defects in development, behavior, fat storage, and reproduction (<link linkend="bib76">Gems et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID9725835-->), as described in greater detail below.</para>
<sect2 id="sec3-1">
<title>IIS regulation of development: dauer, L1 arrest, and germline proliferation</title>
<sect3 id="sec3-1-1">
<title>IIS regulation of dauer arrest</title>
<para>Components of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> IIS first emerged from forward genetic screens designed to identify mutants with abnormal regulation of dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib229">Riddle et al., 1981</link><!--: PMID7219552-->). A detailed description of the role of IIS in dauer regulation is available in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_dauer/dauer.html">Dauer</ulink> chapter of WormBook.</para>
<para>Reduced IIS results in a dauer-constitutive phenotype. Whereas wild-type animals cultured in replete conditions develop into reproductive adults at 25&#x00B0;C and exhibit low levels of dauer arrest at 27&#x00B0;C, mutants with reduced IIS show enhancement of dauer arrest at both temperatures when exposed to the same conditions. Strong <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> loss-of-function, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> null, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000103;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-2</ulink></emphasis> double null mutants all arrest non-conditionally as dauers (<link linkend="bib184"><link linkend="bib184">Morris et al., 1996</link></link><!--: PMID8700226-->; <link linkend="bib129">Kimura et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9252323-->; <link linkend="bib76">Gems et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID9725835-->; <link linkend="bib209">Oh et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID15767565-->; <link linkend="bib3">Alam et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20620993-->), and these dauer-constitutive phenotypes are suppressed by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis>/FoxO null mutations (<link linkend="bib279">Vowels and Thomas, 1992</link><!--: PMID1732156-->; <link linkend="bib82">Gottlieb and Ruvkun, 1994</link><!--: PMID8056303-->; <link linkend="bib138">Larsen et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID7789761-->). Therefore, the conserved PI3K/Akt pathway is the major DAF-2/IGFR output that regulates dauer arrest, and it does so by inhibiting DAF-16/FoxO.</para>
<para>In dauers, the vulval precursor cells (VPCs) that generate the hermaphrodite vulva are reprogrammed to pluripotency, allowing normal vulval development to proceed upon dauer exit. DAF-16/FoxO is specifically required in dauers for VPC reprogramming, acting cell autonomously to prevent VPC specification and maintain pluripotency by blocking inductive (EGFR) and lateral (LIN-12/Notch) signaling (<link linkend="bib120">Karp and Greenwald, 2013</link><!--: PMID23341633-->).</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-1-2">
<title>IIS regulation of L1 arrest</title>
<para>Besides its critical function in dauer regulation, DAF-2/IGFR activity also controls development and starvation-induced non-dauer larval arrest, largely in a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis>-dependent fashion. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants develop at a slower rate than wild-type animals (<link linkend="bib234">Ruaud et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID20944013-->), and overexpression of DAF-16/FoxO slows developmental rates (J. Ashraf and C. T. Murphy, unpublished), suggesting that the larval developmental process is regulated by DAF-16/FoxO and its targets even under normal conditions.</para>
<para>IIS also plays a role in regulating the developmental response to limiting conditions in non-dauer larvae. When <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> eggs hatch, first-stage (L1) larvae undergo developmental arrest if food is absent. This phenomenon is known as &#x201C;L1 arrest.&#x201D; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants have a partially penetrant L1 arrest phenotype even in the presence of food. In the absence of food, L1-arrested <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutant larvae survive starvation more readily than wild-type L1 larvae. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> mutation suppresses both the L1 arrest phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants in the presence of food as well as the prolonged survival of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutant L1 larvae in the absence of food, and DAF-16/FoxO is also required for the survival of L1-arrested wild-type larvae. Therefore, the role of DAF-16/FoxO in promoting survival in starvation-induced L1 arrest is in accord with its role in promoting dauer arrest in response to environmental stressors.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-1-3">
<title>IIS regulation of cell proliferation in arrested states</title>
<para>Developmental arrest in L1 or dauer larvae is accompanied by cessation of developmentally programmed cell divisions. These cell divisions are regulated by IIS through at least two mechanisms. In starvation-induced L1 arrest, cells in the V and M lineages that stop dividing in wild-type larvae continue to divide in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> mutant larvae, indicating that DAF-16/FoxO promotes cell cycle arrest (<link linkend="bib18">Baugh and Sternberg, 2006</link><!--: PMID16631585-->). DAF-16/FoxO may inhibit cell division by upregulating the p27<superscript>kip1</superscript> cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000516;class=Gene" role="_blank">cki-1</ulink>,</emphasis> as induction of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000516;class=Gene" role="_blank">cki-1</ulink></emphasis> transcription in response to starvation is abrogated by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> mutation (<link linkend="bib18">Baugh and Sternberg, 2006</link><!--: PMID16631585-->). DAF-16/FoxO may also contribute to the starvation-induced transcriptional repression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002993;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-4</ulink>,</emphasis> a microRNA induced during the L1 larval stage that orchestrates the temporal program of larval cell divisions in replete conditions by repressing LIN-14 and LIN-28 translation (<link linkend="bib288">Wightman et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID8252622-->; <link linkend="bib185">Moss et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9054503-->; <link linkend="bib18">Baugh and Sternberg, 2006</link><!--: PMID16631585-->). It is likely that DAF-16/FoxO regulates the expression of other genes that in turn regulate cell division, development, and growth (<link linkend="bib18">Baugh and Sternberg, 2006</link><!--: PMID16631585-->).</para>
<para>By contrast, cell cycle arrest of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z2;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z3;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z3</ulink> primordial germ cells in starved L1 larvae is controlled by a distinct mechanism. Whereas most somatic cells that arrest in starved L1 larvae do so prior to replicating their DNA, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z2;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z3;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z3</ulink> arrest in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=G2;class=Cell" role="_blank">G2</ulink> phase of the cell cycle (<link linkend="bib70">Fukuyama et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16631584-->). Mutations that inactivate DAF-18/PTEN cause continued proliferation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z2;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z3;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z3</ulink> in arrested L1 larvae, and arrest was restored in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000913;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-18</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000913;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-18</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> double mutants. Therefore, PI3K/Akt signaling controls starvation-induced <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z2;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z2</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z3;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z3</ulink> arrest. Surprisingly, DAF-16/FoxO was not required for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z2;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z2</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z3;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z3</ulink> arrest under these conditions, indicating that AGE-1/PI3K and AKT-1 control <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z2;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z2</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z3;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z3</ulink> proliferation independently of DAF-16/FoxO (<link linkend="bib70">Fukuyama et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16631584-->). Whether DAF-2/IGFR is the activating input to AGE-1/PI3K in this context is not known.</para>
<para>Analogously, DAF-18/PTEN also controls germline proliferation in dauers. Germline arrest in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/</emphasis>IGFR mutant dauers requires DAF-18/PTEN, as <emphasis>daf-2(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143949;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1370</ulink>); daf-18(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143952;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1375</ulink>)</emphasis> double mutant dauers have three times as many germ cells as <emphasis>daf-2(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143949;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1370</ulink>)</emphasis> dauers (<link linkend="bib198">Narbonne and Roy, 2006</link><!--: PMID16407400-->). This is likely due at least in part to increased activation of the PI3K/Akt pathway, as an <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> gain-of-function mutation also increased germline proliferation in <emphasis>daf-2(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143949;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1370</ulink>)</emphasis> dauers. The role of DAF-16/FoxO in this context is difficult to assess, as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> mutation suppresses <emphasis>daf-2(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143949;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1370</ulink>)</emphasis> dauer arrest. However, analysis of <emphasis>daf-7(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143951;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1372</ulink>)</emphasis> dauers, which are dauer-constitutive due to reduced TGF-&#x03B2;-like signaling (<link linkend="bib228">Ren et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID8910282-->; <link linkend="bib237">Schackwitz et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID8893028-->), revealed that, whereas <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000903;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000913;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-18</ulink></emphasis> double mutant dauers exhibit increased germline proliferation, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> mutation does not influence germline arrest in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000903;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink></emphasis> mutant dauers (<link linkend="bib198">Narbonne and Roy, 2006</link><!--: PMID16407400-->). Taken together, these findings suggest DAF-16/FoxO-independent outputs of PI3K/Akt signaling may play a general role in regulating germline proliferation in arrested larvae.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-1-4">
<title>IIS regulation of germline proliferation in adulthood</title>
<para>In the adult, the only mitotically proliferating cells are in the germline, and IIS plays a critical role in regulating the development and maintenance of the proliferative process. Excessive proliferation can result in germline &#x201C;tumors&#x201D; in mutants in which meiotic germ cells re-enter the mitotic cell cycle and overproliferate (<link linkend="bib66">Francis et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID7713419-->). Such germline &#x201C;tumors&#x201D; are reduced in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants in a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis>-dependent manner, and downstream targets of DAF-16/FoxO influence germline cell proliferation and p53-dependent apoptosis (<link linkend="bib226">Pinkston-Gosse and Kenyon, 2007</link><!--: PMID17934462-->). This effect is likely due to the role of IIS in promoting Notch-independent germline cell proliferation and cell cycle activity during normal development in reproductive larval stages (<link linkend="bib178">Michaelson et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20110332-->).</para>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis>-dependent mitotic proliferation in the germline is regulated by the ILPs INS-3 and INS-33, which are expressed primarily in the nervous system and hypodermis, respectively. These ILPs do not affect dauer formation or intestinal DAF-16/FoxO activity (<link linkend="bib178">Michaelson et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20110332-->), suggesting that the activity of INS-3 and INS-33 is restricted to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis>-mediated regulation of germline proliferation. Notably, INS-33 is also a direct target of LIN-14 (<link linkend="bib101">Hristova et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID16314527-->), the L1 transcriptional repressor that is itself a target of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002993;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-4</ulink></emphasis> microRNA (<link linkend="bib11">Arasu et al., 1991</link><!--: PMID1916265-->; <link linkend="bib143">Lee et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID8252621-->; <link linkend="bib212">Olsen and Ambros, 1999</link><!--: PMID10642801-->), perhaps suggesting the presence of a regulatory loop.</para>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants also maintain their germline cell proliferation and morphology better with age than wild-type animals (<link linkend="bib74">Garigan et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID12136014-->; <link linkend="bib162">Luo et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20946987-->; <link linkend="bib163">Luo and Murphy, 2011</link><!--: PMID21105070-->).</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-2">
<title>IIS regulation of longevity and aging</title>
<para>The isolation and characterization of <emphasis>age-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00087946;class=Variation" role="_blank">hx546</ulink>)</emphasis> as a long-lived mutant (<link linkend="bib131">Klass, 1983</link><!--: PMID6632998-->; <link linkend="bib68">Friedman and Johnson, 1988b</link><!--: PMID3385139-->; <link linkend="bib67">Friedman and Johnson, 1988a</link><!--: PMID8608934-->; <link linkend="bib116">Johnson, 1990</link><!--: PMID2392681-->) and the subsequent demonstration that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants live twice as long as wild-type animals (<link linkend="bib124">Kenyon et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID8247153-->) established the importance of IIS in life span control. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutant longevity phenotype does not require passing through the dauer state, as animals are long-lived when shifted to the restrictive temperature at the L4 larval stage, after both the dauer stage (L3 equivalent) and the dauer decision point late in the L1 larval stage (<link linkend="bib124">Kenyon et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID8247153-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson1157#01--10">Cynthia Kenyon&#x0027;s</ulink> lab also showed that RNAi inactivation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> in early to mid-adulthood could extend life span, while treatment in the L3 larval stage affected progeny number, clearly delineating the temporal regulation of dauer formation, reproduction, and longevity by DAF-2/IGFR (<link linkend="bib51">Dillin et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID12399591-->).</para>
<para>The AGE-1 PI3K downstream of DAF-2/IGFR also regulates longevity. Homozygous <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> mutant progeny of heterozygous mothers live longer than wild-type animals (<link linkend="bib184"><link linkend="bib184">Morris et al., 1996</link></link><!--: PMID8700226-->). Furthermore, when non-maternally rescued homozygotes harboring the strong <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> alleles <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088893;class=Variation" role="_blank">mg44</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088661;class=Variation" role="_blank">m333</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib138">Larsen et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID7789761-->; <link linkend="bib184"><link linkend="bib184">Morris et al., 1996</link></link><!--: PMID8700226-->) are grown at low temperatures, they exhibit severe developmental delays and extreme longevity, living up to ten times longer than wild-type animals (<link linkend="bib15">Ayyadevara et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID17996009-->). As is the case for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants, the longevity phenotypes of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> mutants are largely dependent on <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib124">Kenyon et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID8247153-->; <link linkend="bib138">Larsen et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID7789761-->; <link linkend="bib184"><link linkend="bib184">Morris et al., 1996</link></link><!--: PMID8700226-->; <link linkend="bib190">Murakami and Johnson, 1996</link><!--: PMID8807294-->; <link linkend="bib15">Ayyadevara et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID17996009-->).</para>
<para>IIS regulation of longevity is not restricted to nematodes; similar effects are seen in flies (<link linkend="bib44">Clancy et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11292874-->; <link linkend="bib259">Tatar et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11292875-->) and mice (<link linkend="bib23">Bluher et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12543978-->; <link linkend="bib97">Holzenberger et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12483226-->). The role of IIS in life span control may also extend to humans. Studies in cohorts of Ashkenazi Jewish centenarians have identified non-synonymous polymorphisms in the gene encoding the IGF-I receptor that are associated with longevity (<link linkend="bib249">Suh et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18316725-->). Importantly, cells expressing IGF-1 receptors harboring these polymorphisms exhibit reductions in ligand-dependent Akt phosphorylation, gene regulation, and cell cycle progression compared to cells expressing wild-type IGF-1 receptors, indicating that a reduction in IGF-1 signaling is correlated with longevity in humans (<link linkend="bib260">Tazearslan et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21388493-->). Thus, important downstream functions of IIS may be conserved. Moreover, longevity and phenotypes associated with healthy aging in humans, including cognitive function and metabolic profiles, have been reported to be associated with non-coding genetic variation in FOXO3A (<link linkend="bib289">Willcox et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18765803-->). The impact of these non-coding polymorphisms on FoxO3A function is not known.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-3">
<title>IIS regulation of stress resistance</title>
<para>In addition to their dauer formation and longevity phenotypes, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants retain their mobility and healthy appearance longer than wild-type animals (<link linkend="bib124">Kenyon et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID8247153-->; <link linkend="bib74">Garigan et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID12136014-->; <link linkend="bib94">Herndon et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID12397350-->). They are resistant to a diverse array of stresses, including heat (<link linkend="bib157">Lithgow et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID7963273-->; <link linkend="bib158">Lithgow et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID7638227-->; <link linkend="bib281">Walker et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID9668638-->; <link linkend="bib16">Babar et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10638524-->; <link linkend="bib282">Walker et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11445592-->; <link linkend="bib104">Hsu et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12750521-->), oxidative stress (<link linkend="bib98">Honda and Honda, 1999</link><!--: PMID10428762-->, <link linkend="bib99">2002</link><!--: PMID11976220-->), hypoxia (<link linkend="bib240">Scott et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID12065745-->), osmotic stress (<link linkend="bib134">Lamitina and Strange, 2005</link><!--: PMID15496475-->), heavy metal toxicity (<link linkend="bib17">Barsyte et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11259381-->), ultraviolet radiation (<link linkend="bib190">Murakami and Johnson, 1996</link><!--: PMID8807294-->), and proteotoxicity (<link linkend="bib104">Hsu et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12750521-->; <link linkend="bib183">Morley and Morimoto, 2004</link><!--: PMID14668486-->; <link linkend="bib45">Cohen et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16902091-->; <link linkend="bib125">Keowkase et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20420844-->; <link linkend="bib41">Ching et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21348927-->; <link linkend="bib261">Teixeira-Castro et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21546381-->; <link linkend="bib303">Zhang et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID22232551-->). Most of this stress resistance is mediated by direct DAF-16/FoxO targets (see <link linkend="sec5-4">Section 5.4</link>).</para>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants are also more immune to pathogenic bacterial infections than are wild-type animals (<link linkend="bib75">Garsin et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12817143-->; <link linkend="bib126">Kerry et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID17183709-->), again due to the regulation of DAF-16/FoxO target genes (<link linkend="sec5-4">Section 5.4</link>). Intriguingly, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants also exhibit enhanced RNAi (<link linkend="bib283">Wang and Ruvkun, 2004</link><!--: PMID16117677-->); as the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> RNAi machinery is required for antiviral defense (<link linkend="bib64">Felix et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21283608-->), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants might also be more resistant to viral infection (although this has not yet been shown).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-4">
<title>IIS regulation of fat metabolism</title>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants have increased fat content compared to wild-type animals (<link linkend="bib129">Kimura et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9252323-->; <link linkend="bib206">Ogg et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9353126-->; <link linkend="bib13">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12529643-->; <link linkend="bib223">Perez and Van Gilst, 2008</link><!--: PMID18762027-->; <link linkend="bib203">O&#x0027;Rourke et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19883620-->). Imaging of live animals using coherent anti-Stokes Raman scattering (CARS) indicates that this increase is due at least in part to greater fat accumulation in the hypodermis (<link linkend="bib91">Hellerer et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17804796-->). <emphasis>In vivo</emphasis> labeling of fat stores with <superscript>13</superscript>C-enriched <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> revealed that increased <emphasis>de novo</emphasis> lipogenesis largely accounts for the increased fat phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib223">Perez and Van Gilst, 2008</link><!--: PMID18762027-->). The increased fat storage phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutant animals is dependent on <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib206">Ogg et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9353126-->; <link linkend="bib13">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12529643-->; <link linkend="bib223">Perez and Van Gilst, 2008</link><!--: PMID18762027-->). Several downstream targets of DAF-16/FoxO likely contribute to changes in fat metabolism, including <emphasis>fat-</emphasis> genes that act in fatty acid desaturation and lipolysis, acyl-CoA and alcohol dehydrogenases, glyoxylate cycle regulators, and autophagy regulators (<link linkend="bib174">Melendez et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12958363-->; <link linkend="bib193">Murphy et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12845331-->; <link linkend="bib136">Lapierre et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21906946-->; <link linkend="bib137">Lapierre et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID22186228-->) (see <link linkend="sec5-4">Section 5.4</link> for details). An analysis of several independent long-lived <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants suggests that alterations in lipogenesis may be somewhat uncoupled from longevity (<link linkend="bib223">Perez and Van Gilst, 2008</link>), suggesting that factors other than fat levels may ultimately determine life span.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-5">
<title>IIS regulation of reproductive aging</title>
<para>The extended germline maintenance of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants, coupled with their extension of oocyte quality maintenance (<link linkend="bib162">Luo et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20946987-->), results in the greatly extended reproductive span of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib111">Hughes et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17305431-->; <link linkend="bib164">Luo et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID20041217-->; <link linkend="bib162">Luo et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20946987-->), again highlighting the role of IIS in regulating mitotic cell maintenance as well as post-mitotic survival and stress responses. The cell autonomy of IIS activity in reproductive maintenance differs from that of germline proliferation during development: while DAF-2/IGFR<emphasis>-</emphasis>mediated proliferation requires DAF-16/FoxO activity in the germline (<link linkend="bib178">Michaelson et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20110332-->), maintenance of reproduction with age requires DAF-16/FoxO activity in muscle and intestine (<link linkend="bib162">Luo et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20946987-->), the same tissue that provides the bulk of the longevity-promoting activity of DAF-16/FoxO (<link linkend="bib153">Libina et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID14622602-->). The contribution of muscle DAF-16/FoxO activity to reproductive longevity was a surprise, as this tissue plays no role in somatic longevity (<link linkend="bib153">Libina et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID14622602-->). Interestingly, Michaelson et al. also report a minor contribution from DAF-16/FoxO activity in muscle in regulation of germline proliferation during development (<link linkend="bib178">Michaelson et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20110332-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-6">
<title>IIS and germline/gonad regulation of life span</title>
<para>The state of germline proliferation is, in turn, communicated to the soma to influence organismal longevity. Hsin and Kenyon discovered that ablation of germline precursor cells increases life span, while ablation of the surrounding somatic gonad precursors, which also causes sterility, suppresses this longevity phenotype (<link linkend="bib102">Hsin and Kenyon, 1999</link><!--: PMID10360574-->). These results suggest that two opposing longevity signals are communicated from the germline and somatic gonad (<link linkend="bib102">Hsin and Kenyon, 1999</link><!--: PMID10360574-->; <link linkend="bib297">Yamawaki et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18202391-->; <link linkend="bib298">Yamawaki et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20824162-->). The long life of germline-ablated animals requires <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib102">Hsin and Kenyon, 1999</link><!--: PMID10360574-->) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004013;class=Gene" role="_blank">pha-4</ulink>/FoxA</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib136">Lapierre et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21906946-->), as well as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib102">Hsin and Kenyon, 1999</link><!--: PMID10360574-->) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib83">Goudeau et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21423649-->), which encode conserved nuclear receptors. Germline ablation activates intestinal DAF-16/FoxO by promoting its nuclear translocation, while the somatic gonad signal is dependent on <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib102">Hsin and Kenyon, 1999</link><!--: PMID10360574-->; <link linkend="bib20">Berman and Kenyon, 2006</link><!--: PMID16530050-->). Further communication with DAF-16/FoxO in somatic tissues is mediated by such factors as KRI-1, an ankyrin and FERM-domain protein (<link linkend="bib20">Berman and Kenyon, 2006</link><!--: PMID16530050-->), and TCER-1, a transcription elongation factor (<link linkend="bib80">Ghazi et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19749979-->), both of which are required for germline-mediated longevity. Nuclear localization and activation of DAF-16/FoxO in animals lacking a germline requires the nuclear receptor DAF-12 as well as dafachronic acids (DAs), which are steroid hormone ligands for DAF-12 (<link linkend="bib20">Berman and Kenyon, 2006</link><!--: PMID16530050-->; <link linkend="bib77">Gerisch et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17360327-->) (see <link linkend="sec9-2">Section 9.2</link>).</para>
<para>Intriguingly, although both IIS and the germline control life span by regulating DAF-16/FoxO activity, reducing IIS in animals lacking a germline extends life span substantially (<link linkend="bib10">Arantes-Oliveira et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID14576426-->). Thus, the mechanisms by which IIS and the germline regulate DAF-16/FoxO activity might be distinct to some degree. This is underscored by the observation that KRI-1 and TCER-1 are required for life span extension caused by germline ablation, but are dispensable for longevity in the context of reduced IIS (<link linkend="bib20">Berman and Kenyon, 2006</link>; <link linkend="bib80">Ghazi et al., 2009</link>). Germline proliferation longevity signals regulate the expression of genes both dependent on and independent or upstream of DAF-16/FoxO activity (<link linkend="bib171">McCormick et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID22081913-->). The dafachronic acid pathway makes up one arm of this regulation: in animals lacking a germline, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007536;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-36</ulink></emphasis> expression is induced, generating DA, in turn activating DAF-12. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002285;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-7</ulink></emphasis> family miRNAs <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003312;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-84</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003335;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-241</ulink></emphasis> are induced by DAF-12, and in turn down regulate AKT-1 and LIN-14, resulting in the activation of DAF-16/FoxO (<link linkend="bib244">Shen et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID23239738-->). The miRNA <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003299;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-71</ulink></emphasis>, which is upregulated with age and promotes longevity (<link linkend="bib50">de Lencastre et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID21129974-->), is required for the long lifespan of animals lacking a germline; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003299;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-71</ulink></emphasis> acts in the nervous system to promote longevity, upstream of DAF-16/FoxO activity and independently of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib26">Boulias and Horvitz, 2012</link><!--: PMID22482727-->). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003299;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-71</ulink></emphasis> targets that are important for life span control are not known.</para>
<para>Germline stem cell loss in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> also increases life span through IIS (<link linkend="bib65">Flatt et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18434551-->), suggesting that the germline/gonad communication via IIS to regulate somatic longevity is evolutionarily conserved. Such communication from the soma to the germline, and from the germline to the soma (<link linkend="bib102">Hsin and Kenyon, 1999</link><!--: PMID10360574-->; <link linkend="bib162">Luo et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20946987-->), might enable an organism to tune its reproductive span and life span properly to adapt to changing nutrient availability (<link linkend="bib163">Luo and Murphy, 2011</link><!--: PMID21105070-->). This system-wide signaling integration is discussed in more detail in <link linkend="sec9">Section 9</link>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-7">
<title>IIS and neuronal/behavioral phenotypes</title>
<para>IIS mutants also exhibit reduced rates of neural decline compared to wild-type animals, as indicated by a number of behavioral phenotypes (see <link linkend="bib248">Stein and Murphy 2012</link> for greater detail). They exhibit extended isothermal tracking (<link linkend="bib189">Murakami et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID16306402-->), motor activity (<link linkend="bib56">Duhon and Johnson, 1995</link><!--: PMID7671016-->; <link linkend="bib109">Huang et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15141086-->; <link linkend="bib103">Hsu et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID18255194-->), and positive butanone associative learning with age (<link linkend="bib122">Kauffman et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20502519-->). Touch receptor neurons and VNC cholinergic axons of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants also show delayed progression of age-dependent morphological defects, while such defects are accelerated in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib216">Pan et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21571636-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutant animals also exhibit delayed ectopic neurite branching compared to age-matched wild-type animals, again in a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO-</emphasis>dependent manner (<link linkend="bib258">Tank et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21697377-->). Additionally, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants exhibit improved short- and long-term associative memory early in adulthood compared to wild-type animals (<link linkend="bib122">Kauffman et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20502519-->). While the latter function is due to elevated CREB levels in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib122">Kauffman et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20502519-->), the molecular basis for increased short-term associative memory and extended learning ability in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutant animals is not yet known.</para>
<para>By contrast, other learning behaviors are impaired in IIS mutants. Specifically, salt chemotaxis learning appears to require functional IIS, as calcium signaling in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink> neuron, which senses salt, is altered in IIS mutants (<link linkend="bib267">Tomioka et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16950159-->; <link linkend="bib275">Vellai et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16849598-->; <link linkend="bib154">Lin et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20534848-->; <link linkend="bib205">Oda et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21525368-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutant chemotaxis to salt prior to training (na&#x00EF;ve) is higher than that of wild-type as well (<link linkend="bib267">Tomioka et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16950159-->; <link linkend="bib205">Oda et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21525368-->). Cell-specific rescue experiments suggest that DAF-2/IGFR and AGE-1/PI3K act in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink>, while the ILP INS-1 acts in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006812?query=AIA#01--10" role="_blank">AIA</ulink> interneurons, which have synaptic outputs to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink> (<link linkend="bib267">Tomioka et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16950159-->; <link linkend="bib205">Oda et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21525368-->). IIS mutants are also defective in a paradigm that pairs the positive chemoattractant benzaldehyde with starvation to create a negative association (<link linkend="bib154">Lin et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20534848-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002101;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants, which display normal positive &#x201C;butanone enhancement&#x201D; learning (<link linkend="bib268">Torayama et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17251413-->; <link linkend="bib122">Kauffman et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20502519-->), are defective in benzaldehyde-starvation avoidance learning (<link linkend="bib154">Lin et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20534848-->), an effect that is dependent upon <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000913;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-18</ulink>/PTEN</emphasis> but only partially dependent on <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO.</emphasis> It is possible that insulin signals are required in these negative associative paradigms to properly signal the starved state; if the responses of IIS mutants to starvation and salt stress are muted, then their ability to form associations with these negative states might be hindered (<link linkend="bib248">Stein and Murphy, 2012</link><!--: PMID23226155-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Molecular characterization of IIS pathway components</title>
<sect2 id="sec4-1">
<title>DAF-2, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> insulin/IGF-1 receptor ortholog</title>
<para>Cloning of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> revealed that it encodes a receptor tyrosine kinase that shares greater than 30% amino acid identity with the human insulin, IGF-1, and insulin receptor-related receptors (<link linkend="bib129">Kimura et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9252323-->). Mammalian insulin receptors form &#x03B1;2/&#x03B2;2 heterotetramers that contain extracellular ligand-binding domains in the?&#x03B1;-subunit and transmembrane and intracellular tyrosine kinase domains in the &#x03B2;-subunit. Cysteines in both subunits form disulfide bonds that link each &#x03B1;-subunit to the extracellular domain of a &#x03B2;-subunit as well as to the other &#x03B1;-subunit of the heterotetramer (<link linkend="bib140">Lawrence et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17851071-->). Insulin binding causes a conformational change that induces autophosphorylation, activating intrinsic receptor tyrosine kinase activity (<link linkend="bib161">Luo et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10446056-->; <link linkend="bib127">Kido et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11238471-->).</para>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> encodes the sole <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> insulin receptor family member (<link linkend="bib129">Kimura et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9252323-->). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> locus encodes two alternatively spliced transcripts; nothing is known about the specific functions of these DAF-2/IGFR isoforms. DAF-2/IGFR is highly expressed in the nervous system and the XXX neuroendocrine cells, with weaker expression in hypodermis, intestine, and other tissues (<link linkend="bib112">Hunt-Newbury et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17850180-->; <link linkend="bib128">Kimura et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID22123849-->), and its abundance is modulated by nutritional status (<link linkend="bib128">Kimura et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID22123849-->). Although a family of putative receptors with weak homology to the DAF-2/IGFR extracellular domain has been identified bioinformatically (<link linkend="bib52">Dlakic, 2002</link><!--: PMID11882301-->), their biological significance is not yet known.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-2">
<title>Insulin-like peptides (ILPs)</title>
<para>Although the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome encodes a single insulin/IGF-1-like receptor, it contains a plethora of genes predicted to encode insulin-like peptides (ILPs). Forty members of this gene family have been identified through genetic and bioinformatic studies (<link linkend="bib60">Duret et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID9548970-->; <link linkend="bib123">Kawano et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID10873623-->; <link linkend="bib224">Pierce et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11274053-->; <link linkend="bib151">Li et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12654727-->). Several ILPs have been shown to regulate dauer formation, longevity, and development. A few, such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000920;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-28</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib151">Li et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12654727-->), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002101;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib224">Pierce et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11274053-->), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002089;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-6</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib46">Cornils et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21343369-->; <link linkend="bib38">Chen et al., 2013b</link><!--: PMID23395381-->), and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002090;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-7</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib192">Murphy et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID18025456-->; <link linkend="bib38">Chen et al., 2013b</link><!--: PMID23395381-->), have been studied in some depth, but the biological functions of the vast majority of the ILPs remain unknown at this time. Most ILPs are expressed in neurons (<link linkend="bib224">Pierce et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11274053-->) or subsets of neurons (<link linkend="bib151">Li et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12654727-->; <link linkend="bib192">Murphy et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID18025456-->; <link linkend="bib46">Cornils et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21343369-->; <link linkend="bib38">Chen et al., 2013b</link><!--: PMID23395381-->), but regulation of ILPs outside of neurons has also been observed (<link linkend="bib224">Pierce et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11274053-->; <link linkend="bib192">Murphy et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID18025456-->), particularly in the intestine (<link linkend="bib192">Murphy et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID18025456-->) and hypodermis (<link linkend="bib178">Michaelson et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20110332-->). Overexpression of INS-7 in the intestine shortens lifespan and suppresses expression of the DAF-16/FoxO reporter <emphasis>sod-3p::</emphasis>GFP expression in the head, suggesting that it decreases DAF-16/FoxO activity in other tissues (<link linkend="bib192">Murphy et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID18025456-->).</para>
<para>Although most ILPs lack many of the sequence characteristics of human insulin (<link linkend="bib224">Pierce et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11274053-->), they may still function as receptor ligands. For example, the divergent ILP INS-6, which is predicted to lack a C-peptide, can bind to and activate the human insulin receptor (<link linkend="bib108">Hua et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12654724-->). Another surprising feature of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ILPs is their apparent ability to act either as antagonists (INS-1, INS-18, INS-7) or agonists (INS-7) of DAF-2/IGFR (<link linkend="bib224">Pierce et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11274053-->; <link linkend="bib101">Hristova et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID16314527-->; <link linkend="bib192">Murphy et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID18025456-->; <link linkend="bib46">Cornils et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21343369-->). The mechanistic basis for these differences in function is not yet understood. One hypothetical model is that alternate DAF-2/IGFR-like co-receptors (<link linkend="bib52">Dlakic, 2002</link><!--: PMID11882301-->) might integrate responses to ILPs in a combinatorial fashion, but such a role for these putative co-receptors has not been uncovered. Additionally, whether ILPs that antagonize DAF-2/IGFR signaling do so through direct as opposed to indirect effects on DAF-2/IGFR activity (e.g., by influencing the processing and maturation of other ILPs) is not yet known. Genes encoding agonist/antagonist pairs (e.g., <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002090;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-7</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002101;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-18</ulink></emphasis>), can also be regulated in opposite manners at the expression level (<link linkend="bib193">Murphy et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12845331-->; <link linkend="bib160">Liu et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15380030-->; <link linkend="bib192">Murphy et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID18025456-->; <link linkend="bib242">Shaw et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17900898-->), perhaps to coordinate the downstream IIS response between tissues and pathways (<link linkend="bib192">Murphy et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID18025456-->; <link linkend="bib242">Shaw et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17900898-->). For example, the feed-forward mechanism of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002090;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-7</ulink></emphasis> repression and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002101;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-18</ulink></emphasis> induction in the intestine activates DAF-16/FoxO in other tissues, thus aligning IIS activity in all tissues to coordinate somatic aging, called &#x201C;FoxO-to-FoxO&#x201D; signaling (<link linkend="bib192">Murphy et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID18025456-->). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002090;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-7</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002101;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-18</ulink></emphasis> insulin pair is also regulated by the DAF-7/TGF-&#x03B2; dauer regulatory pathway, linking the two pathways (<link linkend="bib160">Liu et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15380030-->; <link linkend="bib242">Shaw et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17900898-->; <link linkend="bib197">Narasimhan et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21533078-->); this is discussed in greater detail in <link linkend="sec9-3">Section 9.3</link>. In another form of communication called &#x201C;ILP-to-ILP&#x201D; signaling, INS-6 in the ASI neuron represses INS-7 expression in the URX neuron; INS-7 antagonizes DAF-2/IGFR in the RIA neuron, disrupting aversive olfactory learning (<link linkend="bib38">Chen et al., 2013b</link><!--: PMID23395381-->).</para>
<para>While most experiments involving ILPs suggest that they signal through DAF-2/IGFR, there is at least one report of a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis>-independent insulin effect, which is <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002101;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-1</ulink></emphasis> regulation of AWC sensory neuron activity (<link linkend="bib35">Chalasani et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20364145-->). The receptor that mediates INS-1 action in this context is not yet known. The observation that mammalian G-protein-coupled receptors can act as receptors for the relaxin family of insulin-related peptide hormones (<link linkend="bib105">Hsu et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID11809971-->) suggests that non- <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> receptors could mediate some of the biological functions of ILPs.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-3">
<title>Regulation of ILP secretion</title>
<para>Recent studies have identified both positive and negative regulators of ILP secretion. ASNA-1 is a conserved ATPase that positively regulates DAF-2/IGFR signaling by promoting the secretion of the ILP DAF-28 (<link linkend="sec4-2">Section 4.2</link>) and possibly other ILPs (<link linkend="bib119">Kao et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17289575-->).  Human ASNA1 is expressed specifically in the insulin-producing &#x03B2;-cells of pancreatic islets and enhances insulin secretion in &#x03B2;-cell-derived cell lines, suggesting that the role of ASNA-1 in regulating ILP secretion is evolutionarily conserved (<link linkend="bib119">Kao et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17289575-->). DAF-28 secretion also requires intact mitochondrial function, as knockdown of components of the TOMM mitochondrial protein import complex reduces DAF-28 secretion (<link linkend="bib21">Billing et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21264209-->). Whether mitochondria communicate with ASNA-1 to promote DAF-28 secretion is not known.</para>
<para>An analysis of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> orthologs of Bardet-Biedl syndrome (BBS) disease genes has revealed a role for BBS proteins in attenuating ILP secretion. BBS is an autosomal recessive genetic disorder of pleiotropic phenotype caused by mutations in any of fourteen genes encoding proteins that are required for the normal function of cilia (<link linkend="bib302">Zaghloul and Katsanis, 2009</link><!--: PMID19252258-->). Strikingly, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> orthologs of BBS disease genes are expressed specifically in ciliated neurons (<link linkend="bib6">Ansley et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID14520415-->). In contrast to mutations in many cilia genes, which reduce DAF-28 secretion, <emphasis>bbs</emphasis> mutations enhance the secretion of DAF-28 and other neuropeptides (<link linkend="bib141">Lee et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID22180729-->). RNAi of murine BBS genes in the pancreatic &#x03B2;-cell-derived MIN6 cell line induced insulin secretion ~2-fold, suggesting that the role of BBS proteins in limiting ILP secretion is evolutionarily conserved.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-4">
<title>AGE-1/phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K)</title>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink></emphasis> was first identified in a forward genetic screen for long-lived mutants (<link linkend="bib131">Klass, 1983</link><!--: PMID6632998-->; <link linkend="bib68">Friedman and Johnson, 1988b</link><!--: PMID3385139-->; <link linkend="bib67"><link linkend="bib67">Friedman and Johnson, 1988a</link></link><!--: PMID8608934-->; <link linkend="bib116"><link linkend="bib116">Johnson, 1990</link></link><!--: PMID2392681-->). As is the case for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants, the extended longevity of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants requires both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000913;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-18</ulink>,</emphasis> suggesting that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink></emphasis> act in the same pathway to regulate longevity (<link linkend="bib54">Dorman et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID8601482-->). The <emphasis>age-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00087946;class=Variation" role="_blank">hx546</ulink>)</emphasis> mutant that emerged from the screen for long-lived mutants also forms dauers at high temperatures (27&#x00B0;C) (<link linkend="bib168">Malone et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID8807293-->; <link linkend="bib184"><link linkend="bib184">Morris et al., 1996</link></link><!--: PMID8700226-->). Both the extended life span and dauer-constitutive phenotypes of <emphasis>age-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00087946;class=Variation" role="_blank">hx546</ulink>)</emphasis> were mapped to the same genomic region as the dauer-constitutive phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-23</ulink></emphasis> mutants, and <emphasis>age-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00087946;class=Variation" role="_blank">hx546</ulink>)</emphasis> does not complement <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-23</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib168">Malone et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID8807293-->; <link linkend="bib184"><link linkend="bib184">Morris et al., 1996</link></link><!--: PMID8700226-->), suggesting that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-23</ulink></emphasis> are allelic. Cloning of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink></emphasis> confirmed this notion, as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-23</ulink></emphasis> mutants contain molecular lesions in an open reading frame that encodes the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog of the p110 catalytic subunit of Class IA phosphoinositide 3-kinases (PI3K) (<link linkend="bib184"><link linkend="bib184">Morris et al., 1996</link></link><!--: PMID8700226-->; <link linkend="bib15">Ayyadevara et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID17996009-->). As null alleles of both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> undergo non-conditional dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib184"><link linkend="bib184">Morris et al., 1996</link></link><!--: PMID8700226-->; <link linkend="bib221">Patel et al., 2008b</link><!--: PMID18245374-->), AGE-1/PI3K is likely to be the major signaling output of activated DAF-2/IGFR in dauer regulation.</para>
<para>The PI3K superfamily of enzymes phosphorylates phosphoinositides at the 3&#x2019; position of the inositol ring. Activation of Class I PI3Ks by insulin and IGFs increases 3-phosphoinositide (PIP<subscript>3</subscript>) concentrations at the plasma membrane, thus promoting the recruitment and activation of PIP<subscript>3</subscript>-dependent signaling complexes (<link linkend="bib34">Cantrell, 2001</link><!--: PMID11282020-->). Mammalian Class IA PI3Ks are heterodimers consisting of a p110 catalytic subunit and an adaptor subunit that contains two SH2 domains. Upon binding of ligand to insulin and IGF-1 receptors, IRS (<emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>i</emphasis></emphasis>nsulin <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>r</emphasis></emphasis>eceptor <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>s</emphasis></emphasis>ubstrate) scaffold proteins are phosphorylated on multiple tyrosine residues, creating binding sites for the SH2 domains of the PI3K adaptor subunit that promote the recruitment of PI3K to the plasma membrane (<link linkend="bib257">Taniguchi et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16493415-->).</para>
<para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome encodes a single PI3K adaptor subunit (AAP-1; <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>A</emphasis></emphasis>GE-1 <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>a</emphasis></emphasis>daptor <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>p</emphasis></emphasis>rotein) and a putative IRS homolog (IST-1; <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>i</emphasis></emphasis>nsulin receptor <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>s</emphasis></emphasis>ubs<emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>t</emphasis></emphasis>rate homolog) (<link linkend="bib293">Wolkow et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID12393910-->). An <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000001;class=Gene" role="_blank">aap-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant, <emphasis>aap-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088761;class=Variation" role="_blank">m889</ulink>)</emphasis>, was isolated in a genetic screen for thermotolerant mutants (<link linkend="bib188">Munoz and Riddle, 2003</link><!--: PMID12586705-->). Similar to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> mutants, <emphasis>aap-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088761;class=Variation" role="_blank">m889</ulink>)</emphasis> mutants live long in a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO-</emphasis>dependent manner (<link linkend="bib188">Munoz and Riddle, 2003</link><!--: PMID12586705-->). Furthermore, AAP-1 protein synthesized in <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> can bind to an N-terminal fragment of AGE-1/PI3K (<link linkend="bib293">Wolkow et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID12393910-->). However, in contrast to the non-conditional dauer arrest phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> null mutants, <emphasis>aap-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088761;class=Variation" role="_blank">m889</ulink>)</emphasis> animals develop reproductively when cultured at 25&#x00B0;C and only undergo dauer arrest at 27&#x00B0;C (<link linkend="bib188">Munoz and Riddle, 2003</link><!--: PMID12586705-->). This may be a consequence of the fact that the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088761;class=Variation" role="_blank">m889</ulink></emphasis> allele is a nonsense mutation that is predicted to create a truncated AAP-1 protein that still contains the N-terminal SH2 domain as well as the inter-SH2 domain that mediates the association of mammalian p85 with p110 (<link linkend="bib188">Munoz and Riddle, 2003</link><!--: PMID12586705-->). Therefore, the mutant AAP-1 protein synthesized in <emphasis>aap-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088761;class=Variation" role="_blank">m889</ulink>)</emphasis> may still be able to interact with AGE-1/PI3K. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000001;class=Gene" role="_blank">aap-1</ulink></emphasis> null phenotype has not been described. Notably, no <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000001;class=Gene" role="_blank">aap-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant alleles have emerged from genetic screens for dauer-constitutive mutants in which multiple alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> were isolated. Thus, the possibility exists that DAF-2/IGFR may be able to activate AGE-1/PI3K in the absence of AAP-1.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-5">
<title>IRS (<emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>i</emphasis></emphasis>nsulin <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>r</emphasis></emphasis>eceptor <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>s</emphasis></emphasis>ubstrate) proteins</title>
<para>IST-1 was identified based on comparative sequence analysis with mammalian IRS proteins. IST-1 has limited amino acid similarity to mammalian IRS proteins; the greatest sequence identity lies in the pleckstrin homology and phosphotyrosine binding motifs (<link linkend="bib293">Wolkow et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID12393910-->). Unlike mammalian IRS proteins, which contain several YxxM motifs that can bind to Class IA PI3K adaptor subunits when phosphorylated (<link linkend="bib250">Sun et al., 1991</link><!--: PMID1648180-->; <link linkend="bib251">Sun et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID7675087-->), IST-1 contains a single YxxM motif. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002163;class=Gene" role="_blank">ist-1</ulink></emphasis> RNAi does not induce dauer arrest in wild-type animals at any temperature but enhances dauer arrest to a comparable extent in animals harboring either partial loss-of-function or null <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib293">Wolkow et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID12393910-->). Although the phenotype of an <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002163;class=Gene" role="_blank">ist-1</ulink></emphasis> null mutant has not been reported, these results suggest that, in contrast to <emphasis>Drosophila chico</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib25">Bohni et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10399915-->) and mammalian IRS proteins (<link linkend="bib241">Shaw, 2011</link><!--: PMID21597332-->), IST-1 may function primarily to couple DAF-2/IGFR to signaling outputs that act in parallel to AGE-1/PI3K. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002163;class=Gene" role="_blank">ist-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants have also not emerged from dauer-constitutive screens, suggesting that IST-1 may be dispensable for DAF-2/IGFR-dependent activation of AGE-1/PI3K.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-6">
<title>DAF-18/PTEN</title>
<para>The PTEN (<emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>p</emphasis></emphasis>hosphatase and <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>ten</emphasis></emphasis>sin homolog) phosphatase has been well studied in mammalian systems because of its important role as a tumor suppressor. The dauer-defective mutant <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000913;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-18</ulink></emphasis> was identified as the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> PTEN ortholog (<link linkend="bib207">Ogg and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--: PMID9885576-->; <link linkend="bib81">Gil et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10077613-->; <link linkend="bib180">Mihaylova et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10377431-->; <link linkend="bib233">Rouault et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10209098-->)<emphasis>.</emphasis> PTEN is a lipid phosphatase that antagonizes PI3Ks by dephosphorylating PIP<subscript>3</subscript> at the 3&#x2019; position of the inositol ring (<link linkend="bib96">Hollander et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21430697-->). DAF-18/PTEN acts in opposition to AGE-1/PI3K and DAF-2/IGFR, as loss-of-function <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000913;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-18</ulink>/PTEN</emphasis> mutations fully suppress the dauer-constitutive and life span extension phenotypes <emphasis>of</emphasis> <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> loss-of-function mutations (<link linkend="bib82">Gottlieb and Ruvkun, 1994</link><!--: PMID8056303-->; <link linkend="bib54">Dorman et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID8601482-->; <link linkend="bib138">Larsen et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID7789761-->; <link linkend="bib207">Ogg and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--: PMID9885576-->; <link linkend="bib81">Gil et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10077613-->; <link linkend="bib180">Mihaylova et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10377431-->). Although a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000913;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-18</ulink>/PTEN</emphasis> null mutation suppresses <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutant phenotypes to comparable extents (<link linkend="bib81">Gil et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10077613-->; <link linkend="bib180">Mihaylova et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10377431-->), the <emphasis>daf-18(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143952;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1375</ulink>)</emphasis> mutation, which is a 30-base-pair insertion in the fourth exon that introduces a premature termination codon downstream of the phosphatase domain (<link linkend="bib207">Ogg and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--: PMID9885576-->; <link linkend="bib81">Gil et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10077613-->; <link linkend="bib180">Mihaylova et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10377431-->; <link linkend="bib233">Rouault et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10209098-->), fully suppresses <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> null phenotypes but does not suppress the dauer-constitutive phenotype of <emphasis>daf-2(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143949;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1370</ulink>)</emphasis> mutants. This is consistent with the differential suppression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutant phenotypes by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003965;class=Gene" role="_blank">pdk-1</ulink></emphasis> gain-of-function mutations (see <link linkend="sec3-7">Sections 3.7</link> and 3.8) (<link linkend="bib219">Paradis and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--: PMID9716402-->; <link linkend="bib218">Paradis et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10364160-->) and supports the existence of DAF-2/IGFR outputs that transduce signals in parallel to AGE-1/PI3K.</para>
<para>Most PTEN missense mutations found in human tumors reduce its lipid phosphatase activity (<link linkend="bib232">Rodriguez-Escudero et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21828076-->); however, PTEN can also dephosphorylate proteins (<link linkend="bib55">Downes et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17233581-->). Although it is not known whether DAF-18/PTEN has protein phosphatase activity, a DAF-18/PTEN missense mutant corresponding to the mammalian PTEN G129E mutant that lacks lipid phosphatase activity but retains protein phosphatase activity (<link linkend="bib71">Furnari et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID9823298-->; <link linkend="bib194">Myers et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID9811831-->) does not rescue the dauer-defective and life span shortening phenotypes of a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000913;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-18</ulink></emphasis> null mutant, suggesting that DAF-18/PTEN controls dauer arrest and life span by dephosphorylating PIP<subscript>3</subscript> (<link linkend="bib246">Solari et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID15637588-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-7">
<title>AKT-1 and AKT-2</title>
<para>In mammals, Akt/Protein Kinase B (PKB) family serine/threonine kinases mediate many of the cellular responses to insulin and IGF-1. Ligand-dependent activation of Class I PI3Ks increases PIP<subscript>3</subscript> levels, resulting in the recruitment of Akt/PKB to the plasma membrane via binding of its N-terminal pleckstrin homology (PH) domain to PIP<subscript>3</subscript>.<subscript></subscript> Akt/PKB is subsequently activated by phosphorylation at two conserved residues (T308 and S473 in human AKT1) (<link linkend="bib257">Taniguchi et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16493415-->). Mammalian Akt/PKB directly phosphorylates several substrates (<link linkend="bib169">Manning and Cantley, 2007</link><!--: PMID17604717-->).</para>
<para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome encodes two Akt/PKB family members, AKT-1 and AKT-2. A gain-of-function allele of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088913;class=Variation" role="_blank">mg144</ulink>,</emphasis> emerged from a screen for suppressors of the non-conditional dauer-constitutive phenotype of an <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> null mutant (<link linkend="bib219">Paradis and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--: PMID9716402-->), and loss-of-function <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> alleles have been isolated in genetic screens for dauer-constitutive mutants (<link linkend="bib2">Ailion and Thomas, 2003</link><!--: PMID14504222-->). As is the case for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib82">Gottlieb and Ruvkun, 1994</link><!--: PMID8056303-->), the dauer-constitutive phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> loss-of-function mutants requires <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> activity (<link linkend="bib2">Ailion and Thomas, 2003</link><!--: PMID14504222-->; <link linkend="bib107">Hu et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16839187-->). Unlike <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> null mutants, which undergo dauer arrest nonconditionally, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> null mutants have a weaker dauer-constitutive phenotype, developing reproductively when cultured at 25&#x00B0;C and only undergoing dauer arrest at high penetrance when grown at 27&#x00B0;C (<link linkend="bib2">Ailion and Thomas, 2003</link><!--: PMID14504222-->; <link linkend="bib107">Hu et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16839187-->). Accordingly, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> null mutants also live longer than wild-type animals, though not to the same degree as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib3">Alam et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20620993-->). Although <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000103;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants have not yet emerged from forward genetic screens, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000103;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-2</ulink></emphasis> null mutants do have extended life span compared to wild-type animals (<link linkend="bib236">Saul et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19501612-->; <link linkend="bib3">Alam et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20620993-->; <link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->), and inactivation of both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000103;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-2</ulink></emphasis> results in nonconditional dauer arrest and a marked extension of life span that is reminiscent of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> null phenotype (<link linkend="bib209">Oh et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID15767565-->; <link linkend="bib15">Ayyadevara et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID17996009-->; <link linkend="bib3">Alam et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20620993-->). Therefore, AKT-1 and AKT-2 are likely the major outputs of AGE-1/PI3K.</para>
<para>Mammalian Akt/PKB isoforms have several substrates, including FoxO family transcription factors (<link linkend="bib169">Manning and Cantley, 2007</link><!--: PMID17604717-->). By contrast, the observation that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> null mutations fully suppress the dauer-constitutive and life span extension phenotypes of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> null mutants (<link linkend="bib82">Gottlieb and Ruvkun, 1994</link><!--: PMID8056303-->; <link linkend="bib54">Dorman et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID8601482-->; <link linkend="bib138">Larsen et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID7789761-->) indicates that DAF-16/FoxO is the primary target of AGE-1/PI3K, and by extension, AKT-1/2. Akt/PKB family members phosphorylate substrates at serines or threonines within motifs containing arginine residues five and three amino acids N-terminal to the phosphoacceptor residue (RxRxxS/T) (<link linkend="bib169">Manning and Cantley, 2007</link><!--: PMID17604717-->). Akt/PKB inhibits FoxO by inducing FoxO phosphorylation at three sites that lie within conserved RxRxxS/T motifs, thus promoting the sequestration of FoxO in the cytoplasm via binding to 14-3-3 proteins (<link linkend="bib30">Brunet et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10102273-->). The FoxO RxRxxS/T motifs are conserved in DAF-16, and mutation of these phosphoacceptor sites to alanine in both mammalian FoxO and DAF-16 promotes nuclear translocation in the presence of intact IIS (<link linkend="bib30">Brunet et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10102273-->; <link linkend="bib156">Lin et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11381260-->). Accordingly, a functional DAF-16::GFP fusion protein translocates to the nucleus in animals with reduced DAF-2/IGFR or AKT-1 activity (<link linkend="bib92">Henderson and Johnson, 2001</link><!--: PMID11747825-->; <link linkend="bib144">Lee et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11747821-->; <link linkend="bib156">Lin et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11381260-->; <link linkend="bib306">Zhang et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18241854-->; <link linkend="bib214">Padmanabhan et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19249087-->). Thus, the molecular basis for FoxO transcription factor regulation by Akt/PKB is evolutionarily conserved.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-8">
<title>PDK-1</title>
<para>Full activation of Akt/PKB requires phosphorylation of both T308 in the activation segment and S473 in the C-terminal hydrophobic motif (<link linkend="bib48">Datta et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10579998-->). Both of these sites are conserved in AKT-1 and AKT-2 (T350/S517 in AKT-1A and T337/S505 in AKT-2A, respectively) (<link linkend="bib219">Paradis and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--: PMID9716402-->), suggesting that the underlying mechanisms governing Akt/PKB activation are conserved. In both mammalian cells and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, T308 is phosphorylated by the <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>p</emphasis></emphasis>hosphoinositide-<emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>d</emphasis></emphasis>ependent <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>k</emphasis></emphasis>inase Pdk, a serine/threonine kinase that, similar to Akt/PKB, is recruited to the plasma membrane through binding of its PH domain to PIP<subscript>3</subscript> (<link linkend="bib266">Toker and Newton, 2000</link><!--: PMID11057891-->). A gain-of-function mutation in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Pdk ortholog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003965;class=Gene" role="_blank">pdk-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088912;class=Variation" role="_blank">mg142</ulink>,</emphasis> was isolated in the same screen in which the <emphasis>akt-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088913;class=Variation" role="_blank">mg144</ulink>)</emphasis> gain-of-function mutant was isolated (<link linkend="bib218">Paradis et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10364160-->)<emphasis>. pdk-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088912;class=Variation" role="_blank">mg142</ulink>)</emphasis> strongly suppresses the dauer-constitutive phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> null mutants but does not suppress dauer arrest in animals with reduced <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000103;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-2</ulink></emphasis> activity, suggesting that PDK-1 acts downstream of AGE-1/PI3K and upstream of AKT-1 and AKT-2 (<link linkend="bib218">Paradis et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10364160-->). The suppression of <emphasis>age-1(null)</emphasis> dauer arrest by <emphasis>pdk-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088912;class=Variation" role="_blank">mg142</ulink>)</emphasis> is abrogated by RNAi of either <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> or (to a lesser extent) <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000103;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-2</ulink></emphasis>, indicating that AKT-1 and AKT-2 are the major targets of PDK-1 in dauer regulation (<link linkend="bib218">Paradis et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10364160-->). The <emphasis>pdk-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00242604;class=Variation" role="_blank">sa680</ulink>)</emphasis> loss-of-function mutant has a dauer-constitutive phenotype at 25&#x00B0;C and extended longevity; both of these phenotypes require DAF-16/FoxO activity (<link linkend="bib218">Paradis et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10364160-->). The <emphasis>pdk-1(null)</emphasis> phenotype has not been reported; therefore, it is not known whether AGE-1/PI3K has other outputs in addition to PDK-1 that contribute to the activation of AKT-1 and AKT-2.</para>
<para>Multiple mammalian kinases, including Rictor/mTORC2 and DNA-dependent protein kinase, have recently been shown to activate Akt/PKB through phosphorylation of its C-terminal hydrophobic motif site (<link linkend="bib27">Bozulic and Hemmings, 2009</link><!--: PMID19303758-->). The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> kinase(s) that phosphorylates this site is not known. To date, no candidates have emerged from genetic screens. Loss-of-function mutations in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Rictor ortholog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009245;class=Gene" role="_blank">rict-1</ulink></emphasis>, identified in screens for mutants with reduced fat content, shorten life span and do not promote dauer arrest under standard conditions (<link linkend="bib117">Jones et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19260765-->; <link linkend="bib247">Soukas et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19240135-->), suggesting that, in contrast to mammalian Rictor/mTORC2 (<link linkend="bib235">Sarbassov et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID15718470-->), RICT-1 does not contribute to Akt/PKB activation in dauer regulation or life span control.</para>
<para>Notably, whereas both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003965;class=Gene" role="_blank">pdk-1</ulink></emphasis> gain-of-function mutations fully suppress the dauer-constitutive phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K</emphasis> null mutants, they only partially suppress the dauer-constitutive phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib219">Paradis and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--: PMID9716402-->; <link linkend="bib218">Paradis et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10364160-->). Since DAF-2/IGFR activates AGE-1/PI3K, these results suggest that DAF-2/IGFR activates additional pathways that act in parallel to AGE-1/PI3K to regulate dauer arrest.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-9">
<title>PPTR-1</title>
<para>PPTR-1 is the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> protein phosphatase 2A (PP2A) subunit that regulates AKT-1 dephosphorylation (<link linkend="bib214">Padmanabhan et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19249087-->). PPTR-1 binds to AKT-1 and reduces AKT-1 phosphorylation at the site corresponding to T308 in human Akt1 <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012348;class=Gene" role="_blank">pptr-1</ulink></emphasis> knockdown suppresses dauer arrest, reduces thermotolerance, and shortens the life span of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants, suggesting that PPTR-1 antagonizes IIS. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012348;class=Gene" role="_blank">pptr-1</ulink></emphasis> knockdown also promotes the translocation of nuclear DAF-16/FoxO to the cytoplasm, presumably by increasing AKT-1 phosphorylation and activation (<link linkend="bib214">Padmanabhan et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19249087-->). PPTR-1 homologs also modulate Akt activity in mammalian cells and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib277">Vereshchagina et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18827008-->; <link linkend="bib214">Padmanabhan et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19249087-->), indicating that PP2A regulation of Akt activity is evolutionarily conserved.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-10">
<title>SGK-1</title>
<para>The <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>s</emphasis></emphasis>erum- and <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>g</emphasis></emphasis>lucocorticoid-inducible <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>k</emphasis></emphasis>inase Sgk is also activated by growth factors in a PI3K-dependent manner and is similar to Akt/PKB in amino acid sequence as well as in substrate specificity (<link linkend="bib29">Bruhn et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20919962-->; <link linkend="bib222">Pearce et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20027184-->). In mammalian cells, both Sgk and Akt/PKB can phosphorylate FoxO3A, leading to its inhibition through cytoplasmic sequestration (<link linkend="bib31">Brunet et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11154281-->). Accordingly, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Sgk ortholog SGK-1 can phosphorylate DAF-16/FoxO <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib95">Hertweck et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15068796-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, knockdown of SGK-1 by RNAi induces nuclear translocation of DAF-16/FoxO and extends life span in a DAF-16/FoxO-dependent manner, suggesting that SGK-1 may function similarly to AKT-1 and AKT-2 in life span control (<link linkend="bib95">Hertweck et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15068796-->).</para>
<para>However, recent studies have revealed that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004789;class=Gene" role="_blank">sgk-1</ulink></emphasis> null mutants have a shorter life span than wild-type animals (<link linkend="bib247">Soukas et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19240135-->; <link linkend="bib3">Alam et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20620993-->; <link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->). Furthermore, an <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004789;class=Gene" role="_blank">sgk-1</ulink></emphasis> gain-of-function mutation extends life span in a DAF-16/FoxO-dependent manner when animals are incubated at 20&#x00B0;C, suggesting that SGK-1 promotes longevity (<link linkend="bib37">Chen et al., 2013a</link><!--: PMID23786484-->). Notably, in contrast to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> null mutation, which increases the expression of DAF-16/FoxO target genes by promoting DAF-16/FoxO nuclear translocation (<link linkend="bib306">Zhang et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18241854-->; <link linkend="bib3">Alam et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20620993-->; <link linkend="bib59">Dumas et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20178781-->), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004789;class=Gene" role="_blank">sgk-1</ulink></emphasis> null and gain-of-function mutations did not influence DAF-16/FoxO subcellular localization and had different effects on the expression of distinct DAF-16/FoxO target genes (<link linkend="bib37">Chen et al., 2013a</link><!--: PMID23786484-->). These data underscore fundamental differences in DAF-16/FoxO regulation by AKT-1 and SGK-1. Whereas AKT-1 shortens life span by inhibiting DAF-16/FoxO through direct phosphorylation, SGK-1 extends life span, possibly through indirect regulation of a subset of DAF-16/FoxO targets. Further studies will be necessary to resolve the discrepancy between the effects of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004789;class=Gene" role="_blank">sgk-1</ulink></emphasis> mutation and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004789;class=Gene" role="_blank">sgk-1</ulink></emphasis> RNAi on life span (<link linkend="bib95">Hertweck et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15068796-->; <link linkend="bib37">Chen et al., 2013a</link><!--: PMID23786484-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-11">
<title>14-3-3 proteins</title>
<para>In mammalian cells, phosphorylation of FoxO3a by Akt promotes its retention in the cytoplasm and binding to 14-3-3 proteins (<link linkend="bib30">Brunet et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10102273-->). During larval development, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> 14-3-3 proteins PAR-5 and FTT-2 sequester DAF-16/FoxO in the cytoplasm, as knockdown of either <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003920;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-5</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001502;class=Gene" role="_blank">ftt-2</ulink></emphasis> promotes translocation of a functional DAF-16::GFP fusion protein to the nucleus (<link linkend="bib19">Berdichevsky et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16777605-->; <link linkend="bib149">Li et al., 2007a</link><!--: PMID17098225-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001502;class=Gene" role="_blank">ftt-2</ulink></emphasis> RNAi also enhances dauer arrest in animals with reduced IIS (<link linkend="bib149">Li et al., 2007a</link><!--: PMID17098225-->), indicating that FTT-2 inhibits DAF-16/FoxO action. The role of 14-3-3 proteins in the regulation of DAF-16/FoxO activity in adulthood is more complex. FTT-2 inhibits DAF-16/FoxO target gene expression in young adults (<link linkend="bib149">Li et al., 2007a</link><!--: PMID17098225-->), in accord with its effect on dauer arrest and DAF-16::GFP subcellular localization in larvae (<link linkend="bib19">Berdichevsky et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16777605-->; <link linkend="bib149">Li et al., 2007a</link><!--: PMID17098225-->). Paradoxically, FTT-2 promotes life span extension in a SIR-2.1- and DAF-16/FoxO-dependent manner (<link linkend="bib19">Berdichevsky et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16777605-->; <link linkend="bib286">Wang et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16860373-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>The FoxO transcription factor DAF-16</title>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> null mutations fully suppress most phenotypes associated with reduced IIS, suggesting that these phenotypes are a consequence of increased DAF-16/FoxO activity. Accordingly, DAF-16/FoxO is likely the primary mediator of the dauer-constitutive, increased longevity, and stress resistance phenotypes observed in mutants with reduced IIS. DAF-16 is a member of the FoxO family of Forkhead transcription factors, which are key regulators of growth, metabolism, stress responses, cell cycle control, and longevity in many organisms (<link linkend="bib1">Accili and Arden, 2004</link><!--: PMID15137936-->). The Forkhead DNA binding domain, DNA binding specificity, RxRxxS/T phosphorylation motifs, and 14-3-3 binding sites are conserved between <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> DAF-16 and mammalian FoxOs (<link linkend="bib204">Obsil and Obsilova, 2008</link><!--: PMID18391969-->). DAF-16/FoxO is inhibited by the IIS pathway through phosphorylation at its RxRxxS/T motifs, which results in its cytoplasmic retention (<link linkend="bib144">Lee et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11747821-->; <link linkend="bib156">Lin et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11381260-->). Mutation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003965;class=Gene" role="_blank">pdk-1</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink>/2</emphasis> reduces DAF-16/FoxO phosphorylation, resulting in its nuclear translocation and subsequent transcriptional regulation of DAF-16/FoxO target genes (see <link linkend="sec5-4">Section 5.4</link>) that results in IIS loss-of-function phenotypes (see <link linkend="sec3">Section 3</link>).</para>
<sect2 id="sec5-1">
<title>DAF-16/FoxO isoforms</title>
<para>The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> genomic locus encodes eight distinct transcripts. Two of these, <emphasis>daf-16e</emphasis> and <emphasis>daf-16g</emphasis>, are predicted to encode proteins that lack a DNA binding domain; the functions of these isoforms are not known. The remaining six mRNAs comprise three groups of transcripts known as <emphasis>daf-16a</emphasis>, <emphasis>daf-16b</emphasis>, and <emphasis>daf-16d/f/h</emphasis> that are transcribed from three distinct promoters (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2A</link>) and that encode proteins with different N-termini (<link linkend="bib155">Lin et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9360933-->; <link linkend="bib206">Ogg et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9353126-->; <link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->) (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2B</link>).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Transcriptional and translational reporters indicate that <emphasis>daf-16a, daf-16b,</emphasis> and <emphasis>daf-16d/f/h</emphasis> have distinct tissue distributions. <emphasis>daf-16a</emphasis> and <emphasis>daf-16d/f/h</emphasis> promoters are active in most tissues, driving reporter gene expression in hypodermis, muscle, neurons, and intestine (<link linkend="bib206">Ogg et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9353126-->; <link linkend="bib92">Henderson and Johnson, 2001</link><!--: PMID11747825-->; <link linkend="bib144">Lee et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11747821-->; <link linkend="bib156">Lin et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11381260-->; <link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->). By contrast, the <emphasis>daf-16b</emphasis> promoter exhibits greater tissue specificity, driving expression primarily in the pharynx, nervous system, and somatic gonad (<link linkend="bib144">Lee et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11747821-->; <link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->; <link linkend="bib43">Christensen et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID22069193-->). Promoter-swap experiments with isoform-specific <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> transgenes indicate that promoter specificity contributes to the distinct biological functions of specific <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> isoforms (<link linkend="bib144">Lee et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11747821-->; <link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->).</para>
<para>The three groups of DAF-16/FoxO isoforms share carboxy-terminal sequences but diverge at their amino-termini (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2B</link>). Human FoxO1, FoxO3, and FoxO4 proteins are most similar in sequence to DAF-16A and DAF-16D/F/H, which share their 428 carboxy-terminal amino acids (including the entire Forkhead DNA binding domain) (<link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->). Importantly, whereas all three RxRxxS/T motifs in mammalian FoxO transcription factors that are phosphorylated in response to Akt/PKB activation are conserved in DAF-16A, the divergent amino-terminus of DAF-16D/F/H lacks the amino-terminal RxRxxT motif (<link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->). Instead, DAF-16D/F/H isoforms are phosphorylated <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> at an amino-terminal site within a QxRxxS motif (<link linkend="bib24">Bodenmiller et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID19060867-->; <link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->). Since the -5 arginine in the canonical RxRxxS/T motif of the Akt/PKB substrate GSK3 makes important molecular contacts with conserved acidic residues in the kinase domain of Akt/PKB and other highly related kinases (<link linkend="bib300">Yang et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID12434148-->), the QxRxxS motif in DAF-16D/F/H and the amino-terminal RxRxxT motif in DAF-16A may be phosphorylated and regulated by distinct kinases.</para>
<para>The 319 C-terminal amino acids of DAF-16B, which include part of but not the entire Forkhead domain, are identical to those of DAF-16A and DAF-16D/F/H. The amino-terminal 211 amino acids of DAF-16B, including the amino-terminal portion of its Forkhead domain, are encoded by a unique exon (<link linkend="bib206">Ogg et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9353126-->). The fact that the DAF-16B DNA binding domain differs in amino acid sequence from that of DAF-16A and DAF-16D/F/H suggests that it may bind to DNA sequences distinct from those recognized by DAF-16A and DAF-16D/F/H. However, a <emphasis>daf-16b</emphasis> cDNA expressed under the control of the <emphasis>daf-16a</emphasis> promoter extends the life span of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> null mutant animals to nearly the same degree as <emphasis>daf-16a</emphasis> expressed from the <emphasis>daf-16a</emphasis> promoter, and expression of either cDNA under the control of the <emphasis>daf-16b</emphasis> promoter suffices to induce pharyngeal remodeling in dauers (<link linkend="bib144">Lee et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11747821-->). Thus, DAF-16A and DAF-16B may have similar functions in spite of some amino acid sequence divergence in their Forkhead domains. Although the amino-terminus of DAF-16B is unique, it does contain an RxRxxT motif, suggesting that DAF-16A and DAF-16B may be regulated by the same or similar protein kinases.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5-2">
<title>Functions of specific DAF-16/FoxO isoforms</title>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> null mutations and mutations predicted to only affect <emphasis>daf-16a</emphasis> and <emphasis>daf-16d/f/h</emphasis> isoforms suppress the dauer-constitutive and extended life span phenotypes of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants to similar degrees (<link linkend="bib144">Lee et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11747821-->), and RNAi knockdown of <emphasis>daf-16a</emphasis> and <emphasis>daf-16d/f/h</emphasis> together suppresses most of the life span extension caused by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutation (<link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->). Furthermore, expression of <emphasis>daf-16a</emphasis>-specific and <emphasis>daf-16d/f/h</emphasis>-specific transgenes suffices to rescue dauer-constitutive and longevity phenotypes in <emphasis>daf-16(null); daf-2(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143949;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1370</ulink>)</emphasis> double mutants (<link linkend="bib156">Lin et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11381260-->; <link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->). By contrast, <emphasis>daf-16b-</emphasis>specific transgenes have a small effect on longevity and dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib144">Lee et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11747821-->; <link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->). Taken together, these results suggest that DAF-16A and DAF-16D/F/H are the major isoforms that control dauer arrest and life span. Studies with isoform-specific transgenes suggest that AKT-1 influences life span primarily by controlling DAF-16D/F/H activity, whereas AKT-2 controls life span mainly by regulating DAF-16A (<link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->). A recent study examining the contributions of specific mTOR complexes to life span control revealed that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> TORC1 controls life span by regulating the subcellular localization of DAF-16D/F/H without influencing DAF-16A activity (<link linkend="bib231">Robida-Stubbs et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID22560223-->). Thus, a picture is emerging whereby specific DAF-16/FoxO isoforms influence life span by responding to distinct regulatory inputs. The unique transcriptional outputs that may distinguish the biological activities of the different isoforms are not yet known.</para>
<para>No <emphasis>daf-16b-</emphasis>specific mutations have been reported, and the observation that <emphasis>daf-16b</emphasis> is mainly expressed in tissues that may be refractory to RNAi, such as the pharynx and the nervous system, complicates the interpretation of negative <emphasis>daf-16b</emphasis> RNAi results. Expression of <emphasis>daf-16a</emphasis> transgenes under the control of the <emphasis>daf-16a</emphasis> promoter in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> null mutants is sufficient to rescue the dauer-defective phenotype; however, dauer formation in these animals is incomplete, as these dauers do not have fully remodeled pharynxes that are typically seen in natural dauers (<link linkend="bib92">Henderson and Johnson, 2001</link><!--: PMID11747825-->; <link linkend="bib144">Lee et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11747821-->; <link linkend="bib156">Lin et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11381260-->; <link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->). Expression of a <emphasis>daf-16b</emphasis> transgene under the control of its native promoter is sufficient for partial rescue of the dauer-defective phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> null mutants, and dauers formed in this context have fully remodeled pharynxes (<link linkend="bib144">Lee et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11747821-->; <link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->). Therefore, DAF-16B plays an important role in pharyngeal remodeling during dauer formation. A recent study also implicates DAF-16B in promoting neurite outgrowth cell autonomously in the AIY interneuron (<link linkend="bib43">Christensen et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID22069193-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5-3">
<title>The DAF-16 Binding Element (DBE)</title>
<para>The DNA binding domain of DAF-16/FoxO, like that of other members of the FoxO transcription factor family, binds <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> to a core consensus DNA sequence, TTGTTTAC, known as the DBE (DAF-16 Binding Element), as shown through <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> SELEX studies (<link linkend="bib72">Furuyama et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID10880363-->). Variations of the DBE are overrepresented in the promoters of genes that are upregulated in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants in a DAF-16/FoxO-dependent manner (Class 1 DAF-16/FoxO targets) (<link linkend="bib193">Murphy et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12845331-->), and recent DamID (chromatin profiling by <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>D</emphasis></emphasis>NA <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>a</emphasis></emphasis>denine <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>m</emphasis></emphasis>ethyltransferase <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>id</emphasis></emphasis>entification) experiments suggest that DAF-16/FoxO binds directly to these target genes (<link linkend="bib239">Schuster et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20706209-->).</para>
<para>By contrast, DAF-16/FoxO appears not to bind the promoters of genes that are downregulated in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants in a DAF-16/FoxO-dependent manner (Class 2 DAF-16/FoxO targets). These promoters contain a different overrepresented sequence, CTTATCA (<link linkend="bib193">Murphy et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12845331-->), a reverse GATA site that was later dubbed the &#x201C;DAE&#x201D; for &#x201C;DAF-16 Associated Element&#x201D; (<link linkend="bib173">McElwee et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15308663-->). Given its lack of similarity with the DBE, it seems unlikely that FoxO transcription factors would bind to the DAE; thus a transcription factor distinct from DAF-16/FoxO may be involved in the regulation of Class 2 (downregulated) DAF-16/FoxO targets. In fact, ChIP-Seq data implicates the zinc finger transcription factor PQM-1 as the DAE-binding factor, acting antagonistically with DAF-16/FoxO (<link linkend="bib263">Tepper et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID23911329-->) (<link linkend="sec6-12">Section 6.12</link>).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5-4">
<title>Transcriptional targets of IIS</title>
<para>DAF-16/FoxO is the main output of IIS. While the regulation of many DAF-16/FoxO target genes in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants was already known from individual studies of specific stresses, the power of whole-genome techniques, including bioinformatic predictions (<link linkend="bib146">Lee et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12690206-->), expression microarrays (<link linkend="bib172">McElwee et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12882324-->; <link linkend="bib193">Murphy et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12845331-->; <link linkend="bib173">McElwee et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15308663-->; <link linkend="bib242">Shaw et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17900898-->), serial analysis of gene expression (SAGE) (<link linkend="bib87">Halaschek-Wiener et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID15837805-->), protein mass spectrometry (<link linkend="bib53">Dong et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17673661-->), DamID (<link linkend="bib239">Schuster et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20706209-->), and ChIP-Seq (<link linkend="bib202">Niu et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21177963-->; <link linkend="bib263">Tepper et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID23911329-->), have revealed a large complement of DAF-16/FoxO targets (discussed in greater detail in <link linkend="bib191">Murphy, 2006</link><!--: PMID16934425-->). While the functions of many DAF-16/FoxO targets remain obscure, the diverse array of characteristics of known DAF-16/FoxO-regulated genes helps explain why <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutant animals are resistant to virtually every known stress they might encounter.</para>
<para>DAF-16/FoxO upregulates the expression of many genes whose protein products fight various forms of stress, such as oxidative stress through superoxide dismutase (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004932;class=Gene" role="_blank">sod-3</ulink></emphasis>) (<link linkend="bib98">Honda and Honda, 1999</link><!--: PMID10428762-->, <link linkend="bib99">2002</link><!--: PMID11976220-->; <link linkend="bib208">Oh et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16380712-->) and catalase (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000830;class=Gene" role="_blank">ctl-1</ulink>, 2</emphasis>) (<link linkend="bib299">Yanase et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID12470895-->); resistance to heavy metals through the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003473;class=Gene" role="_blank">mtl-1</ulink></emphasis> metallothionein (<link linkend="bib17">Barsyte et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11259381-->); thermotolerance and proteotoxicity via small heat shock proteins (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002020;class=Gene" role="_blank">hsp-16</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002013;class=Gene" role="_blank">hsp-12.6</ulink></emphasis>) (<link linkend="bib104">Hsu et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12750521-->; <link linkend="bib183">Morley and Morimoto, 2004</link><!--: PMID14668486-->; <link linkend="bib45">Cohen et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16902091-->; <link linkend="bib49">David et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20711477-->; <link linkend="bib125">Keowkase et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20420844-->; <link linkend="bib41">Ching et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21348927-->; <link linkend="bib261">Teixeira-Castro et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21546381-->; <link linkend="bib303">Zhang et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID22232551-->); hypertonic stress through trehalose biosynthetic enzymes (<link linkend="bib193">Murphy et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12845331-->; <link linkend="bib134">Lamitina and Strange, 2005</link><!--: PMID15496475-->); mitochondrial oxidative stress (<link linkend="bib12">Arkblad et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID15890626-->) via the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003778;class=Gene" role="_blank">nnt-1</ulink></emphasis> nicotinamide nucleotide transhydrogenase (<link linkend="bib242">Shaw et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17900898-->; <link linkend="bib171">McCormick et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID22081913-->); and antimicrobial defense through thaumatins (PR5 plant defense proteins) and a variety of bacterial pathogen defense genes (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004986;class=Gene" role="_blank">spp-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003096;class=Gene" role="_blank">lys-7</ulink></emphasis>, DUF-23, C-lectins, <emphasis>scl-</emphasis> genes, ShK toxins, etc.) (<link linkend="bib193">Murphy et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12845331-->; <link linkend="bib213">Ookuma et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12620193-->; <link linkend="bib63">Evans et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18927620-->).</para>
<para>In addition to stress response genes, reduction of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> activity results in increased expression of metabolic regulators, such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001564;class=Gene" role="_blank">gei-7</ulink></emphasis> (isocitrate lyase/malate synthase, which is also upregulated in dauers) (<link linkend="bib284">Wang and Kim, 2003</link><!--: PMID12620986-->), the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016716;class=Gene" role="_blank">dod-9</ulink></emphasis> acyl CoA synthetase, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001684;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpd-2</ulink></emphasis> glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001578;class=Gene" role="_blank">ges-1</ulink></emphasis> carboxylesterase; digestive proteins, such as the GCP-1 cysteine protease; fat metabolism genes, including fatty acid desaturase (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink>)</emphasis>, alcohol dehydrogenases (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00010790;class=Gene" role="_blank">sodh-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00010790;class=Gene" role="_blank">dod-11</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00010791;class=Gene" role="_blank">sodh-2</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00010791;class=Gene" role="_blank">dod-14</ulink></emphasis>) and short-chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenases (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016943;class=Gene" role="_blank">acdh-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016943;class=Gene" role="_blank">dod-12</ulink></emphasis>) (<link linkend="bib193">Murphy et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12845331-->); and many cytochrome P450s (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00011671;class=Gene" role="_blank">cyp-13A4</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00011671;class=Gene" role="_blank">dod-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00019472;class=Gene" role="_blank">cyp-35B1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00019472;class=Gene" role="_blank">dod-13</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015044;class=Gene" role="_blank">cyp-34A9</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015044;class=Gene" role="_blank">dod-16</ulink></emphasis>), some of which may function in Phase II detoxification (<link linkend="bib173">McElwee et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15308663-->; <link linkend="bib211">Oliveira et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19575768-->), and others that may function in the synthesis of sterol signaling ligands, similar to DAF-9 (<link linkend="bib78">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11740945-->; <link linkend="bib114">Jia et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID11782415-->; <link linkend="bib193">Murphy et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12845331-->). Autophagy is also controlled by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> through its regulation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000247;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> expression (<link linkend="bib174">Melendez et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12958363-->). Still other genes upregulated in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants, such as the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001852;class=Gene" role="_blank">hil-1</ulink></emphasis> histone H1-like gene (<link linkend="bib242">Shaw et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17900898-->), are required for their long life span, but their functions are not yet well understood.</para>
<para>Conversely, &#x201C;Class 2&#x201D; genes are downregulated in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants in a DAF-16/FoxO-dependent manner (<link linkend="bib193">Murphy et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12845331-->). The functions of most of these genes and their roles in normal development and life span control are not yet understood, but recent GO analysis suggests that many of these genes regulate growth and development (<link linkend="bib263">Tepper et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID23911329-->), and reducing expression of some of these genes by RNAi extends life span (<link linkend="bib193">Murphy et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12845331-->). Many Class 2 genes are upregulated in response to pathogen exposure (<link linkend="bib269">Troemel et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID17096597-->), suggesting a specific role in pathogen response that may normally &#x201C;cost&#x201D; longevity, but this has not yet been shown. Most of the Class 2 genes, and some of the Class 1 genes, are regulated by the zinc finger transcription factor PQM-1, which acts in opposition to DAF-16/FoxO (<link linkend="bib263">Tepper et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID23911329-->) (<link linkend="sec6-12">Section 6.12</link>).</para>
<para>The regulation of Class 1 and Class 2 gene expression by DAF-16/FoxO may function in part to coordinate the state of IIS at the organismal level. When IIS is reduced, DAF-16/FoxO represses the Class 2 ILP gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002090;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-7</ulink></emphasis> (which encodes an agonist of DAF-2/IGFR) and promotes the expression of the Class 1 ILP gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002101;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-18</ulink></emphasis> (which encodes a DAF-2/IGFR antagonist), resulting in feed-forward inhibition of IIS throughout the animal (<link linkend="bib193">Murphy et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12845331-->; <link linkend="bib192">Murphy et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID18025456-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Other DAF-16/FoxO co-factors and regulators</title>
<para>DAF-16/FoxO is regulated by a host of additional proteins that directly or indirectly modulate its activity (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>) (<link linkend="bib135">Landis and Murphy, 2010</link><!--: PMID20140911-->). Like the IIS pathway, DAF-16/FoxO co-factors and regulators and the nature of their interactions with DAF-16/FoxO are remarkably conserved throughout metazoan phylogeny.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<sect2 id="sec6-1">
<title>DAF-16/FoxO regulation by kinases other than Akt</title>
<para>While IIS-regulated DAF-16/FoxO phosphorylation by AKT-1 and AKT-2 at conserved RxRxxS/T motifs promotes the cytoplasmic sequestration of DAF-16/FoxO, phosphorylation of DAF-16/FoxO by other kinases may also regulate DAF-16/FoxO activity. For example, the mammalian MST1 Ste20-like kinase activates FoxO3 by phosphorylating it at a conserved residue within its DNA binding domain (S207), thus promoting its nuclear translocation by disrupting interactions with 14-3-3 proteins. Mammalian MST1 can also phosphorylate <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> DAF-16/FoxO at the site corresponding to S207 in FoxO3 (S196). Overexpression of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> MST-1 homolog CST-1 extends life span in a DAF-16/FoxO-dependent manner, suggesting that MST1 activates FoxO transcription factors via a conserved mechanism (<link linkend="bib147">Lehtinen, 2006</link><!--: PMID16751106-->). However, phosphorylation of the FoxO1 DNA binding domain by MST1 inhibits its binding to cognate DNA sites <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib28">Brent et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18786403-->). Therefore, our understanding of how MST1 regulates FoxO activity appears to be incomplete.</para>
<para>In mammalian cells, oxidative stress activates FoxO4 through c-Jun N-terminal kinase (Jnk)-dependent phosphorylation of two threonine residues near its C-terminus (T447 and T451) (<link linkend="bib62">Essers et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15538382-->). Jnk also activates FoxO in invertebrates, as Jnk orthologs promote life span extension in a FoxO-dependent manner in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib209">Oh et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID15767565-->; <link linkend="bib285">Wang et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID15820683-->). However, whether the underlying mechanisms of FoxO activation by Jnk are conserved is unclear; whereas Jnk phosphorylation sites lie near the C-terminus of mammalian FoxO4 (<link linkend="bib62">Essers et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15538382-->), <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> JNK-1 appears to phosphorylate residues in an N-terminal fragment of DAF-16/FoxO <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib209">Oh et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID15767565-->).</para>
<para>The AMP-dependent protein kinase (AMPK) controls energy balance by sensing changes in intracellular AMP/ATP ratios (<link linkend="bib90">Hardie et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID22436748-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> the AMPK catalytic subunit homolog AAK-2 promotes longevity and stress resistance (<link linkend="bib9">Apfeld et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15574588-->; <link linkend="bib84">Greer et al., 2007a</link><!--: PMID17900900-->; <link linkend="bib142">Lee et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18408008-->; <link linkend="bib199">Narbonne and Roy, 2009</link><!--: PMID19052547-->; <link linkend="bib139">LaRue and Padilla, 2011</link><!--: PMID21304820-->; <link linkend="bib166">Mair et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21331044-->). This may be a consequence of DAF-16/FoxO activation, as an activating mutation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020633;class=Gene" role="_blank">aakg-2</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of the AMPK gamma subunit, enhances resistance to paraquat and extends life span in a DAF-16/FoxO-dependent manner (<link linkend="bib84">Greer et al., 2007a</link><!--: PMID17900900-->). AAKG-2 activation increases DAF-16/FoxO target gene expression without influencing DAF-16/FoxO subcellular localization, suggesting that it regulates DAF-16/FoxO activity independent of the PI3K/Akt pathway (<link linkend="bib84">Greer et al., 2007a</link><!--: PMID17900900-->). Activated AMPK can phosphorylate both DAF-16/FoxO and human FoxO3 at several sites <emphasis>in vitro,</emphasis> resulting in the enhancement of FoxO-dependent transcription in mammalian cells (<link linkend="bib84">Greer et al., 2007a</link><!--: PMID17900900-->; <link linkend="bib85">Greer et al., 2007b</link><!--: PMID17711846-->). The role of AMPK in controlling FoxO activity <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> is likely to be context-dependent, as AMPK can inhibit FoxO transcription factor activity indirectly in mouse hepatocytes through direct effects on Class IIa histone deacetylases (<link linkend="bib179">Mihaylova et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21565617-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6-2">
<title>EAK proteins</title>
<para>Although Akt inhibition of FoxO transcription factors by direct phosphorylation is well established as a conserved mechanism of FoxO regulation by IIS, data from mammalian cell culture as well as <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> experiments suggest that nuclear translocation of FoxO is necessary but not sufficient for full activation of FoxO. For example, in mammalian cells, insulin inhibits transcriptional activation by a FoxO1 mutant that is not exported from the nucleus (<link linkend="bib270">Tsai et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID14500580-->). Similarly, a DAF-16/FoxO mutant with all RxRxxS/T phosphoacceptor sites mutated to alanine localizes to nuclei constitutively but does not promote dauer arrest or extend life span unless IIS is reduced (<link linkend="bib156">Lin et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11381260-->). These data are consistent with the existence of a conserved pathway that acts in parallel to Akt to inhibit FoxO activity after its translocation to the nucleus.</para>
<para>A genetic screen for <emphasis role="underline">e</emphasis>nhancers of the weak dauer-constitutive phenotype of <emphasis><emphasis role="underline">ak</emphasis>t-1</emphasis> null mutants (<emphasis>eak</emphasis> mutants) identified six genes that may encode components of such a pathway (<link linkend="bib107">Hu et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16839187-->; <link linkend="bib306">Zhang et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18241854-->; <link linkend="bib3">Alam et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20620993-->; <link linkend="bib59">Dumas et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20178781-->). Two <emphasis>eak</emphasis> genes, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012394;class=Gene" role="_blank">eak-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004748;class=Gene" role="_blank">eak-5</ulink>,</emphasis> are respectively allelic to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012394;class=Gene" role="_blank">hsd-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004748;class=Gene" role="_blank">sdf-9</ulink></emphasis>, genes identified in unrelated synthetic dauer screens (<link linkend="bib210">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12783794-->; <link linkend="bib220">Patel et al., 2008a</link><!--: PMID18495818-->). In contrast to AKT-1, which inhibits DAF-16/FoxO by promoting its cytoplasmic sequestration, EAK proteins inhibit DAF-16/FoxO activity without influencing its subcellular localization (<link linkend="bib306">Zhang et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18241854-->; <link linkend="bib3">Alam et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20620993-->; <link linkend="bib59">Dumas et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20178781-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012394;class=Gene" role="_blank">hsd-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00010671;class=Gene" role="_blank">eak-7</ulink></emphasis> null mutations both enhance the dauer arrest phenotype of animals expressing a constitutively nuclear DAF-16/FoxO mutant protein, suggesting that HSD-1 and EAK-7 inhibit nuclear DAF-16/FoxO (<link linkend="bib3">Alam et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20620993-->).</para>
<para>The EAK proteins may control nuclear DAF-16/FoxO activity in part by influencing the activity of DAF-12, a conserved nuclear receptor that is regulated by steroid ligands known as dafachronic acids (<link linkend="bib7">Antebi et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID10859169-->; <link linkend="bib186">Motola et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16529801-->; WormBook chapter <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_dauer/dauer.html">Dauer</ulink>). Five EAK proteins, including the conserved 3-&#x03B2;-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase family member HSD-1, are specifically expressed in the hypodermal XXX cells (<link linkend="bib107">Hu et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16839187-->; <link linkend="bib220">Patel et al., 2008a</link><!--: PMID18495818-->; <link linkend="bib306">Zhang et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18241854-->; <link linkend="bib59">Dumas et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20178781-->), where the DA biosynthetic enzyme DAF-9 is also expressed (<link linkend="bib78">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11740945-->; <link linkend="bib114">Jia et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID11782415-->; <link linkend="bib210">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12783794-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000905;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007536;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-36</ulink></emphasis> mutations, which abrogate &#x0394;<superscript>7</superscript>-DA biosynthesis (<link linkend="bib186">Motola et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16529801-->; <link linkend="bib294">Wollam et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21749634-->), also enhance dauer arrest in animals with reduced <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> activity (<link linkend="bib306">Zhang et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18241854-->; <link linkend="bib59">Dumas et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20178781-->). Furthermore, DAF-12 is required for the expression of DAF-16/FoxO target genes in <emphasis>eak; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> double mutants as well as in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007536;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-36</ulink></emphasis> mutants with reduced <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> activity (<link linkend="bib306">Zhang et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18241854-->; <link linkend="bib59">Dumas et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20178781-->). Taken together, these data are consistent with a model whereby EAK proteins act in the XXX cells to promote DA biosynthesis and/or release. DAs then reduce DAF-16/FoxO activity in target tissues by binding to and regulating the activity of DAF-12.</para>
<para>In contrast to the other five <emphasis>eak</emphasis> genes, which are specifically expressed in the XXX cells, the conserved gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00010671;class=Gene" role="_blank">eak-7</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in the same tissues as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis>. EAK-7 and its human ortholog KIAA1609 both contain N-myristoylation motifs and a TLDc domain of unknown function (<link linkend="bib3">Alam et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20620993-->). How EAK-7 controls nuclear DAF-16/FoxO activity is not known. Since EAK-7 localizes to the plasma membrane (<link linkend="bib3">Alam et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20620993-->), it likely acts through intermediary proteins to regulate DAF-16/FoxO in the nucleus.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6-3">
<title>E3 ubiquitin ligases</title>
<para>In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, the RLE-1 ubiquitin ligase controls dauer arrest and life span by promoting the polyubiquitination and proteasomal degradation of DAF-16/FoxO (<link linkend="bib150">Li et al., 2007b</link><!--: PMID17276341-->). Interestingly, although a number of E3 ubiquitin ligases have been shown to promote FoxO polyubiquitination and degradation in mammalian cell culture, the RLE-1 ortholog Roquin is not one of them (<link linkend="bib170">Matsuzaki et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID13679577-->; <link linkend="bib110">Huang et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID15668399-->; <link linkend="bib121">Kato et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18815134-->; <link linkend="bib69">Fu et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19321440-->). This suggests that distinct E3 ligases may be capable of regulating FoxO turnover in different biological contexts. E3 ligases can also regulate DAF-16/FoxO indirectly: components of an SCF E3 ligase complex containing the cullin CUL-1 are required for life span extension in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants, and CUL-1 promotes DAF-16/FoxO target gene expression (<link linkend="bib79">Ghazi et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17392428-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6-4">
<title>PRMT-1</title>
<para>Mammalian FoxO1 is regulated by arginine methylation. The arginine methyltransferase PRMT1 methylates FoxO1 at arginines 248 and 250, which comprise part of the RxRxxS motif that is phosphorylated by Akt/PKB. Methylation of R248 and R250 activates FoxO1 by preventing its phosphorylation by Akt/PKB (<link linkend="bib296">Yamagata et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18951090-->). This mechanism of FoxO regulation is conserved in <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> as the PRMT1 ortholog PRMT-1 binds to and methylates DAF-16/FoxO, thus reducing T242 phosphorylation (analogous to S253 in mammalian FoxO1) and promoting DAF-16/FoxO nuclear translocation, longevity, and stress resistance (<link linkend="bib255">Takahashi et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21531333-->). Surprisingly, whereas <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00013766;class=Gene" role="_blank">prmt-1</ulink></emphasis> mutation shortens life span and reduces stress resistance of <emphasis>daf-2(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143947;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1368</ulink>)</emphasis> mutant animals, it does not suppress the dauer-constitutive phenotype of <emphasis>daf-2(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143947;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1368</ulink>)</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib255">Takahashi et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21531333-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6-5">
<title>BAR-1/&#x03B2;-catenin</title>
<para>&#x03B2;-catenin has a conserved function as a FoxO regulator. A <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> &#x03B2;-catenin, BAR-1, promotes DAF-16/FoxO activity in response to oxidative stress. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000238;class=Gene" role="_blank">bar-1</ulink></emphasis> mutation reduced expression of a DAF-16/FoxO-dependent reporter gene in the presence of paraquat, but not through the canonical &#x03B2;-catenin/TCF pathway. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000238;class=Gene" role="_blank">bar-1</ulink></emphasis> is also required for dauer arrest in <emphasis>daf-2(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088550;class=Variation" role="_blank">m41</ulink>)</emphasis> mutants. BAR-1 physically interacts with DAF-16/FoxO when both proteins are expressed in mammalian cell culture, and this interaction is enhanced in the presence of oxidative stress. Accordingly, mammalian &#x03B2;-catenin binds to FoxO transcription factors directly and promotes transcription from a FoxO-dependent promoter, supporting a conserved role for &#x03B2;-catenin in FOXO activation (<link linkend="bib61">Essers et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID15905404-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6-6">
<title>Sirtuins</title>
<para>A role for the sirtuin family of NAD<superscript>+</superscript>-dependent deacetylases in FoxO regulation was first suggested by studies in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> showing that increased dosage of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004800;class=Gene" role="_blank">sir-2.1</ulink></emphasis> gene extends life span in a DAF-16/FoxO-dependent manner (<link linkend="bib265">Tissenbaum and Guarente, 2001</link><!--: PMID11242085-->). The longevity increase caused by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004800;class=Gene" role="_blank">sir-2.1</ulink></emphasis> overexpression in invertebrates may be milder than originally reported&#x2014;15% (<link linkend="bib265">Tissenbaum and Guarente, 2001</link><!--: PMID11242085-->; <link linkend="bib33">Burnett et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21938067-->; <link linkend="bib278">Viswanathan and Guarente, 2011</link><!--: PMID21938026-->), rather than the 50% originally reported (<link linkend="bib265">Tissenbaum and Guarente, 2001</link><!--: PMID11242085-->; <link linkend="bib33">Burnett et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21938067-->; <link linkend="bib278">Viswanathan and Guarente, 2011</link><!--: PMID21938026-->). A low-copy <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004800;class=Gene" role="_blank">sir-2.1</ulink></emphasis> overexpression strain is long-lived in a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO-</emphasis>dependent manner, and its longevity phenotype is suppressed by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004800;class=Gene" role="_blank">sir-2.1</ulink></emphasis> RNAi (<link linkend="bib230">Rizki et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21909281-->). Additionally, sirtuins interact physically with FoxO <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib19">Berdichevsky et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16777605-->) and in intact mammalian cells (<link linkend="bib32">Brunet et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID14976264-->; <link linkend="bib47">Daitoku et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15220471-->; <link linkend="bib187">Motta et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID14980222-->; <link linkend="bib274">van der Horst et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15126506-->). In response to heat shock, the physical association of SIR-2.1 and DAF-16/FoxO requires 14-3-3 proteins (<link linkend="bib19">Berdichevsky et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16777605-->). These results suggest that SIR-2.1 may control the acetylation state of DAF-16/FoxO in a manner analogous to the regulation of mammalian FoxO transcription factors by SIRT1 (<link linkend="bib32">Brunet et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID14976264-->; <link linkend="bib187">Motta et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID14980222-->; <link linkend="bib274">van der Horst et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15126506-->).</para>
<para>Recently, Chiang et al. characterized the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of mammalian SIRT6 and SIRT7 proteins, SIR-2.4, and found that it is required for nuclear localization of DAF-16/FoxO in response to stress but dispensable for DAF-16/FoxO nuclear localization in the context of reduced IIS. Although DAF-16/FoxO is hyperacetylated in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004803;class=Gene" role="_blank">sir-2.4</ulink></emphasis> mutants, a catalytically inactive mutant SIR-2.4 protein rescued the DAF-16/FoxO localization defect caused by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004803;class=Gene" role="_blank">sir-2.4</ulink></emphasis> mutation, suggesting that SIR-2.4 controls the acetylation state of DAF-16/FoxO indirectly (<link linkend="bib40">Chiang et al., 2012b</link><!--: PMID23028355-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6-7">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00095109;class=Variation" role="_blank">p300</ulink>/CBP-1</title>
<para>CBP-1, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog of the mammalian CBP/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00095109;class=Variation" role="_blank">p300</ulink> acetyltransferase, is ubiquitously expressed, and regulates DAF-16/FoxO acetylation. CBP/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00095109;class=Variation" role="_blank">p300</ulink> acetylates mammalian FoxO1 (<link linkend="bib47">Daitoku et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15220471-->), and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> CBP-1 interacts with DAF-16/FoxO in yeast two-hybrid assays and <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib200">Nasrin et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID10973497-->). More recently, it was shown that RNAi knockdown of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000366;class=Gene" role="_blank">cbp-1</ulink></emphasis> results in DAF-16/FoxO hypoacetylation and nuclear translocation (<link linkend="bib40">Chiang et al., 2012b</link><!--: PMID23028355-->). CBP-1 acetylates DAF-16/FoxO at four sites <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> (K248, K253, K375, and K379), and these acetylation events are blocked by SIR-2.4 in a manner that is independent of SIR-2.4 catalytic activity (<link linkend="bib40">Chiang et al., 2012b</link><!--: PMID23028355-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6-8">
<title>HCF-1/host cell factor</title>
<para>HCF-1 is the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog of mammalian host cell factor, which is a nuclear protein that associates with the herpes simplex virus transcriptional activator VP16 to promote early viral gene expression during lytic infection (<link linkend="bib290">Wilson et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID7956027-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001827;class=Gene" role="_blank">hcf-1</ulink></emphasis> mutation extends life span and enhances stress resistance in a DAF-16/FoxO-dependent manner. HCF-1 is a nuclear protein that binds to DAF-16/FoxO and inhibits its activity by preventing its association with target gene promoters (<link linkend="bib148">Li et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18828672-->). Interestingly, SIR-2.1 may control DAF-16/FoxO activity via HCF-1, as SIR-2.1 overexpression does not enhance stress resistance or extend life span in animals lacking HCF-1. Moreover, expression profiling experiments demonstrate significant overlap in the sets of genes regulated by SIR-2.1 overexpression and loss of HCF-1, and HCF-1 physically associates with SIR-2.1 (<link linkend="bib230">Rizki et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21909281-->). Mammalian host cell factors also regulate FoxO target gene expression and form a complex with FoxO3 and SIRT1, suggesting that the role of host cell factors in mediating sirtuin control of FoxO transcription factor activity may be evolutionarily conserved (<link linkend="bib148">Li et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18828672-->; <link linkend="bib230">Rizki et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21909281-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6-9">
<title>SMK-1</title>
<para>SMK-1, which is orthologous to the mammalian protein phosphatase 4 regulatory subunit 3A, was originally identified in a screen in <emphasis>Dictyostelium</emphasis> for suppressors of the MEK1 null phenotype (<link linkend="bib175">Mendoza et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID16107728-->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> SMK-1 is a nuclear protein that is expressed in the intestine, hypodermis, and nervous system. It is required for longevity in IIS loss-of-function mutants but does not influence dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib291">Wolff et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16530049-->). Interestingly, SMK-1 promotes resistance to oxidative stress, ultraviolet radiation, and pathogens but does not appear to influence thermotolerance or reproduction in IIS mutants (<link linkend="bib291">Wolff et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID16530049-->). These data suggest that SMK-1 regulates a subset of DAF-16/FoxO functions. Although SMK-1 co-localizes and genetically interacts with DAF-16/FoxO, how it controls DAF-16/FoxO activity [specifically, whether it promotes the dephosphorylation of DAF-16/FoxO, and if so, at which site(s)] remains unclear. Furthermore, the full complement of DAF-16/FoxO targets that are regulated by SMK-1 is not known.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6-10">
<title>DPY-21</title>
<para>A genetic screen designed to identify new DAF-16/FoxO regulators that promote dauer arrest has revealed an unexpected role for the conserved dosage compensation protein DPY-21 in the regulation of IIS and DAF-16/FoxO activity. Three independent <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001080;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-21</ulink></emphasis> alleles emerged from a screen for suppressors of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00010671;class=Gene" role="_blank">eak-7</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> dauer-constitutive phenotype. DPY-21 is a component of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> dosage compensation complex (DCC), a ten-protein complex that equalizes X-linked gene expression between XO males and XX hermaphrodites by binding to both hermaphrodite X chromosomes and reducing gene expression from each by approximately two-fold (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_dosagecomp/dosagecomp.html">X-Chromosome dosage compensation</ulink>; <link linkend="bib177">Meyer, 2010</link><!--: PMID20381335-->). DPY-21 activates DAF-16/FoxO by repressing X-linked genes encoding IIS components that promote the cytoplasmic sequestration of DAF-16/FoxO; accordingly, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001080;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-21</ulink></emphasis> knockdown reduces DAF-16/FoxO target gene expression and enhances DAF-16/FoxO translocation to the cytoplasm (<link linkend="bib57">Dumas et al., 2013a</link><!--: PMID23733789-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6-11">
<title>TRPA-1</title>
<para>The cold-sensitive TRP channel TRPA-1 was recently shown to promote longevity at low temperatures (15-20&#x00B0;C) in a DAF-16/FoxO-dependent manner by activating a calcium-dependent kinase cascade involving the calcium-sensitive protein kinase C family member PKC-2 and SGK-1. Although life span extension induced by TRPA-1 activation required DAF-16/FoxO, TRPA-1 activation did not promote DAF-16/FoxO nuclear localization, suggesting that TRPA-1 extends life span by activating nuclear DAF-16/FoxO (<link linkend="bib295">Xiao et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID23415228-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6-12">
<title>PQM-1</title>
<para>The identification of the DAF-16 Associated Element as an overrepresented motif in the promoters of Class 2 (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis>-downregulated) genes suggested that another factor might collaborate with DAF-16/FoxO in IIS<emphasis>-</emphasis>dependent gene regulation. By combining a ranking of genes by DAF-16/FoxO responsiveness with ChIP-Seq analysis, <link linkend="bib263">Tepper, et al. (2013)</link><!--: PMID23911329--> identified the zinc finger transcription factor PQM-1 as a candidate DAE-binding factor. PQM-1 binds to a Class 2 gene promoter in a DAE-dependent manner, and expression is reduced in the context of reduced IIS, as predicted for a Class 2 gene. More interestingly, PQM-1 and DAF-16/FoxO occupy the nucleus in a mutually exclusive and IIS-dependent manner. When IIS is intact, PQM-1 resides in the nucleus, activating growth and development genes, while DAF-16/FoxO is in the cytoplasm. Under stress or conditions of reduced IIS, DAF-16/FoxO enters the nucleus, inducing the expression of stress-response genes, and PQM-1 is primarily cytoplasmic. While PQM-1 is regulated by IIS, DAF-16 and PQM-1 also have an influence on the nuclear localization of one another, as the loss of each increases the nuclear occupancy of the other (<link linkend="bib263">Tepper et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID23911329-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6-13">
<title>FoxO regulators in other organisms</title>
<para>The conserved gene Melted was identified in a gain-of-function screen for genes that affect cell growth in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib262">Teleman et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID16054033-->). Melted mutants are smaller than wild-type flies; however, in contrast to <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> mutants with reduced IIS (<link linkend="bib25">Bohni et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID10399915-->), they have reduced triglyceride stores. The Melted protein contains a C-terminal PH domain that mediates plasma membrane localization. Melted binds to dFoxO and promotes insulin-dependent localization of dFoxO to the plasma membrane. Accordingly, transcript levels of the dFoxO target gene 4E-BP are elevated in Melted mutants. Both the increase in 4E-BP expression as well as the reduction in total body triglycerides observed in Melted mutants are suppressed by mutations in dFoxO. These observations suggest that Melted controls fat metabolism by regulating the expression of dFoxO target genes (<link linkend="bib262">Teleman et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID16054033-->). Although the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Melted ortholog <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=K10B4.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">K10B4.3</ulink> has not yet been implicated in IIS, RNAi of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=K10B4.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">K10B4.3</ulink> extends <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> life span (<link linkend="bib88">Hamilton et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID15998808-->). Whether or not this phenotype requires <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> is not known.</para>
<para>A screen for modulators of <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> FoxO (dFoxO) activity has revealed the role of two conserved pathways in dFoxO regulation. RNAi of <emphasis>Drosophila ksr</emphasis> (<emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>k</emphasis></emphasis>inase <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>s</emphasis></emphasis>uppressor of <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>R</emphasis></emphasis>as) enhances the dFoxO gain-of-function phenotype by reducing sensitivity to insulin, thus promoting dFoxO nuclear translocation (<link linkend="bib305">Zhang et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID22242005-->). <emphasis>ksr</emphasis> was first identified as a protein that is required for Ras pathway action in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib132">Kornfeld et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID8521514-->; <link linkend="bib252">Sundaram and Han, 1995</link><!--: PMID8521513-->; <link linkend="bib264">Therrien et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID8521512-->). Accordingly, RNAi of <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> MEK also reduced sensitivity to insulin. Thus, the <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> Ras/Raf/MEK pathway antagonizes FoxO action (<link linkend="bib305">Zhang et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID22242005-->). Whether the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Ras pathway (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RTKRasMAPKsignaling.2/RTKRasERKsignal.html">Canonical RTK-Ras-ERK signaling and related alternative pathways</ulink>) regulates DAF-16/FoxO activity is not known.</para>
<para>This same screen revealed a role for endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress in dFoxO regulation. ER stress activates dFoxO by inducing dFoxO phosphorylation and subsequent nuclear translocation. dFoxO activation by ER stress requires phosphorylation of dFoxO at serine 243 by the ER-stress-dependent kinase PERK. PERK also phosphorylates human FoxO1 <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> and potentiates FoxO1 activity in human cells, suggesting that FoxO regulation by ER stress is evolutionarily conserved (Zhang et al., 2013). A role for the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> PERK ortholog PEK-1 in DAF-16/FoxO regulation and life span control has not yet been established, and the PERK phosphorylation site in dFoxO does not appear to be conserved in DAF-16/FoxO. However, ER stress likely influences DAF-16/FoxO activity, as the ER-stress-activated transcription factor XBP-1 is required for life span extension in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants and collaborates with DAF-16/FoxO to regulate gene expression (<link linkend="bib93">Henis-Korenblit et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20460307-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>Other transcription factors regulated by IIS</title>
<para>Although genetic analysis indicates that DAF-16/FoxO is the major transcriptional output of IIS, other transcription factors that participate in the regulation of DAF-16/FoxO target gene expression are also regulated by IIS. For example, HSF-1, the heat shock transcription factor that controls stress-induced gene expression (<link linkend="bib183">Morley and Morimoto, 2004</link><!--: PMID14668486-->), extends life span in a DAF-16/FoxO-dependent manner when overexpressed (<link linkend="bib104">Hsu et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12750521-->) and delays the onset of protein aggregation in animals expressing a fluorescent protein containing polyglutamine repeats (<link linkend="bib182">Morley et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID12122205-->; <link linkend="bib104">Hsu et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12750521-->). HSF-1 and DAF-16/FoxO promote longevity by binding to HSEs (heat shock elements) and DBEs (DAF-16/FoxO binding elements) in the promoters of genes encoding small heat shock proteins (<link linkend="bib104">Hsu et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID12750521-->). Notably, HSF-1 is required for longevity induced by reduced IIS. Recent work has shown that IIS regulates HSF-1 activity by promoting the formation of a multimolecular complex containing the conserved proteins DDL-1 and DDL-2 that sequesters HSF-1 in the cytoplasm (<link linkend="bib39">Chiang et al., 2012a</link><!--: PMID22265419-->) (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>).</para>
<para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Nrf family transcription factor SKN-1 is an important component of the organismal response to oxidative stress and is required for life span extension by dietary restriction or inhibition of the TORC1 or TORC2 pathways (<link linkend="bib4">An and Blackwell, 2003</link><!--: PMID12869585-->; <link linkend="bib22">Bishop and Guarente, 2007</link><!--: PMID17538612-->; <link linkend="bib231">Robida-Stubbs et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID22560223-->). SKN-1 regulates genes that defend against oxidative and xenobiotic stress, along with many genes involved in protein homeostasis and metabolism (<link linkend="bib5">An et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID16251270-->; <link linkend="bib118">Kahn et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID17714076-->; <link linkend="bib211">Oliveira et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19575768-->; <link linkend="bib152">Li et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21695230-->; <link linkend="bib215">Paek et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID23040073-->). Some of its downstream targets appear to be shared with DAF-16/FoxO (<link linkend="bib5">An et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID16251270-->; <link linkend="bib211">Oliveira et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19575768-->). As is the case for HSF-1, SKN-1 also contributes to life span extension in animals with reduced IIS (<link linkend="bib271">Tullet et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18358814-->). IIS inhibits SKN-1 activity by promoting its cytoplasmic sequestration through an RxRxxS/T motif that can be directly phosphorylated by Akt/PKB and related kinases (<link linkend="bib271">Tullet et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18358814-->) (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>).</para>
<para>The zinc finger transcription factor PQM-1 (Section 5.12) and DAF-16/FoxO are regulated reciprocally by IIS, as their nuclear localization appears to be mutually exclusive, and loss of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> drives PQM-1 into the cytoplasm (<link linkend="bib263">Tepper et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID23911329-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>Components of IIS in other organisms that are conserved in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
<para>Other than <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, insulin signaling has been most intensively studied in mammals and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>. This section highlights evolutionarily conserved proteins and pathways that have been implicated in IIS in mammals and/or flies but do not have clear functions in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> IIS.</para>
<sect2 id="sec8-1">
<title>Ras signaling</title>
<para>In mammalian cells, insulin and IGF-1 activate Ras signaling through the recruitment and phosphorylation of IRS and Shc adaptor proteins. Tyrosine phosphorylation of IRS proteins and Shc by ligand-activated insulin and IGF-1 receptors generates binding sites for the Grb2/Son-of-Sevenless (Sos) complex, thus promoting the translocation of the Sos guanine nucleotide exchange factor into proximity with membrane-associated Ras. Sos activates Ras by catalyzing the exchange of GDP bound to Ras for GTP. GTP-bound Ras activates the Raf/MEK/MAPK kinase cascade, leading to transcriptional regulatory events that promote mitogenesis (<link linkend="bib245">Siddle, 2011</link><!--: PMID21498522-->).</para>
<para>In <emphasis>C. elegan</emphasis>s, the role of Ras in insulin signaling is less clear. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> LET-60/Ras has a well-established role in vulval cell fate specification during larval development, where it is regulated by the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) ortholog LET-23 (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RTKRasMAPKsignaling.2/RTKRasERKsignal.html">Canonical RTK-Ras-ERK signaling and alternative pathways</ulink>). Based on the mammalian paradigm, DAF-2/IGFR activation would be predicted to activate LET-60/Ras. If activated LET-60/Ras transduces signals from DAF-2/IGFR, then reduction of LET-60/Ras signaling should promote dauer arrest and/or extend life span, whereas increases in LET-60/Ras activity should suppress the dauer-constitutive and life span extension phenotypes caused by reduced IIS. However, unlike <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000090;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>/PI3K, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003965;class=Gene" role="_blank">pdk-1</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000102;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> loss-of-function mutants, which have a dauer-constitutive phenotype, LET-60/Ras pathway loss-of-function mutations do not cause dauer arrest, suggesting that the PI3K/Akt pathway is the major output of DAF-2/IGFR. However, Ras pathway mutations do influence dauer arrest modestly in some (but not all) mutants with reduced IIS. For example, the <emphasis>let-60(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00089919;class=Variation" role="_blank">n1046</ulink>)</emphasis> gain-of-function (gf) mutation can suppress dauer arrest in <emphasis>daf-2(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088709;class=Variation" role="_blank">m577</ulink>)</emphasis> mutants, and loss-of-function mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002335;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-60</ulink>/Ras</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004774;class=Gene" role="_blank">sem-5</ulink>/Grb2</emphasis> enhance <emphasis>daf-2(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088709;class=Variation" role="_blank">m577</ulink>)</emphasis> mutant phenotypes (<link linkend="bib196">Nanji et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID16164423-->). These data suggest that Ras signaling has a weak modulatory effect on IIS in the control of dauer arrest. <emphasis>let-60(gf)</emphasis> also partially suppresses the dauer-constitutive phenotype of the <emphasis>age-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088893;class=Variation" role="_blank">mg44</ulink>)</emphasis> null mutant, indicating that Ras pathway action in dauer regulation is independent of PI3K (<link linkend="bib196">Nanji et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID16164423-->).</para>
<para>Ras pathway mutations have complex effects on life span extension in the context of reduced IIS. In contrast to the enhancement of the dauer-constitutive phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants by LET-60/Ras signaling loss of function, these same mutations partially suppress life span extension of <emphasis>daf-2(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088709;class=Variation" role="_blank">m577</ulink>)</emphasis>. Thus, Ras signaling has opposite effects on dauer-constitutive and life span extension phenotypes in the context of reduced IIS. Although <emphasis>let-60(gf)</emphasis> extends maximum life span in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mutants, it has no effect on mean life span due to increases in early adult mortality in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>; let-60(gf)</emphasis> double mutants (<link linkend="bib196">Nanji et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID16164423-->). The interpretation of these life span experiments is further complicated by the pleiotropies of Ras pathway mutants (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RTKRasMAPKsignaling.2/RTKRasERKsignal.html">Canonical RTK-Ras-ERK signaling and related alternative pathways</ulink>).</para>
<para>Whether Ras acts downstream of or parallel to DAF-2/IGFR to influence dauer arrest and life span remains uncertain: there is no biochemical data directly implicating the LET-60/Ras pathway as a target of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> IIS, and there are differences in the functions of mammalian and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Shc (<link linkend="bib201">Neumann-Haefelin et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18832074-->) and IRS proteins (<link linkend="bib293">Wolkow et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID12393910-->). It is also not known whether LET-60/Ras influences the activity of DAF-16/FoxO.</para>
<para>Although the Ras/MEK/MAPK pathway activated by insulin and IGF-1 in mammals appears to play a minor role in dauer regulation and life span control by IIS in <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> DAF-2/IGFR does regulate this pathway in other contexts. For example, DAF-2/IGFR signaling potentiates Ras/MEK/MAPK signaling in vulval precursor cells during vulval development by promoting phosphorylation of the MAP kinase MPK-1 in an Akt- and DAF-16/FoxO-independent manner (<link linkend="bib195">Nakdimon et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID22916028-->), and DAF-2/IGFR signaling to LET-60/Ras may promote starvation-enhanced ribosome biogenesis in males (<link linkend="bib256">Tan et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21907144-->). Conversely, in muscle, DAF-2/IGFR signals through AGE-1/PI3K and PDK-1 to inhibit Ras/MEK/MAPK-dependent protein degradation (<link linkend="bib254">Szewczyk et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17290229-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec8-2">
<title>Shc</title>
<para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome encodes two Shc homologs, one of which (SHC-1) has been studied in some detail (<link linkend="bib181">Mizuno et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18809575-->; <link linkend="bib201">Neumann-Haefelin et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18832074-->). In contrast to mammalian Shc, which is a critical mediator of Ras pathway activation by insulin (<link linkend="bib227">Ravichandran, 2001</link><!--: PMID11607835-->), <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> SHC-1 does not appear to regulate Ras activity, as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00018788;class=Gene" role="_blank">shc-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants do not have phenotypes reminiscent of Ras pathway loss-of-function mutants (<link linkend="bib181">Mizuno et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18809575-->). This may be a consequence of the fact that the major tyrosine phosphorylation sites on mammalian Shc that engage the GRB2/Sos complex are not conserved in SHC-1 (<link linkend="bib165">Luzi et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID11088019-->). This observation may also explain why Ras activation plays a more significant role in mammalian IIS than it appears to in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> IIS. Although SHC-1 coprecipitates with DAF-2/IGFR when both are overexpressed in mammalian cell culture (<link linkend="bib201">Neumann-Haefelin et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18832074-->), the biological significance of this interaction is not known.</para>
<para>SHC-1 has an established role in promoting stress resistance through a physical interaction with the MAP kinase kinase MEK-1 (<link linkend="bib181">Mizuno et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18809575-->; <link linkend="bib201">Neumann-Haefelin et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18832074-->). This interaction is required for resistance to heavy metals (<link linkend="bib181">Mizuno et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18809575-->) and may also promote the nuclear translocation of DAF-16/FoxO in the context of environmental stress (<link linkend="bib181">Mizuno et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18809575-->; <link linkend="bib201">Neumann-Haefelin et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18832074-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec8-3">
<title>TOR</title>
<para>The mammalian Target of Rapamycin (mTOR) is a conserved serine/threonine kinase that acts in distinct multiprotein complexes to control cell growth in response to nutrient availability and energy balance. mTOR functions primarily through two complexes, known as TORC1 (<emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>T</emphasis></emphasis>arget <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>o</emphasis></emphasis>f <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>R</emphasis></emphasis>apamycin <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>C</emphasis></emphasis>omplex) and TORC2, which consist of common and distinct components. In mammalian cells, insulin and IGF-1 activate TORC1 through phosphorylation and inactivation of the TSC2 tumor suppressor by Akt (<link linkend="bib14">Avruch et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID17041622-->). By contrast, whether and how IIS couples to TOR in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is unclear. The long life span of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002583;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-363</ulink>/TOR</emphasis> RNAi-treated animals is independent of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib276">Vellai et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID14668850-->). Instead, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002583;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-363</ulink>/TOR</emphasis> appears to be part of the dietary restriction-mediated (DR) life span extension pathway (<link linkend="bib89">Hansen et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17266679-->; <link linkend="bib42">Ching et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20456299-->), which is genetically separable from IIS in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and requires the FoxA ortholog PHA-4 rather than DAF-16/FoxO (<link linkend="bib217">Panowski et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17476212-->). The presence of nutrients promotes LET-363/TOR activity, which in turn represses PHA-4/FoxA activity, promoting development and normal life span (<link linkend="bib243">Sheaffer et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18804378-->). Mutants of both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002583;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-363</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000911;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-15</ulink>,</emphasis> the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog of RAPTOR (<emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>r</emphasis></emphasis>egulatory <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>a</emphasis></emphasis>ssociated <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis>p</emphasis></emphasis>rotein of mTOR), form dauer-like larvae constitutively, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000911;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-15</ulink>/RAPTOR</emphasis> heterozygotes are long-lived, like <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002583;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-363</ulink>/TOR</emphasis> knockdown animals (<link linkend="bib115">Jia et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15253933-->). While there is no data to suggest that LET-363/TOR is regulated by IIS, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000911;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-15</ulink>/RAPTOR</emphasis> expression is negatively regulated by DAF-16/FoxO (<link linkend="bib115">Jia et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15253933-->), providing a mechanism by which the IIS and DR pathways could be coordinated in growth vs. longevity decisions.</para>
<para>Although evidence is lacking for the regulation of TOR activity by IIS in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, TORC1 may regulate DAF-16/FoxO activity independently of IIS. The effect of TORC1 activation on DAF-16/FoxO appears to be context-dependent. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog of the TORC1 activator Rheb, RHEB-1<emphasis>,</emphasis> is required for life span extension in response to intermittent fasting (IF) (<link linkend="bib100">Honjoh et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19079239-->). IF induces DAF-16/FoxO nuclear translocation and DAF-16/FoxO target gene expression, both of which require RHEB-1 and LET-363/TOR activity (<link linkend="bib100">Honjoh et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19079239-->). By contrast, under <emphasis>ad lib</emphasis> feeding conditions, TORC1 inhibition extends life span in a DAF-16/FoxO-dependent manner and promotes DAF-16/FoxO target gene expression and nuclear translocation of the D/F/H isoform of DAF-16/FoxO (<link linkend="bib231">Robida-Stubbs et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID22560223-->). Thus, TORC1 promotes DAF-16/FoxO activity in the context of IF but inhibits DAF-16/FoxO activity in well-fed animals. The molecular basis for DAF-16/FoxO regulation by TORC1 has not been established.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec8-4">
<title>Glucose transport</title>
<para>In mammals, insulin regulates glucose uptake in muscle and adipose tissue by promoting the translocation of the facilitative glucose transporter GLUT4 to the plasma membrane. This process requires the activation of both canonical IRS/PI3K/Akt signaling as well as a PI3K-independent pathway involving the tyrosine phosphorylation of the adaptor proteins APS and Cbl and the subsequent nucleation of a protein complex that activates the small GTPase TC10 in plasma membrane lipid rafts (<link linkend="bib36">Chang et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID16307172-->). Although the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome encodes members of the glucose transporter superfamily, there is no evidence to suggest that glucose transport is regulated by ILPs or DAF-2/IGFR. This may be due in part to the fact that, although the PI3K/Akt pathway and Cbl are conserved in <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome appears to lack an ortholog of APS, the tyrosine phosphorylation of which facilitates insulin-dependent recruitment of Cbl to the insulin receptor and insulin-dependent translocation of GLUT4 to the plasma membrane (<link linkend="bib159">Liu et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID11997497-->). However, glucose does shorten <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> life span in an IIS-dependent manner, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002090;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-7</ulink></emphasis> expression increases upon glucose exposure, suggesting that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> IIS does respond to changes in glucose levels (<link linkend="bib145">Lee et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID19883616-->)<emphasis>.</emphasis></para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec8-5">
<title>Cytohesins</title>
<para>The <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> cytohesin ortholog Steppke was identified as a gene required for larval growth (<link linkend="bib73">Fuss et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID17167488-->). It acts in the PI3K/Akt pathway to control dFoxO target gene expression. The triazole derivative SecinH3, which inhibits the guanine nucleotide exchange activity of cytohesins, reduces insulin-induced Akt phosphorylation and blocks insulin-dependent regulation of 4E-BP and insulin receptor transcript abundance in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> S2 cells; accordingly, SecinH3 inhibits insulin signaling in human HepG2 cells and causes hepatic insulin resistance in mice (<link linkend="bib73">Fuss et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID17167488-->; <link linkend="bib86">Hafner et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID17167487-->). Thus, cytohesins have a conserved role in promoting insulin/PI3K/Akt signaling. Although the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome contains a cytohesin ortholog (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=K06H7.4;class=Gene" role="_blank">K06H7.4</ulink>), a potential role in IIS has not been reported.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec9">
<title>System-wide integration of IIS: non-autonomy and interaction with other pathways</title>
<para>Dauer entry, longevity, and reproduction in any individual are determined by the integration of information about nutrient availability, number of neighbors (or competitors), and temperature; these variables may be interpreted as predictors of future survival and reproductive conditions. Much of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> systemic response to these environmental factors is mediated through IIS and its interactions with other signaling pathways.</para>
<sect2 id="sec9-1">
<title>IIS-mediated cell non-autonomous regulation of longevity, dauer formation, metabolism, and reproduction:</title>
<para>Larval and adult expression of a <emphasis>daf-</emphasis>2p::GFP promoter fusion has been reported in the intestine and nervous system (<link linkend="bib112">Hunt-Newbury et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17850180-->), and recent immunofluorescence studies with affinity-purified anti-DAF-2 antibodies suggest that DAF-2/IGFR is most highly expressed in neurons and in the XXX secretory cells (which produce dafachronic acid and regulate dauer formation (<link linkend="bib238">Schaedel et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID22505848-->)), with weaker fluorescence in non-neuronal tissues, such as hypodermis (<link linkend="bib128">Kimura et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID22123849-->). Using mosaic analysis (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_nomarskianatomymosaic/nomarskianatomymosaic.html">Nomarski images for learning the anatomy, with tips for mosaic analysis</ulink>), Apfeld and Kenyon found that DAF-2/IGFR acts cell non-autonomously to regulate dauer formation, longevity, and intestinal pigmentation associated with fat accumulation (<link linkend="bib8">Apfeld and Kenyon, 1998</link><!--: PMID9790527-->). To identify the site of IIS regulation of longevity and metabolism, <link linkend="bib292">Wolkow et al. (2000)</link><!--: PMID11021802--> used tissue-specific promoters to rescue <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> in specific tissues in <emphasis>daf-2(-)</emphasis> mutants. They found that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> expression in neurons and intestine, but not in muscle, rescued longevity and dauer phenotypes, while restoration in muscle rescued metabolic defects (<link linkend="bib292">Wolkow et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID11021802-->). These results suggest that DAF-2/IGFR acts primarily in the neurons to control such system-wide phenotypes as longevity and dauer formation, but may have cell autonomous metabolic functions, at least when expressed at high levels in the intestine. The reason for the apparent discrepancy between the Apfeld and Kenyon and Wolkow et al. results might be due to technical differences (such as variation and non-endogenous levels of gene expression), but together the results do suggest that IIS in neurons is critical for non-autonomous regulation of longevity and dauer formation (<link linkend="bib8">Apfeld and Kenyon, 1998</link><!--: PMID9790527-->; <link linkend="bib292">Wolkow et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID11021802-->). Furthermore, the results imply that a downstream, secondary signal likely communicates with other tissues to coordinate the dauer decision and longevity response.</para>
<para>The tissue-specific and cell autonomous roles of DAF-16/FoxO have also been investigated. The <emphasis>daf-16a</emphasis> and <emphasis>daf-16d/f/h</emphasis> isoforms are expressed in most tissues, whereas the <emphasis>daf-16b</emphasis> isoform has a more limited tissue distribution (<link linkend="sec5-1">Section 5.1</link>) (<link linkend="bib155">Lin et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9360933-->; <link linkend="bib206">Ogg et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID9353126-->; <link linkend="bib144">Lee et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11747821-->; <link linkend="bib133">Kwon et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20613724-->). Similar to the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> mosaic and neuronal rescue results (<link linkend="bib8">Apfeld and Kenyon, 1998</link><!--: PMID9790527-->; <link linkend="bib292">Wolkow et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID11021802-->), expression of DAF-16A in the nervous system restored dauer formation in a significant fraction of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> double mutant animals (<link linkend="bib153">Libina et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID14622602-->), suggesting the existence of an organism-wide response to DAF-16/FoxO activation in neurons. Intriguingly, these animals arrest as dauers in the absence of DAF-16/FoxO activity in other important tissues such as the intestine and hypodermis. When DAF-16A is expressed solely in the intestine in a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> double mutant background, life span is increased up to 60%, while its expression in other tissues, including neurons, had little to no effect on longevity (<link linkend="bib153">Libina et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID14622602-->). These results imply that DAF-16/FoxO may have tissue-specific longevity targets, or that the intestine is particularly sensitive to age-related damage (<link linkend="bib153">Libina et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID14622602-->). Currently, there is no data on the role of DAF-16/FoxO in the hypodermis, a tissue that is increasingly recognized for its role in endocrine function.</para>
<para>In addition to its longevity phenotype, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> restoration in the intestine also rescued reproductive aging, indicating a novel role for DAF-16/FoxO in this tissue (<link linkend="bib162">Luo et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20946987-->). Surprisingly, DAF-16/FoxO expression in the muscle also rescued reproductive aging, suggesting that the muscle plays a previously unappreciated role in IIS/DAF-16 regulation of reproduction (<link linkend="bib162">Luo et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20946987-->).</para>
<para>Signaling between tissues, employing both insulin-like peptides (<link linkend="bib192">Murphy et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID18025456-->) and lipophilic hormones (<link linkend="bib78">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11740945-->; <link linkend="bib114">Jia et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID11782415-->; <link linkend="bib167">Mak and Ruvkun, 2004</link><!--: PMID15084462-->), likely coordinates IIS activity and longevity state throughout the organism. For example, DAF-16/FoxO activity in one tissue can regulate its activity in other tissues, suggesting that DAF-16/FoxO regulates IIS activity in neighboring cells through downstream signaling (<link linkend="bib153">Libina et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID14622602-->). This feed-forward activation of DAF-16/FoxO (FoxO-to-FoxO signaling) in the regulation of longevity is mediated largely by the activity of the INS-7 ILP (<link linkend="bib192">Murphy et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID18025456-->). DAF-16/FoxO activity in the intestine and muscle likely activate signaling to the germline, although the nature of this signal (or signals) and its receptor is unknown. Reproductive aging is also regulated by IIS in the intestine and muscles, but the signal for this non-autonomous activity is unknown (<link linkend="bib162">Luo et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20946987-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec9-2">
<title>IIS interactions with the dafachronic acid/DAF-12 pathway</title>
<para>Genetic analysis underscores the complexity of interactions between IIS and the dafachronic acid/DAF-12 pathway (for more details on this pathway see WormBook chapter <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_dauer/dauer.html">Dauer</ulink>). Mutants that lack dafachronic acid (in which the DAF-12 nuclear receptor is unliganded) undergo dauer arrest independently of DAF-16/FoxO (<link linkend="bib78">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID11740945-->; <link linkend="bib114">Jia et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID11782415-->), suggesting that unliganded DAF-12 acts downstream of IIS. However, studies with <emphasis>eak</emphasis> mutants have shown that the expression of some DAF-16/FoxO target genes requires DAF-12 activity (see <link linkend="sec6-2">Section 6.2</link>), indicating that DAF-16/FoxO and DAF-12 may act in parallel in some contexts (<link linkend="bib306">Zhang et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID18241854-->; <link linkend="bib3">Alam et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20620993-->; <link linkend="bib59">Dumas et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20178781-->). Furthermore, whereas <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> null mutations fully suppress dauer arrest in most dauer-constitutive mutant backgrounds, including weaker <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> loss-of-function alleles such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143947;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1368</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis>daf-2(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143949;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1370</ulink>); daf-12(null)</emphasis> double mutants have a synthetic phenotype, undergoing non-dauer larval arrest at 25&#x00B0;C (<link linkend="bib58">Dumas et al., 2013b</link><!--: PMID23550118-->). Recent work on the interactions of IIS and DA/DAF-12 pathways in life span control suggest that, whereas liganded DAF-12 promotes longevity in the context of reduced IIS, unliganded DAF-12 can either shorten or prolong life span in animals with reduced IIS (<link linkend="bib58">Dumas et al., 2013b</link><!--: PMID23550118-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec9-3">
<title>IIS/TGF-&#x03B2; crosstalk</title>
<para>The TGF-&#x03B2; pathway that controls dauer arrest (see WormBook chapter <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_dauer/dauer.html">Dauer</ulink>) also regulates the expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002090;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-7</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002101;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-18</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib160">Liu et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15380030-->; <link linkend="bib242">Shaw et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17900898-->)<emphasis>,</emphasis> linking TGF-&#x03B2; dauer regulatory activity to IIS, possibly in order to coordinate dauer and longevity decisions through multiple signaling inputs (<link linkend="bib242">Shaw et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17900898-->). A recent study of the pyruvate dehydrogenase phosphatase homolog PDP-1, which acts in the TGF-&#x03B2; dauer pathway to affect insulin signaling upstream of IIS (<link linkend="bib197">Narasimhan et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID21533078-->), supports such a model of IIS/TGF-&#x03B2; signaling coordination through ILP regulation (<link linkend="bib242">Shaw et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID17900898-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec9-4">
<title>IIS coordination of reproduction and longevity</title>
<para>Communication from the soma to the germline, and from the germline back to the soma (<link linkend="bib102">Hsin and Kenyon, 1999</link><!--: PMID10360574-->; <link linkend="bib162">Luo et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID20946987-->), might enable an organism to tune its reproductive span and life span properly to adapt to changing nutrient availability (<link linkend="bib163">Luo and Murphy, 2011</link><!--: PMID21105070-->). While the signals between the tissues are unknown, IIS plays a key role in each arm of this coordinating program, highlighting its importance in the regulation of important life history traits.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec10">
<title>Conclusions and Future Directions</title>
<para>Here we have discussed the major components of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> IIS and its impact on many phenotypes and behaviors, including development, longevity, stress resistance, and reproduction. Despite the vast amount of information that study of this pathway in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has revealed, important questions remain. For example, IIS has both cell autonomous and non-autonomous functions, and the activity of IIS in each tissue is not yet known. Tissue specificity has only been addressed in a few studies, and there is a disconnect between the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/IGFR</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> results regarding their roles in particular tissues. Furthermore, most genome-wide experiments (e.g., microarrays, SAGE, ChIP-Seq) performed on whole animals have not revealed insights into tissue-specific targets of IIS and DAF-16/FoxO. In fact, many of the organismal phenotypes studied in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> IIS mutants (longevity, dauer formation, pathogen survival, stress resistance) are the result of system-wide signal integration. For most of these phenotypes, the communicating signals between tissues are still unknown.</para>
<para>IIS influences important life history phenotypes and integrates signaling information at least in part through interactions with other signaling pathways (including TGF-&#x03B2;, dafachronic acid/DAF-12, and Ras/Raf/MAP kinase pathways) and important transcription factors. Nonetheless, it is likely that the extent of these interactions is not yet fully appreciated.</para>
<para>ILPs may play a role in tissue-specific responses and coordination, but the sheer number of ILPs in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> raises another set of questions. Where do they all act? What do they all do? Why are there so many? Do they all act through DAF-2/IGFR, or are there alternative receptors for ILPs?</para>
<para>What is the cost of the increased robustness of IIS pathway mutants (said another way, why are all worms not IIS mutants?)? First and foremost, IIS mutants are slow to develop, they produce slightly fewer progeny (particularly early progeny), and they produce them over a longer period of time; together, these delays result in lower fitness when compared to wild-type worms, despite the fact that IIS mutants are more stress resistant (<link linkend="bib280">Walker et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID10830948-->; <link linkend="bib113">Jenkins et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID15590605-->). However, IIS mutants are better able to cope with stressful conditions in almost all stages of life. For example, under stressful conditions in early development, IIS controls the trigger for dauer formation, and starvation-induced L1 arrest is also IIS-dependent. With milder stresses, the same pathway can respond with protective transcriptional responses that extend somatic longevity, germline proliferation, and oocyte quality maintenance. Together, these data suggest that the responsiveness of the insulin/IGF-1-like signaling pathway may allow <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to quickly respond to stressful conditions, allowing them to live to fight, or at least to reproduce and survive, another day.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec11">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<para>The authors thank members of the Hu and Murphy labs for critical evaluation of the manuscript. CTM is the Richard B. Fisher Preceptor in Integrative Genomics at Princeton University.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec12">
<title>References</title>
<para/>
&insulingrowthsignal_ref;
</sect1>
</article>