<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 5. Establishment of epithelial cell polarity</title>
        <para>(A) In epithelial cells forming a sheet (the epidermis), individual components of the
            future CeAJ are initially found along the lateral membrane (early). Subsequently, they
            coalesce into the CeAJ apically (late). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-413;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-413</ulink> is present in epithelial precursors and
            becomes restricted to the basolateral membrane in epithelial cells while they
            differentiate. (B) In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-413" role="_blank">let-413</ulink></emphasis> mutants, ectopic electron dense junctions are found along
            the lateral membrane, suggesting that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-413;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-413</ulink> might promote apical coalescence of CeAJ
            components (see A). Apical markers of the epidermis (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CHE-14;class=protein" role="_blank">CHE-14</ulink>) and the intestine (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink>,
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=IFB-2;class=protein" role="_blank">IFB-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ERM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ERM-1</ulink>) also become gradually mislocalized along the lateral membrane,
            which might be due to the junctional defect or reflect an additional role of LET-413.
            (C) Some epithelial cells that form a tube require the activity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> (e.g., in the
            distal spermatheca), or the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZEN-4;class=protein" role="_blank">ZEN-4</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CYK-4;class=protein" role="_blank">CYK-4</ulink> complex (in arcade cells). In animals lacking
            these proteins, cell polarity is not established, CeAJ components form discrete
            speckles, and the cytoskeleton is not enriched at the prospective apical lumenal side
            (not illustrated). </para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>