<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 4. Anchoring of actin microfilaments</title>
        <para>(A) Flat-mount representation of the dorsal half of an embryo (for a more complete
            view, see <xref linkend="figure6"/>), with seam cells (light yellow) and the main dorsal epidermal
            syncytium hyp7 (pink; anterior to the left, posterior to the right). Circumferential
            actin bundles (horizontal green lines) are anchored to the CCC (blue lines). (B) In
           <emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hmp-1" role="_blank">hmp-1</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hmp-2" role="_blank">hmp-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants, actin bundles are not attached dorsally (their attachment is not
            compromised ventrally and laterally); due to morphogenetic forces, they snap back to the
            middle of hyp7. (C) In mutants for the CCC component <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-9;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-9</ulink>, the apical spectrin
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SPC-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SMA-1</ulink>, the FO components <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-19;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-19</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-10;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-10</ulink>, MFs randomly form thicker bundles, are
            not properly aligned or can locally detach from the CeAJ. (D) Schematic representation
            of two intestinal cells. (E) <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ERM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ERM-1</ulink> is required to anchor the actin cytoskeleton at the
            gut lumen. In animals strongly defective for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=erm-1" role="_blank">erm-1</ulink></emphasis>, or partially defective for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=erm-1" role="_blank">erm-1</ulink></emphasis> and
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sma-1" role="_blank">sma-1</ulink></emphasis>, or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=erm-1" role="_blank">erm-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=act-5" role="_blank">act-5</ulink></emphasis>, the lumen folds inside the cells, causing gut constrictions.
            However junctions and epithelial polarity are not affected. (F) Enlarged view of the
            intestinal lumen and brush border in wild-type animals (left), showing the localization
            of EPS-8A which binds actin barbed ends through a novel domain found at its C-terminus.
            In larvae homozygous for a strong <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=eps-8" role="_blank">eps-8</ulink></emphasis> allele or after RNAi against the <emphasis>eps-8A</emphasis> isoform
            (right), microvilli have irregular sizes and orientations or can be missing (note that
            RNAi against all isoforms is embryonic lethal, indicating that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=eps-8" role="_blank">eps-8</ulink></emphasis> might have a
            maternal component).</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>