<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 6. Structure and function of fibrous organelles</title>
        <para>(A - left) Schematized section of an animal in which the cuticle overlaying the dorsal
            epidermis was removed; muscles are oriented longitudinally, fibrous organelles (FOs)
            circumferentially. FOs are found where muscles make contacts with the dorsal and ventral
            epidermis; due to FO attachments, the epidermis flattens out in regions overlying
            muscles (50 to 100 nm in larvae; A - right) FOs correspond to a complex formed basally
            by the myotactin/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-805;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-805</ulink> receptor or apically by the homologous (see <xref
            linkend="figure2"/>) <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MUA-3;class=protein" role="_blank">MUA-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MUP-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MUP-4</ulink> receptors, the plectin/BPAG1e-like VAB-10A, the
            ankyrin-repeat protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-19;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-19</ulink>/Kank, and the intermediate filament heterodimers
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=IFB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">IFB-1</ulink>/IFA-2 or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=IFB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">IFB-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=IFA-3;class=protein" role="_blank">IFA-3</ulink>. How these proteins interact with each other is not known,
            besides that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MUP-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MUP-4</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MUA-3;class=protein" role="_blank">MUA-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-10;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-10</ulink> have potential IF-binding domains. VAB-10B, another
            MACF-like <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=vab-10" role="_blank">vab-10</ulink></emphasis> isoform present in muscle-epidermis contact areas,
            is found in comma embryos at the apical and basal plasma membrane. At later stages, it
            is unknown whether VAB-10B remains basal and apical or only apical (as in the intestine;
            see question marks). (B - left) In <emphasis>vab-10A</emphasis> mutants, muscles are not
            attached to the epidermis and collapse inside the embryo; FOs are strongly
            disorganized/absent. (B &#x02013; right) At the cellular level, the epidermis detaches from the
            embryonic sheath (or the cuticle at later stages); IFs, myotactin and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-19;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-19</ulink> have a very
            abnormal distribution or form aggregates. (C) A similar phenotype, albeit slightly less
            severe, is observed in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-805" role="_blank">let-805</ulink></emphasis>/myotactin or
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=vab-19" role="_blank">vab-19</ulink></emphasis>/Kank mutants; muscles detach, and at the cellular level, FOs
            fail to evolve from foci to circumferential lines (left), or they stretch from one seam
            to the other (right). (D) In <emphasis>vab-10B</emphasis> mutants, the distance between
            the apical and basal plasma membranes increases. At least two possibilities could
            explain this phenotype (see question marks in A-right): either in wild-type embryos two
            apical and basal VAB-10B proteins form homodimers to oppose thickening, or, as it is
            often the case in vertebrate epithelial cells, there are apico-basally oriented
            microtubules that could be anchored by VAB-10B. FO integrity is also partially defective
            in <emphasis>vab-10B</emphasis> mutants, indicating that VAB-10A and VAB-10B could be mutually interdependent
            to maintain their organization.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>