<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 3. The CeAJ and cell-cell adhesion</title>
        <para>(A) Schematic representation of known components CeAJ components. Like in vertebrates
            and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> epithelial cells
            contain two adhesion complexes, the cadherin-catenin (CCC) and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DLG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AJM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">AJM-1</ulink> (DAC)
            complexes. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is unique in three respects: (i) there is a
            single electron-dense area in the CeAJ (see <xref linkend="figure1"/>B); (ii) <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-413;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-413</ulink>
            does not colocalize with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DLG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink> (as its homologue Scribble in
            <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>); (iii) <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PKC-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CRB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CRB-1</ulink> are present at the apical membrane in tubular organs (the existence of apical
            polarity determinants in epidermal cells is an open question). CeAJs from different
            epithelia contain the same set of proteins; notable differences concern the identity of
            the classical claudin-like protein (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CLC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CLC-1</ulink> present in the pharynx, vulva and spermatheca;
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CLC-2;class=protein" role="_blank">CLC-2</ulink> present in the lateral epidermis). The DAC complex might correspond to the
            electron-density in the CeAJ. Indeed, immunogold staining experiments localize <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AJM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">AJM-1</ulink> at
            the electron density, and removal of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DLG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AJM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">AJM-1</ulink> compromise the formation or the
            integrity, respectively, of the electron dense area of the CeAJ (<link linkend="bib43">Koppen et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11715019-->; <link linkend="bib49">McMahon et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11493666-->; <link linkend="bib70">Rostaing et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14688212-->). Similar electron
            microscopy experiments with CCC components should clarify this point. (B) Once born,
            epidermal cells rapidly establish CeAJs (CCC, blue ball; DAC, red ellipse), which remain
            stable unless cells fuse. During ventral enclosure (<symbol
            role="symbolfont">&#x002B;</symbol> sign), ventral epidermal cells extend actin-rich
            filopodial extensions towards the ventral midline (green triangles), where they must
            assemble a new CeAJ with their countralateral homologues through a
            cadherin/ HMR-1-dependent recruitment of other CCC, and presumably DAC, components
            (elongated rectangles; <link linkend="bib66">Raich et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10531027-->). A similar actin-based
            process for junction formation has also been described in vertebrates (<link linkend="bib80">Vasioukhin et
            al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10660044-->). (C) Ventral cells in zygotic <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hmr-1" role="_blank">hmr-1</ulink></emphasis>,
            maternal and zygotic <emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hmp-2" role="_blank">hmp-2</ulink></emphasis> or maternal and zygotic
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hmp-1" role="_blank">hmp-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants can extend towards the ventral midline but fail to
            establish junctions. However, adhesion remains normal elsewhere between cells that
            already had assembled a CeAJ. (D) Cell-cell adhesion is not impaired in mutants lacking
            the DAC. Paracellular gate function is defective in animals lacking the claudin-like
            protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CLC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CLC-1</ulink>, a putative DAC component: pharyngeal cells fail to prevent a small
            fluorescent dye to leak between adjacent cells (pink material infiltrating between
            cells). (E) In animals lacking a CCC and a DAC protein (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HMP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HMP-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DLG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink>, or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-9;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-9</ulink> and
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DLG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink>), cell adhesion is not maintained, causing epithelial cells to round up.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>