<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % local.notation.class '| MOV'>
<!NOTATION MOV SYSTEM 'MOV'>
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'intestinefig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'intestinefig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'intestinefig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'intestinefig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'intestinefig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'intestinefig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'intestinefig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'intestinefig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'intestinefig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'intestinefig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY mov1 SYSTEM 'intestinemov1.mov' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov1legend SYSTEM 'intestinemov1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY intestine_Refs SYSTEM "intestinerefs.xml">
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="intestine_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestine<footnote>
			<para>Edited by Geraldine Seydoux and James R. Priess. Last revised December 13, 2006. Published March 27, 2007. This chapter should be cited as: McGhee, J.D. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestine (March 27, 2007), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.133.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2007 James D. McGhee. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
		<author>
			<firstname>James D.</firstname>
			<surname>McGhee<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:jmcghee@ucalgary.ca">jmcghee@ucalgary.ca</ulink></para></footnote></remark></surname>
			<affiliation><address>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Genes and Development Research Group, University of Calgary, Calgary, Alberta T2N 4N1, Canada</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
<?newpage?>
<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">The intestine is one of the major organs in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">and is largely responsible for food digestion and assimilation as well as the synthesis and storage of macromolecules. In addition, the intestine is emerging as a powerful experimental system in which to study such universal biological phenomena as vesicular trafficking, biochemical clocks, stress responses and aging. The present chapter describes some of these many and varied properties of the</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">intestine: the embryonic cell lineage, intestine morphogenesis, structure and physiology of the intestinal cell and, finally, the transcription factor network controlling intestine development and function.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>The intestine is one of the major organs of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, comprising roughly one third of the total somatic mass. Two views of the intestine are shown in <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>. <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1A</link> is a differential interference contrast image of an adult <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> hermaphrodite (actually, a gonadless-mutant) on which have been superimposed two fluorescent images: Nile red to reveal fat droplets in the intestine cytoplasm and green fluorescent latex beads to reveal the intestine lumen. <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1B</link> shows a scanning electron micrograph of an adult hermaphrodite, decapitated to allow the intestine (and a gonad) to spill from the carcass. Many additional views of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestine, especially transmission electron micrographs, can be inspected at <ulink url="http://www.wormatlas.org" role="_blank">Wormatlas</ulink>.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>At the peak of egg laying, an adult hermaphrodite converts her body mass to embryos once per day (<link linkend="bib97">Hirsh et al., 1976</link><!--; PMID 943344-->), corresponding to several million bacteria consumed, and it is likely that the majority of this mass passes through the intestine (ignoring the possibility of gas or water exchange across the cuticle). Considering that the average residence time for a bacterium within the intestine is less than two minutes (S. Ghafouri and JDM, <link linkend="bib75">in press</link>; see also <link linkend="bib7">Avery and Shtonda (2003<!--; PMID 12796460-->)</link>), the digestive and assimilative power of the worm intestine must be enormous. The present chapter aims to describe the varied aspects of intestinal biology in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, beginning with the intestinal cell lineage, development and morphogenesis, and then proceeding to the cell biology of the polarized enterocyte, to the wide range of biochemical reactions that are centred in the intestine and finally, to the transcription factor network that regulates all of these genes. Wherever possible, reference will be made to other chapters in the Wormbook that are more tightly focused on particular biological processes. The term &#x0201C;intestine&#x0201D; will be used in preference to &#x0201C;gut&#x0201D;; in other metazoons, &#x0201C;gut&#x0201D; usually refers to the entire digestive tract (pharynx, intestine and rectum, for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>).</para>
</sect1>
<?newpage?>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>The intestinal cell lineage in time and space</title>
<para>The entire intestine is produced as a clone of cells descending from a single cell, the E blastomere, of the eight-cell embryo (<link linkend="bib52">Deppe et al., 1978</link>; <link linkend="bib219">Sulston et al., 1983</link>). The customary schematic view of the E lineage is shown on the left side of <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>. The right side of <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link> depicts the more realistic view of the intestinal lineage described by <link linkend="bib136">Leung et al (1999)</link>, which involves a series of cell divisions precisely oriented in three dimensions, together with short range cell migrations (intercalations) and dramatic intracellular polarizations. In the current section, we will consider only the cellular events that produce the intestine (<link linkend="bib136">Leung et al., 1999</link>). The molecular mechanisms by which the E blastomere becomes specified will be described in a future Wormbook chapter by J. Rothman and M. Maduro and will also be summarized below in the section on transcriptional regulation.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="5.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The first division of the E blastomere takes place on the surface of the embryo and produces an anterior daughter <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink> and a posterior daughter <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink> (see <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink> then migrate into the embryo during gastrulation (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_gastrulation/gastrulation.html" role="_blank">Gastrulation in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). The direction of the second cell division of the E lineage is left-right and provides the basis for the bilateral symmetry of the intestine; i.e., the left pair of cells, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Eal;class=Cell" role="_blank">Eal</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Epl;class=Cell" role="_blank">Epl</ulink>, produce the left half of the intestine; the right pair of cells, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ear;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ear</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Epr;class=Cell" role="_blank">Epr</ulink>, produce the right half. The third division is basically anterior-posterior but the division axis for the anterior pair of cells is skewed in the dorsal-ventral plane (see <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). After the fourth division, the intestinal primordium contains 16 cells lying in two tiers: ten cells in a dorsal tier and six cells in a ventral tier (<link linkend="bib136">Leung et al., 1999</link>).</para>
<para>At the two-tiered sixteen cell stage (see <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>), cells in the intestinal primordium become polarized (<link linkend="bib136">Leung et al., 1999</link>): intracellular components shift their relative positions, the cells change their shape and the future intestinal lumen begins to form between the two halves of the primordium. Nuclei of the 16E cells migrate towards the embryonic midline and cytoplasmic constituents (e.g., yolk granules and mitochondria) end up laterally. Despite the prominence of this nuclear migration, it is apparently not necessary: <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-83;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-83</ulink></emphasis> mutants have a functional intestine but the nuclear migrations within the intestine primordium do not occur (<link linkend="bib216">Starr et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11463371-->). The overall cellular polarization within the intestinal primordium appears to be an intrinsic property of E cells, since it can occur in isolated blastomeres (<link linkend="bib136">Leung et al., 1999</link>).</para>
<para>Formation of the intestinal lumen begins with the appearance of small cavities at the midline between the left and right sets of cells. At the same time, small membrane-bounded vacuoles (0.3 to 0.5 microns in diameter) are detected close to the apposed central membranes (<link linkend="bib136">Leung et al., 1999</link>). These vacuoles may be the same as the vacuoles described by (<link linkend="bib200">Roudier et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15998324-->), which are endosomal in origin and contain the protein VPS-27 (vacuole protein sorting).</para>
<para>After the cells in the intestinal primordium have polarized, cells in the lower tier intercalate into the cells of the upper tier but cells do not cross the midline (<link linkend="bib136">Leung et al., 1999</link>). As shown in <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>, the cell pair labelled &#x0201C;g&#x0201D; intercalates between cell pairs &#x0201C;c&#x0201D; and &#x0201C;d&#x0201D; and the cell pair &#x0201C;f&#x0201D; intercalates between cell pairs &#x0201C;a&#x0201D; and &#x0201C;b&#x0201D;. The anterior pair of cells (labelled &#x0201C;a&#x0201D; in <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>) then divide in a dorsal-ventral direction and the posterior pair of cells (labelled &#x0201C;h&#x0201D;) divide in an anterior-posterior direction, leading to the final arrangement of cells within the developing intestine: a series of nine rings referred to as &#x0201C;ints&#x0201D; (<link linkend="bib219">Sulston et al., 1983</link>; <link linkend="bib240">White, 1988</link>). The anterior ring (int1) has four cells and each of the eight more posterior rings (int2 through int9) has two cells. The basic form of the intestine at hatching is shown schematically at the bottom of <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>. A schematic view of the basic &#x0201C;int&#x0201D; unit of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestine is shown in <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link> below. The two semi-circular intestine cells (enterocytes) are attached to each other by apical junctions (<link linkend="bib136">Leung et al., 1999</link>; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_epithelialjunctionsattach/epithelialjunctionsattach.html" role="_blank">Epithelial junctions and attachments</ulink>, and see below) and share the intestinal lumen between their opposed apical microvilli-containing surfaces. Enterocytes are also attached by apical junctions to their anterior and posterior neighbours.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Intestinal morphogenesis and patterning</title>
<para>Although the intestine is usually regarded as a simple tube, there are distinct patterning and morphogenetic events within the intestine in which certain ints behave differently than other ints. For example, the cells of int1 and int2 have shorter microvilli and form a collapsible conical reservoir at the intestine anterior; int5 cells interact intimately with the primordial germline; posterior ints are the seat of the defecation cycle, and; nuclear divisions and gene expression patterns can differ along the anterior-posterior intestine axis. The first example of intestinal patterning to be considered (and the best understood at the molecular level) is the intestinal twist that involves cells of int2, int3 and int4.</para>
<sect2 id="sec3_1">
<title>Intestinal twist</title>
<para>Midway through embryogenesis, at the point when the developing intestine has 20 cells, three of the &#x0201C;int&#x0201D; rings, int2, int3 and int4, undergo a clockwise rotation (as seen facing the embryo) of approximately 90&#x000B0; (<link linkend="bib219">Sulston et al., 1983</link>); this rotation increases to approximately 180&#x000B0; by the time of hatching (<link linkend="bib218">Sulston and Horvitz, 1977</link>) but may be variable (See <ulink url="http://www.wormatlas.org/handbook/alimentary/alimentary2.htm" role="_blank">WormAtlas</ulink>). Presumably, the resulting twist allows the intestine to intertwine with the asymmetrically disposed hermaphrodite gonad. The cellular and molecular basis of this morphogenetic twist has been investigated by <link linkend="bib94">Hermann et al. (2000)</link> and by <link linkend="bib181">Neves and Priess (2005<!--; PMID 15935776-->)</link>, who have shown that the twist is the result of repeated application of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LIN-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>/Notch pathway (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_notchembryo/notchembryo.html" role="_blank">Notch signaling in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo</ulink>).</para>
<para>When the intestine primordium has four cells, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LIN-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> receptor can be detected on the surface of all four cells; no left/right asymmetry can be detected and this early phase of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> gene expression appears to be controlled by the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=END-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">END-1</ulink> GATA factor. By the 8E cell stage, however, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LIN-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> is markedly downregulated in cells of the left half of the primordium because particular MS-lineage cells expressing the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LIN-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> ligand <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LAG-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAG-2</ulink> contact the intestine primordium on the left side, not on the right side. Thus, the intestine asymmetry can be traced to MS-lineage asymmetry, which in turn can be traced to the fundamental left/right asymmetry apparent at the six cell stage of the embyo (<link linkend="bib244">Wood, 1991</link>; <link linkend="bib245">Wood et al., 1996</link>). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LIN-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> asymmetry within the early intestine primordium sets the stage for a second phase in which the actual rotation takes place; this second phase also involves asymmetric <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LIN-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> receptor but now with the alternative ligand <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=APX-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">APX-1</ulink>. Both of these interactions, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LAG-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAG-2</ulink> dependent imposition of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LIN-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> asymmetry at the 4E stage and the subsequent <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=APX-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">APX-1</ulink> dependent process of cell rotation, involve the bHLH protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=REF-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">REF-1</ulink> as a direct downstream target of Notch signaling (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_notchembryo/notchembryo.html" role="_blank">Notch signaling in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo</ulink>; <link linkend="bib181">Neves and Priess, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15935776-->). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=REF-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">REF-1</ulink> effect is ascribed to a repression of downstream genes (in particular, the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> gene itself in the first interaction) and involves the corepressor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-37;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-37</ulink>/Groucho. The decision of which cells will rotate (i.e., what sets the anterior/posterior boundary of the twist) is controlled by the Wnt pathway implicated in the anterior-posterior patterning of gene expression, as will be described in the following section.</para>
<para>Fascinating questions of cell biology remain to be addressed. For example, how do these twisting cells break contact with their neighbours, rotate through this relatively precise angle, rearrange the complex three-dimensional scaffold of apical junctions with their neighbours, and yet still manage to exert the correct degree of rotational torque necessary to impart the helical form to the overall intestine?</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_2">
<title>Anterior-posterior patterning of intestinal transcription</title>
<para>A significant number of genes are expressed in specific non-uniform patterns along the anterior-posterior axis of the intestine: for example, genes associated with the defecation pacemaker are expressed towards the intestine posterior (<link linkend="bib50">Dal Santo et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10499793-->), the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ges-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ges-1</ulink></emphasis><symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0394;</symbol>B transgene is expressed in the anterior int1 and int2 cells (<link linkend="bib206">Schroeder and McGhee, 1998</link>) and the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pho-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pho-1</ulink></emphasis> acid phosphatase gene is expressed everywhere in the intestine except in int1 and int2 (<link linkend="bib12">Beh et al., 1991</link>; <link linkend="bib70">Fukushige et al., 2005</link>). Indeed, <emphasis>in situ</emphasis> hybridization (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_protocolslargescaleishlarvae/protocolslargescaleishlarvae.html" role="_blank">Protocols for large scale <emphasis>in situ</emphasis> hybridization on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> larvae</ulink>, <ulink url="http://nematode.lab.nig.ac.jp/db2/index.php" role="_blank">http://nematode.lab.nig.ac.jp/db2/index.php</ulink>) reveals a number of clear examples where endogenous transcripts, not just reporter gene expression patterns, are expressed either in the intestine anterior, like <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ges-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ges-1</ulink></emphasis><symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00394;</symbol>B, or everywhere but in the intestine anterior, like <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pho-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pho-1</ulink></emphasis>. It is well to keep in mind that reporter genes driven by incomplete promoters often express in the posterior intestine and, to a lesser extent, in the anterior intestine (<link linkend="bib201">Ruvinsky and Ruvkun, 2003</link>; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transcriptionalregulation/transcriptionalregulation.html" role="_blank">Transcriptional regulation</ulink>); thus, such expression patterns should be treated with caution.</para>
<para>The anterior-posterior patterning of gene expression is autonomous within the intestine lineage and reflects zygotic (i.e., non-maternal) application of the Wnt pathway (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_wntsignaling/wntsignaling.html" role="_blank">Wnt signaling</ulink>, <link linkend="bib206">Schroeder and McGhee, 1998</link>), at least as worked out for the case of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ges-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ges-1</ulink></emphasis><symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00394;</symbol>B transgene. At least the major components (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WRM-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">WRM-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LIT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIT-1</ulink>, and the downstream effector <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=POP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink>) of this pathway are the same molecules studied so intensely in the earlier P<subscript><emphasis role="bold">2</emphasis></subscript>-EMS contact that specifies the intestine. Overall, the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ges-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ges-1</ulink></emphasis><symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00394;</symbol>B transgene behaves as if its transcription is activated in the intestine anterior by high levels of the HMG protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=POP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib206">Schroeder and McGhee, 1998</link>). Conversely, expression of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pho-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pho-1</ulink></emphasis> acid phosphatase gene behaves as if it is repressed in the intestine anterior by high levels of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=POP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib70">Fukushige et al., 2005</link>). Because there are no obvious <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=POP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> binding sites in either promoter, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=POP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> and the Wnt pathway may not act directly on the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ges-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ges-1</ulink></emphasis><symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00394;</symbol>B or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pho-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pho-1</ulink></emphasis> promoters but rather may exert their effects <emphasis>via</emphasis> fate changes earlier in the E lineage. As noted in the previous section, the same Wnt pathway also appears to limit the anterior-posterior extent of the intestinal twist (<link linkend="bib94">Hermann et al., 2000</link>).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_3">
<title>Intestine-germ cell interactions</title>
<para>A further example of patterning within the intestine lineage is provided by the germ cell precursors extending lobes into the int5 cells of the intestine, apparently to obtain nutrition (<link linkend="bib219">Sulston et al., 1983</link>). <link linkend="bib57">Edgar et al. (2001<!--; PMID 11133155-->)</link> found that the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pal-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pal-1</ulink></emphasis> homeobox gene (whose maternal phase specifies the fate of the C and D blastomeres (<link linkend="bib104">Hunter and Kenyon, 1996</link>) is expressed in int5 beginning from approximately 350 cells until at least hatching and perhaps this is what makes int5 different from the other ints. However, int5-specific expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pal-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pal-1</ulink></emphasis> may not reflect patterning pathways within the intestine but rather regulatory control from within the primordial germ cells: the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pie-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pie-1</ulink></emphasis> gene appears to promote this germ cell-intestine interaction and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pal-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pal-1</ulink></emphasis> expression within the intestine might then be a downstream consequence (<link linkend="bib226">Tenenhaus et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11316796-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_4">
<title>Control of DNA synthesis and patterned cell/nuclear divisions</title>
<para>At the time of hatching, the L1 intestine has 20 cells, each with a single diploid nucleus (<link linkend="bib93">Hedgecock and White, 1985</link>). At the beginning of the L1 lethargus, intestinal nuclei replicate their DNA and divide in a spatially patterned but slightly variable manner: the six nuclei of int1 and int2 neither replicate their DNA nor divide; the four nuclei of int8 and int9 may or may not replicate and divide; the ten nuclei of int 3 to int7 always replicate and divide. As a result, the late L1 intestine retains 20 cells but now has 30 to 34 nuclei, all still diploid (<link linkend="bib93">Hedgecock and White, 1985</link>). These nuclear divisions do not occur in null mutants of the heterochronic gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-14;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-14</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib98">Hong et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10688674-->) but the intestine appears to function nonetheless.</para>
<para>All intestinal nuclei endoreduplicate their DNA prior to the L1-to-L2 moult, whether or not they have just undergone one of the nuclear divisions described in the last paragraph. These endoreduplications occur without obvious chromosome condensations and are repeated before each of the three remaining moults, thereby producing the large 32C nuclei of the adult intestine (<link linkend="bib93">Hedgecock and White, 1985</link>). Presumably, the basic <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> cell cycle machinery must be involved or must somehow be modified to produce these correctly-timed endoreduplications. For example, it has been shown that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CKI-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CKI-1</ulink> (a member of a family of cyclin dependent kinase inhibitors) is involved in limiting the number of cell divisions in the intestine. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cki-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cki-1</ulink></emphasis> knockouts, either by RNAi or by chromosomal deletions, lead to &gt;30 nuclei, with the extra nuclei being produced by an extra round of division shortly before hatching (<link linkend="bib99">Hong et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9353257-->; <link linkend="bib126">Kostic and Roy, 2002</link><!--; PMID 9716524-->; <link linkend="bib73">Fukuyama et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12857852-->). Simultaneous knockout of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cki-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cki-1</ulink>,<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cki-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-35;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-35</ulink></emphasis>/Rb leads to an average of 84 intestinal nuclei (<link linkend="bib29">Boxem and van den Heuvel, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11684669-->). The effects of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cki-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cki-1</ulink></emphasis> knockdowns are seen in many embryonic lineages, not just the intestine, and this holds true for mutations/RNAi in a number of other cell cycle control genes (see reviews by, <link linkend="bib121">Kipreos, 2005</link><!--; PMID 16314866-->; <link linkend="bib124">Koreth and van den Heuvel, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15838512-->; <link linkend="bib28">Boxem, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16759361-->) or even in a calmodulin gene (<link linkend="bib111">Karabinos et al., 2003a</link><!--; PMID 14529618-->). In contrast, two independent genetic screens identified mutations that affect <emphasis role="bold">only</emphasis> the intestine; both mutations result in an approximate doubling of both intestinal nuclei and intestinal cells, caused by an interpolated round of cell division at the 8E cell stage (<link linkend="bib46">Clucas et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11747818-->; <link linkend="bib126">Kostic and Roy, 2002</link><!--; PMID 9716524-->). In spite of this intestinal phenotype, both mutants are viable and fertile. The two mutations are both maternal dominant (or semi-dominant) gain-of-function, and are caused by single amino acid changes in adjacent residues in a CDC-25.1-like cell cycle phosphatase. Although these two specific gain-of-function alleles affect only the intestine, RNAi-induced loss of function of the same gene clearly affects many lineages and indeed the protein is widespread in the early embryo.</para>
<para>Finally, we recall the observation that expression of biochemical markers in the early E lineage depends upon a critical prior round of DNA synthesis occuring in the E cell, the clonal progenitor of the intestine (<link linkend="bib58">Edgar and McGhee, 1988</link>). Perhaps it would be worthwhile to re-visit this observation in the light of the current detailed understanding of endoderm specification.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_5">
<title>Remodelling of the dauer intestine</title>
<para>In forming the dauer larva, the alternative long-surviving third larval stage, the intestine becomes radially constricted and the lumenal circumference decreases by several-fold, to the point where the microvilli can become indistinct (<link linkend="bib190">Popham and Webster, 1979</link>; <link linkend="bib1">Albert and Riddle, 1988</link><!--; PMID 3350212-->). In the L2d stage, the L2 larval stage leading up to dauer formation, the intestinal cytoplasm can be packed with electron dense &#x0201C;cytosomes&#x0201D; (<link linkend="bib190">Popham and Webster, 1979</link>; <link linkend="bib1">Albert and Riddle, 1988</link><!--; PMID 3350212-->). How loss of intestinal volume and increase in density happens is not understood but autophagy could be involved (<link linkend="bib168">Melendez et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12958363-->). It is also not known how the remodeling or the recovery pathways of the dauer intestine relate to the developmental pathway of the non-dauer intestine. The behaviour of particular mutants in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-15</ulink></emphasis> show that remodeling in the intestine can be separated from the remodeling of other tissues (<link linkend="bib1">Albert and Riddle, 1988</link><!--; PMID 3350212-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Structure of an intestinal cell</title>
<para><link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link> is a schematic representation of a <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> enterocyte, one of the pair of large, roughly centrosymmetric cells that surround the intestinal lumen and that constitute the basic unit of an &#x0201C;int&#x0201D; ring. The present section will emphasize the sub-cellular structures and molecular localizations within the enterocyte, leaving questions of function until later. The section is organized by cellular domain: (see <link linkend="sec4_1">section 4.1</link>) the apical domain including brush border and terminal web; (see <link linkend="sec4_2">section 4.2</link>) the basolateral domain including the basement membrane; (see <link linkend="sec4_3">section 4.3</link>) the apical junctions joining one enterocyte to its partner and to adjacent ints within the overall intestinal structure, and; (see <link linkend="sec4_4">section 4.4</link>) several of the intestine's organelles and inclusions. The spatial distribution of each protein discussed will be summarized on <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>, including proteins for which a role in intestine structure can reasonably be surmised (e.g., actin in microvilli) as well as proteins that were investigated for other reasons (often because of a role in neurons) but whose major site of expression then turned out to be in the intestine.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<sect2 id="sec4_1">
<title>Apical domain, the brush border and the terminal web</title>
<para>The most prominent feature of the intestinal apical domain is the microvillar brush border (see <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>) and a number of genes integral to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> microvilli have now been identified. The following summarizes the various points of interest.</para>
<para>Although it had previously been known that a YFP/GFP-tagged <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ACT-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACT-5</ulink> actin protein produced in the intestine would localize to the apical surface (<link linkend="bib23">Bossinger et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14729475-->; <link linkend="bib78">Gobel et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15177034-->). <link linkend="bib150">MacQueen et al. (2005<!--; PMID 15872090-->)</link> have now shown clearly that, at the ultrastructural level, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ACT-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACT-5</ulink> resides within the microvilli. Knockouts of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=act-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">act-5</ulink></emphasis> cause lethality shortly after hatching. The mutant intestinal cells retain normal polarity and have apical junctions but are completely devoid of microvilli. The intestinal lumen is now circular, rather than the usual squashed ellipse. Expression of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=act-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">act-5</ulink></emphasis> gene is limited to the intestine and several other cells with microvilli. Experiments to replace <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=act-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">act-5</ulink></emphasis> with other <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> actin genes were not successful, suggesting that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ACT-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACT-5</ulink> performs a unique function in microvilli (<link linkend="bib150">MacQueen et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15872090-->).</para>
<para>Proteins belonging to the ERM family (ezrin-radixin-moesin) are usually regarded as connecting the actin cytoskeleton to the plasma membrane and that is where <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ERM-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">ERM-1</ulink>, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog, is placed on <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>. Both antibody staining and GFP reporters place <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ERM-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">ERM-1</ulink> at or closely beneath the intestinal apical surface, certainly more apically disposed than are the apical junctions (<link linkend="bib78">Gobel et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15177034-->; <link linkend="bib208">Segbert et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14623435-->). RNAi to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=erm-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">erm-1</ulink></emphasis> is lethal, producing distorted intestines that appear to have adhesions across the lumen. These defects could arise from a failure in a general process of lumen formation (defects are also present in the excretory canal cell), from aberrant intercalation of cells during intestinal morphogenesis (see <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link> above) or from defects in the maturation of the apical junctions. As in the knockouts of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=act-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">act-5</ulink></emphasis>, the intestinal lumen of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=erm-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">erm-1</ulink></emphasis> knockouts is now circular rather than ellipsoidal and the microvilli are replaced by a disorganized tangle of fibrils, which may well be actin (<link linkend="bib78">Gobel et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15177034-->).</para>
<para>The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EPS-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">EPS-8</ulink> protein has been located by immunoelectron microscopy in the microvillar tips and, to a lesser extent, in the microvillar bases (<link linkend="bib48">Croce et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15470191-->). Loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EPS-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">EPS-8</ulink> function can be lethal, with obvious intestine defects: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EPS-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">EPS-8</ulink> deficient microvilli appear less dense, less rigid and generally more irregular than wildtype microvilli. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EPS-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">EPS-8</ulink> was also shown to have an actin-capping function <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> and might function in the process of quality control, somehow regulating the remarkable uniformity of microvillar length.</para>
<para>The intermediate filament protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=IFB-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">IFB-2</ulink> is the epitope reacting with the monoclonal antibody MH33 (<link linkend="bib67">Francis and Waterston, 1985</link>; <link linkend="bib112">Karabinos et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11427699-->; <link linkend="bib23">Bossinger et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14729475-->) and is located within the &#x0201C;endotube&#x0201D; (<link linkend="bib23">Bossinger et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14729475-->), a well-defined sub-apical layer within the terminal web of nematode intestines (<link linkend="bib174">Munn and Greenwood, 1984</link>). This layer abuts directly onto the inter-enterocyte apical junctions, as seen by immunoelectron microscopy. Presumably, the function of the endotube is to provide structural strength and to anchor the overlying microvilli. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome contains 11 genes coding for intermediate filaments (<link linkend="bib55">Dodemont et al., 1990</link>; <link linkend="bib54">Dodemont et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7925480-->; <link linkend="bib112">Karabinos et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 8013462-->; <link linkend="bib113">Karabinos et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11427699-->; <link linkend="bib114">Karabinos et al., 2003b</link><!--; PMID 12488092-->; <link linkend="bib113">Karabinos et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12204276-->; <link linkend="bib116">Karabinos et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14703012-->) and six are expressed in the intestine (<link linkend="bib116">Karabinos et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14703012-->); of these, three (in addition to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=IFB-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">IFB-2</ulink>) are expressed exclusively in the intestine and produce proteins that, at least from light microscopy, are also located in the terminal web. These intestinal intermediate filaments probably function redundantly; intestinal malformations can be observed when several of the intermediate filament genes are simultaneously targeted by RNAi (<link linkend="bib116">Karabinos et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14703012-->).</para>
<para>Electron micrographs show a fuzzy layer of material encasing the microvilli and extending slightly into the intestinal lumen (see <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). Presumably this layer corresponds to the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> glycocalyx or &#x0201C;peritrophic matrix&#x0201D; (<link linkend="bib135">Lehane, 1997</link><!--; PMID 15012322-->), a complex, relatively unstructured collection of highly modified glycoproteins that serves several critical functions, including: (i) to protect the microvillar surfaces from mechanical injury or from pathogenic attack (see below); (ii) to serve as a filter allowing only digestion products to reach the absorptive surfaces, and; (iii) to provide a scaffold for presenting digestive enzymes to the contents of the intestinal lumen. The ultrastructure of this layer has been investigated in several nematodes, including <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib18">Borgonie et al., 1995</link>) and chemical stains reveal both heparin sulfate and dermatan sulfate in the region of the terminal web and brush border (<link linkend="bib205">Schimpf et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10461863-->). Several lectins have been shown to bind to the edge of the intestinal lumen, some in an anterior-posteriorly patterned manner (<link linkend="bib20">Borgonie et al., 1994</link>; <link linkend="bib19">Borgonie et al., 1997</link>).</para>
<para>A number of further proteins show distinct apical localization within the intestine but may not play a primary role in enterocyte structure. Many of these proteins could be equally well discussed in later sections on digestion, metabolism, channels and transporters but are described here because what is presently known about their subcellular distribution appears more striking than what is known about their function:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PKC-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink>, a <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> atypical protein kinase C, is tightly localized to the apical surface of the intestine (<link linkend="bib136">Leung et al., 1999</link>; <link linkend="bib24">Bossinger et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 9778533-->; <link linkend="bib78">Gobel et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15177034-->; <link linkend="bib234">Van Furden et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15242805-->). Together with the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PAR-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PAR-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> proteins so critical in establishing the fundamental asymmetry of the early embryo (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_gastrulation/gastrulation.html" role="_blank">Gastrulation in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PKC-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink> apical localization persists from mid-embryogenesis into adulthood and thus is unlikely to function only in the establishment of the intestinal apical-basal polarity (<link linkend="bib247">Wu et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9045693-->). A protein (CKA1 for C kinase adaptor) was identified in a two-hybrid screen as interacting with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PKC-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink> and is thought to anchor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PKC-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink> to the cell membrane (<link linkend="bib255">Zhang et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 10854422-->). CKA1 is highly expressed in the intestine and shows significant sequence similarity to Drosophila and mouse Numb proteins.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The copine protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GEM-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">GEM-4</ulink> (a calcium dependent phosphatidylserine binding protein) is widespread in the embryo but after hatching, most <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GEM-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">GEM-4</ulink> is located in the intestinal brush border (<link linkend="bib44">Church and Lambie, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14573470-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MTM-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">MTM-6</ulink> is one of the five myotubularins in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (phosphatidylinositol(3) phosphate phosphatases). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MTM-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">MTM-6</ulink> is present almost exclusively in the intestine and is strongly localized to the apical membrane, consistent with roles in endocytosis and in controlling the level of inositol phosphates (<link linkend="bib249">Xue et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12788949-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>High levels of dynamin are associated with the lumenal surface of the intestine, consistent with high rates of endocytosis associated with retrieving food from the intestinal lumen (<link linkend="bib130">Labrousse et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9802908-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SEL-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SEL-1</ulink> protein, originally identified through suppression of mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis>, can be detected in vesicles concentrated near the apical surface of intestinal cells (<link linkend="bib84">Grant and Greenwald, 1997</link><!--; PMID 9043078-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Following heat shock, the small HSP16 proteins localize to discrete cytoplasmic structures bordering the intestinal lumen (<link linkend="bib53">Ding and Candido, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11001875-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>There must be many additional proteins attached to the intestine lumenal surface but only a small fraction have been identified: e.g., the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PHO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHO-1</ulink> intestinal acid phosphatase GPI-anchored to the intestine lumenal surface (<link linkend="bib12">Beh et al., 1991</link>; <link linkend="bib70">Fukushige et al., 2005</link>), the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OPT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">OPT-2</ulink>/PEP-2 peptide transporter (<link linkend="bib179">Nehrke, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12021279-->; <link linkend="bib167">Meissner et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15123614-->), the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=VHA-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">VHA-6</ulink> vacuolar ATPase subunit (<link linkend="bib184">Oka et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11441002-->) and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NHX-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHX-2</ulink> sodium-hydrogen exchanger (<link linkend="bib180">Nehrke and Melvin, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11078724-->; <link linkend="bib179">Nehrke, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12021279-->). Several of these proteins will be discussed in later sections.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_2">
<title>Basolateral domain</title>
<para>The basement membrane surrounding the intestine (see <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>) has three of the four major constitutents found in other <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> basement membranes: laminin <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> and <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol> chains (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_basementmb/basementmb.html" role="_blank">Basement membranes</ulink>; <link linkend="bib102">Huang et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783803-->; <link linkend="bib110">Kao et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16376872-->), nidogen/entactin (<link linkend="bib109">Kang and Kramer, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10811890-->) and type IV collagen (<link linkend="bib83">Graham et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9194814-->), all detected on the surface of the intestine beginning in early morphogenesis phase. Interestingly, type IV collagen is not synthesized in the intestine but rather in muscles and in somatic gonads (<link linkend="bib83">Graham et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9194814-->), from which the product must be able to diffuse through the pseudocoelom to assemble into the basement membrane covering the intestine as well as the pharynx. In contrast, perlecan assembly appears to be cell-autonomous (<link linkend="bib172">Moerman et al., 1996</link>) but is not found in the basement membrane of the intestine (<link linkend="bib182">Norman and Moerman, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11071784-->). Longitudinal tracts of hemicentin, a large member of the immunoglobulin superfamily, are produced by muscles and gonads and apparently mechanically anchor the intestine, probably via the intestinal basement membrane, to the regions between muscles and hypodermis (<link linkend="bib235">Vogel and Hedgecock, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11222143-->).</para>
<para>The following proteins have been associated with the basolateral domain of intestine cells:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LET-413;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-413</ulink>, the homolog of <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> scribble (<link linkend="bib133">Legouis et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10655601-->; <link linkend="bib134">Legouis et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14578922-->; <link linkend="bib23">Bossinger et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14729475-->; <link linkend="bib208">Segbert et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14623435-->) is distributed throughout the basolateral domain. Depletion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LET-413;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-413</ulink> causes the apical junctions to become extended and discontinuous; more dramatically, apical markers such as the entire terminal web, now extend to the basolateral surface (<link linkend="bib133">Legouis et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10655601-->; <link linkend="bib166">McMahon et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11437447-->; <link linkend="bib23">Bossinger et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14729475-->). Thus <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LET-413;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-413</ulink> appears to act as a fence to confine the apical domain but has also been proposed to function in polarized protein trafficking (<link linkend="bib133">Legouis et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10655601-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NFM-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">NFM-1</ulink>, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of neurofibrularin, is located throughout the basolateral domain, a distribution more-or-less complementary to that of its relative <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ERM-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">ERM-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib78">Gobel et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15177034-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Syntaxin is expressed strongly in neurons but is also detected on the basolateral surface of the intestine (<link linkend="bib202">Saifee et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9614171-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=INX-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">INX-3</ulink> is a gap junction channel protein, widely expressed in the embryo. At the comma stage, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=INX-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">INX-3</ulink> becomes strongly (if transiently) concentrated to the membranes between intestine cells (<link linkend="bib215">Starich et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12679112-->).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_3">
<title>Apical junctions</title>
<para>Discrete electron dense regions can be detected just beneath the apical, lumenal surface of the intestinal cells, joining each cell to its neighbour (<link linkend="bib133">Legouis et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10655601-->). The nomenclature of these structures has changed over the years but they are now generally referred to as &#x0201C;apical junctions&#x0201D;. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> apical junctions are regarded as the counterpart of the bipartite cell junctions seen in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> epithelia (zonula adherens and septate junctions) and the tripartite structures seen in vertebrate epithelia (tight junctions, zonula adherens and desmosomes). Indeed, many of the proteins found in fly and vertebrate cell junctions have clear homologs in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and this is how many of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> components were identified. However, the function of each component and its position in the assembly pathway in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> epithelia can differ markedly from other systems. As particular examples, depletion of cadherins, catenins and proteins such as crumbs (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CRB-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CRB-1</ulink>) has disasterous consequences for fly epithelia but relatively minor consequences in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestine (<link linkend="bib47">Costa et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9133443-->; <link linkend="bib24">Bossinger et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 9778533-->). One particular view of the relative positioning of proteins and protein complexes within the apical junctions, is shown in <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>. The WormBook chapter by Labouesse (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_epithelialjunctionsattach/epithelialjunctionsattach.html" role="_blank">Epithelial junctions and attachments</ulink>) provides a much more detailed discussion of the important topic of apical-basal polarity in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> epithelia, including the intestine.</para>
<para>Two other interesting genes are highly expressed in the intestine, with the encoded proteins apparently located in the apical junctions:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EGL-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-8</ulink> is a phospholipaseC&#x000DF; with a documented function in the nervous system (<link linkend="bib171">Miller et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10571227-->) and may play a role in oscillating Ca<superscript>++</superscript> signaling (see below).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LIN-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-7</ulink> is a PDZ-containing protein well studied for its interactions with the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LET-23;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> receptor tyrosine kinase in vulva induction (<link linkend="bib212">Simske et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8612272-->).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_4">
<title>Intestinal organelles</title>
<para>The well-known birefringent &#x0201C;gut granules&#x0201D; that have served so well as markers of intestinal differentiation have been shown to be lysosome-related organelles (<link linkend="bib45">Clokey and Jacobson, 1986</link><!--; PMID 3736133-->; <link linkend="bib95">Hermann et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15843430-->). The evidence derives from staining with a number of lysosome-specific dyes and protein markers, as well as showing that gut granule formation is prevented by ablating genes whose homologs are known to function in lysosome biogenesis in other experimental systems. (<link linkend="bib95">Hermann et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15843430-->) have screened for a gut granule loss (Glo) phenotype in order to identify genes involved in lysosome formation. In some of these Glo mutants, the birefringent material is no longer retained within intestinal cells but rather is mis-routed into the intestinal lumen. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLO-1</ulink> is a RAB GTPase expressed only in the intestine and is indeed found to be associated with the granules. The identity of other genes in this pathway have suggested that gut granules may be similar to pigment granules in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> and melanosomes in humans (<link linkend="bib95">Hermann et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15843430-->).</para>
<para>Several other proteins have been associated with gut granules or with related intestinal organelles:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=VHA-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">VHA-11</ulink> protein is a subunit of a vacuolar ATPase and appears in embryonic intestinal cells at the comma stage in punctae that could be gut granules. It is proposed that VHA-11-containing vacuolar ATPase contributes to acidification of cellular compartments, crucial to intracellular sorting and endocytosis (<link linkend="bib183">Oka and Futai, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10610763-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LMP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LMP-1</ulink> is the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of mammalian &#x0201C;lysosome-associated-membrane-protein&#x0201D;. Beginning at the lima bean stage of early embryogenesis, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LMP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LMP-1</ulink> can be detected on the periphery of a class of intestinal granules that also seem to be good candidates for &#x0201C;gut granules&#x0201D; (<link linkend="bib127">Kostich et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10862717-->). In the early embryo, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LMP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LMP-1</ulink> protein is more widespread and is associated with the cell membrane and perhaps earlier stages in the endosomal compartment (<link linkend="bib95">Hermann et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15843430-->). A knockout of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lmp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lmp-1</ulink></emphasis> gene has little effect on the general health of the animal but one particular size of intestine granules is now missing (<link linkend="bib127">Kostich et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10862717-->). <link linkend="bib40">Chen et al. (2006<!--; PMID 16394106-->)</link> have described a number of new protein markers that are beginning to reveal the true diversity of vesicles in the intestine.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, like mammals, appears to have two sites of <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation of fatty acids: mitochondria and peroxisomes (<link linkend="bib89">Gurvitz et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11025529-->) and most <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> peroxisomes are found in the intestine, as shown by immunostaining for catalase (<link linkend="bib232">Togo et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10691967-->) and by electron microscopy (<link linkend="bib253">Yokota et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12376829-->). The use of RNAi to inhibit peroxisome biogenesis leads to complete L1 arrest, much like starvation (<link linkend="bib229">Thieringer et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12665560-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <emphasis>C. elegans <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pex-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">pex-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pex-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">pex-6</ulink></emphasis> peroxin genes are expressed mainly in the intestine, as shown by <emphasis>in situ</emphasis> hybridization (<link linkend="bib76">Ghenea et al., 2001</link>). In other systems, peroxins are associated with peroxisome biogenesis.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The enzyme Type II 3-oxoacyl-coA thiolase (also called sterol carrier protein) is expressed largely in the intestine and is located within the peroxisome matrix; levels of this enzyme are induced several-fold by the peroxisome proliferator drug clofibrate (<link linkend="bib156">Maebuchi et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10491098-->).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Function: towards a molecular physiology of the intestine</title>
<sect2 id="sec5_1">
<title>Digestion and metabolism</title>
<para>It is difficult to disagree with the lament that &#x0201C;unfortunately, the biology of digestion (in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>) represents something of a blind spot in this otherwise remarkably well-characterised organism&#x0201D; (<link linkend="bib237">Walker et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15896824-->). However, digestion and metabolism have been studied in other nematodes (<link linkend="bib13">Behm, 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib175">Munn and Munn, 2002</link>) and there is increasing understanding of these processes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as well. For example, analysis of a SAGE library prepared from dissected adult intestines identifies transcripts from over four thousand genes (<link linkend="bib164">McGhee et al., 2007</link>) and this list of genes must hold many keys to understanding digestion, metabolism and other aspects of intestinal physiology. In this section, we will highlight genes that are expressed highly, often exclusively, in the intestine and for which a functional role in digestion and metabolism is either known or plausible.</para>
<para>The general steps by which the animal digests its bacterial food can be surmised and are fully supported by analysis of the most highly expressed, most intestine-restricted set of genes identified in our SAGE analysis (<link linkend="bib164">McGhee et al., 2007</link>). Presumably, the first act of digestion is physical damage to the bacteria inflicted by the pharyngeal grinder (<link linkend="bib8">Avery and Thomas, 1997</link>). A small number of lysozymes (<link linkend="bib158">Mallo et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12176330-->; <link linkend="bib164">McGhee et al., 2007</link>) are highly expressed in the intestine, are probably secreted and are the likely perpetrators of the next step in digestion, degradation of the bacterial cell wall. Several saposins/amoebapores are also highly expressed in the intestine and some appear to be secreted; presumably these small pore-forming proteins are able to puncture the bacterial membranes to release contents that can now be degraded by lumenal hydrolases (<link linkend="bib10">Banyai and Patthy, 1998</link><!--; PMID 9920402-->).</para>
<para>What is known about the general properties of the lumenal environment in which digestive hydrolases must act? For example, what is the lumenal pH? Most protease activity in crude extracts likely derives from intestinal proteases (see below) and the pH optimum of this overall protease activity is approximately 5 (<link linkend="bib203">Sarkis et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID 3277541-->; <link linkend="bib74">Geier et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10491135-->). The pH optimum of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PHO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHO-1</ulink> acid phosphatase, which is GPI-anchored in the intestinal lumen, is approximately 4 (<link linkend="bib12">Beh et al., 1991</link>). These two observations suggest that the intestinal lumen must be mildly acidic. Considering that roughly half of the intestinal contents are ejected with each defecation cycle of less than one minute (<link linkend="bib7">Avery and Shtonda, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12796460-->; <link linkend="bib75">Ghafouri and McGhee, 2007</link>) and considering that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> can live in highly buffered media, the acidification capacity of the intestine must be enormous. Indeed, several vacuolar ATPase subunits are highly expressed in the intestine and, in particular, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=VHA-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">VHA-6</ulink> protein is localized to the apical surface of the intestine, where it is suggested to acidify the intestinal lumen as part of the mechanism of nutrient uptake (<link linkend="bib184">Oka et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11441002-->).</para>
<para>Proteases/peptidases appear to be more prominent than any other class of lumenal digestive hydrolases. For example, 18 of the top 80 genes expressed largely (or exclusively) in the adult intestine are proteases/peptidases and five of these are aspartic proteases (<link linkend="bib164">McGhee et al., 2007</link>). Indeed, &gt;90% of the protease activity in crude <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> extracts can be inhibited by pepstatin, a specific inhibitor of aspartic proteases (<link linkend="bib74">Geier et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10491135-->). Probably the most thoroughly characterized digestive enzyme in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is the aspartic protease <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">ASP-1</ulink>, which was shown to be expressed exclusively in the intestine; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">ASP-1</ulink> appears late in embryogenesis, reaches peak levels during the first two larval stages and declines thereafter (<link linkend="bib225">Tcherepanova et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10854422-->). Antibody staining indicated that most <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">ASP-1</ulink> protein is in the intestinal lumen, although some protein could also be detected in lysosome-like cytoplasmic punctae (<link linkend="bib225">Tcherepanova et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10854422-->). Other peptidases, some apparently quite specialized, are also highly expressed in the intestine: the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PAM-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAM-1</ulink> puromycin sensitive aminopeptidase (<link linkend="bib38">Brooks et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12421629-->), the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=APP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">APP-1</ulink> aminopeptidase (<link linkend="bib132">Laurent et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11223883-->) and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LAP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAP-1</ulink> leucine aminopeptidase (<link linkend="bib107">Joshua, 2001</link>).</para>
<para>Nematodes rely heavily on lipids for energy storage and energy metabolism (<link linkend="bib13">Behm, 2002</link>) and the intestine appears to be a major site of these biochemical activities. Lipases are highly represented on the SAGE list of intestinally-expressed genes and a number of these are likely to be secreted and function in lumenal digestion of lipids (<link linkend="bib164">McGhee et al., 2007</link>). It was mentioned in the previous section that peroxisomes are one of the two sites of fatty acid oxidation in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and most peroxisomes are in the intestine. A number of enzymes involved in lipid metabolism are highly expressed in the intestine: for example, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cln-3.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cln-3.1</ulink></emphasis> is homologous to a human gene involved in the degenerative disorder neuronal ceroid lipofuscinosis (<link linkend="bib51">de Voer et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16435200-->) and the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=spl-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">spl-1</ulink></emphasis> gene encodes sphingosine phosphate lyase (<link linkend="bib169">Mendel et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12682045-->; <link linkend="bib186">Oskouian et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15734735-->). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELO-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELO-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELO-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELO-5</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELO-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELO-6</ulink> enzymes have fatty acid elongation activities and are involved in the synthesis of polyunsaturated and branched fatty acids (<link linkend="bib123">Kniazeva et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12524338-->; <link linkend="bib122">Kniazeva et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15314147-->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has three <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00394;</symbol>-9-desaturase enzymes, expressed primarily (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink></emphasis>) or exlusively (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis>) in the intestine (<link linkend="bib34">Brock et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839188-->); single knockouts have little phenotype but the triple knockout is lethal, demonstrating an overall requirement of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> for adequate levels of unsaturated fatty acids (<link linkend="bib34">Brock et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839188-->). Finally, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GES-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">GES-1</ulink> nonspecific carboxylesterase resides in the intestinal endoplasmic reticulum (<link linkend="bib163">McGhee, 1987</link>; <link linkend="bib118">Kennedy et al., 1993</link>) and could function in lipid metabolism and/or detoxification.</para>
<para>The following list contains a brief description of other genes that are all expressed highly and often exclusively in the intestine. The list provides a hint of the enormous metabolic diversity of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestine:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NUC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">NUC-1</ulink> nuclease was originally identified because mutants retained bacterial DNA undigested within the intestine (<link linkend="bib217">Sulston, 1976</link>); (also, unpublished results of J.E. Sulston and of P. Babu, cited in, <link linkend="bib96">Hevelone and Hartman, 1988</link><!--; PMID 3228446-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NUC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">NUC-1</ulink> also functions in the removal of apoptotic corpses (<link linkend="bib248">Wu et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10716942-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TRX-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">TRX-1</ulink> thioredoxin expression in the intestine increases with starvation and aging; it is suggested that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TRX-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">TRX-1</ulink> provides protection against oxidative damage associated with the metabolically active intestine (<link linkend="bib106">Jee et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16324156-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cdd-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cdd-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cdd-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">cdd-2</ulink></emphasis> encode two cytidine deaminases highly expressed in the intestine. Similar enzymes are usually associated with pyrimidine salvage pathways but the two <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CDD-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDD-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CDD-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDD-2</ulink> have been shown also to bind RNA, thereby raising the possibility of an RNA editing pathway in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestine, perhaps similar to the editing of apolipoprotein B mRNA in the mammalian intestine (<link linkend="bib230">Thompson et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12071843-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>At least three of the 21 <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Skp1-related genes (involved in ubiquitin-mediated protein turnover) are expressed highly in the intestine, suggesting a dedicated pathway to control the degradation of intestinal proteins (<link linkend="bib250">Yamanaka et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11864566-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ftn-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ftn-1</ulink></emphasis>, one of the two <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ferritin-encoding genes, is expressed exclusively in the intestine, from embryo to adult, and is induced at the transcriptional level by exposure to iron (<link linkend="bib119">Kim et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15327944-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The three enzymes ornithine decarboxylase, S-adenosylmethionine decarboxylase and spermidine synthase are expressed primarily in the intestine (<link linkend="bib146">Luersen et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15449707-->), suggesting that the intestine provides the animal's supply of polyamines.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Calreticulin (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CRT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CRT-1</ulink>) is a calcium-binding molecular chaperone expressed predominantly in the intestine, beginning from mid-embryogenesis (after an apparently ubiquitous early maternal phase). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CRT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CRT-1</ulink> may be involved in the intestinal stress response; in addition, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=crt-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">crt-1</ulink></emphasis> genetically interacts with the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=itr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">itr-1</ulink></emphasis> IP3 receptor and shows synergistic effects both on the defecation cycle and on brood size (<link linkend="bib187">Park et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11553721-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Three p38 homologs (members of the MAPK superfamily) are arranged as a three-member operon, are expressed apparently exclusively in the intestine (<link linkend="bib15">Berman et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11703092-->) and may be involved in the intestinal stress response.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PHO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHO-1</ulink> intestinal acid phosphatase is highly similar to lysosomal acid phosphatases in other species but most of the enzymatic activity resides at the edge of the intestinal lumen (<link linkend="bib12">Beh et al., 1991</link>), retained by a GPI anchor (<link linkend="bib70">Fukushige et al., 2005</link>). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pho-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pho-1</ulink></emphasis> knockouts are maternal effect lethal, suggesting that mothers require <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PHO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHO-1</ulink> to process some nutrient that will then be supplied to the next generation embryos (<link linkend="bib70">Fukushige et al., 2005</link>).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gob-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gob-1</ulink></emphasis> gene was identified because mutant larvae have a lethally obstructed intestine; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GOB-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOB-1</ulink> turns out to be the enzyme trehalose-6-phosphate phosphatase and the lethality turns out to be caused, not by the absence of trehalose, but by a buildup of the intermediate trehalose-6-phosphate; a similar toxicity is seen in corresponding yeast mutants, emphasizing both the conservation and the expected future complexities of metabolic regulation (<link linkend="bib125">Kormish and McGhee, 2005</link><!--; PMID 16197937-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=FUT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">FUT-2</ulink> fucosyltransferase is expressed exclusively in the intestine, beginning in mid-embryogenesis; enzymes with related activity are found in mammalian intestines and are involved in sustaining bacterial flora (<link linkend="bib256">Zheng et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12163507-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GLY-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLY-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GLY-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLY-5</ulink> are N-acetylgalactosamine transferases that produce mucin type linkages (<link linkend="bib90">Hagen et al., 2001</link>).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GLY-14;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLY-14</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GLY-19;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLY-19</ulink> are N-acetylglucosaminyl transferases expressed exclusively in the intestine, from early larval stages through to adulthood (<link linkend="bib41">Chen et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 9867843-->; <link linkend="bib238">Warren et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11744632-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Deletion of the Glc-NAC transferase gene causes intestinal glycogen stores to increase several fold and intestinal fat stores to decrease several fold (<link linkend="bib91">Hanover et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16051707-->); the homologous enzyme in other systems may be involved in nutrient sensing, perhaps suggesting wider and more complex metabolic control in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as well.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<?newpage?>
<sect2 id="sec5_2">
<title>Channels and transporters</title>
<para>Combined with the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> strengths of classical genetics and RNAi, recent technical advances (e.g., the ability to image intracellular fluorescent dyes, fluorescent substrates and environmentally responsive GFP variants and the ability to directly investigate the electrophysiology of dissected intestines or intestinal cells) hold great promise for understanding nutrient transport, ionic homeostasis and complex behaviours such as defecation.</para>
<para>	The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome contains nine genes encoding sodium-hydrogen exchangers and three of the genes are expressed exclusively in the intestine (<link linkend="bib180">Nehrke and Melvin, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11078724-->). Translational fusions with GFP show that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NHX-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHX-2</ulink> is located on the apical membrane, NHX-7 is located in the basolateral membrane and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NHX-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHX-6</ulink> appears to be a mixture, basolateral at the ends of the intestine and apical in the central. Perfusion experiments, combined with intestine-specific expression of pH-sensitive GFP variants, were used to investigate how <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> controls the intracellular pH of the intestine and, more particularly, how the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NHX-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHX-2</ulink> exchanger compensates for the acidification caused by uptake of food-derived peptides (<link linkend="bib179">Nehrke, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12021279-->). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OPT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">OPT-2</ulink>/PEP-2 protein is the major <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> dipeptide transporter and is also located on the lumenal surface of the intestine (<link linkend="bib179">Nehrke, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12021279-->; <link linkend="bib167">Meissner et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15123614-->).</para>
<para>The intestine is the most likely site for the receptor/transporter responsible for uptake of double-stranded RNA from the environment when dsRNA mediated interference (RNAi) is performed by feeding or soaking. Several candidate genes have been described. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SID-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SID-1</ulink> is a multi-transmembrane protein located at the periphery of most <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> cells but appears especially enriched in cells, such as the intestine, exposed to the environment (<link linkend="bib241">Winston et al., 2002a</link><!--; PMID 11834782-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SID-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SID-1</ulink> functions cell autonomously, is necessary for systemic RNAi and can confer dsRNA uptake capabilities on heterologous cells (<link linkend="bib242">Winston et al., 2002b</link><!--; PMID 11834782-->; <link linkend="bib66">Feinberg and Hunter, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12937270-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SID-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">SID-2</ulink> is less well characterized but is also required for effective RNAi following feeding or soaking and is strongly expressed in the intestine (personal communication from Craig Hunter, cited in <link linkend="bib33">Britton and Murray (2006<!--; PMID 16616144-->)</link>). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=haf-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">haf-6</ulink></emphasis> gene encodes a half molecule ABC transporter expressed predominantly in the intestine and germline; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=haf-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">haf-6</ulink></emphasis> mutants are especially defective in RNAi administered by feeding (<link linkend="bib220">Sundaram et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16723499-->). A further eight ABC transporter genes (of the approximately 60 such genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>) show effects in RNAi uptake or spreading and several of these are expressed in the intestine (<link linkend="bib220">Sundaram et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16723499-->).</para>
<para>Brief descriptions of other intestinal transporters are provided in the following list:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABTS-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">ABTS-4</ulink> is an intestinal anion bicarbonate transporter and appears localized to the basolateral surface, at least as revealed by GFP translational fusions (<link linkend="bib210">Sherman et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15814591-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Several intestinally-expressed sulfate permeases also appear localized to the basolateral membrane (<link linkend="bib210">Sherman et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15814591-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NAC-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">NAC-2</ulink> sodium-coupled citrate transporter (similar to <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> &#x0201C;I&apos;m not dead yet&#x0201D;) is expressed throughout the intestine and is suggested to take up citrate and other TCA-cycle intermediates from the intestinal lumen for energy production (<link linkend="bib65">Fei et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14678010-->). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NAC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">NAC-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NAC-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">NAC-3</ulink> sodium-dicarboxylate anion transporters are also expressed strongly and exclusively in the intestine (<link linkend="bib64">Fei et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12480943-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Two nucleoside transporters <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ENT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">ENT-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ENT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">ENT-2</ulink> are also expressed in the intestine (and pharynx; <link linkend="bib4">Appleford et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14559923-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Two of the four TRPM-family channels in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GTL-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">GTL-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GON-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">GON-2</ulink>, are expressed predominantly in the intestine; translational fusions with GFP show that the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GTL-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">GTL-1</ulink> protein accumulates at the intestinal apical surface. Both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GON-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">GON-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GTL-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">GTL-1</ulink> play major roles in Mg<superscript>++</superscript> ion transport and homeostasis in the intestine (<link linkend="bib228">Teramoto et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16054081-->).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5_3">
<title>Defecation</title>
<para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> defecation motor program coordinates events that occur in the intestine, in muscles (especially enteric muscles) and in a small number of neurons (<link linkend="bib8">Avery and Thomas, 1997</link>). A recent review (<link linkend="bib31">Branicky and Hekimi, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16911844-->) lists <symbol role="symbolfont">&gt;</symbol>50 genes acting in one phase or another of the pathway and approximately 20 of these genes act in the intestine.</para>
<para>An important and striking finding was that the basic 45-50 second interval of the defecation cycle is associated with cyclic fluctuation in calcium ion levels in the posterior intestine; moreover, these calcium fluctuations reflect the behaviour of the inositol trisphosphate receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ITR-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">ITR-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib50">Dal Santo et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10499793-->). Recently, powerful new techniques (e.g., electrophysiology, loading with calcium sensitive dyes, expression of calcium-sensitive GFP variants, combined with RNAi) have been applied to understand the molecular basis of these calcium fluctuations. Distinct calcium conductances have been identified by patch-clamping isolated intestinal cells (<link linkend="bib61">Estevez et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12663863-->; <link linkend="bib62">Estevez and Strange, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15961418-->). Dissected intestines (as long as they remain attached at the posterior to the carcass) are capable of sustained rhythmic oscillations in calcium ion levels (<link linkend="bib60">Espelt et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16186564-->; <link linkend="bib227">Teramoto and Iwasaki, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16780946-->). The rise in calcium ion levels closely corresponds to the pBoc phase of the defecation motor program (<link linkend="bib60">Espelt et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16186564-->; <link linkend="bib227">Teramoto and Iwasaki, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16780946-->). Waves of fluorescence reflecting transient increases in calcium ions can be observed to propagate from the posterior to the anterior intestine (<link linkend="bib60">Espelt et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16186564-->; <link linkend="bib227">Teramoto and Iwasaki, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16780946-->); the oscillations in fluorescence appear tightly focused on the apical region of the intestinal cell (<link linkend="bib60">Espelt et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16186564-->). An example of this remarkable behaviour is shown in <link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link> (<link linkend="bib227">Teramoto and Iwasaki, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16780946-->). Blocking propagation of the calcium wave half-way down the intestine halts the defecation motor program, suggesting that the calcium wave is responsible for triggering the later muscle and neuronal phases (<link linkend="bib227">Teramoto and Iwasaki, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16780946-->). <link linkend="bib60">Espelt et al. (2005<!--; PMID 16186564-->)</link> have extended such assays to show that only two of the six phospholipase C genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-8</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=plc-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">plc-3</ulink></emphasis>, influence the defecation behaviour, either cycle time or cycle regularity. It was mentioned earlier that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-8</ulink></emphasis> is expressed highly in the intestine, with the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EGL-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-8</ulink> enzyme concentrated near the apical junctions (<link linkend="bib171">Miller et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10571227-->); <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=plc-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">plc-3</ulink></emphasis> is also expressed in the intestine (<link linkend="bib60">Espelt et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16186564-->). Intestine-specific RNAi was used to demonstrate that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-8</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=plc-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">plc-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=itr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">itr-1</ulink></emphasis> do indeed function in the intestine. It was further suggested that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PLC-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLC-3</ulink> is responsible for generating the inositol triphosphates that control <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ITR-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">ITR-1</ulink> activity; in contrast, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EGL-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-8</ulink> seems to function in a separate pathway to maintain the rhythmic oscillations in calcium ion (<link linkend="bib60">Espelt et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16186564-->).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="movie1" xreflabel="Movie 1">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="mov1" width="4.6in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>movie 1</phrase>
			</textobject> &mov1legend;</mediaobject>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=flr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">flr-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants were originally isolated on the basis of resistance to fluoride (<link linkend="bib117">Katsura et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 8138152-->) but turned out to have a short defecation interval. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=FLR-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">FLR-1</ulink> is a degenerin/epithelial sodium channel type of protein, expressed only in the intestine and possibly concentrated at apical membranes (<link linkend="bib222">Take-Uchi et al., 1998</link>). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=flr-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">flr-4</ulink></emphasis> gene encodes an apparently membrane-associated kinase that is expressed in the intestine (+ pharynx and several neurons) beginning from the comma stage; only intestinal expression is necessary for mutant rescue. GFP translational fusions to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=FLR-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">FLR-4</ulink> appear localized to the enterocyte membranes, especially the lateral membranes (<link linkend="bib223">Take-Uchi et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15647385-->). Proteins binding to the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ITR-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">ITR-1</ulink> protein in a yeast two-hybrid assay have also been identified in the intestine (and other tissues; <link linkend="bib236">Walker et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 12062062-->). All of the above genes are candidates for participating in signals that originate from the oscillating calcium levels in the posterior intestine and that result in contraction of the posterior body wall muscles (the pBoc phase of defecation). Cycle times are influenced by additional intestinally-expressed genes, for example, genes that influence fatty acid composition (<link linkend="bib31">Branicky and Hekimi, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16911844-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5_4">
<title>Endocytosis, exocytosis and trafficking</title>
<para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestine becomes active in endocytosis at least by the 8E cell stage, when there is transfer of yolk into the intestine primordium from the remainder of the embryo (<link linkend="bib25">Bossinger and Schierenberg, 1996</link><!--; PMID 1601175-->; <link linkend="bib254">Yu et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16740477-->). Once the animal hatches and begins to feed, nutrient uptake and trafficking must become an even larger fraction of intestinal activity, one that is just beginning to be investigated. Digestive and protective molecules must be secreted into the intestinal lumen and displayed on the apical plasma membranes. Nutrients must be taken up, either by endocytosis or by dedicated transporters. Processed food must be passed on to the rest of the animal through basolateral domains, either as building blocks or as synthesized products such as the vitellogenins. Similarly, there must be a variety of molecules, ranging from waste products to signals, passing in the opposite direction, back across the intestine basal surface from the rest of the animal. Thus one would expect that the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestine is a hotbed of endocytosis, exocytosis and trafficking in general. Consistent with such a view, the intestine cell cytoplasm is filled with rough endoplasmic reticulum but smooth ER is either rare or absent (<link linkend="bib196">Rolls et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12006669-->).</para>
<para>The process of endocytosis has been most productively studied in oocytes and in coelomocytes (<link linkend="bib63">Fares and Grant, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11872138-->) but the identified genes are probably common to most <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> cells and indeed are now beginning to be identified in the intestine (<link linkend="bib204">Sato et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15895077-->; <link linkend="bib40">Chen et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16394106-->). See also the WormBook chapter &#x0201C;<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_intracellulartrafficking/intracellulartrafficking.html" role="_blank">Intracellular trafficking</ulink>&#x0201D; which discusses the general topic of intracellular trafficking in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> in the detail it deserves.</para>
<para>Transport of a toxic derivative of linolenic acid from the intestine to the gonad may involve proteins such as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NRF-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">NRF-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NRF-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">NRF-6</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NDG-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">NDG-4</ulink> (<link linkend="bib239">Watts and Browse, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16487504-->). The <emphasis>nrf</emphasis> genes were originally identified because of an altered response to Prozac (fluoxetine) (<link linkend="bib43">Choy and Thomas, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10393123-->) and one class of these genes is proposed to be involved in transport of hydrophobic molecules from the intestine to the rest of the animal (<link linkend="bib42">Choy et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16118202-->). In particular, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NRF-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">NRF-5</ulink> is a secreted lipid binding protein similar to the cholesterol ester binding protein of higher organisms (<link linkend="bib42">Choy et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16118202-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5_5">
<title>Stress response</title>
<para>Considering the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> habitat and dietary practices, it is not surprising that the intestine is a major site of response to toxins and chemical stressors in the environment. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome has two metallothionein genes (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mtl-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">mtl-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mtl-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">mtl-2</ulink></emphasis>), both encoding proteins that are cysteine-rich but otherwise not closely related to metallothioneins described in other organisms (<link linkend="bib213">Slice et al., 1990</link>; <link linkend="bib68">Freedman et al., 1993</link>). Both genes are induced at the transcriptional level by exposure to low levels of cadmium (in the dose range of 1-100 micromolar), with a response time on the order of hours. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mtl-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">mtl-2</ulink></emphasis> gene is expressed exclusively in the intestine, from L1 larvae through to adults, and either metal exposure or heat shock are required for detectable expression. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mtl-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">mtl-1</ulink></emphasis> gene is also inducible in the intestine but has a minor constitutive component in several cells of the pharynx (<link linkend="bib68">Freedman et al., 1993</link>). Gene knockouts show that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MTL-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">MTL-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MTL-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">MTL-2</ulink> do indeed protect against cadmium toxicity (<link linkend="bib221">Swain et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15328611-->).</para>
<para>There are other pathways besides metallothioneins that protect <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> against metal toxicity and several dozen genes responding to cadmium exposure have been identified (<link linkend="bib138">Liao and Freedman, 1998</link><!--; PMID 9822667-->). One gene in particular (called <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cdr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cdr-1</ulink></emphasis> for cadmium responsive gene) has been studied in greater detail (<link linkend="bib137">Liao et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12189149-->). Like <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mtl-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">mtl-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mtl-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">mtl-2</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cdr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cdr-1</ulink></emphasis> is induced at the transcriptional level with a response time of hours but induction is highly specific for cadmium; expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cdr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cdr-1</ulink></emphasis> is exclusively in the intestine in all stages post-hatching. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CDR-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDR-1</ulink> protein is highly hydrophobic, appears novel and has been located in intestinal lysosomes (<link linkend="bib137">Liao et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12189149-->). RNAi-induced loss-of-function shows that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CDR-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDR-1</ulink> does indeed protect against cadmium toxicity. A series of related genes (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cdr-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">cdr-2</ulink></emphasis> through <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cdr-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">cdr-7</ulink></emphasis>) have now been identified (<link linkend="bib56">Dong et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15652154-->) but it is not known whether these genes are also expressed in the intestine.</para>
<para>The maternally-provided <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> transcription factor has been well studied for its role in specification of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> cell fate in the early embryo but <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> has long been suspected of having an additional role in intestinal differentiation and/or intestinal function (<link linkend="bib27">Bowerman et al., 1992</link>; <link linkend="bib26">Bowerman et al., 1993</link>). The proposed somatic function of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> is to regulate a bank of genes, possibly all intestinal, that are involved in &#x0201C;phase II&#x0201D; detoxification and that provide protection against reactive oxygen species and other environmental toxins (<link linkend="bib2">An and Blackwell, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12869585-->). One example of such a gene is <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gcs-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gcs-1</ulink></emphasis>, encoding the enzyme glutamylcysteine synthetase involved in the production of glutathione. A <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gcs-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gcs-1</ulink></emphasis>::GFP reporter construct is expressed in the intestine, pharynx and ASI neurons; intestinal expression is induced by heat or by oxidative stress and is abolished either by mutating a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> binding site in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gcs-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gcs-1</ulink></emphasis> promoter or by abolishing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> activity (<link linkend="bib2">An and Blackwell, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12869585-->). Thermal or oxidative stress causes a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink>::GFP reporter protein to relocate from intestinal cytoplasm to intestinal nuclei within minutes (see <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>). The distribution of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> protein between nucleus and cytoplasm reflects competition between two kinases: glycogen synthase kinase-3 and p38 MAP kinase (<link linkend="bib3">An et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16251270-->; <link linkend="bib105">Inoue et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16166371-->). Consistent with a function of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> in regulating intestinal detoxification genes, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=skn-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">skn-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants show shorter lifespans and are more sensitive to agents such as paraquat (<link linkend="bib2">An and Blackwell, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12869585-->).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 4</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome contains approximately 80 genes encoding cytochrome P450 proteins, among whose roles is the metabolism of &#x0201C;xenobiotics&#x0201D;. A number of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> P450 genes respond to compounds that induce mammalian cytochrome P450 genes (<link linkend="bib170">Menzel et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11697852-->). Transcription of one gene in particular, CYP35A2, is strongly induced by exposure to &#x000DF;-naphthoflavone and expression is exclusively in the intestine.</para>
<para>The four <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> P-glycoproteins (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PGP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PGP-1</ulink> to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PGP-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">PGP-4</ulink>) belong to a family of membrane transporters containing an ATP-binding cassette. P-glycoproteins are often found on absorptive/excretory epithelial surfaces in higher organisms, where they are involved in the excretion of large hydrophobic toxins encountered in the diet or, for humans, encountered during chemotherapy. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pgp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pgp-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pgp-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">pgp-3</ulink></emphasis> genes are expressed heavily in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestine throughout the lifespan (<link linkend="bib143">Lincke et al., 1993</link>); antibody staining reveals that the proteins are located in the apical membranes facing the intestinal lumen (<link linkend="bib36">Broeks et al., 1995</link>). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pgp-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">pgp-3</ulink></emphasis> is also expressed highly in the excretory cell. A deletion of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pgp-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">pgp-3</ulink></emphasis> gene increases sensitivity to colchicines and to chloroquine (<link linkend="bib36">Broeks et al., 1995</link>). The <emphasis>pgp</emphasis> genes, together with the related <emphasis>mdr</emphasis> genes, also contribute to protection against heavy metals (<link linkend="bib35">Broeks et al., 1996</link>).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5_6">
<title>Role of the intestine in host-pathogen interactions</title>
<para>During the past decade, an entirely new field has developed in which <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is used as a host to study the effects of pathogenic micro-organisms. The response of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to such pathogens is varied, ranging from no apparent effect up to killing within hours (in this case, usually because of a secreted toxin; see below). Probably the most common observation is that pathogenic bacteria are able to visibly and persistently colonize the intestine; indeed, a summary of responses of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to a series of pathogenic microbes (28 bacteria and two fungi) lists intestine as the main target (<link linkend="bib207">Schulenburg et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15151149-->). This infectious interaction between microbes and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is beyond the scope of the present chapter and here we focus only on the best understood example of how the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestine responds to a secreted bacterial toxin.</para>
<para>Aroian and coworkers have used <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to study interactions with a set of crystal toxins produced by <emphasis>Bacillus thuringiensis</emphasis> (of agricultural fame) and the intestine appears to be the major target; see also the earlier work of Borgonie and coworkers (<link linkend="bib18">Borgonie et al., 1995</link><!--; PMID 7876593-->; <link linkend="bib17">Borgonie et al., 1996</link>). Exposure of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to purified toxin causes the intestine to become vacuolated within hours, followed ultimately by death (<link linkend="bib160">Marroquin et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10557211-->). A series of BT-toxin-resistant mutants (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bre-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bre-1</ulink></emphasis> to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bre-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">bre-5</ulink></emphasis>) were isolated and the corresponding genes subsequently cloned. The major conclusion is that toxin resistance is associated with a series of glycosyltransferases, some of which are highly related to <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> genes with apparently similar function (<link linkend="bib160">Marroquin et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10557211-->; <link linkend="bib88">Griffitts et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11336504-->; <link linkend="bib87">Griffitts et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 11832245-->; <link linkend="bib86">Griffitts et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15705852-->). The &#x0201C;<emphasis>bre</emphasis>&#x0201D; genes thus appear to form a conserved glycosylation pathway, the end product of which forms the toxin receptor or at least part of the receptor. Indeed, the intestines of resistant mutants no longer take up labeled toxin and expression of the appropriate <emphasis>bre</emphasis> gene <emphasis role="bold">only</emphasis> in the intestine is sufficient to restore sensitivity (<link linkend="bib87">Griffitts et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 11832245-->). A major (if not the major) receptor has now been shown to be a glycolipid, of a type common to invertebrates but not found in vertebrates (<link linkend="bib86">Griffitts et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15705852-->); it is expected that this glycolipid forms part of the intestine lumenal membranes. Finally, microarrays have been used to identify <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes differentially regulated by exposure to Bt toxins; such genes include mitogen-activated protein kinases, which were shown to be important for normal toxin resistance (<link linkend="bib103">Huffman et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15149037-->). Overall, these studies provide an encouraging example how <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> can be used to investigate problems of immense importance for world economics and public health.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5_7">
<title>Aging and the intestine</title>
<para>There are a number of reasons to suspect that the adult intestine could play a central role in aging and lifespan. Dietary restriction can increase lifespan in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as in other organisms (<link linkend="bib237">Walker et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15896824-->; <link linkend="bib30">Braeckman et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16732407-->) and the intestine must be involved at some level in this phenomenon. Lipid accumulation responds to the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis>/<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> signalling pathway and the intestine is a major site of lipid storage (<link linkend="bib6">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529643-->). Expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> only in the adult intestine is able to reconstitute much of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis>-dependent lifespan-extension in wildtype animals and essentially all of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis>-dependent lifespan extension in animals lacking a germline (<link linkend="bib139">Libina et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14576426-->). Moreover, in animals lacking a germline (and which are consequently long-lived), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> protein accumulates in intestinal nuclei (<link linkend="bib140">Lin et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11311160-->). Finally, reasonable connections can be advanced between aging, lifespan, stress responses (<link linkend="bib101">Hsu et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12471266-->; <link linkend="bib131">Lamitina and Strange, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15194811-->) and the fact that, as discussed in an earlier section, many of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> stress responses are focused in the intestine.</para>
<para>Microarray analyses have identified genes whose expression is influenced by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> mutations (<link linkend="bib162">McElwee et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12872001-->; <link linkend="bib176">Murphy et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12845331-->). Comparison of these gene lists to the list of intestinal genes identified by our SAGE analysis (<link linkend="bib164">McGhee et al., 2007</link>) indicates that, overall, the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis>/<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> responsive genes do not appear to be preferentially expressed in the adult intestine. However, this conclusion does not preclude particular lifespan-related genes acting in the intestine and there have been two recent important examples of such behaviour. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=kri-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">kri-1</ulink></emphasis> gene acts in the intestine to promote the nuclear localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> in response to a signal from the germline (<link linkend="bib14">Berman and Kenyon, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16530050-->). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-36;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-36</ulink></emphasis> gene encodes an oxygenase that is expressed primarily in the intestine and that has been suggested to perform an early step in the synthesis of a steroid-like ligand used for communicating between different tissues, including the intestine (<link linkend="bib199">Rottiers et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16563875-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Transcriptional control in the intestine</title>
<para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestine is one of the few cell lineages where a plausible sequence of direct molecular interactions can be proposed throughout the life cycle, beginning with maternally-derived factors in the cytoplasm of the fertilized zygote, progressing through a small number of zygotic transcription factors and ending with the transcription of vitellogenin genes in the adult intestine to provide food for the next generation. In the current section, we emphasize steps that occur after endoderm specification, i.e., the transcription factors involved with intestinal differentiation, function and maintenance.</para>
<sect2 id="sec6_1">
<title>Analysis of intestine specific promoters</title>
<para>Beginning with the early work on vitellogenin genes by Blumenthal and coworkers, promoters of the following genes, expressed exclusively or primarily in the intestine and at a range of developmental stages, have been analyzed to the point where specific <emphasis>cis</emphasis>-acting sites have been mutated: <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=vit-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">vit-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib147">MacMorris and Blumenthal, 1993</link>; <link linkend="bib149">MacMorris et al., 1994</link>); <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cpr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cpr-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib32">Britton et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9761670-->); <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ges-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ges-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib59">Egan et al., 1995</link>; <link linkend="bib161">Marshall and McGhee, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11784040-->); <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mtl-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">mtl-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mtl-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">mtl-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib173">Moilanen et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10514435-->); <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pho-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pho-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib70">Fukushige et al., 2005</link>); <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=spl-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">spl-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib186">Oskouian et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15734735-->); <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elo-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">elo-6</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib188">Pauli et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16354718-->) and three genes encoding the enzmyes of polyamine synthesis (<link linkend="bib146">Luersen et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15449707-->). For all of the genes investigated, an extended GATA-like site is critically important for intestine-specific transcription. This conclusion has been confirmed by computational analyses of intestine gene promoters (<link linkend="bib164">McGhee et al., 2007</link>; <link linkend="bib188">Pauli et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16354718-->). Only a small number of non-GATA sites have been experimentally implicated in the control of intestine gene transcription: the VPE1/TGTCAAT elements in vitellogenin promoters (<link linkend="bib148">MacMorris et al., 1992</link>; <link linkend="bib149">MacMorris et al., 1994</link>), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MAB-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">MAB-3</ulink> binding sites in vitellogenin promoters (<link linkend="bib252">Yi and Zarkower, 1999</link><!--; PMID 9927589-->) and a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> binding site in the promoter of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gcs-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gcs-1</ulink></emphasis> gene (<link linkend="bib2">An and Blackwell, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12869585-->). In the case of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gcs-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gcs-1</ulink></emphasis> gene, the critical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> site overlaps with a GATA site so it remains possible that a GATA factor is also involved here as well. A plausible interaction between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MAB-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">MAB-3</ulink> and GATA sites in regulating vitellogenin transcription will be discussed below.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6_2">
<title>Intestinal GATA factors and the predominance of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELT-2</ulink></title>
<para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome encodes eleven zinc-finger GATA-related factors, compared to six GATA-factors in vertebrates (Lowry, 2000<!-- #1897-->; Patient, 2002<!-- #1899-->). The crucial involvement of several of these GATA factors in the specification of the endoderm will be discussed in the future WormBook chapter by J. Rothman and M. Maduro and is only briefly summarized here.</para>
<para>Specification of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> endoderm begins with the maternally-derived bZIP-like <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> factor determining the fate of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> blastomere of the four cell embryo (see <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>; <link linkend="bib27">Bowerman et al., 1992</link>; <link linkend="bib26">Bowerman et al., 1993</link>). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> blastomere then divides asymmetrically to produce the anterior <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink> cell (mesoderm) and posterior E cell (endoderm), the clonal progenitor of the intestine. The crucial asymmetry of this division is introduced by a signal passed to the E cell from the adjacent posterior cell P<subscript>2</subscript> (<link linkend="bib79">Goldstein, 1992</link>; <link linkend="bib80">Goldstein, 1993</link>); this Wnt-MAPK-Src-pathway-based signal (<link linkend="bib195">Rocheleau et al., 1997</link>; <link linkend="bib231">Thorpe et al., 1997</link>) leads to a lowering of the nuclear concentration of the HMG protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=POP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib142">Lin et al., 1995</link>; <link linkend="bib141">Lin et al., 1998</link>; <link linkend="bib145">Lo et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 12781695-->), thereby relieving repression of the endoderm pathway and, at the same time converting <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=POP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> (or a fraction of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=POP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink>) into an endoderm gene activator (<link linkend="bib153">Maduro et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16084508-->; <link linkend="bib211">Shetty et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16112103-->). Together with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=POP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> in its role as transcriptional activator, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> also directly activates transcription of genes encoding the two endoderm-specifying GATA factors <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=END-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">END-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=END-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">END-3</ulink> (<link linkend="bib258">Zhu et al., 1997</link>; <link linkend="bib257">Zhu et al., 1998</link>; <link linkend="bib152">Maduro et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15979606-->; <link linkend="bib153">Maduro et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16084508-->; <link linkend="bib211">Shetty et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16112103-->). In the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> blastomere, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> is also responsible for activating transcription of genes encoding two small redundant highly-diverged GATA factors called <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MED-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">MED-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MED-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">MED-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib154">Maduro et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11463373-->); although important to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink> blastomere fate (<link linkend="bib154">Maduro et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11463373-->; <link linkend="bib37">Broitman-Maduro et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15737937-->), the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MED-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">MED-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MED-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">MED-2</ulink> factors appear much less important in determining E cell fate (<link linkend="bib81">Goszczynski and McGhee, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15998721-->; <link linkend="bib39">Captan et al., 2006</link>; <link linkend="bib151">Maduro et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16979152-->). The homeobox protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PAL-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink>, whose principal maternal role is to specify the fate of the C and D blastomeres (<link linkend="bib104">Hunter and Kenyon, 1996</link>), also contributes to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=end-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">end-1</ulink></emphasis>/<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=end-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">end-3</ulink></emphasis> activation (<link linkend="bib153">Maduro et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16084508-->) but perhaps only in the experimentally-induced situation where <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> has been removed. Expression of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=end-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">end-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=end-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">end-3</ulink></emphasis> genes is transient; transcripts can be detected at the 1E cell stage but have largely decayed by the 8E cell stage (<link linkend="bib258">Zhu et al., 1997</link>; <link linkend="bib11">Baugh et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15772128-->); at the moment, there is no evidence either for or against the perdurance of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=END-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">END-1</ulink>/3 protein. The current model is that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=END-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">END-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=END-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">END-3</ulink> set in motion the entire endoderm specification pathway, one of the central features of which is the activation of genes encoding the next round of GATA factors, chiefly ELT-2.</para>
<para>	The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elt-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">elt-2</ulink></emphasis> gene (where <emphasis>elt</emphasis> stands for erythrocyte-like transcription factor (<emphasis>sic</emphasis>); <link linkend="bib214">Spieth et al., 1991</link>) encodes a single-zinc-finger GATA-type transcription factor (<link linkend="bib92">Hawkins and McGhee, 1995</link>) that, we suggest, is the predominant transcription factor in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestine following the early steps of endoderm specification (<link linkend="bib164">McGhee et al., 2007</link>); see <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELT-2</ulink> expression begins during the 2E cell stage and persists into adulthood; maintenance of correct <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELT-2</ulink> levels likely involves direct <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elt-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">elt-2</ulink></emphasis> gene autoregulation (<link linkend="bib71">Fukushige et al., 1998</link>; <link linkend="bib72">Fukushige et al., 1999</link>). Deletion of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elt-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">elt-2</ulink></emphasis> is lethal: the intestinal lumen is blocked (the gut-obstructed or Gob phenotype; <link linkend="bib71">Fukushige et al., 1998</link>) and the afflicted animals die as hatched L1 larvae, presumably from starvation. Nonetheless, the <emphasis>elt-2(-/-)</emphasis> intestine is reasonably well-formed and, at a casual glance, almost normal. Thus, other transcription factors (possibly only <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=END-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">END-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=END-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">END-3</ulink>) must be capable of building most of the early embryonic intestine. However, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELT-2</ulink> probably contributes to this early phase of intestine development because it is sufficient (though not necessary) for expression of early endoderm markers such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ges-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ges-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ifb-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">ifb-2</ulink></emphasis> and gut granules (<link linkend="bib71">Fukushige et al., 1998</link>). The essential functions of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELT-2</ulink> are first revealed later in embryogenesis. In particular, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELT-2</ulink> has been shown to be necessary for the expression of three intestine-specific genes first expressed late in embryogenesis and analyzed immediately following hatching: the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mtl-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">mtl-2</ulink></emphasis> metallothionein gene (<link linkend="bib173">Moilanen et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10514435-->), the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=spl-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">spl-1</ulink></emphasis> sphingosine phosphate lyase gene (<link linkend="bib186">Oskouian et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15734735-->) and the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pho-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pho-1</ulink></emphasis> intestinal acid phosphatase gene (<link linkend="bib70">Fukushige et al., 2005</link>).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4.3in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 5</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELT-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELT-4</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELT-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELT-7</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C18G1.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">C18G1.2</ulink>) are two other GATA factors expressed in the developing intestine beginning approximately mid-embryogenesis (<link linkend="bib69">Fukushige et al., 2003</link>) and unpublished results of K. Strohmaier cited in (<link linkend="bib155">Maduro and Rothman, 2002</link><!--; PMID 12027435-->). However, neither factor seems to have a major influence on intestine development, i.e., animals in which the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elt-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">elt-4</ulink></emphasis> gene (<link linkend="bib69">Fukushige et al., 2003</link>) or the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elt-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">elt-7</ulink></emphasis> gene (<link linkend="bib70">Fukushige et al., 2005</link>; <link linkend="bib186">Oskouian et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15734735--> and unpublished results of Keith Strohmaier) or both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elt-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">elt-4</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elt-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">elt-7</ulink></emphasis> genes (<link linkend="bib164">McGhee et al., 2007</link>) have either been deleted or their transcripts ablated by RNAi are essentially wildtype. Nonetheless, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elt-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">elt-2</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elt-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">elt-7</ulink></emphasis> double knockouts show a slightly more severe phenotype than does the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elt-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">elt-2</ulink></emphasis> single knockout (unpublished results of Keith Strohmaier; our unpublished results), suggesting that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elt-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">elt-7</ulink></emphasis> is partially redundant with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elt-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">elt-2</ulink></emphasis>.</para>
<para>We thus propose the simple model (see <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>) that, following endoderm specification, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELT-2</ulink> participates in all acts of transcription in the intestine. However, other transcription factors are clearly present in the intestine (see below) and are likely to modulate the action of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELT-2</ulink> in different developmental or environmental circumstances. Transcription of the vitellogenin genes in the hermaphrodite intestine provides a possible example how this could occur. The vitellogenin (yolk protein) genes are expressed in the adult hermaphrodite intestine but not in the male intestine (<link linkend="bib120">Kimble and Sharrock, 1983</link>). It had been known for some time that the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> gene is involved in repressing male vitellogenin synthesis (<link linkend="bib209">Shen and Hodgkin, 1988</link>) and Yi and Zarkower have shown that this effect is direct (<link linkend="bib252">Yi and Zarkower, 1999</link><!--; PMID 9927589-->). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MAB-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">MAB-3</ulink> protein shows similarity to <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> <emphasis>doublesex</emphasis>, which, among other things, is also responsible for sex-specific regulation of yolk protein synthesis in flies (<link linkend="bib193">Raymond et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9490411-->). The preferred <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MAB-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">MAB-3</ulink> binding sequence was identified <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> and related sequences were then identified in the promoters of the half-dozen vitellogenin genes (<link linkend="bib252">Yi and Zarkower, 1999</link><!--; PMID 9927589-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MAB-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">MAB-3</ulink> binds directly to one such site in an abbreviated promoter-reporter construct from the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=vit-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">vit-2</ulink></emphasis> gene and mutation of this site causes reporter gene derepression in male intestines. A critical GATA site (<link linkend="bib148">MacMorris et al., 1992</link>; <link linkend="bib149">MacMorris et al., 1994</link>) lies immediately adjacent to this <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MAB-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">MAB-3</ulink> site, suggesting that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MAB-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">MAB-3</ulink> could act in the male intestine by repressing the activity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELT-2</ulink>. GATA-like sites also lie in the vicinity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MAB-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">MAB-3</ulink> sites found in other vitellogenin gene promoters (<link linkend="bib148">MacMorris et al., 1992</link>; <link linkend="bib149">MacMorris et al., 1994</link>; <link linkend="bib252">Yi and Zarkower, 1999</link><!--; PMID 9927589-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6_3">
<title>Other transcription factors in the intestine</title>
<sect3 id="sec6_3_1">
<title>Embryonic</title>
<para>Analysis of a SAGE library prepared from FACS-sorted embryonic intestine cells identifies dozens of different transcription factors (D. G. Moerman and JDM, in preparation) but only a small number have been investigated experimentally.</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tbx-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">tbx-8</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tbx-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">tbx-9</ulink></emphasis> are highly similar T-box genes expressed in the embryo posterior (intestine, muscles and hypodermis). Expression in the intestine can be detected in the 2E and 4E cells but declines thereafter. Most phenotypes of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tbx-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">tbx-8</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tbx-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">tbx-9</ulink></emphasis> double knockouts are associated with hypodermis and muscle but cells in the mutant intestine appear mis-positioned and clumped (<link linkend="bib189">Pocock et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15102704-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The forkhead factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PHA-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHA-4</ulink> is critical for embryonic formation of the pharynx and the rectum (<link linkend="bib159">Mango et al., 1994</link>; <link linkend="bib9">Azzaria et al., 1996</link>; <link linkend="bib100">Horner et al., 1998</link>; <link linkend="bib108">Kalb et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9584117-->). However, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pha-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">pha-4</ulink></emphasis> is also expressed in the intestine at all stages; rather subtle morphological changes can be detected in the embryonic intestine of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pha-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">pha-4</ulink></emphasis> mutants. Intestinal expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pha-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">pha-4</ulink></emphasis> may well be controlled by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELT-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib108">Kalb et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9584117-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-130;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-130</ulink> protein is a forkhead transcription factor best known for its role in regulating cell migration (<link linkend="bib178">Nash et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10964959-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-130;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-130</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in a variety of tissues, among which is the intestinal primordium. Intestinal expression begins at the approximately 8E cell stage and persists into adulthood (<link linkend="bib178">Nash et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10964959-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ceh-13;class=Gene" role="_blank">ceh-13</ulink></emphasis> homeobox gene is expressed in the posterior cells of the intestinal primordium (<link linkend="bib243">Wittmann et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 8654891-->), among several other places in the embryo. It is not clear what causes this patterned expression nor whether <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ceh-13;class=Gene" role="_blank">ceh-13</ulink></emphasis> expression has any consequences for overall anterior-patterning in the intestine. As mentioned earlier, the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pal-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pal-1</ulink></emphasis> homeobox gene is expressed in the int5 cells of the developing intestine primordium (<link linkend="bib57">Edgar et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11133155-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=die-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">die-1</ulink></emphasis> gene encodes a zinc-finger protein, possibly a transcription factor, that was identified because mutants show aberrant morphogenesis of the hypodermis (<link linkend="bib93a">Heid et al., 2001</link><!-- #3386-->). However, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=die-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">die-1</ulink></emphasis> is expressed widely in the embryo, including in the developing intestine; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=die-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">die-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants show intestinal defects in which the intestine does not attach to the pharynx or to the rectum.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NHR-25;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink>, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of FtzF1, has an early phase of expression restricted to the E lineage (approximately 4E cell stage to comma stage) but subsequently becomes expressed more widely (<link linkend="bib5">Asahina et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10971653-->). Knockout of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NHR-25;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> causes embryonic arrest but the intestine primordium still expresses differentiation markers. HNF-4 type nuclear hormone receptors (like <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NHR-25;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink>) are usually associated with endoderm in other animals but this does not appear to be true of the same family of factors in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib194">Robinson-Rechavi et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15983867-->).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec6_3_2">
<title>Postembryonic</title>
<para>SAGE analysis of adult intestines identifies transcripts corresponding to over a hundred different transcription factors (<link linkend="bib164">McGhee et al., 2007</link>) but, like the transcription factors in the embryonic intestine, only a small number have been investigated experimentally. However, one important conclusion is that the majority of these transcription factors do not show an RNAi phenotype, at least in high throughput screens. Of the approximately 10% of adult intestine transcription factors that do show an RNAi phenotype, none except <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELT-2</ulink> show a major developmental phenotype centred on the intestine.</para>
<para>Control of lipid metabolism and lipid homeostasis is a burgeoning field of study in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, holding promise for understanding lipid-related diseases in humans. Several transcription factors controlling specific genes in, for example, fatty acid metabolism, have been identified and the emerging view is of complex redundant overlapping transcriptional control, centred on the intestine but acting in other tissues as well. Three points of interest are:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para>The nuclear hormone receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NHR-49;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-49</ulink> (a candidate PPAR homologue) is expressed in a number of different tissues including the intestine. Knockout of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NHR-49;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-49</ulink> leads to enhanced fat storage in the intestine (and presumably other tissues as well). A number of potential targets have been identified, in particular genes involved in mitochondrial <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation of fatty acids and genes involved in fatty acid desaturation (<link linkend="bib77">Gilst et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15719061-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-80;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis> gene has also been shown to be involved in controlling genes involved in fatty acid desaturation, in particular the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> genes encoding <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00394;</symbol>9-desaturases (<link linkend="bib34">Brock et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839188-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> is expressed exclusively in the intestine and expression is abolished in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-80;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis> mutants. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink></emphasis> are expressed strongly but not exclusively in the intestine; their expression levels are decreased (but not abolished) by loss of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-80;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis>. As noted earlier, simultaneous loss of all three <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> genes is lethal but when only <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> are lost, the remaining genes are able to adjust their levels of expression. This ability to compensate by adjusting expression levels is controlled by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-80;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib34">Brock et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839188-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LPD-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LPD-1</ulink> is the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of mammalian SREBP (sterol response element binding protein) and is expressed exclusively in the intestine. A number of potential direct downstream targets have been identified and one such target (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lpd-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">lpd-3</ulink></emphasis>) has also been shown to be exclusively expressed in the intestine (<link linkend="bib165">McKay et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12530969-->). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elo-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">elo-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elo-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">elo-6</ulink></emphasis> genes encode fatty acid elongation enzymes, and are good candidates to be direct targets of <ulink url="http://wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LPD-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LPD-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib122">Kniazeva et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15314147-->). Intestinal expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elo-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">elo-6</ulink></emphasis> is largely abolished by mutation of a GATA site in the promoter (<link linkend="bib188">Pauli et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16354718-->) suggesting that regulation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elo-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">elo-6</ulink></emphasis> might involve cooperation between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ELT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">ELT-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LPD-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LPD-1</ulink>.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>We note the following additional points of interest concerning intestinal transcription factors:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para>Overall, nuclear hormone receptors are highly represented among transcription factors expressed at the highest levels in the adult intestine. In addition to the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-80;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis> genes described above, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-8</ulink></emphasis> is expressed exclusively in the intestine and loss of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-8</ulink></emphasis> function enhances sensitivity to toxins such as colchicine (<link linkend="bib144">Lindblom et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11516648-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-62;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-62</ulink> homeobox factor is the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> homothorax and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-62;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-62</ulink></emphasis> transcripts are present at high levels in the adult intestine (<link linkend="bib164">McGhee et al., 2007</link>). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-62;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-62</ulink></emphasis> is expressed widely in the embryo and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-62;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-62</ulink></emphasis> mutants are embryonic lethal (<link linkend="bib233">Van Auken et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12399316-->).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CEH-20;class=Protein" role="_blank">CEH-20</ulink> is the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> extradenticles (<link linkend="bib233">Van Auken et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12399316-->) and transcripts can be detected at moderate levels in the adult intestine (<link linkend="bib164">McGhee et al., 2007</link>).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Transcripts corresponding to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pha-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">pha-4</ulink></emphasis>, the forkhead &#x0201C;organ identity factor&#x0201D; for the pharynx, can also be detected in the adult intestine (<link linkend="bib164">McGhee et al., 2007</link>).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The forkhead factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> is expressed widely throughout the worm and its potential role in the intestine was described above in the section on aging.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec6_3_3">
<title>&#x0201C;Other&#x0201D;</title>
<para>In the preceding section, we have focused on transcription factors that bind to specific DNA sequences in the regulatory regions of intestinal genes. However, there are dozens and dozens of other factors that are usually referred to as General Transcription Factors, either involved with the basic transcriptional machinery or in providing links between this basic machinery and the promoter specific factors. This important subject is covered in the WormBook chapter by Blackwell and Walker (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transcriptionmechanisms/transcriptionmechanisms.html" role="_blank">Transcription mechanisms</ulink>). Of particular interest to understanding control of gene expression in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestine are two recent studies that show that two transcription factors involved in the control of lipid metabolism, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink>/lpd-1</emphasis> interact with a particular subunit of the mediator complex; the mediator subunit involved in controlling these genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-15;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-15</ulink>) is the homolog of the mediator subunit controlling the homologous genes in humans (<link linkend="bib224">Taubert et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16651656-->; <link linkend="bib251">Yang et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16799563-->)</para>
<para>Finally, there are increasing hints how transcription in the intestine might also be subject to &#x0201C;higher&#x0201D; control, possibly including regulation of chromatin structure. For example, members of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Polycomb-like group of factors, in particular <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MES-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">MES-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MES-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">MES-6</ulink>, are prominently expressed in the intestine (<link linkend="bib197">Ross and Zarkower, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12791273-->). Also, screens for SynMuv (synthetic multivulva) genes, some of which have been found to be involved in higher order control of gene regulation, can be detected because of their permissive effects on intestine gene expression (<link linkend="bib191">Poulin et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15990876-->). Suppressors of SynMuv genes have also been identified, many of which reverse SynMuv effects on ectopic expression of reporter genes in the intestine (<link linkend="bib49">Cui et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16710447-->). It is not yet known how these genes/factors/mechanisms are involved in normal processes of gene expression in the intestine but they point to complex additional layers of regulation.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>Future directions in the intestine</title>
<para>It is clear that the above descriptions have only touched the surface of intestinal biology in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> but they do lead to the following set of (rather obvious) questions that must now be addressed:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para>What fraction of the food-derived macromolecules is taken up by endocytosis and what fraction is digested within the intestinal lumen, with degradation products assimilated via dedicated transporters? How can <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ingest and digest so many bacteria so quickly?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>At the molecular level, how does such a spectacular sub-cellular structure as the brush border assemble, with all microvilli the same length?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>How does the intestine communicate with the outside environment or with other tissues such as the gonad? There have been several important recent insights into such communication pathways (<link linkend="bib14">Berman and Kenyon, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16530050-->; <link linkend="bib157">Mak et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16462744-->) but there are certain to be others.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>How does the intestine participate in the overall energy economy of the animal and in fundamental biological processes such as regulation of growth and size? Is food distribution from the intestine to the rest of the worm constitutive or &#x0201C;on demand&#x0201D;?</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Even if the main transcription factors regulating intestine development have been identified, how do they all work together? Will understanding transcription factors really tell us how <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> makes its intestine?</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>Work in the author's laboratory was funded by the Canadian Institutes of Health Research, the Alberta Heritage Foundation for Medical Research and the Canada Research Chairs. I welcome comments about errors, omissions, mis-interpretations and suggestions for future revisions.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Bibliography</title>
&intestine_Refs;
<para/>
</sect1>
</article>