<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'autophagyfig1leg.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'autophagyfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'autophagyfig2leg.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'autophagyfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY melendezautophagy_Refs SYSTEM 'autophagyrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="melendezautophagy_ArticleID">
<articleinfo>
<title>Autophagy in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis><footnote>
<para>Edited by James M. Kramer and Donald C. Moerman. Last revised February 22, 2009. Published August 21, 2009. This chapter should be cited as: Mel&#x00E9;ndez, A. and Levine, B. Autophagy in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (August 21, 2009), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.147.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2009 Alicia Mel&#x00E9;ndez and Beth Levine. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
</footnote>
</title>
<author>
<othername>Alicia Mel&#x00E9;ndez<superscript>1&#x2013;2,&#x00A7;</superscript>, Beth Levine<superscript>3&#x2013;5</superscript><remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail : <ulink url="mailto:alicia.melendez@qc.cuny.edu">alicia.melendez@qc.cuny.edu</ulink> or <ulink url="mailto:beth.levine@utsouthwestern.edu">beth.levine@utsouthwestern.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></othername>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>1</superscript>Department of Biology, Queens College, 65-30 Kissena Boulevard, Flushing, NY 11367; <superscript>2</superscript>The Graduate Center, The City University of New York, 365 Fifth Avenue, NY 10016; <superscript>3</superscript>Howard Hughes Medical Institute and Departments of <superscript>4</superscript>Internal Medicine and <superscript>5</superscript>Microbiology,</orgname><address>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center, 5323 Harry Hines Boulevard, Dallas, TX 75390</address></affiliation>
</author>
</articleinfo>
<?newpage?>
<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Autophagy is a ubiquitous cellular process responsible for the bulk degradation of cytoplasmic components through an autophagosomal-lysosomal pathway. Genetic screens, primarily in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">S. cerevisiae</emphasis></emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">have identified numerous genes that are essential for autophagy. Many of these genes have orthologs in higher eukaryotes, including</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans, Drosophila</emphasis></emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">and mammals. Gene knockdown/knockout studies in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">have been useful to probe the functions of autophagy in an intact multicellular organism that undergoes development to produce different cell types. This review summarizes important themes that have emerged regarding the roles of autophagy in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">in adaptation to stress, aging, normal reproductive growth, cell death, cell growth control, neural synaptic clustering, and the degradation of aggregate-prone proteins.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction to evolutionarily conserved features of autophagy</title>
<sect2 id="sec1_1">
<title>Cellular events</title>
<para>The term autophagy literally means &#x201C;self-eating&#x201D; and denotes any cellular pathway involving the delivery of cytoplasmic material to the lysosome for degradation. There are at least three types of autophagy, chaperone-mediated autophagy, microautophagy and macroautophagy, which differ with respect to the mode of delivery to the lysosome. Chaperone-mediated autophagy is a mechanism that allows the direct lysosomal import of proteins which contain a particular pentapeptide motif (<link linkend="bib91">Majeski and Dice, 2004</link><!--:PMID 15325583-->; <link linkend="bib94">Massey et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15325582-->), whereas both microautophagy and macroautophagy involve dynamic membrane rearrangements that terminate at the lysosome. In microautophagy, cytoplasmic material is directly engulfed at the surface of the lysosome by septation, protrusion or invagination of the limiting membrane. Macroautophagy involves the sequestration of cytoplasm into a double-membrane cytosolic vesicle referred to as an autophagosome, that subsequently fuses with a late endosome or lysosome to form an autophagolysosome (or autolysome). Inside the autophagolysosome, the lysosomal hydrolases degrade the sequestered material, which then becomes available to the cell for recycling. Macroautophagy is the major regulated cellular pathway for degrading long-lived proteins and the only known pathway for degrading cytoplasmic organelles (reviewed in <link linkend="bib23">Dunn, 1994</link><!--:PMID 14731737-->; <link linkend="bib67">Klionsky, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17712358-->; <link linkend="bib68">Klionsky and Emr, 2000</link><!--:PMID 11099404-->).</para>
<para>How autophagosomes are formed remains somewhat controversial because the origin of the membrane is unknown. In <emphasis>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</emphasis>, the initial step of autophagy consists of the formation of a phagopore, or isolation membrane (vesicle nucleation step). The proposed site for autophagosome formation is the phagopore assembly site (PAS) (<link linkend="bib62">Kim et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 11675395-->; <link linkend="bib65">Kirisako et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10525546-->; <link linkend="bib155">Suzuki et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11689437-->). This structure consists of the phagopore, or its precursor, and the autophagy proteins that form the core machinery of the forming autophagosome. The concerted action of the autophagy core machinery proteins at the PAS is thought to lead to the expansion of the phagopore into an autophagosome. In mammalian systems, it is not yet known whether the PAS exists, although colocalization of autophagy core machinery proteins to the phagopore has also been observed (<link linkend="bib105">Mizushima et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12665549-->; <link linkend="bib108">Mizushima et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11266458-->). Fusion of the phagopore edges forms the autophagosome during the vesicle elongation and completion steps. Docking and fusion occurs when the outer membrane of the autophagosome fuses with the vacole (in yeast) or the lysosome (in mammalian cells), producing an autophagolysosome in mammals, and an autophagic body in yeast. Finally, the sequestered material is degraded by vacuolar or lysosomal hydrolases inside the autophagosome, and the degradation products are reutilized by the cell.</para>
<para>In this review we focus on macroautophagy (herein referred to as autophagy) as virtually all of the studies in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have centered on this form of autophagy. Investigations of the cellular events involved in autophagy in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have been limited, but it is presumed that the formation and fate of the autophagosome is essentially similar to that in yeast and mammalian cells (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). There may, however, be some subtle differences between <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and other species. For example, <emphasis>S. cerevisiae</emphasis> autophagosomes are usually about 400-900 nm in diameter (<link linkend="bib161">Takeshige et al., 1992</link><!--:PMID 1400575-->), and mammalian autophagosomes are usually between 500-2000 nm, whereas <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> autophagosomes appear to be smaller, about 300-500 nm in diameter (<link linkend="bib70">Kov&#x00E1;cs, 2004</link>; <link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->). The reason for the size difference of autophagosomes is unknown. Given the ease of studying the cellular events of autophagy in yeasts or cultured mammalian cells (and the challenges that occur in addressing this area in the intact nematode), it is likely that future studies in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> will continue to focus on the genetics of the autophagy pathway and its biological roles in metazoan development and biology.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="6.0in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec1_2">
<title>Molecular machinery</title>
<para>As detailed in numerous reviews on yeast autophagy, several genetic screens led to the identification of <emphasis role="underline">a</emphasis>u<emphasis role="underline">t</emphasis>opha<emphasis role="underline">g</emphasis>y-related genes, or <emphasis>ATG</emphasis> genes, in <emphasis>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</emphasis>, <emphasis>Hansenula polymorpha,</emphasis> and <emphasis>Pichia pastoris</emphasis>. The analyses of yeast <emphasis>atg</emphasis> mutants have provided the framework for dissecting the autophagic process into distinct steps, including (<link linkend="figure1">Fig. 1</link>): (a) induction, (b) cargo selection and packaging, (c) vesicle nucleation, (d) vesicle expansion and completion, (e) retrieval, and (f) vesicle targeting, docking, and fusion (reviewed in <link linkend="bib157">Suzuki and Ohsumi, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17382324-->; <link linkend="bib176">Xie and Klionsky, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17909521-->). Gene products have been identified that act at each of these steps, and that are required for the formation of the sequestering membrane (<link linkend="figure2">Fig. 2</link>).</para>
<para>Four enzymatic complexes are required for autophagosome formation (<link linkend="figure2">Fig. 2</link>); a serine/threonine protein kinase complex that responds to upstream inhibitory signals like the TOR kinase and induces autophagic activity; a class III phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K) lipid kinase enzymatic complex that acts in vesicle nucleation; two novel ubiquitin-like conjugation pathways that lead to vesicle expansion and completion; and a protein retrieval system. In yeast, the induction complex includes the kinase, Atg1, and its regulators, Atg13 and Atg17, and it may interact with Atg23 and the integral membrane protein, Atg9, to recruit membrane to the nascent phagophore (<link linkend="figure2">Fig. 2A</link>). Vesicle nucleation requires a lipid kinase complex, including: Atg6, Atg14, Vps15 and the class III PI3K Vps34, which function to generate phosphatidylinositol 3-phosphate (PI3P) (<link linkend="figure2">Fig. 2B</link>) (<link linkend="bib59">Kihara et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11157979-->). This class III PI3K complex functions in the localization of other autophagy proteins to the forming autophagosome (<link linkend="bib59">Kihara et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11157979-->). Two other enzymatic complexes are the Atg12 conjugation system (Atg12, Atg5, and Atg16), and the Atg8 lipidation system (Atg8, Atg3, and Atg7) which mediate vesicle expansion, and vesicle completion (<link linkend="figure2">Fig. 2C</link>). The retrieval system includes Atg9 which is the only transmembrane protein in the core machinery of autophagy proteins. Atg9 functions in the shuttling of membrane from the PAS to non-PAS structures, a process required for the formation of the autophagosome (<link linkend="bib138">Reggiori and Klionsky, 2006</link><!--:PMID 16787937-->; <link linkend="bib139">Reggiori et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 14723849-->; <link linkend="bib177">Yen and Klionsky, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17297289-->). The efficient delivery of Atg9 to the PAS involves the transport factors Atg23 and Atg27 (<link linkend="bib75">Legakis et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17426440-->; <link linkend="bib170">Tucker et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14504273-->; <link linkend="bib178">Yen et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17135291-->). Finally, the retrieval of Atg9 (<link linkend="figure2">Fig. 2D</link>) from the PAS involves the Atg1 kinase complex, as well as Atg2 and Atg18, two interacting peripheral proteins (<link linkend="bib139">Reggiori et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 14723849-->; <link linkend="bib154">Shintani et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11382761-->; <link linkend="bib156">Suzuki et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17295840-->; <link linkend="bib173">Wang et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11382760-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="6.0in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Fusion of the autophagosome vesicle requires proteins common to all pathways (not just macroautophagy) that terminate at the vacuole/lysosome. It has been proposed that autophagosomes fuse with endosomes and become amphisomes, before fusion with lysosomes, which may provide the nascent autophagosomes with machinery that can be used for fusion with lysosomes (<link linkend="bib9">Berg et al., 1998</link><!--:PMID 9705327-->; <link linkend="bib166">Tooze et al., 1990</link><!--:PMID 2166050-->). In mammals, autophagolysosomal fusion involves the integral membrane protein LAMP2 (<link linkend="bib30">Gonzalez-Polo et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16091749-->; <link linkend="bib118">Nishino et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 10972294-->), and Rab7, a GTP-binding protein (<link linkend="bib64">Kimura et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17534139-->). Fusion in yeast involves the Rab family GTPase Ypt7, the SNAREs, Vam3, Vam7, Vti1 and Ykt6, members of the HOPS complex, and two components, Ccz1 and Mon1, which act at the docking stage (<link linkend="bib87">Luzio et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17637737-->). In yeast, the breakdown of the vesicle and degradation requires Atg15, a putative lipase (<link linkend="bib164">Teter et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11085977-->). In mammals, degradation requires a series of lysosomal proteases (cathepsins B, D and L) (<link linkend="bib152">Shacka and Roth, 2005</link><!--:PMID 16314462-->). Subsequent to degradation, the resulting monomeric units (e.g. amino acids) that have been generated can be exported to the cytosol for reuse.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<para>Many of the yeast genes encoding autophagy proteins have orthologs in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>), for example: <emphasis>ATG2, ATG3, ATG4, ATG5, ATG6, ATG7, ATG8, ATG9, ATG10, ATG12, ATG16, ATG18</emphasis>, have been found in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome. Autophagy function has been documented for genes acting in autophagy induction (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-51;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-51</ulink>/ATG1</emphasis>), vesicle nucleation (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink>/ATG6</emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=vps-34;class=Gene" role="_blank">vps-34</ulink>/VPS34</emphasis>), the protein conjugation systems (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00010882;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-7</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M7.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">M7.5</ulink>/ATG7</emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lgg-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-1</ulink>/ATG8, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lgg-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-3</ulink>/ATG12</emphasis>), retrieval and vesicle recycling (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00018294;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-18</ulink>/F41E6.13/ATG18</emphasis>) (<link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18282106-->; <link linkend="bib37">Hars et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17204841-->; <link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->). When searching for structural homology between yeast and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, there are a few yeast autophagy genes missing in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome, including genes encoding critical components of the induction step, (e.g., <emphasis>ATG13</emphasis>, <emphasis>ATG17</emphasis>), or components that act during the vesicle nucleation step (e.g., <emphasis>ATG14</emphasis>). An interesting question is whether functional orthologs of such components exist in <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> but lack apparent structural homology, or whether there is imprecise conservation of the molecular mechanisms of autophagy in the nematode.</para>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75%">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1.</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">orthologs of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">S. cerevisiae</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">autophagy-related genes</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="0.6*" colnum="1"/>
<colspec colname="c2" align="left" colwidth="0.6*" colnum="2"/>
<colspec colname="c3" align="left" colwidth="0.7*" colnum="3"/>
<colspec colname="c4" align="left" colwidth="0.7*" colnum="4"/>
<colspec colname="c5" align="left" colwidth="0.9*" colnum="5"/>
<!--<colspec colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="0.8*" colnum="1"/>
<colspec colname="c2" align="left" colwidth="0.8*" colnum="2"/>
<colspec colname="c3" align="left" colwidth="0.8*" colnum="3"/>
<colspec colname="c4" align="left" colwidth="0.8*" colnum="4"/>
<colspec colname="c5" align="left" colwidth="0.9*" colnum="5"/>-->
<thead>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>S. cerevisiae</emphasis> gene</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog</entry>
<entry align="left">Function</entry>
<entry align="left">Phenotype of <emphasis>Ce</emphasis> gene inactivation</entry>
<entry align="left">References</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>Regulation of Induction</emphasis></entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>TOR1,2</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left" valign="top">
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-363;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-363</ulink></emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>B0261.2</emphasis></para></entry>
<entry align="left">PI K-related protein kinase, Rapamycin target</entry>
<entry align="left">L, LL</entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><link linkend="bib120">Noda and Ohsumi, 1998</link><!--PMID 9461583-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib171">Vellai et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 14668850-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib48">Jia, et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 15253933-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 18282106-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib36">Hansen et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 1726667--></para>
</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>ATG1</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-51;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-51</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Ser/Thr Protein kinase</entry>
<entry align="left">Unc, Egl, A<superscript>d</superscript></entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><link linkend="bib38">Hedgecock et al., 1985</link><!--PMID 3928418-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib95">Matsuura et al., 1997</link><!--PMID 9224897-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 12958363-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib124">Ogura et al., 1994</link><!--PMID 7958904--></para>
</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>ATG13</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=D2007.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">D2007.5</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Phosphoprotein component of Atg1 complex</entry>
<entry/>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib26">Funakoshi et al., 1997</link><!--PMID 9224892--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>Vesicle Nucleation</emphasis></entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>ATG6</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>T19E7.4</emphasis></para>
</entry>
<entry align="left">Component of the PI3K complex</entry>
<entry align="left">L, A<superscript>d</superscript>, St, SL, pQ</entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 18282106-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 12958363-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib150">Seaman et al., 1997</link><!--PMID 9105038-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib156">Kametaka et al., 1998</link><!--PMID 9712845-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib50">Jia and Levine, 2007</link><!--PMID 17912023-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib49">Jia et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17172799-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib159">Tak&#x00E1;cs-Vellai et al., 2005</link><!--PMID 16111945--></para>
</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>VPS34</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-512;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-512</ulink></emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>B0025.1</emphasis></para>
</entry>
<entry align="left">PtdIns 3-Kinase</entry>
<entry align="left">L, SL</entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 18282106-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib151">Seglen and Gordon, 1982</link><!--PMID 6952238-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib142">Roggo et al., 2002</link><!--PMID 11927551-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib59">Kihara et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11157979--></para>
</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>VPS15</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ZK930.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ZK930.1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Component of the PI3K complex</entry>
<entry align="left">?</entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 18282106-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib59">Kihara et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11157979--></para>
</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>Vesicle Expansion</emphasis></entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>ATG3</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y55F3AM.4;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y55F3AM.4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">E2-like enzyme conjugates PE to Atg8</entry>
<entry align="left">?</entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><link linkend="bib45">Ichimura et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 11100732-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib163">Tanida et al., 2002</link><!--PMID 11825910--></para>
</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>ATG4</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ZK792.8;class=Gene" role="_blank">ZK792.8</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Cysteine protease cleaves Atg8 C-terminus</entry>
<entry align="left">?</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib66">Kirisako et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 11038174--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry/>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y87G2A.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y87G2A.3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry/>
<entry align="left">?</entry>
<entry/>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>ATG5</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00022152;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-5</ulink></emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>Y71G12B.12</emphasis></para>
</entry>
<entry align="left">Conjugated to Atg12 through internal Lys</entry>
<entry align="left">?</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib55">Kametaka et al., 1996</link><!--PMID 8921905--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>ATG7</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00010882;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-7</ulink></emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M7.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">M7.5</ulink></emphasis></para>
</entry>
<entry align="left">E1-like enzyme activates Atg8 and Atg12</entry>
<entry align="left">SL,A<superscript>d</superscript>, pQ</entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 12958363-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib50">Jia and Levine, 2007</link><!--PMID 17912023-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib61">Kim et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 10233148--></para>
</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>ATG8</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lgg-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-1</ulink></emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>C35D5.9</emphasis></para>
</entry>
<entry align="left">Ubiquitin-like protein conjugated to PE</entry>
<entry align="left">L, A<superscript>d</superscript></entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 12958363-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib66">Kirisako et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 11038174--></para>
</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry/>
<entry align="left">
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lgg-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-2</ulink></emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ZK593.6;class=Gene" role="_blank">ZK593.6</ulink></emphasis></para>
</entry>
<entry/>
<entry align="left">NE</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 12958363--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>ATG10</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=D2085.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">D2085.2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">E2-like enzyme conjugates Atg5 and Atg12</entry>
<entry align="left">?</entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 12958363-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib53">Shintani et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 10508157--></para>
</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>ATG12</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lgg-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-3</ulink></emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B0336.8;class=Gene" role="_blank">B0336.8</ulink></emphasis></para>
</entry>
<entry align="left">Ubiquitin-like protein conjugated to Atg5</entry>
<entry align="left">SL</entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 12958363-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib107">Mizushima et al., 1998</link><!--PMID 9759731-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib37">Hars et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17204841--></para>
</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>ATG16</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=K06A1.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">K06A1.5</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Component of Atg5-Atg12 complex</entry>
<entry align="left">?</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib106">Mizushima, et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 10406794--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry/>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F02E8.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">F02E8.5</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry/>
<entry align="left">?</entry>
<entry/>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>Recycling</emphasis></entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>ATG2</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M03A8.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">M03A8.2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Peripheral membrane protein interacts with Atg9</entry>
<entry align="left">?</entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><link linkend="bib154">Shintani et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11382761-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib173">Wang et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11382760--></para>
</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>ATG9</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00020706;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-9</ulink></emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>T22H9.2</emphasis></para>
</entry>
<entry align="left">Integral membrane protein Interacts with Atg2</entry>
<entry align="left">NE</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib119">Noda et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 10662773--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>ATG18</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00018294;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-18</ulink></emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis>F41E6.13</emphasis></para>
</entry>
<entry align="left">Peripheral membrane protein binds PI3P and PI(3,5)P</entry>
<entry align="left">L, A<superscript>d</superscript>, pQ</entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 12958363-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib49">Jia et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17172799-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib8">Barth et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11707261--></para>
</entry></row>
<row valign="top">
<entry namest="c1" nameend="c5" align="justify"><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> phenotypes are: Unc, uncoordinated; LL, long lifespan; SL, short lifespan; pQ, susceptibility to polyQ expansion disease; A<superscript>d</superscript>, abnormal dauer; Egl, egg laying deficient; St, survival under starvation conditions; L, lethal; NE, no effect;?, not known.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>When comparing the number of autophagy genes in yeast with that of higher eukaryotes, there are multiple orthologs for some autophagy genes. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and mammals have multiple orthologs of <emphasis>ATG4</emphasis>. In addition, there are two orthologs of <emphasis>ATG8</emphasis> in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome, although only one may function in autophagy, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lgg-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-1</ulink></emphasis> and not <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00002981;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->). In mammals, similarly, there are three versions of <emphasis>ATG8</emphasis> (<emphasis>LC3</emphasis>, <emphasis>GATE-16</emphasis>, and <emphasis>GABARAP</emphasis>), but only <emphasis>LC3</emphasis> seems to function in autophagy (<link linkend="bib52">Kabeya et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 11060023-->). There also may be some notable functional divergences between yeast and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> autophagy genes, especially for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink>/ATG6</emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-51;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-51</ulink>/ATG1</emphasis>. Yeast <emphasis>ATG6</emphasis> is required for survival during starvation, but not for survival during vegatative growth whereas the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog<emphasis>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink>,</emphasis> is essential for embryonic viability (see <link linkend="sec3_3">section 3.3</link> below). Moreoever, <emphasis>ATG6</emphasis> functions in two distinct <emphasis>VPS34</emphasis> complexes in yeast, one that functions in autophagy and one that functions in vacuolar protein sorting (VPS) (<link linkend="bib150">Seaman et al., 1997</link><!--:PMID 9105038-->). However, <emphasis>C. elegans <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> can only complement the autophagy but not the VPS function of <emphasis>ATG6</emphasis> in yeast (<link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->). Another difference between yeast and mammals is the functional interaction between the antiapoptotic protein Bcl-2 and the autophagy protein Beclin 1 (<link linkend="bib88">Maiuri et al., 2007a</link><!--:PMID 17438366-->; <link linkend="bib89">Maiuri et al., 2007b</link><!--:PMID 17446862-->; <link linkend="bib133">Pattingre et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16179260-->). The association of Beclin 1 with Bcl-2 or the Bcl-2 family of antiapoptotic proteins (Bcl -X<subscript>L</subscript>, Mcl-1, Bcl-w) inhibits autophagy (<link linkend="bib24">Erlich et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17643073-->; <link linkend="bib89">Maiuri et al., 2007b</link><!--:PMID 17446862-->; <link linkend="bib133">Pattingre et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16179260-->). When Beclin 1 dissociates from Bcl-2, autophagy is induced. The Bcl-2-Beclin 1 association has been shown to be conserved among the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> orthologs of these proteins, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CED-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CED-9</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=BEC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">BEC-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib159">Tak&#x00E1;cs-Vellai et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16111945-->).</para>
<para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog of <emphasis>ATG1</emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-51;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-51</ulink></emphasis>, (<link linkend="figure2">Fig. 2A</link>) appears to have unique functions in the nematode that are distinct from other components of the autophagic machinery. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-51;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-51</ulink> is a neuronal specific protein that functions in axonal elongation and guidance (<link linkend="bib38">Hedgecock et al., 1985</link><!--:PMID 3928418-->; <link linkend="bib124">Ogura et al., 1994</link><!--:PMID 7958904-->) and the uncordinated phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-51;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-51</ulink></emphasis> mutation is thought to result from the abnormal localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-5</ulink>, the receptor for the axon guidance protein Netrin/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-6</ulink>, in neuronal cell bodies (<link linkend="bib123">Ogura and Goshima, 2006</link><!--:PMID 16887826-->). However, RNAi for other autophagy-related genes such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis>/<emphasis>ATG6</emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00010882;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-7</ulink>/ATG7</emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lgg-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-1</ulink></emphasis>/<emphasis>ATG8</emphasis>, or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00018294;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-18</ulink>/ATG18,</emphasis> has no effect in the localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-5</ulink> (<link linkend="bib123">Ogura and Goshima, 2006</link><!--:PMID 16887826-->), suggesting that the localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-5</ulink> is mediated by an unknown mechanism that does not involve autophagy. Although <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-51;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-51</ulink></emphasis> mutants are viable (unlike <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-51;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-51</ulink> likely does play a role in autophagy induction similar to its yeast and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> orthologs (<link linkend="bib95">Matsuura et al., 1997</link><!--:PMID 9224897-->; <link linkend="bib148">Scott et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17208179-->) since the phenotype of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-51;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-51</ulink></emphasis> mutants resembles other autophagy gene mutants, with respect to abnormal dauer development and mislocalization of the autophagy marker, GFP-LGG-1 (<link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec1_3">
<title>Signaling regulation</title>
<para>Based on studies in yeast and mammalian cells, it is presumed that, in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, autophagy occurs at basal levels in most tissues during normal growth conditions, but is rapidly upregulated in response to certain types of environmental stress. This is supported by a low number of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LGG-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGG-1</ulink>::GFP punctae in wild-type animals (<link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18282106-->; <link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->). Autophagy can be induced by a number of stimuli, including nutrient starvation, hypoxia, intracellular stress, high temperature, high density, hormones, and various developmental signals (reviewed in <link linkend="bib68">Klionsky and Emr, 2000</link><!--:PMID 11099404-->; <link linkend="bib76">Levine, 2003</link><!--:PMID 15984551-->; <link linkend="bib78">Levine and Klionsky, 2004</link><!--:PMID 15068787-->). Autophagy upregulation occurs when cells need to generate intracellular nutrients and energy (e.g. during starvation, trophic factor withdrawal, or high bioenergetic demands), undergo cellular remodeling (e.g. during developmental transitions), or rid themselves of damaging cytoplasmic components (e.g. during oxidative stress, infection, protein aggregate accumulation, aging). The molecular signaling cascades that regulate autophagy in yeast and mammalian cells have been the subject of recent comprehensive reviews (<link linkend="bib77">Levine, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17429391-->; <link linkend="bib90">Maiuri et al., 2007c</link><!--:PMID 17717517-->; <link linkend="bib96">Meijer and Codogno, 2004</link><!--:PMID 15325584-->; <link linkend="bib97">Meijer and Codogno, 2006</link><!--:PMID 16973212-->; <link linkend="bib176">Xie and Klionsky, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17909521-->).</para>
<para>Many of the key signaling mechanisms for autophagy regulation in other eukaryotic organisms appear to be conserved in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. These include the target of rapamycin (TOR, also known as FRAP1), the class I and class III PI3Ks, the insulin/IGF-1-like receptor, and the Ras/Raf/mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase 1/2 (MEK1/2) (<link linkend="bib18">Codogno and Meijer, 2005</link><!--:PMID 16247498-->; <link linkend="bib96">Meijer and Codogno, 2004</link><!--:PMID 15325584-->). The TOR and Class I PI3Ks pathways negatively regulate autophagy when nutrients and growth factors are abundant, whereas Class III PI3K and MEK1/2 positively regulate autophagy.</para>
<para>In yeast, all <emphasis>ATG</emphasis> genes have been shown to act downstream of TOR (<link linkend="bib54">Kamada et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 14560952-->), however the mechanisms by which nutrients regulate the TOR signaling pathway in yeast and higher eukaryotes, as well as the protein targets of this pathway remain poorly understood. In <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> the TOR ortholog<emphasis>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-363;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-363</ulink>,</emphasis> encodes, by alternative splicing, two proteins orthologous to <emphasis>S. cerevisiae</emphasis> Tor1 and Tor2, and to human TOR (<link linkend="bib85">Long et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12225660-->). Loss of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-363;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-363</ulink></emphasis> activity, through RNAi or mutation, causes developmental arrest at the L3 stage of larval development, with gonadal and intestinal degeneration and increased hypodermal granules. Furthermore, TOR function affects lifespan and interacts with the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink>/insulin-like signaling pathway (<link linkend="bib171">Vellai et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14668850-->). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-363;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-363</ulink></emphasis> developmental arrest phenotype is phenocopied by RNAi of the orthologs of components of the translation machinery: eIF4G (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=IFG-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">IFG-1</ulink>), eIF2&#x03B1;(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y37E3.10;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y37E3.10</ulink>), or eIF-2&#x03B2;(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=IFTB-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">IFTB-1</ulink>), suggesting that this phenotype may arise from failure to promote global translation of mRNA (<link linkend="bib85">Long et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12225660-->). However, the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-363;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-363</ulink></emphasis> phenotype is not phenocopied by the inactivation of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> orthologs of yeast negative regulators of TOR (e.g. SIT4/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PPH-4.1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPH-4.1</ulink> and TIP42/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PPFR-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPFR-3</ulink>) (<link linkend="bib85">Long et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12225660-->). Thus, although one has to be careful about interpreting negative RNAi results, it is possible that there are differences in the way that TOR signaling occurs in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> versus <emphasis>S. cerevisiae</emphasis>. An important question regards the extent to which autophagy activation, in the setting of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LET-363;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-363</ulink>/TOR inhibition, contributes to the phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-363;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-363</ulink></emphasis> mutants.</para>
<para>The levels of dietary protein or amino acid availability also affect the insulin-like signaling pathway to control metabolism and growth. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, the insulin-like growth factor 1 pathway (IGF-1/PI3K) inhibits dauer arrest through the activation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink>, the insulin receptor, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AGE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AGE-1</ulink>, a Class I PI3K, and protein kinases <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PDK-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PDK-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AKT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AKT-1</ulink>/ <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AKT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">AKT-2</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SGK-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SGK-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib41">Hertweck et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15068796-->; <link linkend="bib63">Kimura et al., 1997</link><!--:PMID 9252323-->; <link linkend="bib112">Morris et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8700226-->; <link linkend="bib127">Paradis et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10364160-->; <link linkend="bib128">Paradis and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--:PMID 9716402-->). Upon activation of the Class I PI3K, the generated PIP3 recruits <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AKT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AKT-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AKT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">AKT-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SGK-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SGK-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PDK-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PDK-1</ulink> kinases to the plasma membrane, where <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PDK-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PDK-1</ulink> activates AKT and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SGK-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SGK-1</ulink> by phosphorylation (<link linkend="bib41">Hertweck et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15068796-->; <link linkend="bib128">Paradis and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--:PMID 9716402-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AKT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AKT-1</ulink>, in turn, phosophorylates and inhibits the FOXO transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> by promoting its sequestration in the cytoplasm (<link linkend="bib41">Hertweck et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15068796-->; <link linkend="bib73">Lee et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11747821-->; <link linkend="bib83">Lin et al., 1997</link><!--:PMID 9360933-->; <link linkend="bib84">Lin et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11381260-->; <link linkend="bib121">Ogg et al., 1997</link><!--:PMID 9353126-->). In the absence of ligand, or in the presence of a mutation in any gene upstream (ie., <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=age-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pdk-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pdk-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=akt-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink>/2</emphasis>) in the pathway, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO is dephosphorylated and translocates into the nucleus (<link linkend="bib39">Henderson and Johnson, 2001</link><!--:PMID 11747825-->; <link linkend="bib84">Lin et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11381260-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-18;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-18</ulink>, the phosphoinositide 3-phosphatase PTEN, dephosphorylates PI3P and antagonizes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AGE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AGE-1</ulink>/PI3K (<link linkend="bib27">Gil et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10077613-->; <link linkend="bib100">Mihaylova et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10377431-->; <link linkend="bib122">Ogg and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--:PMID 9885576-->; <link linkend="bib143">Rouault et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10209098-->). In mammalian cells, the Class I PI3K pathway inhibits autophagy, and this PI3K inhibition is counteracted by the PTEN tumor suppressor (<link linkend="bib3">Arico et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11477064-->; <link linkend="bib134">Petiot et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 10625637-->). The Class I PI3K regulation of autophagy is conserved in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib145">Rusten et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15296715-->; <link linkend="bib149">Scott et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15296714-->) and likely is also conserved in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, since a loss-of-function mutation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> increases autophagy (<link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18282106-->; <link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->). Other components of the pathway have not been formally tested yet in the regulation of autophagy in either organism. In the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome, there are multiple FOXO orthologs, and it is suspected but unclear if <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> directly or indirectly regulates autophagy (see <link linkend="sec3_4">section 3.4</link>).</para>
<para>In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, two other pathways regulate dauer development and thus could potentially regulate autophagy: the guanylyl cyclase pathway (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> is the guanylyl cyclase) and the TGF-&#x03B2;-like pathway (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink> is the ligand (<link linkend="bib140">Ren et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8910282-->)). These are described in detail in other sections of Wormbook (see <ulink url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/1.22.1" role="_blank">TGF-&#x03B2; signaling</ulink>, or <ulink url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/1.144.1" role="_blank">Dauer</ulink>). <emphasis>daf-7(m62)</emphasis> mutants treated with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> RNAi do not develop into normal dauers when grown at the dauer inducing temperature (<link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->) (see <link linkend="sec3_2">section 3.2</link> on the function of autophagy in dauer development), providing some indirect evidence for a role of the TGF-&#x03B2; pathway in controlling autophagy. Although genetic analyses are consistent with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF-&#x03B2; and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> pathways functioning in parallel, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> may also function upstream of TGF-&#x03B2; and IGF-1/PI3K (<link linkend="bib165">Thomas et al., 1993</link><!--:PMID 8375650-->). Thus, it is possible that the autophagy pathway is a downstream effector of all three pathways (the IGF-1/PI3K/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink>, the TGF-&#x03B2;/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink> and the guanylyl cyclase/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> pathways); further experiments are necessary to resolve this question. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, an additional TGF-&#x03B2; signaling pathway is the Sma/Mab pathway, a major regulator of body size (see <ulink url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/1.22.1" role="_blank">TGF-&#x03B2; signaling</ulink>; <link linkend="bib147">Savage et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8570636-->). Mutants in this pathway have a small body size phenotype due to reduction in cell size. As of yet, it has not been investigated whether the cause for this smaller cell or body size is an increase in autophagy.</para>
<para>Similar to the insulin-like signaling pathway, the mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathway also plays an important role in cellular stress response. The c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK) is a member of the MAPK superfamily that is activated by cytokines, including TNF and IL-1, and by exposure to environmental stresses (<link linkend="bib60">Kim et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15256594-->), and stimulates autophagy in both mammalian cells and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib47">Jia et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16942488-->; <link linkend="bib101">Mills et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 14993595-->; <link linkend="bib130">Pattingre et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19029119-->; <link linkend="bib174">Wei et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18570871-->: <link linkend="bib180">Yu et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15131264-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO phosphorylation by JNK, at different sites from AKT phosphorylation, can lead to its enhanced nuclear localization following stress (<link linkend="bib125">Oh et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15767565-->), indicating that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> phoshorylation by AKT and JNK may have opposing effects on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> translocation to the nucleus (and potentially on autophagy regulation). In addition, <link linkend="bib32">Greer et al. (2007</link><!--:PMID 17711846-->) have reported that the AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK), another autophagy-stimulatory kinase in yeast and mammalian cells (for reviews see <link linkend="bib43">H&#x00F8;yer-Hansen and J&#x00E4;&#x00E4;ttel&#x00E4;, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17457036-->; <link linkend="bib98">Meijer and Codogno, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17224623-->), phosphorylates human FOXO3 at an unidentified novel regulatory site. This phosphorylation leads to activation of FOXO3 transcriptional activity without affecting its subcellular localization in mammalian cells. AMPK also phosphorylates <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and increases longevity and stress resistance (<link linkend="bib20">Curtis et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16626391-->). Thus, several different kinases that regulate autophagy in other species can phosphorylate <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO and affect either its localization or its transcriptional activity. It seems likely, but is not yet proven, that these kinases also regulate autophagy in the worm via direct or indirect effects on DAF-16.</para>
<para>The overactivated muscarinic acetylcholine receptor pathway normally responds to starvation in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> pharynx, and can cause excessive autophagy, pharyngeal muscle dysfunction, and animal death (<link linkend="bib57">Kang et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17785524-->). Inhibitors of muscarinic signaling such as atropine, a muscarinic acetylcholine receptor antagonist, U0126, an upstream kinase MEK inhibitor, and a reduction-of-function mutation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mpk-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">mpk-1</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a MAPK activated by starvation, all reduce autophagy and the effects of the overactivated muscarinic pathway. Loss of activity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAPK-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAPK-1</ulink>, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog of the death-associated protein kinase (DAP kinase), or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RGS-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-2</ulink>, a regulator of G protein signaling, also reduces starvation-induced autophagy and partially reduces the lethal effects of the overactivated muscarinic acetylcholine pathway. These results suggest that the muscarinic acetylcholine signaling pathway positively regulates autophagy in response to starvation, and that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAPK-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAPK-1</ulink> acts downstream of or in parallel to muscarinic signaling, possibly with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RGS-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-2</ulink> in the regulation of autophagy (<link linkend="bib57">Kang et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17785524-->). These data are consistent with previous reports in mammalian cells (<link linkend="bib31">Gozuacik and Kimchi, 2006</link><!--:PMID 17139808-->; <link linkend="bib46">Inbal et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 11980920-->; <link linkend="bib131">Pattingre et al., 2003a</link><!--:PMID 12609989-->; <link linkend="bib132">Pattingre et al., 2003b</link><!--:PMID 12642577-->; <link linkend="bib162">Tall&#x00F3;czy et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 11756670-->).</para>
<para>In recent studies in mammalian cells four new genes have been identifed that function as positive regulators of autophagy and some have orthologs in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>). Three of these genes, UVRAG, Bif-1 and Ambra1, function as inducers of autophagy through their association with Beclin 1, the mammalian ortholog of Atg6/Vps30 (<link linkend="bib15">Cecconi et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17622796-->; <link linkend="bib81">Liang et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16799551-->; <link linkend="bib160">Takahashi et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17891140-->). The fourth gene, DRAM (<emphasis role="underline">d</emphasis>amage-<emphasis role="underline">r</emphasis>egulated <emphasis role="underline">a</emphasis>utophagy <emphasis role="underline">m</emphasis>odulator), is a p53 target gene encoding a lysosomal protein that induces autophagy (<link linkend="bib19">Crighton et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16839881-->). UVRAG (<emphasis role="underline">UV</emphasis> irradiation <emphasis role="underline">r</emphasis>esistance-<emphasis role="underline">a</emphasis>ssociated <emphasis role="underline">g</emphasis>ene) encodes a coiled coil protein that positively regulates the Beclin 1-PI3K complex (<link linkend="bib81">Liang et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16799551-->). UVRAG, like Beclin 1, is a candidate tumor suppressor gene, and is monoallelicaly mutated at a high frequency in certain human cancers (<link linkend="bib81">Liang et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16799551-->). Bif-1, also known as Endophilin B1, interacts with Beclin 1 through UVRAG, and functions to activate the Beclin 1-PI3K complex and induce autophagosome formation (<link linkend="bib160">Takahashi et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17891140-->). Ambra1 (activating molecule in Beclin 1-regulated autophagy) is a WD40 protein that acts as a positive regulator of Beclin 1-dependent autophagy (<link linkend="bib15">Cecconi et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17622796-->). Lack of Ambra 1 activity in mouse embryos leads to severe neural tube defects asssociated with autophagy dysfunction, accumulation of ubiquitinated proteins, uncontrolled cell proliferation, and excessive programmed cell death. Orthologs of Bif-1 and DRAM are found in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome (<link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>), while Ambra1 and UVRAG appear to be missing. It will be interesting to determine whether functional orthologs of UVRAG and Ambra 1 are identified that act in a similar fashion to positively regulate autophagy, although they lack obvious structural homology.</para>
<table id="table2" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75%">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 2.</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">orthologs of mammalian autophagy-related genes</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="0.6*" colnum="1"/>
<colspec colname="c2" align="left" colwidth="0.6*" colnum="2"/>
<colspec colname="c3" align="left" colwidth="0.7*" colnum="3"/>
<colspec colname="c4" align="left" colwidth="0.7*" colnum="4"/>
<colspec colname="c5" align="left" colwidth="0.9*" colnum="5"/>
<thead>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left">Mammalian gene</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> gene</entry>
<entry align="left">Function</entry>
<entry align="left">Phenotype of <emphasis>Ce</emphasis> gene inactivation</entry>
<entry align="left">References</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left">UVRAG</entry>
<entry align="left">-</entry>
<entry align="left">UV irradiation resistance-associated gene</entry>
<entry align="left">?</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib81">Liang et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16799551--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left">Bif-1</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=erp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">erp-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Bax interacting factor that associates with Uvrag and Beclin 1</entry>
<entry align="left">?</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib160">Takahashi et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17891140--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left">DRAM</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C33A11.4;class=Gene" role="_blank">C33A11.4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">p53-induced damage-regulated</entry>
<entry align="left">?</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib19">Crighton et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16839881--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left">Bcl-2</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ced-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">ced-9</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">
<para>Anti-apoptotic protein, negative regulator of</para>
<para>Beclin 1-mediated autophagy</para>
</entry>
<entry align="left">CD</entry>
<entry align="left">
<para><link linkend="bib159">Tak&#x00E1;cs-Vellai et al., 2005</link><!--PMID 16111945-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib40">Hengartner &amp; Horvitz, 1994</link><!--PMID 7907274-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib88">Maiuri et al., 2007a</link><!--PMID 17438366-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib89">Maiuri et al., 2007b</link><!--PMID 17446862-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib133">Pattingre et al., 2005</link><!--PMID 16179260-->;</para>
<para><link linkend="bib82">Liang et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 10604474--></para>
</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry namest="c1" nameend="c5" align="justify"><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> phenotypes are: CD, increase in apoptotic cell death; ?, not known.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec1_4">
<title>Physiology</title>
<para>To interpret the phenotypes of genetic studies of autophagy in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, it is useful to have a general understanding of the physiological functions of autophagy. This topic has been reviewed extensively elsewhere (<link linkend="bib67">Klionsky, 2007</link><!--:PMID  17712358-->; <link linkend="bib77">Levine, 2007</link><!--:PMID  17429391-->; <link linkend="bib79">Levine and Kroemer, 2008</link><!--; PMID  18191218-->; <link linkend="bib90">Maiuri et al., 2007c</link><!--:PMID 17717517-->; <link linkend="bib103">Mizushima, 2007</link><!--:PMID 18006683-->; <link linkend="bib104">Mizushima and Klionsky, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17311494-->). Briefly, the major known physiological functions of autophagy in multicellular organisms, as determined largely by knockout studies in mice, include (1) provision of nutrients during catabolism, (2) generation of ATP in stressed or starved cells, (3) generation of signals for heterophagic removal of apoptotic corpses, (4) degradation of misfolded proteins, (5) removal of surplus or damaged organelles, and (6) preservation of genomic stability. The ability of autophagy to defend cells against metabolic stress, through the generation of substrates to maintain macromolecular synthesis and ATP production, likely underlies its evolutionarily conserved role in promoting organismal survival during starvation. The ability of autophagy to function in both routine housekeeping (i.e., basal levels of autophagy are required to prevent the abnormal accumulation of proteins and organelles) as well as in the removal of abnormal or damaged proteins and organelles (e.g., aggregate-prone proteins, damaged mitochondria, peroxisomes, stressed endoplasmic reticulum) likely underlies its roles in preventing tissue degeneration, aging, and potentially, cancer. It is not yet known specifically (or at least not at the level of single cell physiology) whether autophagy performs each of these physiological functions in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. However, many of the phenotypes of autophagy gene knockout/knockdowns discussed in <link linkend="sec3">Section 3</link> below (e.g., failure to survive during starvation, decreased lifespan extension, susceptibility to polyglutamine expansion-induced disease, etc.) are likely a consequence of autophagy&#x0027;s essential role in nutrient and energy recycling or in protein and organelle breakdown.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Tools to study autophagy in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
<sect2 id="sec2_1">
<title>Genetic models</title>
<para>Our understanding of the role of autophagy in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> development is emerging from studies using either chromosomal mutations or RNA inactivation of autophagy genes. Chromosomal mutations exist for <emphasis>ATG6/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis>TOR/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-363;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-363</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis>VPS34/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-512;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-512</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis>ATG1/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-51;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-51</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis>ATG18/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00018294;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-18</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). Inactivation by RNAi is achieved by injection of dsRNA, as was done for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> to uncover its role in longevity and dauer development (<link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->), as well as RNAi of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-51;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-51</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00010882;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-7</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M7.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">M7.5</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lgg-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-1</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00018294;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-18</ulink></emphasis> to uncover the role of autophagy during dauer development (<link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->). RNAi is also accomplished by feeding worms dsRNA-expressing bacteria, and this has been successfully done for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink>,</emphasis> <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00010882;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-7</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=vps-34;class=Gene" role="_blank">vps-34</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lgg-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-3</ulink></emphasis> to show the role of autophagy in lifespan extension (<link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18282106-->; <link linkend="bib37">Hars et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17204841-->; <link linkend="bib50">Jia and Levine, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17912023-->; <link linkend="bib98a">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 19185737-->), as well as for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-51;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-51</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lgg-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00018294;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-18</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> to show that autophagy is required for necrotic cell death (<link linkend="bib146">Samara et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 17901876-->; <link linkend="bib168">T&#x00F3;th et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17327275-->). Orthologs to yeast <emphasis>ATG3</emphasis>, <emphasis>ATG4</emphasis>, <emphasis>ATG5</emphasis>, <emphasis>ATG10</emphasis>, and <emphasis>ATG16</emphasis> have still to be tested for a role in autophagy or development (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> orthologs to the recently reported mammalian coactivators of the Class III PI3K complex, the UVRAG-associated protein Bif-1, and the p53-induced molecule, DRAM, also exist (<link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>), but have not been tested for their role in autophagy <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Future studies on these genes will likely yield more information on the regulation of autophagy and its role during development.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2_2">
<title>Detection of autophagy</title>
<para>Prior to the identification of the molecular machinery of autophagy, autophagy was detected primarily by using electron microscopy to visualize autophagosomes. Autophaghosomes are characterized ultrastructurally by the presence of double-membranes surrounding sequestered cytoplasmic material. The electron microscopy approach to detect autophagy is extremely tedious, and difficult to use to assess autophagic activity in different cell types or tissues at the organismal level. Another complicating factor in using electron microscopy to study autophagic activity is the very short half-life of autophagosomes. Indeed, in yeast autophagosomes were originally detected in proteinase-deficient strains, and protease inhibitors are needed to visualize autophagosomes at the microscopic level (<link linkend="bib161">Takeshige et al., 1992</link><!--:PMID 1400575-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> subjected to electron microscopic analysis during dauer development, a stage in which autophagic activity is high, it is much easier to detect late structures in the autophagic pathway (e.g., autolysosomes) than intact autophagosomes (<link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->).</para>
<para>The discovery that one of the autophagy proteins, Atg8 (and its orthologs) undergoes lipidation and stable association with the autophagosomal membrane has facilitated <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> assays to monitor autophagy. In the absence of autophagy, Atg8 has a diffuse cytoplasmic localization; when autophagy is induced, it tightly associates with the pre-autophagosomal/autophagosomal membrane and has a punctate appearance. Therefore, the monitoring of the intracellular localization of green fluorescent protein-tagged Atg8 molecules has become an effective and reliable method to monitor autophagy in diverse organisms, including <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib52">Kabeya et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 11060023-->; <link linkend="bib102">Mizushima, 2004</link><!--:PMID 15325587-->; <link linkend="bib109">Mizushima et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 14699058-->).</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LGG-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGG-1</ulink> is the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog of mammalian LC3 and yeast Atg8, proteins that are commonly used as autophagy markers in yeast and mammalian systems (<link linkend="bib44">Huang et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 10681575-->; <link linkend="bib52">Kabeya et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 11060023-->; <link linkend="bib65">Kirisako et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10525546-->). To study autophagy in live nematodes<emphasis>,</emphasis> a visual autophagy marker was generated using transgenic worms that express a GFP-tagged <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LGG-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGG-1</ulink> protein (Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al, 2003). In <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> the subcellular pattern of the chimeric GFP-LGG-1 protein (e.g. diffuse versus punctate) can easily be determined under a high-resolution fluorescent microscope. The GFP-LGG-1 molecular marker for autophagy has been validated by its correlation with electron microscopy (<link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->), and is now considered the method of choice for the detection and quantitation of autophagy in the nematode. Wild-type animals carrying the GFP::LGG-1 extrachromosomal array express the GFP::LGG-1 protein in multiple tissues throughout development, including the nervous system, pharynx, intestine, hypodermis, somatic gonad, and vulva (<link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->). GFP::LGG-1 has now been used to detect the formation of autophagosomes in several different cell types in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (ie. this reporter has limited use in some tissues, e.g., intestine in adults), including hypodermal seam cells, intestine, neurons, and muscle (<link linkend="bib6">Bamber and Rowland, 2006</link><!--:PMID 16874044-->; <link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18282106-->; <link linkend="bib57">Kang et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID  17785524-->; <link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->; <link linkend="bib117">Nicot et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16801682-->; <link linkend="bib168">T&#x00F3;th et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17327275-->). RNAi-mediated knockdown of genes involved in the execution of autophagy result in GFP::LGG-1 forming large aggregates (rather than small punctae that represent &#x201C;normal&#x201D; autophaghosomes), presumably due to ineffective clearance of this protein through the autophagolysosomal pathway (<link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18282106-->; <link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Functions of autophagy in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
<sect2 id="sec3_1">
<title>Survival during starvation</title>
<para>Similar to its role in other eukaryotic organisms (<link linkend="bib86">Lum et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15928708-->; <link linkend="bib179">Yorimitsu and Klionsky, 2005</link><!--:PMID 16247502-->), the autophagic machinery is involved in promoting nematode survival during starvation (<link linkend="bib57">Kang et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17785524-->). Using <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> that express the GFP::LGG-1 reporter as an integrated transgene, <link linkend="bib57">Kang et al. (2007</link><!--:PMID 17785524-->) found that autophagy is activated by starvation in the pharyngeal muscle. Moreover, an insufficient level of autophagy, caused by either partial RNAi of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> or RNAi against <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00010882;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-7</ulink></emphasis>, promotes the death of animals undergoing starvation. In starved <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> RNAi animals, pharyngeal pumping is decreased and can increase with the addition of food. Pumping efficiency correlates with survival, suggesting that autophagy provides the energy essential to maintain pharyngeal pumping efficiency and survival during starvation. It is not yet fully known which other cell types undergo autophagy activation in response to starvation, but GFP::LGG-1 foci have also been observed in seam cells of starved animals (Malene Hansen, personal communication). Presumably, as in mammals, other muscle cells may also be an important site of autophagic catabolism and serve to generate systemic nutrients that can maintain the health of neurons and other vital cells.</para>
<para>While physiological levels of autophagy are adaptive during starvation, <link linkend="bib57">Kang et al. (2007</link><!--:PMID 17785524-->) also found that excessive levels of autophagy contribute to nematode death. In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gbp-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gbp-2</ulink></emphasis> (a G protein &#x03B2; subunit involved in RGS-mediated inhibition of the Gq&#x03B1; pathway) mutants, in which muscarinic signaling is hyperactive in the pharyngeal muscle, starvation induces excessive autophagy in pharyngeal muscles, pharyngeal muscle damage, and nematode death that can be partially suppressed by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00010882;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-7</ulink></emphasis> RNAi. It is not yet known how excessive autophagy promotes pharyngeal muscle damage or how the damage to the pharyngeal muscle causes death of the animal. Nonetheless, these data provide <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> genetic evidence that excessive autophagy can promote cellular pathology and organismal death, and underscore the importance of tight regulation of the autophagy pathway so that it can serve adaptive functions (associated with physiological levels) but not maladaptive functions (associated with overactive, non-physiological levels).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_2">
<title>Dauer development</title>
<para>The first evidence for a role of autophagy in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> development was provided by studies in <emphasis>daf-2(e1370)</emphasis> mutant dauer animals. During growth in unfavorable environmental conditions (e.g. starvation, high population density, increased temperature) or exposure to &#x201C;dauer&#x201D; pheromone, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> larvae arrest in an alternative third larval stage, referred to as the dauer diapause (<link linkend="bib14">Cassada and Russell, 1975</link><!--:PMID 1183723-->; <link linkend="bib141">Riddle and Albert, 1997</link>). Dauer development is regulated in a temperature-sensitive manner by different signaling pathways that also regulate fat storage, longevity, reproduction and stress responses; including the insulin/IGF-1, the transforming growth factor (TGF-&#x03B2;), and the cyclic guanosine monophosphate (cGMP) pathways (<link linkend="bib7">Barbieri et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14534077-->; <link linkend="bib129">Patterson and Padgett, 2000</link><!--:PMID 10637628-->; <link linkend="bib136">Raizen et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16547093-->). Dauer larvae undergo a number of metabolic and morphologic changes that permit long-term survival during harsh environmental conditions, such as increased intestinal fat storage, pharyngeal, intestinal and hypodermal constriction, total body elongation, and the formation of a thick cuticle that seals them from the environment. If conditions improve, dauer larvae can resume reproductive development, reach the adult stage, and have a normal lifespan. Although the regulation of dauer development has been extensively characterized, the cellular pathways involved in dauer morphogenesis are less well understood.</para>
<para>Interestingly, the control of dauer development in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> shares similarities with the induction of autophagy in other eukaryotes; environmental cues such as temperature, starvation, and high population, are potent inducers of autophagy in yeast, <emphasis>Dictyostelium</emphasis> and mammals and also induce dauer formation in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. In dauer larvae with a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> (the insulin-like receptor) mutation, <link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al. (2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->) observed an increase in autophagy (detectable both by both visualization of GFP::LGG-1 punctae and by electron microscopy) in the hypodermal seam cells, a cell type required for multiple aspects of dauer morphogenesis. This autophagy induction is required for dauer morphogenesis since the majority of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> animals that are grown at the dauer-restrictive temperature and treated with RNAi against <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-51;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-51</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00010882;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-7</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lgg-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-1</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00018294;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-18</ulink></emphasis> fail to complete normal dauer development (<link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->). Such animals have less fat storage, do not undergo pharyngeal and total body constriction and elongation, are not resistant to treatment with detergent (sodium dodecyl sulfate or SDS), die within a few days, and fail to resume normal development when tranferred to the non-dauer permissive temperature.</para>
<para>These data suggest that autophagy genes act downstream of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink> insulin/IGF-1 signaling, that autophagy is required for normal dauer morphogenesis, and that autophagy may be essential for the cellular and tissue remodeling that permits <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to successfully adapt to environmental stress. Autophagy is also required for dauer formation triggered by lack of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink></emphasis>/TGF-&#x03B2; (<link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->). The mechanisms by which autophagy is regulated during dauer formation are not known. One possibility is that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO, a forkhead transcription factor negatively regulated by insulin-like signaling (<link linkend="bib84">Lin et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11381260-->), transcriptionally activates components of the autophagic machinery. However, there are no published data to support this from multiple <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>;<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> microarrays experiments. Indeed, several autophagy genes, including <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lgg-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink>,</emphasis> contain <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> binding sites; but so do many other genes. In mammals, a constitutively active form of the forkhead transcription factor FOXO3, has been recently shown to induce autophagosome formation in skeletal muscle, as visualized by electron microscopy and GFP-LC3 fluorescence (<link linkend="bib92">Mammucari et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18054315-->). The transcription of autophagy-related genes such as <emphasis>LC3</emphasis> (the <emphasis>ATG8/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LGG-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGG-1</ulink></emphasis> ortholog) and <emphasis>Bnip3</emphasis> (a BH3-only protein identified as a major effector of FOXO3-mediated autophagy in skeletal muscle) is activated during fasting and is mediated by FOXO3. However, rapamycin fails to induce autophagy in skeletal muscle <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>; thus it has been hypothesized that an AKT/FOXO3 complex rather than a AKT/TOR complex is involved in the induction of autophagy in skeletal muscle (<link linkend="bib93">Mammucari et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18367868-->). The complex crosstalk between these pathways and their regulation of autophagy warrants further investigation. Another open question is whether autophagy, in addition to its role in dauer morphogenesis, is also required for dauer survival and/or dauer recovery. One clue suggesting that autophagy may have a role in these processes is the phenotype of nematodes with mutation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pcm-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pcm-1</ulink></emphasis>, a gene that encodes the protein L-isoaspartyl-O-methyltransferase which participates in the repair of age-damaged proteins. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pcm-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pcm-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants display a defect in the ability to recover from starvation-induced L1 larval arrest, and decreased autophagy during dauer formation (<link linkend="bib28">Gomez et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17187774-->; <link linkend="bib29">Gomez and Clarke, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17404495-->). Thus, the lack of normal protein repair may interfere with the autophagic pathway, although it is not yet known whether the defect in autophagy is mechanistically responsible for the survival and recovery defects of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pcm-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pcm-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_3">
<title>Reproductive development</title>
<para>The role of autophagy in early development in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is not confined to developmental changes that occur in adaptation to stress. High concentration of dsRNA directed against <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> orthologs of <emphasis>ATG6 (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink>), ATG8 (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lgg-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-1</ulink>)</emphasis>, and <emphasis>ATG18 (F41E6.13)</emphasis> result in early developmental arrest, during or before the first larval stage (<link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->). A deletion allele of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00018294;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-18</ulink></emphasis> is available from the <emphasis><ulink url="http://celeganskoconsortium.omrf.org/" role="_blank">C. elegans</ulink></emphasis> <ulink url="http://celeganskoconsortium.omrf.org/" role="_blank">Gene Knockout Consortium</ulink>, and described as superficially wild-type in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/" role="_blank">WormBase</ulink>. It is possible that the deletion does not completely inactivate the gene or that the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00018294;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-18</ulink></emphasis> RNAi effect was not due to the inactivation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00018294;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-18</ulink></emphasis> alone. Nevertheless, worms carrying a mutation in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=BEC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">BEC-1</ulink> partner protein, the Class III PI3K Vps34 (<emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog is <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-512;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-512</ulink></emphasis>), also display a lethal phenotype (<link linkend="bib142">Roggo et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 11927551-->). In addition, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> homozygous animals derived from a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> heterozygous parent arrest at various stages of development and exhibit increased vacuolization, uncoordinated phenotypes, and molting defects (<link linkend="bib159">Tak&#x00E1;cs-Vellai et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16111945-->). Mutant <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> animals that reach adulthood are sterile. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants also display a maternal effect lethality; animals that lack both the maternal and zygotic expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> die early during embryogenesis (unpublished, A.M.). Thus, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> activity is required for viability and fertility (<link linkend="bib159">Tak&#x00E1;cs-Vellai et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16111945-->). It is not yet known whether other autophagy gene mutations confer similar phenotypes, nor specifically how the lack of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=BEC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">BEC-1</ulink> function (and presumably autophagy) results in these developmental defects.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_4">
<title>Lifespan extension</title>
<para>Multiple processes, such as neuroendocrine signaling, mitochondrial function, and nutritional sensing, play a role in determining lifespan in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Experiments in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have provided direct evidence for a role of autophagy in lifespan extension in at least two settings: mutations in the insulin-like signaling pathway and dietary restriction (<link linkend="bib37">Hars et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17204841-->; <link linkend="bib50">Jia and Levine, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17912023-->; <link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, mutations in the endocrine signaling pathway, involving the insulin-like growth factor (IGF-1) receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink> and the PI3K <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AGE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AGE-1</ulink>, display an increase in adult longevity that requires the forkhead transcription factor FOXO/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> (reviewed in <link linkend="bib58">Kenyon, 2005</link><!--:PMID 15734678-->). <link linkend="bib99">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al. (2003</link><!--:PMID 12958363-->) found that autophagy inactivation by RNAi of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis>, decreases lifespan of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> animals at doses that have minimal or no effect on the lifespan of N2 animals. In addition, <link linkend="bib37">Hars et al. (2007</link><!--:PMID 17204841-->) showed that RNAi of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00010882;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-7</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=atg-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-12</ulink> C. elegans</emphasis> orthologs shortened the lifespan of both N2 (wild-type) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants, but the decrease in lifespan was greater in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants. Thus, multiple autophagy genes are required for lifespan extension in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> (IGF-1) mutants.</para>
<para>Dietary restriction plays an evolutionarily conserved role in lifespan extension in yeasts, flies, mammals, and <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis> The correlation between increased autophagy and increased lifespan in feeding-defective <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> mutants, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pha-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">pha-3</ulink></emphasis>, provided a clue that autophagy might be involved in dietary restriction-mediated lifespan extension (<link linkend="bib20">Curtis et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16626391-->; <link linkend="bib53">Kaeberlein et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 17081160-->; <link linkend="bib72">Lee et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 17096674-->; <link linkend="bib110">M&#x00F6;rck and Pilon, 2006</link><!--:PMID 16884547-->). Mutations in TOR, a nutrient sensor downstream of the dietary-restriction response that negatively regulates autophagy, also extend lifespan (<link linkend="bib36">Hansen et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 1726667-->; <link linkend="bib171">Vellai et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14668850-->). Recently, the autophagy genes, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=vps-34;class=Gene" role="_blank">vps-34</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00010882;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-7</ulink></emphasis>, have been shown to be required for the lifespan extension of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18282106-->; <link linkend="bib50">Jia and Levine, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17912023-->). In addition, the specific inhibition of autophagy during adulthood shortens the long lifespan of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> and TOR pathway mutants (<link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18282106-->; <link linkend="bib98a">Mel&#x00E9;ndez et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 19185737-->) indicating that the autophagic machinery is indeed part of the mechanism by which TOR inhibition increases lifespan, and supporting the idea that autophagy is required for dietary restriction-mediated lifespan extension (<link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18282106-->; <link linkend="bib50">Jia and Levine, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17912023-->). The specific inhibition of autophagy genes by RNAi treatment during adulthood eliminates the potential complication of autophagy having a developmental role that affects longevity. Since autophagy and longevity regulation are highly conserved from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to mammals, a similar role for autophagy in dietary restriction-mediated lifespan extension may also exist in mammals.</para>
<para>The mechanisms by which autophagy mediates lifespan extension are not yet understood. However, one possibility is that the increase in lifespan is mediated through the autophagy-dependent nonspecific or selective removal of damaged mitochondria, decrease in levels of intracellular reactive oxygen species, and subsequent protection against oxidative damage. Such a mechanism would overlap with the presumed means by which autophagy may protect against genomic instability and tumor progression. It would also provide a framework for the conceptual integration of the oxidative damage theory of aging and the known stimuli that influence aging through autophagy-dependent mechanisms in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, including dietary restriction and insulin-like signaling. Many of the long-lived mutants in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are resistant to oxidative stress and many mutations that decrease mitochondrial electron transport are long-lived, whereas conversely, mutations that increase oxidative damage shorten lifespan in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib2">Antebi, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17907808-->; <link linkend="bib33">Guarente and Kenyon, 2000</link><!--:PMID 11089983-->). Thus, longevity in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (and potentially other organisms) may be mediated either by mutations that directly affect cellular generation or breakdown of reactive oxygen species, or indirectly, decrease reactive oxygen specifies via upregulation of the autophagic turnover of the damaged organelles that generate these harmful species.</para>
<para>As with autophagy induction during dauer diapause, it is not yet known which transcription factors regulate autophagy in long-lived mutant nematodes. Unlike the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink>/insulin/IGF-1 signaling pathway, dietary restriction is not dependent on the FOXO transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> (<link linkend="bib42">Houthoofd et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16183950-->; <link linkend="bib71">Lakowski and Hekimi, 1998</link><!--:PMID 9789046-->). Instead, the FOXA transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PHA-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHA-4</ulink> is required for the longevity of dietary<emphasis>-</emphasis>restricted mutants (<link linkend="bib12">Brenkman and Burgering, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17550774-->; <link linkend="bib126">Panowski et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17476212-->), as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pha-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">pha-4</ulink></emphasis> mutants are able to completely suppress the long lifespan of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> mutant animals. <link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al. (2008</link><!--:PMID 18282106-->) have shown that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pha-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">pha-4</ulink></emphasis> is required for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants to have elevated numbers of GFP::LGG-1 foci. Reduced <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/</emphasis>insulin/IGF-1 signaling mutants lacking <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/</emphasis>FOXO activity still show high levels of autophagic vesicles as measured by the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LGG-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGG-1</ulink>::GFP reporter, even though the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> double mutant animals are short-lived (<link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18282106-->). Thus, an increase in the levels of autophagy does not appear to be sufficient to extend lifespan in the context of reduced <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis>/insulin IGF-1 signaling. One interesting point is that overexpression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pha-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">pha-4</ulink></emphasis> extends longevity only in the absence of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> activity (<link linkend="bib126">Panowski et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17476212-->), suggesting that the role of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pha-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">pha-4</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> may be partially redundant with regards to longevity or that there is inherent competition for these two transcription factors. How this may relate to autophagy remains unclear.</para>
<para>Inactivation of several mitochondrial electron transport (ETC) genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> also extends lifespan (<link linkend="bib21">Dillin et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12471266-->; <link linkend="bib74">Lee et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12447374-->). Whether autophagy is specifically involved in mitochondrial-mediated lifespan extension is not clear. In order to observe a longevity phenotype, RNAi treatment of ETC genes has to be initiated during development, specifically in the L3/L4 stage (<link linkend="bib21">Dillin et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12471266-->; <link linkend="bib137">Rea et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17914900-->). Inhibiting the ETC genes by RNAi only during adulthood has no effect on lifespan (<link linkend="bib21">Dillin et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12471266-->). In long-lived mitochondrial mutants, inactivation of autophagy genes by RNAi delivered throughout the adult life had no effect (<link linkend="bib35">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18282106-->). In contrast, the ETC RNAi treatment delivered throughout development cannot fully extend the lifespan of mutants defective in autophagy, suggesting that autophagy is required for the longevity of mutants with reduced mitochondrial respiration (<link linkend="bib167">T&#x00F3;th et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18219227-->). However, the short lifespan of autophagy defective mutants may be partly or fully due to developmental defects. Thus, it remains to be experimentally tested whether autophagy genes are specifically involved in the lifespan extension of mitochondrial mutants that have been RNAi-treated specifically in the L3/L4 stage.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_5">
<title>Programmed cell death</title>
<para>Autophagy has been historically classified as type II programmed cell death based on the presence of autophagic vacuoles in dying cells. However, the question of whether autophagy is a death mechanism <emphasis>per se</emphasis> has been an area of intense debate. In <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>, the developmental process of insect metamorphosis involves the massive destruction and elimination of larval tissues, such as the salivary glands and larval gut, through a dramatic upregulation of autophagy (<link linkend="bib5">Baehrecke, 2005</link><!--:PMID 15928714-->). However, components of the apoptotic machinery are also upregulated during metamorphosis and seem to act cooperatively with autophagy for the efficient elimination of larval tissues (<link linkend="bib11">Berry and Baehrecke, 2007</link><!--:PMID 18083103-->; <link linkend="bib51">Juh&#x00E1;sz et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18056421-->; <link linkend="bib113">Muro et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16887831-->).</para>
<para>The well-recognized role of autophagy as a survival mechanism during stress seemingly contradicts a role in cell death. When autophagosomes are present in dying cells, it is often unclear if autophagy represents a form of nonapoptotic cell death or a failed strategy of cell survival (reviewed in <link linkend="bib80">Levine and Yuan, 2005</link><!--:PMID 16200202-->; <link linkend="bib90">Maiuri et al., 2007c</link><!--:PMID 17717517-->). A third possibility, suggested by recent studies in mammalian autophagy-defective embryoid bodies (<link linkend="bib135">Qu et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17350577-->), is that autophagy is activated in dying cells to generate energy-dependent engulfment signals and successful apoptotic corpse clearance.</para>
<para>In mammalian cells, most studies indicating that autophagy can be involved in the death execution process are in cells that have defects in apoptosis (<link linkend="bib80">Levine and Yuan, 2005</link><!--:PMID 16200202-->; <link linkend="bib90">Maiuri et al., 2007c</link><!--:PMID 17717517-->). As of yet, there is no evidence that autophagy functions as a death mechanism in physiological settings in cells with an intact apopototic pathway or <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> during developmental cell death. In fact, most autophagy gene knockout organisms, including in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, display increased rather than decreased cell death, supporting a pro-survival role for autophagy during development. Studies of <emphasis>C. elegans <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> null mutants, carrying the chromosomal deletion <emphasis>ok691</emphasis>, support the concept that autophagy plays a pro-survival role at the cellular and organismal level during development. These animals have a highly penetrant lethal phenotype during normal growth conditions, and have been reported to display an early arrest phenotype with an increase in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CED-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">CED-3</ulink>/caspase dependent apoptotic cell death (<link linkend="bib159">Tak&#x00E1;cs-Vellai et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16111945-->). While these results suggest that lack of autophagy may trigger the apoptotic pathway, it is also possible that, similar to mammalian development (<link linkend="bib135">Qu et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17350577-->), the observed increase in apoptotic corpses in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos may represent a defect in apoptotic corpse clearance. The cellular focus for the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> lethal phenotype, and the question of whether autophagy functions in a cell autonomous fashion in development remains unknown.</para>
<para>Parallel to findings in mammalian cells, it is likely that cross-talk occurs between the apoptotic and autophagic machinery in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. For example, the interaction between the mammalian anti-apoptotic protein Bcl-2 and autophagy protein Beclin 1 (<link linkend="bib89">Maiuri et al., 2007b</link><!--:PMID 17446862-->; <link linkend="bib133">Pattingre et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16179260-->) is conserved among the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> orthologs of these proteins, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CED-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CED-9</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=BEC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">BEC-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib159">Tak&#x00E1;cs-Vellai et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16111945-->) (<link linkend="figure2">Fig. 2B</link>) <link linkend="bib159">Tacaks-Vellai et al. (2005</link><!--:PMID 16111945-->) found that the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> orthologs of these proteins, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CED-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CED-9</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=BEC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">BEC-1</ulink>, interact. It is not yet known, however, whether <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CED-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CED-9</ulink>, like Bcl-2, functions as an anti-autophagy protein. Yet, recent studies with the BH3-only protein, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EGL-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-1</ulink>, from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> hint that this may be the case. The interaction between mammalian Bcl-2/Bcl-xL involves a BH3 domain within Beclin 1, and this interaction can be competitively disrupted by overexpression of BH3-only pro-apoptotic proteins or pharmacological BH3 mimetics (<link linkend="bib88">Maiuri et al., 2007a</link><!--:PMID 17438366-->; <link linkend="bib89">Maiuri et al., 2007b</link><!--:PMID 17446862-->). Similarly, a gain-of-function mutation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> induces autophagy, while deletion of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> compromises starvation-induced autophagy (<link linkend="bib89">Maiuri et al., 2007b</link><!--:PMID 17446862-->). This suggests that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EGL-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-1</ulink> may not only positively regulate programmed cell death by interacting with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CED-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CED-9</ulink> to induce <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CED-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">CED-4</ulink> release from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CED-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">CED-4</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CED-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CED-9</ulink> complexes, but also may positively regulate autophagy by interacting with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CED-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CED-9</ulink> to induce <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=BEC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">BEC-1</ulink> release from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CED-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CED-9</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=BEC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">BEC-1</ulink> complexes. Whether this increase in autophagy in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants contributes to cell death is not yet clear. Future studies in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> should further clarify the molecular cross-talk between the autophagic and apoptotic machinery during development.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_6">
<title>Necrotic cell death</title>
<para>Another open question is whether autophagy plays a role in necrotic cell death. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, gain-of-function mutations in ion channel genes, either <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-4</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=deg-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">deg-1</ulink>,</emphasis> the acetylcholine receptor channel subunit gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=deg-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">deg-3</ulink>,</emphasis> and the Gs protein &#x03B1;-subunit gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gsa-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gsa-1</ulink>,</emphasis> cause a necrotic-like cell degeneration in neurons that express the mutant proteins (<link linkend="bib10">Berger et al., 1998</link><!--:PMID 9526004-->; <link linkend="bib16">Chalfie and Wolinsky, 1990</link><!--:PMID 2342572-->; <link linkend="bib22">Driscoll and Chalfie, 1991</link><!--:PMID 1672038-->; <link linkend="bib69">Korswagen et al., 1997</link><!--:PMID 9203577-->; <link linkend="bib169">Treinin and Chalfie, 1995</link><!--:PMID 7718248-->). Electron microscopy studies of dying neurons in animals carrying the gain-of-function <emphasis>mec-4(d)</emphasis> allele, have shown extensive degradation of cellular contents during the process of necrosis (<link linkend="bib34">Hall et al., 1997</link><!--:PMID 8994058-->). This ultrastructural feature is reminiscent of autophagy and does not require the caspase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CED-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">CED-3</ulink>, which mediates programmed cell-death, nor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CSP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CSP-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CSP-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">CSP-2</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CSP-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">CSP-3</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CED-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">CED-3</ulink> related proteases)(<link linkend="bib17">Chung et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 11146658-->), indicating that a distinct, non-apoptotic mechanism may function in neurodegeneration (<link linkend="bib158">Syntichaki et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12410314-->). Inactivation of three autophagy genes (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-51;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-51</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lgg-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-1</ulink></emphasis>) suppresses the degeneration of neurons with hyperactive toxic ion channels (<link linkend="bib168">T&#x00F3;th et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17327275-->). These observations indicate a possible role for autophagy in cellular necrosis, and suggest that autophagy inhibition may protect neurons against necrotic cell death. However, inactivation of the TOR-kinase-mediated signaling pathway, a negative regulator of autophagy, also has a protective function in the same neurons (<link linkend="bib168">T&#x00F3;th et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17327275-->). These data are difficult to interpret, since inactivation of TOR, a negative regulator of autophagy, should increase autophagy and thus should not have the same effects as autophagy gene inactivation. More recently, <link linkend="bib146">Samara et al. (2008</link><!--:PMID 17901876-->) also showed that excessive autophagosome formation is induced early during necrotic cell death and that the autophagy pathway synergizes with lysosomal proteolytic mechanisms to facilitate necrotic cell death in neurons.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_7">
<title>Neurodegenerative diseases</title>
<para>The autophagy pathway may play an important role in the clearance of mutant aggregate-prone proteins associated with chronic human neurodegenerative diseases (e.g., Huntington&#x0027;s disease, Parkinson&#x0027;s disease, Alzheimer&#x0027;s disease), muscle diseases (e.g., sporadic inclusion body myositis, limb-girdle muscular dystrophy type 2B, Miyoshi myopathy), and liver disease (e.g., &#x03B1;1-antitrypsin deficiency). Until recently, evidence in support of this stemmed primarily from pharmacological studies in mice and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> using regulators of autophagy such as the TOR inhibitor, rapamcyin, that have pleiotropic effects on the cell. Recent studies in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> provide more direct genetic evidence that the autophagic machinery protects against diseases caused by aggregate-prone proteins associated with human neurodegenerative and muscular diseases.</para>
<para>There are two established models of polyglutamine (polyQ) expansion protein-induced disease in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. One model involves the expression of fluorescent-tagged proteins containing polyQ expansion tracts in muscle cells. Transgenic animals that express polyQ fragments containing 40 repeats (Q40-YFP) display visible aggregates in muscle cells and impaired locomotion (<link linkend="bib13">Brignull et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 17046663-->; <link linkend="bib111">Morley et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12122205-->). A second model utilizes the expression of human huntingtin fragments contaning a tract of 150 polyQ residues (Htn-150) in ASH sensory neurons (<link linkend="bib49">Jia et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17172799-->; <link linkend="bib172">Voisine et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17551584-->). These animals accumulate Htn-150 aggregates in the ASH neurons and undergo progressive neuronal degeneration. In both models, RNAi against the autophagy genes, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00010882;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-7</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00018294;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-18</ulink></emphasis>, increases the accumulation of disease protein aggregates and enhances their toxicity (<link linkend="bib49">Jia et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17172799-->), indicating a role for autophagy genes <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> in the suppression of polyQ aggregate accumulation and protection against disease caused by polyQ toxicity.</para>
<para>In another <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> model, transgenic animals express human &#x03B2;-amyloid peptide in muscle, providing an opportunity to examine the mechanism of toxicity of aggregate-prone A&#x03B2; peptides (<link linkend="bib25">Florez-McClure et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17675890-->). In this nematode model, A&#x03B2; expression inhibits the maturation of autophagosomes into degradative autolysosomes, resulting in the abnormal accumulation of autophagosomes (and presumably blockade of the neuroprotective effects of successful autophagy); this pathology parallels that observed in the brains of patients with Alzheimer&#x0027;s disease and the muscles of patients with sporadic inclusion body myositis (<link linkend="bib4">Askanas and Engel, 2006</link><!--:PMID 16432144-->; <link linkend="bib114">Murphy and Golde, 2006</link><!--:PMID 16432148-->). The autophagy genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=WBGene00010882;class=Gene" role="_blank">atg-7</ulink></emphasis> appear to be required for the degradation of A&#x03B2; in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> model (<link linkend="bib25">Florez-McClure et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17675890-->). These observations in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> support the concept that pharmacological activation of the autophagy pathway may be beneficial in the treatment of Alzheimer&#x0027;s disease and other human neurodegenerative disorders.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_8">
<title>Cell size regulation</title>
<para>Similar to reports in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib116">Neufeld, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17525525-->; <link linkend="bib148">Scott et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17208179-->), the activation of autophagy in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> may be associated with a reduction in cell size. <link linkend="bib110">M&#x00F6;rck and Pilon (2006</link><!--:PMID 16884547-->) examined the level of autophagy, fat deposits, and body and cell size in feeding-defective mutants like <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pha-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">pha-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pha-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">pha-3</ulink>,</emphasis> which have abnormal pharyngeal anatomy; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-3</ulink></emphasis> mutants, which have reduced pharyngeal pumping rates; and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-10;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-10</ulink></emphasis> mutants, which have a slippery pharynx that inefficiently traps bacteria. All of these feeding-defective mutants are short and exhibit a reduced body width and cell size (most notable during the L4 stage), independently of the nature of the genetic defect that impairs their feeding behavior. This reduction in cell and body size is associated with an upregulation of autophagy, as observed by analyzing the subcellular localization of the GFP::LGG-1 autophagy marker in the hypodermal seam cells of L3 animals. Whether the increase in autophagy directly decreases the cell size of the feeding-defective mutants is not yet known.</para>
<para>In a recent article by <link linkend="bib1">Aladzsity et al. (2007</link><!--:PMID 17890369-->), inactivation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-51;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-51</ulink></emphasis> results in a small cell and body size phenotype; however, whether this is due to a lack of autophagy is not shown. The authors suggests that both excessive and insufficient levels of autophagy lead to retarded cell growth (i.e. small cell and body size), but a mechanism by which both an excess and lack of autophagy would result in a similar phenotype is not provided. In <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>, conditions that stimulate autophagy, such as starvation, have been shown to result in reduced cell growth (<link linkend="bib115">Neufeld, 2003</link><!--:PMID 14623438-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_9">
<title>Neurotransmitter receptor trafficking</title>
<para>A novel function for autophagy in GABA<subscript>A</subscript> receptor degradative trafficking has been shown in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib144">Rowland et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16467519-->). The clustering of neurotransmitter receptors is the end result of a developmental pathway that is initiated when presynaptic terminals contact the postsynaptic cell. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, body-wall muscles form synapses with both GABA and non-GABA neurons (<link linkend="bib175">White et al., 1986</link>). GABA terminals organize GABA<subscript>A</subscript> receptors into synaptic clusters and in the absence of presynaptic inputs, GABA<subscript>A</subscript> receptors are internalized and degraded through autophagy. In these neurons, autophagy is used selectively to degrade GABA<subscript>A</subscript> receptors, since acetylcholine receptors in the same cells do not traffic to autophagosomes (<link linkend="bib144">Rowland et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16467519-->). These findings demonstrate a novel role for autophagy in the degradation of cell surface receptors. In addition to a possible function in controlling the balance of neuronal excitation and inhibition (due to selective GABA<subscript>A</subscript> receptor degradation), the selective degradation of other cell surface receptors by autophagy may help regulate cellular growth, differentiation, and development.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<para>Our understanding of the role of autophagy as an essential process in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> development has advanced greatly in the past few years. We have learned that autophagy is involved in cell survival, cell death, normal development, dauer development, negative control of cell growth, longevity, clearance of toxic aggregate-prone proteins, and cell surface receptor trafficking. Despite the great importance of autophagy in the physiology of higher eukaryotes, the molecular mechanisms and functions of autophagy in these organisms remain vague. Hopefully, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, as a genetically tractable system, will continue to allow us to unravel the mechanisms of autophagy regulation, execution, and function at the cellular and organismal level.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>The work in the authors&#x0027; laboratories is supported by grants from the National Institutes of Health (A.M., B.L.), the American Cancer Society (B.L.), the National Science Foundation (A.M.), the PSC CUNY Research Award Program (A.M.) and the Ellison Medical Foundation (B.L., A.M.). We thank Hannes B&#x00FC;low and Malene Hansen for critical reading and helpful suggestions, and Renee Talley for administrative assistance.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>References</title>
<para/>
&melendezautophagy_Refs;
</sect1>
</article>