<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 2: Schematic diagram of the presumed role for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> autophagy proteins involved in the formation of an autophagosome.</title><para/>
</formalpara>
<formalpara><title/><para><emphasis role="bold">A)</emphasis> Regulation of induction: In yeast, the Tor kinase and its effectors regulate the induction of autophagy. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-51;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-51</ulink> is the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Atg1 ortholog, however, it is not clear if there are similar regulatory proteins to Atg17 or Atg13.</para></formalpara>
<formalpara><title/><para><emphasis role="bold">B)</emphasis> Vesicle nucleation requires a lipid kinase complex, which includes the class III phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K), Vps34 (in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LET-512;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-512</ulink>). In yeast, Vps34 activation depends on its binding partners, Atg6, Atg14, and Vps15 (<link linkend="bib59">Kihara et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11157979-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, the <emphasis>ATG6</emphasis> ortholog is <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bec-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bec-1</ulink></emphasis>, however, orthologs to <emphasis>ATG14</emphasis> and <emphasis>VPS15</emphasis> appear to be missing in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome. The interaction between the antiapoptotic protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CED-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CED-9</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=BEC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">BEC-1</ulink> is conserved in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib159">Tak&#x00E1;cs-Vellai et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16111945-->). A similar interaction between the mammalian proteins Bcl-2 and Beclin 1, inhibits autophagy (<link linkend="bib88">Maiuri et al., 2007a</link><!--: PMID 17438366-->; <link linkend="bib89">Maiuri et al., 2007b</link><!--: PMID 17446862-->; <link linkend="bib133">Pattingre et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16179260-->).</para></formalpara>
<formalpara><title/><para><emphasis role="bold">C)</emphasis> Two novel ubiquitin-like conjugation pathways: the Atg12 conjugation system (Atg5, Atg12, and Atg16), and the Atg8 lipidation system (Atg8, Atg3, and Atg7) mediate vesicle expansion, and vesicle completion. Orthologs to all the members of these two complexes have been found in <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> where they are named ATG-3, ATG-4, ATG-5, ATG-7, ATG-16, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LGG-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGG-1</ulink>/Atg8<emphasis></emphasis> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LGG-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGG-3</ulink>/Atg12. In yeast, Atg8 undergoes two posttranslational processing events resulting in conjugation to phosphatidylethanolamine (PE) and recruitment to the PAS membrane. ATG-7 is an E1 ubiquitin activating enzyme required for the activation of of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LGG-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGG-1</ulink>. LGG-3-ATG-5 oligomerize with ATG-16 to allow for the formation of the multimeric complex. ATG-3 and ATG-10 are E2-like ubiquitin conjugating enzymes and ATG-4 is a cysteine protease. As for its yeast ortholog, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LGG-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGG-1</ulink> appears to remain in the completed autophagosome and thus is an excellent marker for early and late autophagosomal structures.</para></formalpara>
<formalpara><title/><para><emphasis role="bold">D)</emphasis> The retrieval of the integral membrane protein ATG-9 from the phagophore assembly site (PAS) involves <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ATG-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">ATG-2</ulink> and ATG-18, two interacting peripheral proteins.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>