<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'Itrafig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'Itrafig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'Itrafig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'Itrafig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'Itrafig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'Itrafig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'Itrafig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'Itrafig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'Itrafig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'Itrafig5leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY Itra_Refs SYSTEM 'Itrarefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="Itra_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Intracellular trafficking<footnote>
                <para>Edited by James M. Kramer and Donald G. Moerman. Last revised March 10, 2005. Published January 21, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Grant, B. D. and Sato, M. Intracellular trafficking (January 21, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.77.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 Barth D. Grant and Miyuki Sato. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para></footnote>
        </title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 3/10/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>-->
        <author>
            <othername>Barth D. Grant<remark>
                    <footnote>
                        <para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:grant@biology.rutgers.edu">grant@biology.rutgers.edu</ulink></para>
                    </footnote>
                </remark>, Miyuki Sato</othername>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Department of Molecular Biology and Biochemistry, Rutgers University, Piscataway, NJ 08854 USA</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Studies in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">have begun to reveal new components and new
            mechanisms associated with intracellular membrane traffic in a variety of cell types.
            The worm benefits from many of the advantages of yeast as a genetically tractable
            organism for these kinds of studies while offering the unique opportunity to probe how
            these pathways have been extended and modified in the context of a multicellular animal
            undergoing development to produce diverse cell types such as muscles, nerves, and
            polarized epithelia. This review summarizes recent work elucidating endocytic pathways,
            primarily in the worm germ line and coelomocytes, and also touches on diverse studies of
            secretion, especially in ectodermal cells of epithelial character.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
    <sect1>
        <title>The endocytic pathway</title>
        <para>Endocytosis is the vesicle-mediated process used by all cells to internalize
            extracellular macromolecules, plasma membrane lipids, and plasma membrane proteins (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). There are several endocytic pathways that utilize different mechanisms to
            internalize portions of the plasma membrane. The best studied endocytosis pathway in
            worms (<link linkend="bib6">Fares and Grant, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11872138-->) and mammalian cells (<link linkend="bib2">Brodsky et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11687498-->) is the clathrin-coated pit pathway (<xref linkend="figure2"/>). Many receptors and their
            associated ligands cluster into clathrin-coated pits by association with clathrin
            adaptor proteins such as the four-subunit complex AP2. Clathrin adaptors in turn bind to
            the clathrin lattice which is thought to provide the force required to deform the
            membrane into a curved bud. The large GTPase dynamin is then involved in pinching off
            the coated pit to form a clathrin-coated vesicle. Such vesicles are then uncoated by the
            chaperone hsc70 and the DNA-J domain co-chaperone auxillin. Uncoated endocytic vesicles
            then fuse with one another and with early endosomes in a reaction requiring the small
            GTPase Rab5. In early endosomes some ligand-receptor complexes dissociate due to the
            reduced pH of the endosomal lumen. Many receptors then recycle to the plasma membrane
            either directly or indirectly via recycling endosomes. Many ligands do not recycle but
            instead are transported from early to late endosomes and eventually to lysosomes for
            degradation. Early to late endosome transport may be mediated by small vesicular
            intermediates, or may be a maturation process whereby early endosomes lose components
            through recycling pathways and gain components through fusion with vesicles derived from
            the secretory pathway. Late endosomes are then thought to fuse with pre-lysosomes to
            form &#x0201C;hybrid&#x0201D; organelles, which mature back into lysosomes
            through sorting and fission.</para>
               <literallayout></literallayout>
        <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig1" align="center" width="5in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>General model of the endocytic pathway</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
     <sect2>
            <title>Endocytosis in oocytes</title>
            <para>One important model for mechanistic studies of endocytosis in <emphasis>C.
                elegans</emphasis> focuses on oocytes, which internalize huge quantities of yolk
                proteins and their associated lipids by clathrin-mediated endocytosis (<link linkend="bib9">Grant and Hirsh, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10588660-->). This process is most easily followed by fluorescence
                microscopy using strains that express transgenes encoding the major yolk protein
                YP-170 (aka <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VIT-2;class=protein" role="_blank">VIT-2</ulink>) fused to GFP (<xref linkend="figure3" />; <link linkend="bib9">Grant and Hirsh, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10588660-->).
                YP170-GFP is synthesized in the intestine of adult hermaphrodites and is secreted
                basolaterally into the body cavity (pseudocoelom). YP170-GFP, like endogenous yolk,
                is a cholesterol binding/transport protein related to human ApoB-100, the major
                protein component of serum low-density lipoprotein (LDL). The yolk receptor in
                    <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RME-2;class=protein" role="_blank">RME-2</ulink>, an LDL-receptor related molecule
                expressed specifically in the oocytes (<xref linkend="figure3"/>; <link linkend="bib9">Grant and Hirsh, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10588660-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RME-2;class=protein" role="_blank">RME-2</ulink> contains a typical NPXY internalization motif in its intracellular
                domain that is known to direct other members of the LDL-receptor family into
                clathrin-coated pits. Trafficking of yolk and yolk receptors also depends critically
                upon the activities of the endocytic Rab proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RAB-5;class=protein" role="_blank">RAB-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RAB-7;class=protein" role="_blank">RAB-7</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RAB-11;class=protein" role="_blank">RAB-11</ulink>, known
                modulators of endocytosis in all eukaryotes (<link linkend="bib9">Grant and Hirsh, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10588660-->).
                Thus yolk uptake provides a genetically tractable system for the study of clathrin
                and Rab dependent transport processes.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig2" align="center" width="5in"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase>Mechanism of clathrin-dependent endocytosase fig2</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
               <literallayout></literallayout>
            <mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig3" align="center" width="5in"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase>YP17::GFP endocytosis by oocytes fig3</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
            <para>Screens for mutants defective in YP170-GFP uptake by oocytes identified 11
                    <emphasis>rme</emphasis> genes (<emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis></emphasis>eceptor-<emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis>ediated <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="bold">e</emphasis></emphasis>ndocytosis defective) required for various steps in endocytic transport
                (<xref linkend="figure3" />; <link linkend="bib9">Grant and Hirsh, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10588660-->). In contrast to secretory defects,
                defects in endocytosis <emphasis>per se</emphasis> do not severely affect the
                organization or morphology of the germ line or oocytes as judged by Nomarski optics.
                The best studied of the general endocytosis regulators identified in this screen are
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RME-1;class=protein" role="_blank">RME-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RME-8;class=protein" role="_blank">RME-8</ulink> (<link linkend="bib9">Grant and Hirsh, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10588660-->; <link linkend="bib24">Zhang et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11451999-->). Both of these proteins are found in the cytoplasm of most <emphasis>C.
                    elegans</emphasis> cells and are associated with the limiting membrane of endosomes. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RME-1;class=protein" role="_blank">RME-1</ulink> is an EH domain protein associated with recycling endosomes and is
                thought to contribute to the formation of membrane tubules that recycle receptors
                from endosomes to the cell surface (<link linkend="bib10">Grant et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11389442-->). There are
                several mammalian homologues of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RME-1;class=protein" role="_blank">RME-1</ulink>, at least one of which functions in recycling
                endosomes (<link linkend="bib27">Lin et al., 2001<!-- PMID 11389441--></link>). In the absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RME-1;class=protein" role="_blank">RME-1</ulink>, yolk receptors
                become trapped in endosomes of the oocyte and cannot efficiently recycle through
                multiple rounds of endocytosis. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rme-1" role="_blank">rme-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants are also
                defective in endocytosis by coelomocytes and in basolateral endocytic traffic in the
                intestine (<link linkend="bib10">Grant et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11389442-->).</para>
                        <para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RME-8;class=protein" role="_blank">RME-8</ulink> is a large DNA-J domain protein (<link linkend="bib24">Zhang et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11451999-->). The
                precise step in trafficking regulated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RME-8;class=protein" role="_blank">RME-8</ulink> remains unclear, since the protein
                appears to localize to early and/or late endosomes, but <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rme-8" role="_blank">rme-8</ulink></emphasis>
                mutants appear defective in the earliest detectable internalization step (<link linkend="bib24">Zhang et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11451999-->). Recent studies in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> indicate similar
                localization and transport defects in Dm-<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rme-8" role="_blank">rme-8</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib4">Chang et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15051737-->). These studies also indicated that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RME-8;class=protein" role="_blank">RME-8</ulink> may interact
                with Hsc70 and clathrin. J-domains are known to mediate interactions with heat shock
                protein 70 family members, and clathrin-coated vesicles are uncoated by the action
                of cytoplasmic Hsc70 (<link linkend="bib2">Brodsky et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11687498-->). Previous work in
                    <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> demonstrated that yolk endocytosis depends upon
                the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> auxillin homologue <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dnj-25" role="_blank">dnj-25</ulink></emphasis>,
                an other J-domain protein. RNAi of <emphasis>Ce-auxillin</emphasis> results in
                abnormal accumulation of clathrin-coated structures and interferes with clathrin
                dynamics <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib11">Greener et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11175756-->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Endocytosis in coelomocytes</title>
            <para>The other major model developed for mechanistic studies of endocytosis in
                    <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> focuses on coelomocytes, 6 macrophage-like
                scavenger cells in the body cavity (pseudocoelom) that are highly active in
                endocytosis of fluid-phase molecules (<link linkend="bib8">Fares and Greenwald, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11560892-->).
                While the natural molecules that are removed from the body cavity by coelomocytes
                are unknown, coelomocytes are capable of removing many foreign compounds from the
                body cavity after they are introduced by micro-injection (<link linkend="bib7">Fares and Greenwald, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11326278-->). The most common of these endocytosis tracers are fluorescently
                labeled BSA or dextrans. These observations allowed the development of a pulse-chase
                type assay of coelomocyte endocytosis (<link linkend="bib24">Zhang et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11451999-->).
                Fluorescently labeled BSA or dextran trafficking through the endosomes of
                coelomocytes is monitored as a function of time after introduction into the body
                cavity. Expression of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RME-8;class=protein" role="_blank">RME-8</ulink>:: GFP is often used to facilitate visualization of
                endosomes during fluorescent tracer trafficking from the cell surface to the
                lysosomes (<link linkend="bib24">Zhang et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11451999-->).</para>
            <para>In wild-type animals Texas Red labeled BSA (TR-BSA) molecules endocytosed by
                coelomocytes first appear in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RME-8;class=protein" role="_blank">RME-8</ulink> positive endosomes within 5 to 10 minutes after they
                are introduced into the pseudocoelom. TR-BSA is rapidly concentrated into
                subendosomal structures, probably membrane buds. The concentrated TR-BSA then
                appears in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LMP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">LMP-1</ulink> positive lysosomes about 30-60 minutes after uptake (<link linkend="bib21">Treusch et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15070744-->; <link linkend="bib24">Zhang et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11451999-->).</para>
            <para>A simpler and more generally useful assay for coelomocyte endocytic function was
                developed by Fares and Greenwald (<xref linkend="figure4"/>; <link linkend="bib7">Fares and Greenwald, 2001a</link><!-- PMID 11560892-->;
                <link linkend="bib8">Fares and Greenwald, 2001b</link><!-- PMID 11326278-->). They created transgenic worms expressing
                signal sequence-GFP fusion protein in body-wall muscles
                (p<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=myo-3" role="_blank">myo-3</ulink>::ssGFP</emphasis>). In this strain, GFP is constitutively secreted
                from body-wall muscle cells into the pseudocoelom and is then efficiently taken up
                and degraded by coelomocytes. At steady-state this strain shows weak pseudocoelom
                labeling and stronger labeling of late endosome and lysosome structures within
                coelomocytes. Using this assay, <emphasis>cup</emphasis> (<emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="bold">c</emphasis></emphasis>oelomocyte <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="bold">up</emphasis></emphasis>take defective) mutants were identified that show accumulation of GFP in
                the pseudocoelom, and/or aberrant morphology of endocytic organelles within
                coelomocytes (<xref linkend="figure4" />; <link linkend="bib8">Fares and Greenwald, 2001b</link><!-- PMID 11560892-->).</para>
            <para>Interestingly, all three <emphasis>cup</emphasis> genes cloned so far encode worm
                homologues of human disease genes. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CUP-5;class=protein" role="_blank">CUP-5</ulink> is a homologue of human mucolipin-1,
                mutations in which lead to Mucolipidosis type IV (<link linkend="bib7">Fares and Greenwald, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11326278-->). This family of proteins is thought to act as
                Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> channels in endosomal or lysosomal membranes.
                    <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cup-5" role="_blank">cup-5</ulink></emphasis> mutants show severe defects in lysosome biogenesis
                that result in the formation of grossly enlarged vacuoles accumulating late
                endosome, lysosome, and Golgi markers (<link linkend="bib21">Treusch et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15070744-->). The
                most likely explanation for this phenotype is that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CUP-5;class=protein" role="_blank">CUP-5</ulink> is required for
                    Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> release during the reformation of lysosomes from
                late endosome-lysosome hybrid organelles.</para>
            <mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig4" align="center" width="5in"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase>GFP endocytosis by coelomocytes</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
            <para>CUP-6/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MTM-6;class=protein" role="_blank">MTM-6</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CUP-10;class=protein" role="_blank">CUP-10</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MTM-9;class=protein" role="_blank">MTM-9</ulink> belong to a family of lipid phosphatases called
                myotubularins (<link linkend="bib5">Dang et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14565969-->). Members of this protein family are
                associated with the human diseases X-linked myotubular myopathy and
                Charcot-Marie-Tooth type 4B1 and 4B2. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MTM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">MTM-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MTM-3;class=protein" role="_blank">MTM-3</ulink>, other worm myotubularin
                homologues, are also required for coelomocyte endocytosis (<link linkend="bib23">Xue et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12788949-->). Several myotubularins have been demonstrated to specifically
                dephosphorylate phosphoinositide 3-phosphate [PI(3)P], a key lipid regulator of the
                endocytic pathway that is normally enriched in early endosomal membranes (<link linkend="bib19">Stenmark and Gillooly, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11292385-->). RNAi of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VPS-34;class=protein" role="_blank">VPS-34</ulink>,
                a homologue of the primary PI-3 kinase, also causes a Cup phenotype, suggesting that
                the balance of PI(3)P production and degradation is important for regulating
                coelomocyte endocytosis (<link linkend="bib8">Fares and Greenwald, 2001b</link><!-- PMID 11560892-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MTM-6;class=protein" role="_blank">MTM-6</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MTM-9;class=protein" role="_blank">MTM-9</ulink>
                form a complex, and both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mtm-6" role="_blank">mtm-6</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mtm-9" role="_blank">mtm-9</ulink></emphasis>
                mutants show defects in a very early step of endocytosis. Although both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MTM-6;class=protein" role="_blank">MTM-6</ulink> and
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MTM-9;class=protein" role="_blank">MTM-9</ulink> possess the lipid phosphatase domain, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MTM-9;class=protein" role="_blank">MTM-9</ulink> lacks key residues thought to be
                essential for PI-3 phosphatase activity. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MTM-9;class=protein" role="_blank">MTM-9</ulink> may play a regulatory role in
                controlling the phosphatase activity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MTM-6;class=protein" role="_blank">MTM-6</ulink> (<link linkend="bib21">Treusch et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15070744-->).</para>
            <para>It is still unclear to what extent clathrin-dependent endocytosis and
                clathrin-independent pinocytosis mechanisms contribute to uptake of plasma membrane
                components and extracellular fluid in coelomocytes. However,
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dyn-1" role="_blank">dyn-1</ulink></emphasis> and a set of <emphasis>rme</emphasis> mutants
                    (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rme-1" role="_blank">rme-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis>-4</emphasis>, <emphasis>-6</emphasis>
                and <emphasis>-8</emphasis>) show clear defects in coelomocyte endocytosis in
                addition to defects in yolk uptake by oocytes (<link linkend="bib8">Fares and Greenwald, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11560892-->; <link linkend="bib10">Grant et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11389442-->; <link linkend="bib24">Zhang et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11451999-->).
                These results indicate that the oocyte and coelomocyte pathways share some
                components. However, oocyte-specific <emphasis>rme</emphasis> mutants and coelomocyte specific
                    <emphasis>cup</emphasis> mutants have been isolated, indicating that not all
                components are shared between these cells/pathways (<link linkend="bib8">Fares and Greenwald, 2001b</link><!-- PMID 11560892-->; our unpublished observation).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Signaling and endocytosis</title>
            <para>Signaling receptors are thought to be regulated in part through regulated
                endocytosis. In some cases endocytosis is thought to down-regulate signaling, while
                in others endocytosis may be required for signaling receptors to contact their
                downstream effectors located on endosomal membranes. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> receptor is
                primarily associated with the apical membranes of the VPC cells where it specifies
                the secondary cell fate (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RTKRasMAPKsignaling/RTKRasMAPKsignaling.html" role="_blank">RTKRas/MAP kinase signaling</ulink>). The signaling activity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> has been
                shown to be developmentally down-regulated in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink> by endocytosis (<link linkend="bib18">Shaye and Greenwald, 2002</link><!-- PMID 12478297-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> endocytosis is triggered in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink> by a signal
                (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink>) from the anchor cell received by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> and transduced by Ras (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RTKRasMAPKsignaling/RTKRasMAPKsignaling.html" role="_blank">RTKRas/MAP kinase signaling</ulink>). Furthermore signaling by the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> EGF
                receptor is downregulated in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> in response to the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> mediated
                lateral signal, probably in part by increased expression of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> associated
                endocytosis factors (<link linkend="bib25">Yoo et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14752159-->).</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
<?newpage?>
    <sect1>
        <title>The secretory pathway</title>
        <para>Most work on the mechanisms of secretion in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has
            focused on neuronal cells, and more specifically on the mechanism of synaptic vesicle
            exocytosis, and to a lesser extent synaptic vesicle biogenesis and axonal transport
                (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_synapticfunction/synapticfunction.html" role="_blank">Synaptic function</ulink>). Much less is known about general or regulated secretion in other
            <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> cell types (<xref linkend="figure5" />).</para>
               <literallayout></literallayout>
        <mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig5" align="center" width="4in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>General model of vesicular transport pathways</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>As in other eukaryotes <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> cells possess an endoplasmic
            reticulum into which most membrane or secretory proteins are inserted
            co-translationally. Some lumenal ER-resident proteins are retained in the ER by KDEL or
            HDEL signals in their extreme C-termini. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> cells also
            possess Golgi stacks, the next organelle through which secretory proteins pass. Unlike
            mammalian cells, invertebrates such as <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have many small
                "mini stacks" throughout
            the cytoplasm of most cells rather than one large stack positioned near the nucleus.
            From the Golgi, secretory proteins and some membrane proteins proceed to either the
            plasma membrane or to the endosomal system, depending upon various signals embedded in
            the primary sequence of the proteins. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> does not possess
            any obvious homologs of the mannose-6-phosphate receptors, and so may not use the
            mannose-6-phosphate system for tagging and sorting newly synthesized lysosomal
            hydrolases. Worms may instead use amino acid based signals and a vps10/sortillin
            receptor type system for such sorting, as is known to be the case in yeast.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>General secretion</title>
        <para>Genome-wide RNAi experiments indicate that loss of general secretory factors often
            results in embryonic lethality and/or larval lethality associated with developmental
            arrest during molting (<link linkend="bib9">Grant and Hirsh, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10588660-->). Analysis in the germline
            indicates that general secretory defects also result in abnormal oogenesis and often
            result in multinucleate oocytes, presumably reflecting a defect in cytokinesis (<link linkend="bib9">Grant and Hirsh, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10588660-->; <link linkend="bib17">Roberts et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14551256-->). In addition
            oocytes lacking normal secretory function can produce embryos lacking a strong eggshell
            or lacking an eggshell altogether (<link linkend="bib9">Grant and Hirsh, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10588660-->). This was not
            unexpected as the eggshell is thought to form by secretion of eggshell components by the
            embryo itself shortly after fertilization.</para>
        <para>Several other proteins associated with cytokinesis are known or assumed to function in
            membrane traffic. These include the endocytic protein dynamin and the syntaxin (t-SNARE)
            homolog <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYN-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SYN-4</ulink> (<link linkend="bib12">Jantsch-Plunger and Glotzer, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10421575-->; <link linkend="bib20">Thompson et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12498685-->). Both of these proteins are associated with cleavage furrows in dividing
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> germ cells and embryonic cells and are required for
            completion of cytokinesis (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_celldivision/celldivision.html" role="_blank">Cell division</ulink>). Many proteins associated with the midbody
            during cytokinesis are thought to have functions in membrane trafficking (<link linkend="bib26">Skop et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15166316-->).</para>
        <para>One component of the general secretory pathway that has been studied in significant
            detail in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SEC-23;class=protein" role="_blank">SEC-23</ulink>, a part of the endoplasmic reticulum
            vesicle coat complex known as COPII (<xref linkend="figure5" />). COPII is known to be the primary vesicle
            coat complex used in yeast and mammalian cell transport from the ER to the Golgi.
            Roberts et al. identified a single mutant allele of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sec-23" role="_blank">sec-23</ulink></emphasis> in a
            screen for embryonic lethals defective in cuticle synthesis as assayed by a cuticle
            collagen reporter, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=col-12" role="_blank">col-12</ulink>::GFP</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib17">Roberts et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14551256-->). These authors went on to show severe defects in cuticle synthesis in
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sec-23" role="_blank">sec-23</ulink></emphasis> mutants resulting in accumulation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DPY-7;class=protein" role="_blank">DPY-7</ulink> collagen
            intracellularly, presumably in the ER. Zygotic embryonic lethality during elongation was
            found in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sec-23" role="_blank">sec-23</ulink></emphasis> homozygous mutants derived from heterozygous
            mothers. Normal progression through early development presumably relies upon maternally
            derived <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SEC-23;class=protein" role="_blank">SEC-23</ulink>. RNAi experiments revealed a requirement for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sec-23" role="_blank">sec-23</ulink></emphasis>
            during larval development, particularly during molting. Adults depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SEC-23;class=protein" role="_blank">SEC-23</ulink> by
            RNAi also showed severe germline defects including binucleate oocytes, lack of yolk
            uptake by oocytes resulting from a failure of yolk receptors (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RME-2;class=protein" role="_blank">RME-2</ulink>) to reach the cell
            surface, and premature maturation/partitioning of individual germ cells, possibly
            resulting from loss of cell surface <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLP-1</ulink> receptors in the distal gonad. A partially
            functional <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SEC-23;class=protein" role="_blank">SEC-23</ulink>::GFP reporter gene indicated that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SEC-23;class=protein" role="_blank">SEC-23</ulink> is broadly expressed at all
            life stages, and that in hypodermal cells the protein is concentrated in distinct foci.
            In the embryonic hypodermis these foci were enriched apically at the periphery of the
            endoplasmic reticulum. These <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SEC-23;class=protein" role="_blank">SEC-23</ulink> positive foci likely represent ER exit sites where
            newly synthesized cargo molecules concentrate and are packaged into COPII coated
            vesicles for delivery to the Golgi.</para>
                <para>Another class of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> proteins thought to function in
            secretion are those related to the putative hedgehog receptor Patched. Kuwabara and
            colleagues have identified 29 patched (PTC) or patched related (PTR) genes in the
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome, each of which encodes a predicted multipass
            transmembrane protein with a predicted sterol-sensing domain (<link linkend="bib14">Kuwabara et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10921907-->). The phenotypes of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ptc-1" role="_blank">ptc-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants indicate a likely
            defect in the secretory pathway and in germline cytokinesis in particular. The presence
            of such a large and diverse family of these proteins in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
            could indicate diverse functions in membrane trafficking processes (<link linkend="bib14">Kuwabara et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10921907-->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Polarized secretion</title>
        <para>Polarized cells such as epithelia maintain distinct apical and basolateral plasma
            membrane domains with distinct protein and lipid compositions. These specializations of
            the plasma membrane require complex membrane trafficking pathways thought to include
            unique basolateral versus apical sorting mechanisms in the secretory pathway to direct
            newly synthesized proteins to the correct membrane domain. Additional regulation of the
            endocytosis pathway maintains polarity of lipid and protein components after
            internalization and recycling.</para>
        <para>Ectodermal cells with epithelial characteristics are an important class of polarized
            cells that have come under intense scrutiny in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> in recent
            years. These include epidermal cells (hypodermal cells), vulval and rectal epithelia,
            glia-like sheath and socket cells that support sensory neurons of the amphid and phasmid
            sensory organs, and the excretory cell, a single cell that forms a renal-type organ,
            extending a long cytoplasmic process called the excretory canal on each side of the
            animal.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Apical secretion</title>
            <para>A large number of mutants (<emphasis>exc</emphasis> genes) that display defects in
                apical membrane formation in excretory cells have been identified (<link linkend="bib3">Buechner et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10491271-->). Some of these are likely to function directly in membrane
                transport to form or maintain apical membranes. A likely candidate for mediating
                vesicular transport is <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EXC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">EXC-4</ulink>, a member of the CLIC chloride channel family (<link linkend="bib1">Berry et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14684823-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EXC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">EXC-4</ulink> localizes to vesicles that fuse together to form
                the apical membrane of the lumen in the excretory canals. Furthermore
                    <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=exc-4" role="_blank">exc-4</ulink></emphasis> is continuously required for tube formation and
                maintenance. Although the precise mechanisms remain unclear, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EXC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">EXC-4</ulink> may function in
                apical secretory vesicle fusion to promote tube formation.</para>
            <para>All of the ectodermal epithelial-like cells are known to require the
                    <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-26" role="_blank">lin-26</ulink></emphasis> transcription factor to aquire their final
                differentiated forms (<link linkend="bib15">Labouesse et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 7956818-->). In particular it is the
                apical membrane domain that appear most severely affected in
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-26" role="_blank">lin-26</ulink></emphasis> mutant ectodermal epithelia. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-26;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-26</ulink> has therefore been
                proposed to regulate the expression of gene products that form and maintain apical
                epithelial character. Screens for mutants with Lin-26-like defects could therefore
                identify apical-specific trafficking factors. Michaux et al (<link linkend="bib16">Michaux et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 10996790-->) took just this approach and identified <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CHE-14;class=protein" role="_blank">CHE-14</ulink>, a predicted 12-pass
                transmembrane protein required for the function of these cell-types.
                    <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=che-14" role="_blank">che-14</ulink></emphasis> mutants displayed defects in the hypodermis,
                excretory canal, vulva, rectum and amphids and phasmids. In
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=che-14" role="_blank">che-14</ulink></emphasis> mutants vesicles and amorphous material accumulate near
                the apical surface of the affected cells suggesting that secretion is defective.
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CHE-14;class=protein" role="_blank">CHE-14</ulink> contains a sterol-sensing domain, a type of domain found in proteins such as
                Dispatched, Patched and PC1 that are involved in cholesterol associated trafficking
                processes. A rescuing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CHE-14;class=protein" role="_blank">CHE-14</ulink>::GFP reporter is localized to the apical surface of
                epithelial cells that require <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=che-14" role="_blank">che-14</ulink></emphasis> function, consistent with
                such a proposed function (<link linkend="bib16">Michaux et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10996790-->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Basolateral secretion</title>
            <para>Basolateral-specific transport pathways are also thought to play key roles in
                polarized cells. The best studied of these pathways in <emphasis>C.
                elegans</emphasis> is in the transport of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> EGF-receptor in the vulval
                precursor cells (VPCs; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RTKRasMAPKsignaling/RTKRasMAPKsignaling.html" role="_blank">RTKRas/MAP kinase signaling</ulink>). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> is normally restricted to the
                basolateral membrane of the VPCs, a process that requires the PDZ-domain proteins
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-2;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-7;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-7</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-10;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-10</ulink> (<link linkend="bib13">Kaech et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9753323-->). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-2;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-2</ulink>/7/10 complex
                binds directly to the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> intracellular domain, and is therefore likely to
                function as a sorting factor, directing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> to the basolateral membrane during
                secretion and/or after endocytosis and recycling (<link linkend="bib13">Kaech et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9753323-->).
                The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-10;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-10</ulink> protein has been shown to associate with an intracellular compartment on
                or near the Golgi consistent with a role in protein sorting during secretion (<link linkend="bib22">Whitfield et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10359617-->).</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
		<para/>
		&Itra_Refs;</sect1>
</article>