<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'transsplicingfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'transsplicingfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'transsplicingfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'transsplicingfig2leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY transsplicing_Refs SYSTEM 'transsplicingrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="Transsplicingandoperons_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Trans-splicing and operons<footnote><para>Edited by Lisa R. Girard. Last revised July 7, 2005.  Published June 25, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Blumenthal, T. Trans-splicing and operons (June 25, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.5.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 Thomas Blumenthal. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
</footnote></title>
        <author>
            <firstname>Thomas</firstname>
            <surname>Blumenthal<remark>
<footnote>
                        <para>Current address: Department of Molecular, Cellular, and Developmental Biology, University of Colorado, Boulder, CO 80309-0347 USA</para></footnote>
<footnote>
                        <para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:tom.blumenthal@colorado.edu">tom.blumenthal@colorado.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Department of Biochemistry &amp; Molecular Genetics, University of Colorado School of Medicine, Aurora, CO 80045 USA</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">About 70% of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">mRNAs are
            trans-spliced to one of two 22 nucleotide spliced leaders. SL1 is used to trim off the
            5' ends of pre-mRNAs and replace them with the SL1 sequence. This processing event is
            very closely related to cis-splicing, or intron removal. The SL1 sequence is donated by
            a 100 nt small nuclear ribonucleoprotein particle (snRNP). This snRNP is structurally
            and functionally related to the U snRNAs (U1, U2, U4, U5 and U6) that play key roles in
            intron removal and trans-splicing, except that it is consumed in the process of
            splicing. More than half of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">pre-mRNAs
            are subject to SL1 trans-splicing. About 30% are not trans-spliced at all. The remaining
            genes are trans-spliced by SL2. These genes are all downstream genes in closely spaced
            gene clusters similar to bacterial operons. They are transcribed from a promoter at the
            5' end of the cluster of between 2 and 8 genes. This transcription makes a polycistronic pre-mRNA that
            is co-transcriptionally processed by cleavage and polyadenylation at the 3' end of each
            gene, and this event is closely coupled to the SL2 trans-splicing event that occurs only
            ~100 nt further downstream. Recent studies on the mechanism of SL2 trans-splicing have
            revealed that one of the 3' end formation proteins, CstF, interacts with the only
            protein known to be specific to the SL2 snRNP. The operons contain primarily genes whose products are needed for mitochondrial function and the basic machinery of gene
            expression: transcription, splicing and translation. Many operons contain genes whose
            products are known to function together. This presumably provides co-regulation of these
            proteins by producing a single RNA that encodes both.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
    <sect1>
        <title>Trans-splicing</title>
        <para>mRNAs of ~70% of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes begin with a 22 nucleotide sequence, the spliced leader or SL, which is not associated with the gene (recently reviewed in <link linkend="bib6">Blumenthal and Steward, 1997</link> and <link linkend="bib23">Hastings, 2005</link>). The SL is donated by a 100 nucleotide RNA, SL RNA, by trans-splicing. This process is closely related to cis-splicing (intron removal): the 5' splice site is on the SL RNA, and the site of SL addition, the trans-splice site is the 3' splice site on the pre-mRNA (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). The reaction proceeds by way of a branched intermediate similar to the lariat of cis-splicing. Trans-splicing is catalyzed by spliceosomes, including U2, U4, U5, and U6 snRNPs but not U1 (<link linkend="bib22">Hannon et al., 1991</link><!-- PMID 1835972 -->). A similar reaction occurs throughout the nematode phylum as well as in some protists (e.g., trypanosomes) and many other animals including flatworms, hydra and primitive chordates (<link linkend="bib1">Agabian, 1990</link><!-- PMID 2142018 -->; <link linkend="bib12">Davis, 1997</link><!-- PMID 9233671 -->; <link linkend="bib20">Ganot et al., 2004</link>; <link linkend="bib42">Stover and Steele, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11331766 -->; <link linkend="bib44">Vandenberghe et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11159910 -->). SL1 is the major spliced leader in nematodes, and it is used primarily for trans-splicing at the 3' splice sites following outrons, sequences resembling introns at the very 5' ends of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> pre-mRNAs (<link linkend="bib11">Conrad et al., 1991</link><!-- PMID 1848665 -->). About half the genes are estimated to have outrons and are consequently trans-spliced to SL1 (<link linkend="bib47">Zorio et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 7969472 -->). Furthermore, a second SL, SL2, is trans-spliced to some <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes (<link linkend="bib26">Huang and Hirsh, 1989</link><!-- PMID 2813415 -->). SL2 trans-splices exclusively at trans-splice sites between genes in polycistronic pre-mRNAs from operons (<link linkend="bib4">Blumenthal et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12075352 -->; <link linkend="bib40">Spieth et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8098272 -->). About 15% of all <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes are found in operons. Finally, about 30% of genes specify mRNAs that are not subject to trans-splicing. In these cases, the promoter is at the 5' end of the first exon like in genes of organisms that do not trans-splice.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
			<imageobject>
			<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
<textobject><phrase> figure 1</phrase></textobject>
			&fig1legend;
		</mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Trans-splicing precursors</title>
        <para>The SL RNAs exist as snRNPs (<link linkend="bib6">Blumenthal and Steward, 1997</link>; <link linkend="bib23">Hastings, 2005</link>). They have a discrete secondary structure as do other snRNAs, they are bound to the Sm proteins, and they have a trimethylguanosine (TMG) cap like the U snRNAs. In the
            SL snRNPs the 5' splice sites are base paired to the upstream part of the SL sequence,
            resembling the U1-5' splice site base pairing. The trans-splice site consensus on the
            pre-mRNAs is the same as the intron 3' splice site consensus. The signal for
            trans-splicing is simply the presence of intron-like sequence, the outron, at the 5' end
            of the mRNA, with no functional 5' splice site upstream (<link linkend="bib9">Conrad et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 7585246 -->; <link linkend="bib10">Conrad et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8458337 -->; <link linkend="bib11">Conrad et al., 1991</link><!-- PMID 1848665 -->). Genes
            whose pre-mRNAs are subject to trans-splicing are distinguished from those that are not
            only by the presence of an outron. Thus, the choice between cis- and trans- splicing at
            any 3' splice site is based solely on the presence or absence of an upstream 5' splice
            site. Because trans-splicing is relatively efficient (like cis-splicing), it is
            difficult to isolate outron-containing pre-mRNAs, so very few natural outrons have been
            defined. Nevertheless, in a few cases the promoters of trans-spliced genes or start
            sites of outrons have been identified [e.g., <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=col-13" role="_blank">col-13</ulink></emphasis> has a 64 bp
            outron (<link linkend="bib36">Park and Kramer, 1990</link><!-- PMID 1689778 -->) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rol-6" role="_blank">rol-6</ulink></emphasis> has a 172 bp
            outron (<link linkend="bib10">Conrad et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8458337 -->) ].</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Mechanism of trans-splicing</title>
        <para>Trans-splicing follows the same course as cis-splicing: cleavage of the 5' exon, the
            SL, and formation of an intermediate with the 5' splice site of the SL RNA branched to
            an A on the outron in the first step, and splicing of the SL to the first exon of the
            pre-mRNA in the second step (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). However, we still do not know
            how the SL snRNP is attracted to a 3' splice site on a pre-mRNA target only when there
            is no 5' splice site upstream. One can imagine U2 snRNP interacting with the 3' splice
            site and attracting the SL1 snRNP only when there is no upstream U1 snRNP with which to
            interact, but this is conjecture. A second possibility is that the SL snRNP is attracted
            to the trans-spliceosome by an affinity for the nuclear cap binding complex present at
            the 5' end of the pre-mRNA, and therefore just upstream of the trans-splice site (<xref
            linkend="figure1"/>), or by an affinity for the RNA polymerase II C-terminal domain.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>The role of snRNP proteins</title>
        <para>The SL snRNP was purified from <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis>, a parasitic
            nematode, and found to contain a heterodimeric protein, neither subunit of which has
            known homologs outside of the nematodes (<link linkend="bib14">Denker et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12050671 -->). The larger
            subunit, SL-175p, is actually 95 kD, but runs anomalously large on SDS gels. In
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, this polypeptide has a single homolog of 75 kD that
            is required for viability and is associated with both SL1 and SL2 snRNPs (M. Kumar, M.
            MacMorris, A. Larsen, and T. Blumenthal, unpublished). The smaller
            <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis> polypeptide, SL-30p, interacts with the branchpoint binding
            protein, an interaction that was shown to be important for trans-splicing (<link linkend="bib14">Denker et
            al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12050671 -->). SL-30p has two orthologs in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>:
            SL-21p is associated with the SL1 snRNP and is more closely related to the
            <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis> protein than is the other ortholog, SL-26p. The latter is
            associated primarily with the SL2 snRNP (M. Kumar, M. MacMorris, A. Larsen and T.
            Blumenthal, unpublished). These proteins may be the key to both SL1 versus SL2
            specificity and mechanistic aspects of the reaction.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Evolution and role of trans-splicing</title>
        <para>Trans-splicing occurs throughout the nematodes, and there is striking conservation of
            the SL sequence, whereas the portions of the SL RNAs downstream of the splice site have
            diverged (<link linkend="bib6">Blumenthal and Steward, 1997</link>). The role that SL plays in the cell, however, is not known.. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> the SL tends to be spliced very
            close to the initiating methionine codon (often immediately adjacent), so it seems
            likely to play a role in translation initiation (<link linkend="bib6">Blumenthal and Steward, 1997</link>;
            <link linkend="bib30">Lall et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15322127 -->). The TMG cap present at the 5' end of the SL becomes
            the 5' end of trans-spliced mRNAs. A TMG cap stimulates translation in nematodes, at
            least when it is present at the 5' end of the SL sequence (<link linkend="bib30">Lall et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15322127 -->; <link linkend="bib35">Maroney et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 7585256 -->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, variants of the cap binding translation initiation factor, eIF4E can recognize
            the TMG cap (<link linkend="bib27">Keiper et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10744754 -->). </para>
        <para>In <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis>, the SL sequence in the DNA is needed for
            transcription of the SL RNA gene, which may be one reason why it has been so highly
            conserved (<link linkend="bib21">Hannon et al., 1990</link><!-- PMID 2347310 -->). Although the roles the SL sequence itself may perform are unknown, trans-splicing is in fact required for
            viability (<link linkend="bib18">Ferguson et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8666237 -->). Its required role could be a positive
            effect such as providing a sequence that can facilitate translation initiation, mRNA
            stability or localization, or it could be required for suppression of a negative effect
            such as inhibition of translation initiation by AUG codons in the outron.</para>
        <para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome contains 110 SL1 RNA genes on the 1 kb
            tandem repeat that also contains the genes for 5S rRNA (<link linkend="bib28">Krause and Hirsh, 1987</link><!-- PMID 3581169 -->). In contrast, the genome contains only18 dispersed SL2 RNA genes, which specify
            a variety of variant SL2 RNAs (<link linkend="bib41">Stein et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14624247 -->). Some of these have
            different SL2 sequences, and these have been given different names, such as SL3, SL4 etc. (<link linkend="bib39">Ross et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 7665629 -->). Nonetheless, they are all variants of SL2 and they
            are used randomly at SL2-accepting trans-splice sites (T. Blumenthal, unpublished). The
                <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> genome also contains 18 SL2 RNA genes, and all 36
            genes from the two species descended from four primordial SL2 RNA genes present in their
            last common ancestor (<link linkend="bib41">Stein et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14624247 -->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Discovery of operons</title>
        <para>The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gpd-3" role="_blank">gpd-3</ulink></emphasis> gene and several other genes whose mRNAs receive SL2
            were found to occur at downstream positions in closely-spaced clusters of identically
            oriented genes (<link linkend="bib3">Blumenthal, 2004</link>; <link linkend="bib40">Spieth et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8098272 -->; <link linkend="bib47">Zorio et al.,
            1994</link><!-- PMID 7969472 -->). Although first genes in some clusters are trans-spliced to SL1,
            others are not trans-spliced. The presence of a gene in a downstream location in a
            closely-spaced cluster signals that its product should be SL2 trans-spliced (<xref
            linkend="figure2"/>). A microarray analysis of the entire genome demonstrated how truly
            robust this correlation is (<link linkend="bib4">Blumenthal et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12075352 -->). This analysis
            identified more than 1000 such clusters in which the downstream mRNAs are trans-spliced
            to SL2; these clusters contain more than 2600 genes. These operons range from two to
            eight genes in length and can cover more than 50 kb of the genome. They are found on all
            chromosomes, but they are rare on the X chromosome.</para>

    <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
			<imageobject>
			<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="5.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
<textobject><phrase>  figure 2</phrase></textobject>
			&fig2legend;
		</mediaobject>
        <para>How does chromosomal position translate into SL2 specificity? The clusters are operons
            in the sense that the gene cluster is transcribed from a single promoter and regulatory
            region. The resulting polycistronic pre-mRNA is converted into monocistronic mRNAs by
            cleavage and polyadenylation at the 3' ends of the upstream genes, accompanied by
            SL2-specific trans-splicing at the 5' ends of the downstream genes.
	    A look at the list of 1000 operons reveals some general properties (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/operon?name=*;class=Operon" role="_blank">WormBase operon list</ulink>). The genes are very close together;
            typically only 100 bp separates the poladenylation site of the upstream gene from the
            trans-splice site of the downstream gene, although the spacing can range up to a kb or
            two in extreme cases. Both SL2 and SL1 can be used to process downstream genes, with a
            greater fraction of SL2 when the genes are closer together (T. Blumenthal, unpublished observations).</para>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Signals on the polycistronic pre-mRNA for SL2 trans-splicing</title>
        <para>Besides the splice site itself, only two sequences on the pre-mRNA play an important
            role in SL2-specific trans-splicing: the two presumptive signals for 3' end formation of
            the gene just upstream (<xref linkend="figure2"/>; <link linkend="bib25">Huang et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11158298 -->;
            <link linkend="bib29">Kuersten et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9056764 -->; <link linkend="bib33">Liu et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11233975 -->; <link linkend="bib34">Liu et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12756326 -->). The AAUAAA just 5' of the cleavage site, which is absolutely required
            for 3' end formation, binds the cleavage and polyadenylation specificity factor (CPSF),
            and a U-rich sequence just 3' of the cleavage site binds the cleavage stimulatory factor
            (CstF). CPSF and CstF bind cooperatively to these two sites and together position the
            site of cleavage. When the AAUAAA is mutated, 3' end cleavage fails to occur, and
            trans-splicing just downstream becomes less efficient and less specific for SL2.
            Nevertheless, AAUAAA is not required for SL2 trans-splicing since SL2 trans-splicing
            downstream still occurs in its absence. CPSF bound to AAUAAA may act by facilitating
            binding of CstF to the U-rich sequence or by catalyzing 3' end formation itself, which
            in turn may play a role in SL2 trans-splicing. The protein that binds to the U-rich
            sequence appears to play the major role in SL2 trans-splicing. When this sequence is
            mutated, 3' end formation can still occur, albeit somewhat less efficiently, but
            downstream trans-spliced product fails to accumulate. Thus, either transcription
            terminates or the downstream RNA is degraded from the site of 3' end formation. When 3'
            end formation is prevented by mutating both the AAUAAA and the U-rich sequence,
            downstream product is restored, but all of it is trans-spliced to SL1. The protein that
            binds to the U-rich element, presumably CstF, performs two functions: it blocks
            exonucleolytic degradation of the downstream RNA beginning at the site of 3' end
            cleavage and it recruits the SL2 snRNP. The MS2 phage coat protein tethered to this
            region in place of the U-rich sequence can substitute for the first function, but not
            the second (<link linkend="bib34">Liu et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12756326 -->).</para>
        <para>How does the protein bound to the U-rich element attract the SL2 snRNP? Presuming the protein is CstF, it appears to do so by direct interaction. Antibodies to CstF have been found
            to immunoprecipitate the SL2 snRNP from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo extracts,
            and the region of SL2 RNA required for SL2 identity is also required for the CstF
            interaction, although it is not required for snRNP function (<link linkend="bib15">Evans and Blumenthal, 2000</link><!-- PMID 10958663 -->; <link linkend="bib16">Evans et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11581161 -->). The current model for polycistronic
            pre-mRNA processing involves first 3' end cleavage at the upstream gene by conventional
            mechanisms. This sets in motion the chain of events that leads to SL2 trans-splicing:
            the free 5' phosphate at the cleavage site is attacked by an exonuclease that is then
            stopped at the U-rich element by the CstF that had bound there for 3' end formation.
            CstF attracts, or is already bound to, the SL2 snRNP, which splices to the trans-splice
            site just downstream.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>SL1-type operon</title>
	<para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome also contains a
        second type of operon different from those described above in two significant ways (<xref
        linkend="figure2"/>; <link linkend="bib46">Williams et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 9858561 -->). The mRNA of the downstream gene
        is trans-spliced to SL1, rather than SL2, and there is no intercistronic sequence. The site
        of polyadenylation of the upstream gene and the trans-splice site are at adjacent
        nucleotides. Only twenty operons of this type have been identified, so it is quite uncommon
        (T. Blumenthal, unpublished). This kind of operon is distinguished from the major type by
        the fact that 3' end formation of the upstream gene eliminates the trans-splice site of the
        downstream gene, so that any given pre-mRNA gives rise to either the upstream or the
        downstream mRNA, but not both.</para></sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Function of operons</title>
        <para> Do the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> operons exist to assure coordinate regulation
            of genes whose products function together? There is no question that the genes in
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> operons are often co-expressed (<link linkend="bib31">Land et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 8182089 -->) but in many cases they appear not to be (K. Seggerson-Gleason and T.
            Blumenthal, unpublished observations; <link linkend="bib2">Baugh et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12538516 -->). This could be
            because the mRNAs have very different stabilities or because processing is modulated.
            One reasonable idea is that the operons have accumulated genes that are regulated at
            some level after transcription initiation. In this model the operons are transcribed
            from promiscuously expressed promoters because they are regulated at the level of RNA
            stability or translation. Consistent with this idea, genes that encode proteins that act
            in mRNA degradation are the most frequent class of genes to be contained in operons (80%
            are in operons; <link linkend="bib5">Blumenthal and Gleason, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12560808 -->). These may be autogenously
            regulated at the level at which they act. This idea is quite similar to current thinking
            on gene regulation in trypanosomes, where all transcription is polycistronic and genes
            are thought to be regulated primarily or entirely post-transcriptionally (<link linkend="bib8">Clayton, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11953307 -->).</para>
        <para>However, there are unquestionably examples among the operons where genes of related
            function are co-expressed due to their presence in an operon under the control of a
            single promoter. For instance, the two <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-15" role="_blank">lin-15</ulink></emphasis> genes are contained
            in an operon; these two unrelated proteins collaborate in an aspect of signal
            transduction required for formation of the vulva (<link linkend="bib7">Clark et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 7982579 -->;
            <link linkend="bib24">Huang et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 8054684 -->). A second example is the<emphasis>
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=des-2" role="_blank">des-2</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=deg-3" role="_blank">deg-3</ulink></emphasis> operon, which encodes both subunits of the acetylcholine receptor
            channel (<link linkend="bib43">Treinin et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9860996 -->). Clearly, these two genes are co-regulated
            in the same transcription unit because their products function together. In another
            instance a protein function was hypothesized based on the two genes being present in an
            operon together: one gene was found to encode a modifier of the gating of an ion channel
            encoded by another gene in the same operon (<link linkend="bib19">Furst et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 11706026 -->). There
            are also several examples of operons that encode both a basic transcription factor for
            RNA polymerase I, II or III, along with a subunit of that polymerase. So co-expression
            of genes of related function is clearly a feature of at least some of the operons
            (<link linkend="bib5">Blumenthal and Gleason, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12560808 -->). </para>
        <para>Certain classes of genes are dramatically overrepresented in operons while other
            classes are missing or nearly so from the operon list (<link linkend="bib5">Blumenthal and Gleason, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12560808 -->). In general, tissue-specific genes are not transcribed in operons. The
            most frequently operon-included genes are those that encode mitochondrial proteins and
            the basic machinery of gene expression: transcription, splicing and translation. It
            appears that the driving force for operon inclusion is high expression in the female
            germ line (<link linkend="bib38">Reinke, 2004</link>).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Evolution of operons in the nematodes</title>
        <para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> operons are probably not ancient but
            are instead an innovation, perhaps having evolved as a response to selection for a small
            genome due to very rapid cell divisions during embryogenesis. The two molecules known to
            be specific for operon pre-mRNA processing, SL2 RNA and SL-26p, an SL2 snRNP protein,
            are both evolving very rapidly, consistent with the idea that they are relatively recent
            innovations; T. Blumenthal, unpublished). Once formed, the operons appear to be very
            stable: 97% of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> operons are present in <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>, a
            nematode that is ~100 million years diverged from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib41">Stein
            et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14624247 -->).</para>
        <para>The SL2 snRNP has been found in several members of the rhabditid nematode group
            including <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>, <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis>,
            <emphasis>Haemonchus</emphasis> and <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis>, many of which
            have been shown to use SL2 to trans-splice downstream genes in operons (<link linkend="bib17">Evans et al.,
            1997</link><!-- PMID 9275196 -->; <link linkend="bib32">Lee and Sommer, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12949121 -->; <link linkend="bib37">Redmond and Knox, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11551637 -->). Distantly related nematodes may not contain a specialized snRNP for
            processing operons, but they appear to contain operons nonetheless (<link linkend="bib45">Whitton et al.,
            2004</link><!-- PMID 15383292 -->). It seems likely that operons developed early in nematode evolution
            because they had trans-splicing to process downstream mRNAs. The same snRNP could serve
            for either outron or operon processing. However, during nematode evolution, a new snRNP,
            SL2, evolved from SL1, specialized for processing operon pre-mRNAs more efficiently. It
            appears this was accomplished by evolving a site for CstF interaction (<link linkend="bib16">Evans et al.,
            2001</link><!-- PMID 11581161 -->). Once this snRNP evolved, it was able to process operons
            efficiently, so it provided the opportunity for further evolution of operons. These
            additional operons then provided the selective pressure to improve SL2 function in
            operon processing. </para>
        <para>Evolution away from dependence on trans-splicing and operons must be very difficult. Trans-splicing removes selective pressure contraints on regions upstream from the splice acceptor site, presumably allowing upstream AUG codons to accumulate in the region that is removed by trans-splicing in most mRNAs. If trans-splicing did not occur, translation of these mRNAs would be abrogated by the out of frame AUG codons. Similarly, operons may be stable because downstream genes become dependent on the upstream gene's promoter. Flatworms and primitive chordates, representing two very distantly related animal phyla, also have both trans-splicing and operons, so the evolutionary scenario hypothesized above may have occurred several times in different animal lineages (<link linkend="bib13">Davis and Hodgson, 1997</link><!-- PMID 9297698 -->; <link linkend="bib20">Ganot et al., 2004</link>).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Acknowledgements</title>
        <para>I am grateful to Dick Davis for helpful comments on the manuscript. This work was
            supported by grants from the National Institute of General Medical Sciences.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
		<para/>
		&transsplicing_Refs;</sect1>
</article>