<caption>
	<formalpara>
		<title>Figure 1. The analysis of measurements of age-related changes.</title>
		<para>A comprehensive description of an age-related decline involves a large data set consisting of phenotypic values measured at many different times. These panels illustrate several approaches that are used to analyze these data sets. These approaches generate summary statistics that are used to compare age-related changes displayed by two groups of animals. The blue and red lines (A-D) are hypothetical examples of data sets generated by measuring a quantitative phenotype as a function of time for two groups of animals. The blue animals displayed a more rapid age-related decline than the red animals. (A) Blue and red animals were compared by determining the phenotypic value for each group of animals at one predetermined time. The typical summary statistic is the average phenotypic value at the predetermined time. Colored bars on the Y-axis illustrate the phenotypic value of the blue and red groups, and a black triangle represents the difference between these groups. The blue value is smaller, indicating a more rapid decline. (B) Blue and red animals were compared by modeling each data set with a straight line. One approach to comparing these lines is to compute the value of the X-intercept. As shown below, the X-intercept of the blue group occurred at an earlier time, indicating a more rapid decline. (C) Blue and red animals were compared by analyzing the time when each group transitioned to a predetermined phenotypic value. The typical summary statistic is the average span of time from the start of the experiment to the transition time. As shown below, the transition time of the blue group occurred at an earlier time, indicating a more rapid decline. (D) If a phenotypic value is predetermined as shown in panel C, then each animal can be classified as above or below that value. The fraction of animals above the value can be plotted. This is the standard approach for survival data, where the predetermined phenotypic value is alive (versus dead), and the typical summary statistic is the mean lifespan. In addition, this approach can be used for other binary phenotypes, such as fast body movement versus slow body movement. The graph shows that the fraction of animals above the predetermined value declines more rapidly in the blue group. (E) Stages of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> aging as presented by <link linkend="bib26">Huang et al. (2004)</link>. This is a representation of four different age-related declines that were analyzed using the approach shown in panel D. Stage I is the period of self-fertile progeny production and is defined as the time from L4 to the end of the self-fertile reproductive span. Stage II is a post reproductive period characterized by vigorous motor activity and is defined as the time from the end of stage I to the end of the fast body movement span. Stage III is a period of reduced motor activity and is defined as the time from the end of stage II to the end of the pharyngeal pumping span. Stage IV is a period of minimal motor activity and is defined as the time from the end of stage III to the end of the lifespan. The bars show data from wild-type animals cultured at 20&#x000B0;C and 15&#x000B0;C and <emphasis>daf-2(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1370;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1370</ulink>)</emphasis> animals cultured at 20&#x000B0;C. These bars represent average values for the self-fertile reproductive span, fast body movement span, pharyngeal pumping span and lifespan determined as shown in panel D.</para>
	</formalpara>
</caption>