<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 8. <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> Rheb has converged towards the Ral subfamily.</title><para>The convergence was observed for <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> Rheb and Ral, but not <emphasis role="italic">Drosophila</emphasis> and human Rheb and Ral. Core GTPase sequences of human, fly, and worm Rheb subfamily and Ral subfamily proteins were aligned and scored for number of convergent vs. divergent residues. Residues that converge towards the consensus of the compared subfamily (here called &ldquo;transvergent&rdquo;) and are identical (light green highlighting) were valued at 1, with conservative transvergence (dark green highlighting) valued at 0.5. True convergence of a residue from both subfamilies to a new residue type (light green letter) was also valued at 0.5, while divergence (blue letter) was valued as zero. Events in the broad effector binding region (grayed, with core underlined) or G boxes were rated with higher impact (0.5 becoming 1.0). By this standard <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00191;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHEB-1</ulink> converged toward <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46416;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAL-1</ulink>, with <emphasis role="italic">Drosophila</emphasis> and human Rheb and Ral as negative controls (Fisher&apos;s Exact Test, P&lt;0.0001). <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00191;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHEB-1</ulink>, and to a lesser degree <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46416;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAL-1</ulink>, also contains significantly more divergent residues, perhaps reflecting a protein under more intense selective pressure than is typical. This convergent evolution may reflect the loss of TSC/RhebGAP but retention of HGAP/RalGAP in the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> clade, so the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00191;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHEB-1</ulink> protein is adapted to co-regulation by RalGAP. Classic Rheb changes at positions 12 and 13 (Ras numbering) are indicated by purple (blue in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00191;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHEB-1</ulink>).</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>