<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 1. Light fixation and staining of multiple antigens in the head of an adult OH99 <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/misc/etree?name=mgIs18;class=Transgene" role="_blank">mgIs18</ulink></emphasis> [P<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis>GFP] prepared using <link linkend="sec2_6">Protocol 6</link>. Freeze-crack</title>
        <para>(A) Staining of the vesicular monoamine transporter (VMAT = <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CAT-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CAT-1</ulink>), shown in red. This antigen is found in synaptic vesicles of monoaminergic neurons.(B) DNA, white, was labeled with DAPI. (C) The vesicular acetylcholine transporter (VAChT = <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-17;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-17</ulink>), found in cholinergic synaptic vesicles, is shown in blue. (D) Staining with an anti-GFP antibody is shown in green. The GFP fills the cytoplasm of the AIY neurons. (E) Merged image of anti-VMAT (red), anti-VAChT (blue), and anti-GFP (green). (F) Merged image of anti-VMAT (red), anti-GFP (green) and DAPI (blue). Fixation was for 2 minutes in methanol followed by 4 minutes in acetone. Staining followed <link linkend="sec2_13">Protocol 13: Staining slides</link>. Primary antibodies were goat anti-VMAT (Goat 258 polyclonal antibody purified with <link linkend="sec2_4">Protocol 4: Affinity purification</link>), rabbit anti-GFP (Molecular Probes) and mouse anti-VAChT (Monoclonal 1403). Secondary antibodies were Cy3-conjugated donkey anti-goat, Oregon Green 488-conjugated donkey anti-rabbit, and Cy5-conjugated donkey anti-mouse. See <link linkend="sec2_13">Protocol 13: Staining slides</link> for a discussion of anti-GFP and secondary antibodies. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/misc/etree?name=mgIs18;class=Transgene" role="_blank">mgIs18</ulink></emphasis> [P<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis>::GFP] was a gift of O. Hobert; <emphasis>unc-104(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1265;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1265</ulink>)</emphasis> was provided by the CGC. Images are maximum projections of confocal series, contrast enhanced in Adobe Photoshop&#x000AE;. Anterior to left, ventral down, scale bar is 10 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03BC;</symbol>m.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>