<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 4. Staining in wild-type versus transgenic strains</title>
        <para>The transgenic strain RM1810 <emphasis>cha-1(md39)</emphasis>; mdEx10 [<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/clone?name=F57G7;class=Clone" role="_blank">F57G7</ulink>] contains multiple copies of the cosmid that contains the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cha-1" role="_blank">cha-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-17" role="_blank">unc-17</ulink></emphasis> genes. This strain produces abnormally high levels of the ChAT and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-17;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-17</ulink>/VAChT proteins. It is useful for testing the specificity of anti-ChAT and anti-VAChT antibody staining in situ, for increased ease of cell identification, and also for Westerns (see <link linkend="sec2_17">Protocol 17: Western transfer</link>). (A) Staining of the VAChT, shown in red, in RM1810. (B) The same worm stained with DAPI to show nuclei. (C) A higher magnification view of the head of the same individual. (D) VAChT staining in a wild-type N2 shows the typical synaptic localization of the protein. Note that over-expression of VAChT leads to mislocalization of the protein in neuronal somas (compare panels C and D). The RM1810 and wild-type worms were prepared using <link linkend="sec2_6">Protocol 6: Freeze-crack</link>. Fixation was for 2 minutes in methanol followed by 4 minutes in acetone. Staining followed <link linkend="sec2_13">Protocol 13: Staining slides</link>, with mouse anti-VAChT (Monoclonal 1403) as the primary antibody, followed by Cy3-conjugated donkey anti-mouse. DNA was labeled by addition of DAPI in the mounting medium. Maximum projection of overlapping confocal series, contrast enhanced in Adobe Photoshop&#x000AE;. Anterior to left, ventral down, scale bar is 10 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03BC;</symbol>m.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>