<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 7. The Poison and Dosage Models of vesicle priming at the synapse</title>
        <para>(A) A schematic of primed vesicles along the active zone at a wild-type synapse. In The
            Dosage Model, the <emphasis>unc-13(null)/+</emphasis> ; <emphasis>unc-64(null)/+</emphasis> trans-heterozygote would have half the
            amount of UNC-13 and UNC-64, which would result in a decrease in the number of primed
            vesicles ready for synaptic release. In The Poison Model, the <emphasis>unc-13(poison)/+</emphasis>;
            <emphasis>unc-64(poison)/+</emphasis> trans-heterozygote would produce products that would interfere with the
            formation of functional complexes. Altered UNC-13 and altered UNC-64 can participate in
            the same complex and render it non-functional. In addition these altered products can
            form complexes with wild-type partners, sequestering them in non-functional complexes.
            These interactions would reduce the level of functional complexes to below half the
            normal amount. (B) The synaptic vesicle cycle at a cholinergic synapse. Synaptic vesicles
            and associated proteins are transported to the synapse from the cell body by the
            synaptic vesicle kinesin protein UNC-104. Acetylcholine, made by CHA-1, is packaged into vesicles by the acetylcholine transporter, UNC-17. Mature synaptic vesicles must be
            docked and primed at the synapse so that the vesicle can rapidly fuse with the plasma
            membrane when the neuron is depolarized. Docking and priming of the vesicle requires the
            dissociation of UNC-18 from UNC-64/syntaxin and the association of UNC-13 with UNC-64. The vesicle is fully primed when SNB-1 joins the UNC-13/UNC-64 complex. After vesicle fusion, the vesicle and its associated proteins are recovered from the plasma membrane through clathrin-mediated endocytosis, which utilizes the <symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x03BC;</symbol>2/DPY-23 containing AP-2
            adaptor complex (W.S. Davis et al., WBPaper00023077). Recycling
            of the synaptic vesicles and their associated proteins is required for maintaining a
            readily releasable pool.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>
