<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 4. Intragenic complementation of <emphasis>let-2</emphasis> alleles</title>
        <para>(A) <emphasis>let-2</emphasis> alleles exhibit a very complex pattern of complementation. Lines between
            alleles indicate non-complementation (the expected outcome). Alleles that are not joined
            by a line complement one another to some extent. Reprinted with permission from <link linkend="bib35">Meneely and Herman, 1981</link><!-- ; PMID 7196363 -->. Copyright &#x000A9;1981 the Genetics Society of America. (B) A schematic of the LET-2 (<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>2)IV collagen, adapted from <link linkend="bib52">Sibley et al. (1993<!-- ; PMID 7691828 -->)</link>. Conserved type IV collagen features include extensive Gly-X-Y repeats (in blue) with interspersed interruptions (vertical
            black lines), non-collagenous termini (in grey) with a conserved NC1 domain at the
            C-terminus. Cross-hatched area denotes an alternative splice region. Locations of
            mutations are indicated with the strongest mutations (&gt;90% homozygous embryonic
            lethality at 20<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>) in bold. <emphasis>mn153</emphasis> (boxed in red), is the only mutation that does not
            complement any other allele aside from <emphasis>b246</emphasis> (boxed in green), which complements all
            other alleles to some extent. The interruptions in the Gly-X-Y repeat domains lower the
            thermal stability of the region resulting in more severe phenotypes of Gly-X-Y mutations
            (noted in bold). (C) Type IV collagen is composed of a heterotrimer of 1 <symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>2(IV) collagen
            chain and 2 <symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>1(IV) chains. These heterotrimers can dimerize at their C-terminal NC1
            domains, and then form a complex lattice through tetramerization of their N-terminal
            regions and lateral interactions along their triple helical domains. Mutations in the
            Gly-X-Y repeats would disrupt heterotrimer formation and subsequent associations.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>