<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 3. <emphasis>cha-1</emphasis> and <emphasis>unc-17</emphasis> form a complex locus</title>
        <para>(A) The complementation matrix of alleles of <emphasis>cha-1</emphasis> and <emphasis>unc-17</emphasis>. "+" indicates complementation, "&#x02014;" indicates non-complementation. <emphasis>p1156</emphasis>, <emphasis>e113</emphasis> and <emphasis>e876</emphasis> do not complement alleles of <emphasis>cha-1</emphasis> or <emphasis>unc-17</emphasis> (boxed in red). <emphasis>unc-33(e204)</emphasis> was used as a complementation control. Reprinted with permission from <link linkend="bib49">Rand and Russell, 1984</link>. Copyright &#x000A9;1984 the Genetics Society of America. (B) <emphasis>p1156</emphasis>,<emphasis> e113</emphasis> and <emphasis>e876</emphasis> were fine mapped to two separate regions of the <emphasis>cha-1/unc-17</emphasis> locus. <emphasis>p1156</emphasis> defines the alpha region, to the left of the other <emphasis>unc-17</emphasis> alleles, while <emphasis>e113</emphasis> and <emphasis>e876</emphasis> define the beta region, to the right of <emphasis>unc-17</emphasis>
            alleles. Reprinted with permission from <link linkend="bib48">Rand, 1989</link>. Copyright &#x000A9;1989 the Genetics Society of America. (C) <link linkend="bib3">Alfonso et al. (1994)</link> molecularly determined
            that <emphasis>unc-17</emphasis> lies within the first intron of the <emphasis>cha-1</emphasis> locus, the beta region is a
            non-coding region of the complex locus shared with <emphasis>cha-1</emphasis>, and the alpha region lies
            between the 3' end of <emphasis>unc-17</emphasis> and splice site junction of <emphasis>cha-1</emphasis>. Top line corresponds to
            genetic boundaries between <emphasis>cha-1</emphasis> and <emphasis>unc-17</emphasis>, with mutations noted. Middle line corresponds to genomic DNA with <emphasis>SalI (S)</emphasis> and <emphasis>EcoRI</emphasis> sites noted. Bottom line corresponds
            to cDNA structures of <emphasis>cha-1</emphasis> and <emphasis>unc-17</emphasis>. Reprinted with permission from <link linkend="bib3">Alfonso et al. (1994)</link>, Copyright (1994), with permission from Elsevier. See reference for more details.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>