<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 2. Construction of double mutant strains</title>
	<para>(A) No markers. Animals carrying mutations in one gene of interest (gene A) with phenotype A are mated with animals carrying mutations in the other gene of interest (gene B) with phenotype B. The F1 heterozygote (gene a/+; gene b/+) will produce progeny of both phenotype A and phenotype B. Next, F2 animals of phenotype A and phenotype B are individually cultured and their F3 progeny examined to determine whether animals of phenotype A produce progeny of phenotype B or <emphasis>vice versa</emphasis>. By analyzing both classes, one can ensure that the desired strain will be constructed, even if one's assumption about the double mutant phenotype is incorrect. "?" indicates the allele at a given locus in a particular animal is not inferable from its phenotype or the genotype of its parents. (B) <emphasis role="bold">Linked markers in <emphasis>cis</emphasis></emphasis>. The second method used for epistasis analysis involves using linked markers in <emphasis>cis</emphasis> to (on the same chromosome as) the genes of interest. The markers linked to the two genes should be different, closely linked to the gene of interest to avoid recombinants, not have any epistatic relationships to each other, not have any interactions with the genes of interest, and be easily scored as a double mutant. Males carrying mutation <emphasis>b</emphasis> with linked marker <emphasis>n</emphasis> are mated to hermaphrodites homozygous for mutation <emphasis>a</emphasis> and linked recessive marker <emphasis>m</emphasis>. Cross-progeny are non-M and heterozygous for <emphasis>a</emphasis> and b. Cross-progeny that do not produce N progeny are discarded, as they did not receive the <emphasis>b n</emphasis> chromosome from their father. From this heterozygote, hermaphrodites with phenotype M or N  are picked, and the double mutant M N (also homozygous for <emphasis>a</emphasis> and <emphasis>b</emphasis>) is easily recognized. (C) <emphasis role="bold">Linked markers in <emphasis>trans</emphasis></emphasis>. The best method for determining epistatic relationships involves using markers (m, n) linked in <emphasis>trans</emphasis> to (on the homologous chromosome as) the genes of interest. This will eliminate non-specific marker effects while ensuring that the double mutation of the two genes of interest is actually being constructed. Once again, the markers should be fairly close to the gene of interest to reduce the possibility of recombination. This construction is similar to that in part A, except that doubly mutant animals can be ascertained by the method described above and also by their failure to produce progeny carrying the markers linked in <emphasis>trans</emphasis>.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>