<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[-->
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "file:///C:/Techbooks/Wormbook/docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'Zahler_Pre-mRNA_fig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'Zahler_Pre-mRNA_fig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'Zahler_Pre-mRNA_fig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'Zahler_Pre-mRNA_fig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'Zahler_Pre-mRNA_fig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'Zahler_Pre-mRNA_fig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'Zahler_Pre-mRNA_fig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'Zahler_Pre-mRNA_fig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'Zahler_Pre-mRNA_fig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'Zahler_Pre-mRNA_fig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY Zahler_Pre-mRNA_refs SYSTEM 'Zahler_Pre-mRNA_ref.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="Wormbook_splicing_Zahler_id">
<articleinfo>
<title>Pre-mRNA splicing and its regulation in <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis><footnote>
<para>Edited by Thomas Blumenthal. Last Revised November 11, 2011. Published March 16, 2012. This chapter should be cited as: Zahler, A. M. Pre-mRNA splicing and its regulation in <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> (March 16, 2012), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.31.2, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2012 Alan M. Zahler. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
</footnote>
</title>
<author><othername>Alan M. Zahler<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:zahler@biology.ucsc.edu">zahler@biology.ucsc.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></othername>
<affiliation><orgname>Department of Molecular, Cellular and Developmental Biology, Center for Molecular Biology of RNA, Sinsheimer Laboratories, University of California, Santa Cruz, CA 95064 USA</orgname></affiliation></author>
</articleinfo>
<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para>Alternative splicing is a common mechanism for the generation of multiple isoforms of proteins. It can function to expand the proteome of an organism and can serve as a way to turn off gene expression after transcription. This review focuses on splicing, its regulation and the progress in this field achieved through studies in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Recent experiments, including RNA-Seq to uncover and measure the extent of alternative splicing, comparative genomics to identify splicing regulatory elements, and the development of elegant genetic screens using fluorescent reporter constructs, have increased our understanding of the <emphasis>cis</emphasis>-acting sequences that regulate alternative splicing and the <emphasis>trans</emphasis>-acting protein factors that bind to these sequences. The topics covered in this review include constitutive splicing factors, identification of alternatively spliced genes<emphasis></emphasis>, alternative splicing regulation and the coupling of alternative splicing to nonsense-mediated decay. The significant progress towards uncovering the alternative splicing code in this organism is discussed.</para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>The importance of alternative splicing</title>
<para>In multicellular eukaryotes, many genes show evidence for alternative splicing; introns are removed and exons are spliced together in different combinations to yield different multiple distinct messenger RNAs from a single gene. In humans, recent studies suggest that ~95% of genes are capable of undergoing alternative splicing (<link linkend="bib89">Pan et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 18978789-->; <link linkend="bib126">Wang et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 18978772-->). Alternative splicing can be highly regulated under developmental-, tissue-, and signal-specific controls leading to the regulated generation of multiple protein-coding mRNAs from a single gene (<link linkend="bib18">Calarco et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21415141-->; <link linkend="bib31">Hartmann and Valcarcel, 2009</link><!--PMID 19307111-->; <link linkend="bib61">Licatalosi and Darnell, 2010</link><!--PMID 20019688-->). This extensive use of alternative splicing can lead to a more highly diverse proteome (<link linkend="bib86">Nilsen and Graveley, 2010</link><!--PMID 20110989-->). In addition, alternative splicing can lead to a downstream change in open reading frame in the mRNA and thus produce a premature termination codon (PTC) in one of the isoforms. mRNAs containing PTCs are degraded by the nonsense-mediated decay (NMD) machinery. This coupling of alternative splicing and nonsense-mediated decay (AS-NMD) is a post-transcriptional mechanism for shutting off gene expression that occurs for roughly 1/3 of human alternative splicing events (<link linkend="bib58">Lewis et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 12502788-->). Alternative splicing occurs for ~25% of genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib95">Ramani et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21177968-->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has proven to be a useful model system for identifying targets for alternative splicing, the factors that regulate the process and improving our understanding of the mechanisms of this regulation. Like vertebrates, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is an intron-rich organism. Using the Table Browser feature of the UCSC Genome Browser (<link linkend="bib43">Karolchik et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21975940-->) to examine RefSeq genes (<link linkend="bib91">Pruitt et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17130148-->), one finds that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> transcripts are assembled from an average of 6.4 exons while human transcripts are assembled from an average of 9.7 exons. Average exon sizes are similar in length between worms and humans, with a larger mean exon size of 218 nt for worm versus 145 nt for human (<link linkend="bib54">Lander et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11237011-->). However, intron size in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is much smaller than in humans, with a peak of intron size clustered near the minimal intron length of 47 nt (56% of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> introns are under 100 nt in length), while human introns have a median intron length of 1,023 nt and an average of 3,365 nt (<link linkend="bib54">Lander et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11237011-->). This review will examine the work that has been done in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to identify and understand the components of the splicing machinery, the extent of alternative splicing in this organism, the sequences in the genome that regulate this splicing, and the factors that regulate specific alternative splicing events.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Splicing of messenger RNA precursors</title>
<para>The machinery that performs pre-mRNA splicing, the removal of introns and the ligation of exons, is called the spliceosome. The spliceosome assembles onto the nascent pre-mRNA as it is being transcribed. The two <emphasis>trans</emphasis>-esterification reaction steps of pre-mRNA splicing occur in this large multi-component ribonucleoprotein complex (<link linkend="bib81">Moore and Proudfoot, 2009</link><!--PMID 19239889-->; <link linkend="bib123">Wahl et al., 2009</link><!--PMID 19239890-->). The spliceosome assembles onto the pre-mRNA via an ordered binding of its subunits, the uridine-rich small nuclear ribonucleoprotein complexes (U snRNPs). Over 100 different proteins are found in the spliceosome, as part of the snRNP complexes or as associated factors that bind to the pre-mRNA (<link linkend="bib39">Jurica and Moore, 2003</link><!--PMID 12887888-->; <link linkend="bib121">Valadkhan and Jaladat, 2010</link><!--PMID 21080498-->). snRNP complex assembly is guided by RNA-RNA interactions between the U snRNAs and the pre-mRNA and the snRNAs with each other. First U1 binds to the pre-mRNA guided by base-pairing interactions between its 5&#x2032; end and the 5&#x2032; splice site. U2 binding is guided by base pairing interactions with the branchpoint sequence in the intron. Then the U4/U6&#x2022;U5 tri-snRNP is recruited to the forming spliceosome. Extensive rearrangements of RNA-RNA and RNA-protein interactions then occur in the spliceosome to generate a catalytically active form containing U2, U5 and U6 snRNP (<link linkend="bib3">Ares and Weiser, 1994</link><!--PMID 7754032-->; <link linkend="bib71">Madhani and Guthrie, 1994</link><!--PMID 7534458-->). Through genetic experiments in yeast, eight ATP-dependent DExD/H box helicases have been identified that are required for the assembly of the spliceosome, for the complex RNA-RNA and RNA-protein interaction rearrangements before, between and after the first and second <emphasis>trans</emphasis>-esterification reactions, and for the disassembly of the spliceosome (<link linkend="bib97">Rocak and Linder, 2004</link><!--PMID 14991003-->).</para>
<para>Several classes of splicing factor proteins have been identified as being essential for metazoan spliceosome assembly (<link linkend="bib10">Blencowe, 2000</link><!--PMID 10694877-->; <link linkend="bib50">Kramer, 1996</link><!--PMID 8811184-->). The SR protein family of splicing factors is required for the earliest interactions of U1 snRNP with the pre-mRNA and for subsequent spliceosome assembly steps (<link linkend="bib108">Sanford et al., 2005</link><!--PMID 15916537-->). SR proteins have redundant functions in promoting constitutive splicing, but certain family members have distinct roles in promoting specific alternative splice site usage. SR protein family members have distinct binding specificities for sequences within exons that serve as splicing enhancer elements (<link linkend="bib20">Cartegni and Krainer, 2002</link><!--PMID 11925564-->). Analysis of the RNA sequences that bind directly to the human SR protein SF2/ASF (SRSF1) using the technique of cross-linking immunoprecipitation (CLIP) have identified preferred exonic sequences for binding to pre-mRNA and a role for shuttling the mRNA out to the cytoplasm for translation (<link linkend="bib107">Sanford et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 18841201-->; <link linkend="bib109">Sanford et al., 2009</link><!--PMID 19116412-->). U2 auxiliary factor (U2AF) is a heterodimeric splicing factor composed of 35 and 65 kD subunits in humans (<link linkend="bib48">Kielkopf et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 15231733-->; <link linkend="bib133">Zamore et al., 1992</link><!--PMID 1538748-->). It binds to the polypyrimidine tract and recognizes the AG dinucleotide at the 3&#x2032; end of the intron to promote U2 snRNA interactions with the intron branchpoint sequence (<link linkend="bib75">Merendino et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 10617208-->; <link linkend="bib129">Wu et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 10617206-->; <link linkend="bib136">Zorio and Blumenthal, 1999</link><!--PMID 10617207-->). U2AF, SR proteins and U1 snRNP assemble onto the pre-mRNA in an ATP-independent manner to form the early (E) complex (<link linkend="bib76">Michaud and Reed, 1991</link><!--PMID 1836445-->; <link linkend="bib116">Staknis and Reed, 1994</link><!--PMID 7935481-->). It is important to note that assembly of the E complex essentially identifies both the 5&#x2032; and 3&#x2032; splice site for further spliceosome assembly, and thus control of this assembly can be a way of regulating alternative splice site choice (<link linkend="bib77">Michaud and Reed, 1993</link><!--PMID 8504926-->). Splicing factors interact with the pre-mRNA, with other splicing factors and with protein components of the snRNPs (<link linkend="bib15">Burge et al., 1999</link>; <link linkend="bib17">Caceres and Krainer, 1997</link>; <link linkend="bib50">Kramer, 1996</link><!--PMID 8811184-->). This cooperative assembly increases the local concentration of the snRNAs in the vicinity of splice sites and therefore is likely to promote the RNA-RNA interactions required for spliceosome assembly.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Constitutive splicing factors in <emphasis role="bolditalic">C. elegans</emphasis></title>
<para>The spliceosomal snRNAs of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are very similar to their yeast and mammalian counterparts (<link linkend="bib119">Thomas et al., 1990</link><!--PMID 2339054-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, the 5&#x2032; end of U1 snRNA is fully complementary to a 5&#x2032; splice site sequence of AG|guaaguu (where upper case letters indicate the 3&#x2032; end of the exon and lower case letters are the 5&#x2032; end of the intron). While only a very small fraction of 5&#x2032; splice sites are a completely complementary match to the 5&#x2032; end of U1 snRNA, this sequence represents a consensus 5&#x2032; splice site. In an alignment of over 28,000 <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> introns that begin with GU, it was found that for each position in the 5&#x2032; splice site region, at least 51% of the introns showed a match to this consensus (<link linkend="bib45">Kent and Zahler, 2000</link><!--PMID 0010958630-->). The importance of U1 snRNA base-pairing with the 5&#x2032; splice site is demonstrated by two extragenic allele-specific suppressors of mutations of the canonical G that begins <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> introns. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sup-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">sup-6</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sup-39;class=Gene" role="_blank">sup-39</ulink></emphasis> encode two of the 12 U1 snRNA genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and were identified in screens as suppressors that can allow mutated splice donors to be recognized by the splicing machinery (<link linkend="bib99">Roller et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 10757761-->; <link linkend="bib102">Run et al., 1996</link><!--PMID 8722777-->). These suppressor alleles are compensatory mutations in the 5&#x2032; end of U1 snRNA genes that allow them to base pair with the mutated 5&#x2032; splice sites (<link linkend="bib132">Zahler et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 15342508-->). These U1 snRNA suppressors are informational suppressors, allele-specific gene-nonspecific suppressors, and join the amber suppressors and the <emphasis>smg</emphasis> genes as members of this group (<link linkend="bib83">Mount and Anderson, 2000</link><!--PMID 10729829-->). A forward genetic screen to identify additional allele-specific suppressors of a 5&#x2032; splice site mutation identified three non-snRNA suppressors, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=smu-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">smu-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=smu-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">smu-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis>snrp-27</emphasis>, all protein coding genes (<link linkend="bib23">Dassah et al., 2009</link><!--PMID 19380478-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SMU-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMU-1</ulink> is the nematode homolog of mammalian protein fSAP57, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SMU-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMU-2</ulink> is the nematode homolog of mammalian protein RED. The mammalian proteins have been found to be associated with the mammalian spliceosomal C complex (the catalytically active form) (<link linkend="bib39">Jurica and Moore, 2003</link><!--PMID 12887888-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SMU-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMU-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SMU-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMU-2</ulink> were previously identified as playing a role in alternative splicing of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-52;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib113">Spartz et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 15254247-->). SNRP-27 is the nematode homolog of the mammalian tri-snRNP 27K protein that is associated with the U4/U6&#x2022;U5 tri-snRNP (<link linkend="bib27">Fetzer et al., 1997</link><!--PMID 9085842-->) and the allele identified in this genetic screen is a dominant one (<link linkend="bib23">Dassah et al., 2009</link><!--PMID 19380478-->). Given that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SMU-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMU-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SMU-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMU-1</ulink> and SNRP-27 are homologs of proteins that are involved in later assembled stages of the spliceosome in other studies, their role as suppressors of cryptic splice site usage suggests that these factors contribute to the fidelity of splice site choice at later assembly stages, after the initial identification of 5&#x2032; splice sites by U1 snRNP.</para>
<para>In <emphasis>C elegans</emphasis>, the snRNP-associated proteins U1A and U2B&#x2033; are approximately 50% identical to each other, but are somewhat different from their mammalian counterparts or the single <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> homolog, SNF (<link linkend="bib104">Saldi et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17535930-->). Saldi et al. showed that the genes that encode these proteins (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rnp-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">rnp-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rnp-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">rnp-3</ulink></emphasis>) are co-transcribed in an operon, and that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RNP-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">RNP-2</ulink> is U1 snRNP-associated (U1A) whereas <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RNP-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">RNP-3</ulink> is U2 snRNP-associated (U2B&#x2033;). In addition to their co-regulation, they also showed that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RNP-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">RNP-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RNP-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">RNP-3</ulink> are functionally redundant. Both genes must be knocked out before a phenotype is observed, indicating that either can interact with both snRNPs when the other is absent.</para>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> contains eight different members of the SR protein family called the <emphasis>rsp</emphasis> genes (<link linkend="bib44">Kawano et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 10906451-->; <link linkend="bib63">Longman et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 10747030-->; <link linkend="bib64">Longman et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11747818-->; <link linkend="bib82">Morrison et al., 1997</link><!--PMID 9275202-->). Family members are expressed in all cells at all stages of development (<link linkend="bib44">Kawano et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 10906451-->). There is functional overlap among the family members as studies suggest that, with the exception of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rsp-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">rsp-3</ulink></emphasis>, multiple SR proteins need to be targeted by RNA interference in order for a phenotype to become evident (<link linkend="bib44">Kawano et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 10906451-->; <link linkend="bib63">Longman et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 10747030-->; <link linkend="bib64">Longman et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11747818-->). Several viable mutant alleles of SR proteins have been generated by the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Gene Knockout Consortium. These include <emphasis>rsp-2(ok639)</emphasis> (human homolog is SRSF5/SRp40), <emphasis>rsp-5(ok324)</emphasis> (human homolog is SRSF2/SC35) and <emphasis>rsp-6(tm367)</emphasis> (human homolog is SRSF7/9G8). All three deletion alleles are viable with no obvious deleterious phenotypes. Using alternative splicing-sensitive DNA microarrays, Barberan-Soler et al. were able to detect >2-fold changes in alternative splicing isoform ratios for at least 10 target genes each, suggesting that SR proteins in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> do play a role in alternative splice site determination (<link linkend="bib7">Barberan-Soler et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 20805248-->). The phenomenon of <emphasis>trans</emphasis> splicing is common in nematode species (<link linkend="bib1">Allen et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21177958-->; <link linkend="bib11">Blumenthal, 2005</link><!--PMID 18050426-->; <link linkend="bib14">Bruzik, 1996</link><!--PMID 8878012-->; <link linkend="bib57">Lasda and Blumenthal, 2011</link><!--PMID 21957027-->). Using splicing competent embryonic extracts from the parasitic nematode <emphasis>Ascaris lumbricoides</emphasis>, Sanford and Bruzik showed that SR proteins are essential for the <emphasis>trans</emphasis> splicing reaction and that the phosphorylation state and activity level of these proteins changes during early development (<link linkend="bib105">Sanford and Bruzik, 1999</link><!--PMID 10385619-->; <link linkend="bib106">Sanford and Bruzik, 1999</link><!--PMID 10411135-->).</para>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has a homolog of each U2AF subunit, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=uaf-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">uaf-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=uaf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">uaf-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib137">Zorio and Blumenthal, 1999</link><!--PMID 10199565-->; <link linkend="bib138">Zorio et al., 1997</link><!--PMID 9001248-->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has a short, defined polypyrimidine tract at the 3&#x2032; end of its introns (<link linkend="bib12">Blumenthal and Steward, 1997</link><!--PMID 21413218-->). Studies in this organism demonstrated the specificity with which the U2AF heterodimer subunits recognize the polypyrimidine tract and 3&#x2032; splice site at the end of the intron. The U2AF65 homolog, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UAF-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">UAF-1</ulink>, interacts with the short polypyrimidine tract while the U2AF35 homolog <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">UAF-2</ulink> recognizes the AG dinucleotide at the 3&#x2032; end of the intron (<link linkend="bib34">Hollins et al., 2005</link><!--PMID 15661845-->; <link linkend="bib136">Zorio and Blumenthal, 1999</link><!--PMID 10617207-->). These studies clearly demonstrated that, even though the AG at the 3&#x2032; end of the intron is involved in the second <emphasis>trans</emphasis>-esterification reaction of splicing, it also has an important role in early spliceosome assembly. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UAF-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">UAF-1</ulink> regulates its own expression. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=uaf-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">uaf-1</ulink></emphasis> message is alternatively spliced to contain an unusual exon with an in-frame stop codon. This exon is unusual because it contains 10 matches to the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> 3&#x2032; splice acceptor sequence UUUUCAG/R, the sequence recognized directly by <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> U2AF (<link linkend="bib136">Zorio and Blumenthal, 1999</link><!--PMID 10617207-->). MacMorris et al.<!--PMID 10097120--> showed that these splice acceptor repeats cause the pre-mRNA to be retained in the nucleus and thus not become a substrate for translation or nonsense-mediated decay. Experiments in which the UUUUCAG/R repeats were placed in a GFP transgene indicate that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UAF-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">UAF-1</ulink> is responsible for the nuclear retention of its message, suggesting a model in which an autoregulatory feedback loop controls U2AF homeostasis (<link linkend="bib70">MacMorris et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 10097120-->). Genetic suppressor screens have identified viable mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=uaf-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">uaf-1</ulink></emphasis> that can activate changes in splicing of cryptic 3&#x2032; splice sites in a target gene (<link linkend="bib69">Ma and Horvitz, 2009</link><!--PMID 19893607-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, there is little available information about the identity of the branchpoint sequence at which lariat formation occurs during the first catalytic step of splicing, and no strong branchpoint consensus sequence is found in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> introns. Branchpoint formation in other systems has been shown to require splicing factor 1/branchpoint binding protein (SF1/BBP) which binds to both U2AF and the branchpoint sequence (<link linkend="bib62">Liu et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11691992-->; <link linkend="bib110">Selenko et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 12718882-->). The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of SF1/BBP, SFA-1, is essential for development and has strong binding affinity with human U2AF65 protein <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib73">Mazroui et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 10606272-->). SFA-1 binding to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UAF-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">UAF-1</ulink>, which in turn binds strongly to the 3&#x2032; splice acceptor sequence, has been proposed as a key step in identifying the weak branchpoint for splicing (<link linkend="bib34">Hollins et al., 2005</link><!--PMID 15661845-->). Viable mutations in <emphasis>sfa-1</emphasis> were identified in the same screen for suppressors of the <emphasis>unc-93(e1500)</emphasis> missense mutation in which <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=uaf-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">uaf-1</ulink></emphasis> suppressors were isolated; this is consistent with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=uaf-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">uaf-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis>sfa-1</emphasis> working together in 3&#x2032; splice site recognition, although a role for the <emphasis>sfa-1</emphasis> suppressors in altering splice site usage has yet to be demonstrated (<link linkend="bib69">Ma and Horvitz, 2009</link><!--PMID 19893607-->).</para>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has been used as an important model system to study the transition from mitotic proliferation to entry into meiosis in the germ line (<link linkend="bib25">Ellis and Schedl, 2007</link><!--PMID 18050498-->; <link linkend="bib49">Kimble and Crittenden, 2005</link><!--PMID 18050413-->). Screens for genes that masculinize the germline of hermaphrodites (loss of the ability to stop the limited sperm meiosis) led to identification of the mog (<emphasis role="underline">m</emphasis>asculinization <emphasis role="underline">o</emphasis>f <emphasis role="underline">g</emphasis>ermline) genes (<link linkend="bib28">Graham and Kimble, 1993</link><!--PMID 8462850-->; <link linkend="bib29">Graham et al., 1993</link><!--PMID 8111975-->). Four of the five <emphasis>mog</emphasis> genes that have been cloned so far are all homologs of constitutive splicing factors. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MOG-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">MOG-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MOG-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">MOG-4</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MOG-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">MOG-5</ulink> are all homologs of the DEXD/H helicases PRP16, PRP2 and PRP22 respectively (<link linkend="bib93">Puoti and Kimble, 1999</link><!--PMID 10022905-->; <link linkend="bib94">Puoti and Kimble, 2000</link><!--PMID 10737793-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MOG-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">MOG-2</ulink> is a homolog of the U2 snRNP protein U2A&#x2032; (<link linkend="bib134">Zanetti et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21504747-->). In oocyte production, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GLP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLP-1</ulink>/Notch activation in pre-meiotic germ cells, in response to signaling from the distal tip cell of the gonad arm, controls the mitotic/meiotic proliferation/differentiation of the germ cells through repression of the redundant <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GLD-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLD-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GLD-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLD-2</ulink> pathways (<link linkend="bib49">Kimble and Crittenden, 2005</link><!--PMID 18050413-->). A screen for enhancers of a weak gain of function allele of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=glp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> identified the worm homolog of the yeast PRP17 splicing factor, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=prp-17;class=Gene" role="_blank">prp-17</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib47">Kerins et al., 2010</link><!--PMID 20419786-->). Given that both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=prp-17;class=Gene" role="_blank">prp-17</ulink></emphasis> and the <emphasis>mog</emphasis> genes appear to be constitutive splicing factors, Kerins and colleagues performed an RNAi screen against known splicing factors and looked for phenotypes of extensive proliferation in the germline. 47/114 factors tested by RNAi showed over-proliferation and/or Mog sex determination phenotypes (<link linkend="bib47">Kerins et al., 2010</link><!--PMID 20419786-->). Table 2 and supplemental table S1 of the <link linkend="bib47">Kerins et al. 2010</link> (<!--PMID 20419786-->) paper are an excellent resource as catalogs of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homologs of known yeast and mammalian spliceosome components. So why are mutations in the splicing machinery specifically associated with the proliferation/meiosis switch and with sex determination? Kerins et al. propose three models to explain these observations (<link linkend="bib47">Kerins et al., 2010</link><!--PMID 20419786-->): 1) that one or more genes required for controlling meiosis are spliced inefficiently, and so mutations that make splicing less efficient are more likely to show these phenotypes; 2) that one or more genes controlling meiosis are regulated through alternative splicing, and that defects that make splicing less efficient change alternative splicing; 3) that pre-mRNA splicing may be necessary for assembly of ribonucleoprotein complexes on mRNAs in the nucleus, such as the exon-junction complex, that may be important for RNA stability and translational regulation of target genes in the cytoplasm (<link linkend="bib47">Kerins et al., 2010</link><!--PMID 20419786-->). The finding that key developmental processes require efficient splicing opens up important opportunities for further research in both developmental biology and splicing regulation.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Alternative pre-mRNA splicing</title>
<para>Alternative splicing is a mechanism for generating multiple mRNA transcripts from a single gene (<link linkend="bib42">Kalsotra and Cooper, 2011</link><!--PMID 21921927-->). Types of alternative splicing include the use of alternative 5&#x2032; splice sites, alternative 3&#x2032; splice sites, cassette exons, retained introns and mutually exclusive exons. These are represented graphically in <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>. Alternative splicing often leads to changes in the primary amino acid sequence of the protein, sometimes subtle and sometimes quite dramatic. Alternative splicing can control where the site of 3&#x2032; end cleavage and polyadenlyation occurs, indicating a strong interaction between the splicing and 3&#x2032; end formation machineries (<link linkend="bib90">Proudfoot, 2011</link><!--PMID 21896654-->). Many of the genes with alternative isoforms are generated through the use of alternative promoters. Even though these alternative promoters will lead to alternative 5&#x2032; exons spliced to common downstream exons, the generation of the unique first exon is not regulated at the level of alternative splicing but instead by the decisions that govern transcriptional initiation. Alternative splicing may also produce isoforms that use different stop codons. An isoform containing a premature termination codon (PTC) is a candidate for degradation by the nonsense-mediated decay (NMD) pathway. Evidence for the coupling of alternative splicing and NMD was first demonstrated in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> in a forward genetic screen for regulators of alternative splicing. Morrison <emphasis>et al</emphasis>.<!--PMID 9275202--> showed that two of the genes encoding SR protein splicing factors have alternative isoforms with premature termination codons. These alternatively spliced forms were preferentially stabilized in <emphasis role="underline">s</emphasis>uppressor with <emphasis role="underline">m</emphasis>orphogenetic effects on <emphasis role="underline">g</emphasis>enitalia (smg) mutants leading to a change in the steady-state ratio of the alternative isoforms (<link linkend="bib82">Morrison et al., 1997</link><!--PMID 9275202-->). This was the first demonstration that natural substrates for the NMD pathway are alternative isoforms of transcripts. Previously, mutant alleles of genes that introduce a PTC were used to identify mutations in smg genes as suppressors (<link linkend="bib32">Hodgkin et al., 1989</link><!--PMID 2583479-->), and a role in suppression of aberrant transcripts caused by mutation had been proposed as the function of the NMD pathway (<link linkend="bib92">Pulak and Anderson, 1993</link><!--PMID 8104846-->). Extensive analysis of vertebrate alternative splicing indicates that one third of alternative splicing events leads to production of an isoform that is a substrate for the NMD pathway (<link linkend="bib58">Lewis et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 12502788-->). To measure the ratio of alternative mRNA isoforms for a particular gene, scientists determine the relative steady-state levels of the isoforms in RNA extracted from cells, tissues or animals by reverse transcription-PCR, quantitative PCR, splicing-sensitive DNA microarrays or RNA-seq. When measuring alternatively spliced isoforms it is important to remember that the steady-state ratio of the isoforms represents a combination of two variables; the relative amounts of the isoforms generated co-transcriptionally by the splicing machinery in the nucleus and the relative stability of those mRNA isoforms in the nucleus and cytoplasm.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Identification of alternatively spliced genes in <emphasis role="bolditalic">C. elegans</emphasis></title>
<para>Initial identification of alternatively spliced genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> was dependent on comparison of Expressed Sequence Tags (ESTs; libraries of randomly sequenced cDNAs) to the genome sequence (<link linkend="bib45">Kent and Zahler, 2000</link><!--PMID 0010592190-->). From this initial identification of 844 alternatively spliced genes there has been steady growth in this number through constant annotation of genes based on experimental results, additional EST evidence as well as SAGE data analysis (<link linkend="bib103">Ruzanov et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 18053145-->). New data for identifying alternatively spliced genes comes from the new high-throughput RNA sequencing technologies. Ramani et al.<!--PMID 21177968--> have reported using RNA-seq to identify alternatively spliced genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> at various developmental time points (<link linkend="bib95">Ramani et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21177968-->). In addition to using this approach to confirm the existence of 71% of the previously annotated alternative splicing events in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, they report sequence evidence for 2183 new alternatively splicing events, with 759 of these new splice junctions detected in 5 or more independent sequencing reads. Their alternative splicing predictions and evidence for developmental regulation are accessible in a genome browser format at <emphasis role="underline">http://splicebrowse.ccbr.utoronto.ca/</emphasis>. As of Wormbase release WS226, there are 4732 alternative mRNA isoforms annotated for 20,439 protein-coding genes. Ramani and colleagues performed an extrapolation from their data based on 200,000,000 sequence reads to suggest that there are ~5000 genes that undergo alternative splicing in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, representing ~25% of protein coding genes (<link linkend="bib95">Ramani et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21177968-->). While this number is less than the percentage of genes predicted to undergo alternative splicing in mammals, it is strong indication that alternative splicing is a major gene regulatory process in nematodes. Consistent with the model that alternative splicing is a critical process in nematodes, several studies have shown that worm alternative splicing and its regulation are under strong evolutionary selective pressure (<link linkend="bib8">Barberan-Soler and Zahler, 2008</link><!--PMID 18718918-->; <link linkend="bib37">Irimia et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 18048400-->; <link linkend="bib60">Li et al., 2010</link><!--PMID 20610403-->; <link linkend="bib101">Rukov et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17272679-->).</para>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> alternatively spliced genes are capable of undergoing developmental regulation. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-2</ulink></emphasis>, an alpha(2) type IV collagen gene has two mutually exclusive exons; this was the first gene to be shown to undergo a dramatic switch in alternative isoform usage to generate embryo- and adult-specific versions of the protein (<link linkend="bib112">Sibley et al., 1993</link><!--PMID 7691828-->). Using custom DNA microarrays designed to detect alternative splicing, Barberan-Soler uncovered 62 genes whose alternative splicing showed >4-fold changes in isoform ratios during development (<link linkend="bib9">Barberan-Soler and Zahler, 2008</link><!--PMID 18454200-->). Recently RNA-Seq combined with microarray approaches uncovered 574 temporally-regulated alternative splicing events (<link linkend="bib95">Ramani et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21177968-->). Examples of sex-specific alternative splicing in nematodes have been uncovered. One isoform of the nuclear hormone receptor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-55;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-55</ulink></emphasis> is only produced in males (<link linkend="bib111">Shan and Walthall, 2008</link><!--PMID 18652814-->). In hermaphrodites, the <emphasis role="underline">f</emphasis>eminizing locus <emphasis role="underline">o</emphasis>n <emphasis role="underline">X</emphasis> (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fox-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">fox-1</ulink></emphasis>) gene encodes an RNA binding protein that is a regulator of sex determination and acts as a numerator for counting X chromosomes (<link linkend="bib33">Hodgkin et al., 1994</link><!--PMID 7821230-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fox-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">fox-1</ulink></emphasis> acts post-transcriptionally to inhibit the expression of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=xol-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis> gene, the major specifier of male fate (<link linkend="bib85">Nicoll et al., 1997</link><!--PMID 9217163-->). The mammalian homologs of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=FOX-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">FOX-1</ulink> were subsequently shown to be key regulators of tissue-specific alternative splicing (<link linkend="bib38">Jin et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 12574126-->; <link linkend="bib120">Underwood et al., 2005</link><!--PMID 16260614-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Regulation of alternative splicing</title>
<para>The spliceosome assembles through an ordered binding of its snRNP subunits onto the pre-mRNA (<link linkend="bib15">Burge et al., 1999</link>). Alternative splicing regulation essentially controls where the assembly of a functional spliceosome occurs. Alternatively spliced exons often have weak consensus sequences at the 5&#x2032; and 3&#x2032; ends of the introns, suggesting that additional signals are required for recognition of the exon by the splicing machinery (<link linkend="bib65">Lopez, 1998</link><!--PMID 9928482-->). Twenty five years of genomic, genetic, and biochemical experiments have led to the understanding that <emphasis>cis</emphasis> splicing regulatory elements on the pre-mRNA are responsible for controlling alternative splicing (<link linkend="bib30">Hallegger et al., 2010</link><!--PMID 20082635-->). These regulatory regions are found in alternative exons or in flanking introns and can be enhancers or silencers of splice site usage (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). These sequence motifs serve as binding sites for protein factors that can enhance or inhibit the ability of the spliceosome to recognize the exons. The exonic elements not only encode amino acids but also regulate their own ability to be spliced into the mature message. In the "splicing code" hypothesis, the combinatorial assembly of different splicing factors onto multiple <emphasis>cis</emphasis> elements controls where a functional spliceosome assembles (<link linkend="bib127">Wang and Burge, 2008</link><!--PMID 18369186-->). Since the same pre-mRNA sequence is transcribed in different cell types and the constitutive splicing machinery is present in all cells, the regulation of cell type-specific splicing is dependent on the presence and the activity of <emphasis>trans</emphasis>-acting protein factors that bind the nascent transcript in a given cell. Catalogs of <emphasis>cis</emphasis> splicing elements, as well as models for their potential role in affecting alternative splicing in specific cell types based on their position relative to the alternative splicing event, have increased in recent years to the point where most major players have likely been identified (<link linkend="bib18">Calarco et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21415141-->). A recent major advance in computational prediction of mouse tissue-specific alternative splicing has dramatically improved our understanding of the role of splicing elements (<link linkend="bib5">Barash et al., 2010</link><!--PMID 20445623-->). Despite improvements in probabilistic models for decoding alternative splicing, mechanistic studies are still required to understand how the <emphasis>trans</emphasis>-acting factors binding to these <emphasis>cis</emphasis> elements act in a combinatorial manner to regulate spliceosome assembly.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Although the catalogs of <emphasis>cis</emphasis> elements and <emphasis>trans</emphasis>-acting factors are increasing, the mechanisms by which these control spliceosome assembly have been difficult to resolve. For example, splicing factors Fox1, hnRNP L and PTB act through dramatically different mechanisms to silence splicing of target exons. FOX1 binding to UGCAUG sequences blocks formation of the spliceosomal E complex at two distinct steps (<link linkend="bib135">Zhou and Lou, 2008</link><!--PMID 18573872-->). HnRNP L blocks tri-snRNP recruitment through interactions with adjacent assembled U1 and U2 snRNPs (<link linkend="bib35">House and Lynch, 2006</link><!--PMID 16998487-->). Interactions between PTB proteins bound to both introns flanking an alternative cassette exon are proposed to loop out the exon and prevent its inclusion in the mature message (<link linkend="bib59">Li et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17895907-->; <link linkend="bib122">Wagner and Garcia-Blanco, 2001</link><!--PMID 11313454-->). Mechanistic studies must take into account the fact that multiple regulatory proteins assemble onto splicing control sequences. One example of the challenges in deciphering alternative splicing regulation is in the regulation of the neural-specific N1 exon of human c-src. The downstream control sequence (DCS), found in the intron downstream of the N1 exon, binds multiple factors to regulate N1 splicing; these include hnRNP H, hnRNP F, <emphasis role="underline">K</emphasis>H-type <emphasis role="underline">s</emphasis>plicing <emphasis role="underline">r</emphasis>egulatory <emphasis role="underline">p</emphasis>rotein (KSRP), Fox1 and a neural-specific homolog of PTB (nPTB) (<link linkend="bib21">Chou et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 9858532-->; <link linkend="bib22">Chou et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 10911989-->; <link linkend="bib72">Markovtsov et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 11003644-->; <link linkend="bib79">Min et al., 1995</link><!--PMID 7590243-->; <link linkend="bib80">Min et al., 1997</link><!--PMID 9136930-->; <link linkend="bib120">Underwood et al., 2005</link><!--PMID 16260614-->). Comparisons of the factors that assemble onto this element from neuronal cell nuclear extract vs. epithelial cell nuclear extract indicate that a subset of these proteins binds from each extract. Factors in the neuronal extract promote assembly of a different complex that is required to activate splicing of the neural-specific exon. Given that only a small number of alternative splicing substrates have been analyzed in detail, much more work is required to understand how binding of splicing factors to an intron or exon regulates splicing.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>Identifying the elements of the <emphasis role="bolditalic">C. elegans</emphasis> splicing code</title>
<para>With <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as the first completely sequenced animal genome (<link linkend="bib16"><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Sequencing Consortium, 1998</link><!--PMID 9851916-->), and with comparative genomic information available, initially from <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib117">Stein et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 14624247-->) but now from many related nematodes, this model system offers advantages to the identification of alternative splicing regulatory elements. After 100 million years of evolutionary divergence, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> exons have maintained 80% sequence identity, while the introns flanking these exons have diverged rapidly such that it is rare to find evolutionarily conserved sequences within them (<link linkend="bib45">Kent and Zahler, 2000</link><!--PMID 0010958630-->). However, in many introns flanking alternatively spliced exons there are defined patches of evolutionary conservation. <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link> shows five examples of alternative splicing showing regions of evolutionary conservation in introns flanking alternative exons. It was hypothesized that these distinct evolutionarily conserved intronic sequences had the potential to define key splicing regulatory elements (<link linkend="bib46">Kent and Zahler, 2000</link><!--PMID 0010958630-->). An analysis of the frequency of pentamer and hexamer sequence occurrence in these highly conserved intronic elements compared to their frequency in a total intron database was used to identify hexamer and pentamer words associated with alternative splicing in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib40">Kabat et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16839192-->). Pentamers and hexamers were chosen for these studies because these represent the known length of preferred RNA binding sequences for many RNA binding proteins involved in splicing regulation. Many of these conserved intronic pentamers/hexamers are a direct match to human alternative splicing regulatory elements, such as GCAUG for Fox1 (<link linkend="bib38">Jin et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 12574126-->), CUCUCU for PTB (<link linkend="bib87">Oberstrass et al., 2005</link><!--PMID 16179478-->) and GUGUGU for ETR-3 (<link linkend="bib26">Faustino and Cooper, 2005</link><!--PMID 15657417-->), indicating the conserved nature of alternative splicing regulation in animals. In addition to identifying lists of regulatory elements, distinct biases were observed as to whether these elements were likely to appear in the intron upstream or the intron downstream of the alternative cassette exon. One of the high scoring words in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> that has not been identified as a splicing regulatory element in mammals is UCUAUC. This element was demonstrated to regulate alternative splicing in combination with a flanking GCAUG <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=FOX-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">FOX-1</ulink> binding site (<link linkend="bib40">Kabat et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16839192-->). RNA affinity chromatography techniques were employed to identify proteins in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> that bind to this new splicing regulatory element. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> cellular extracts were passed over columns containing immobilized UCUAUC RNA sequences. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of the human hnRNP Q protein, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HRP-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">HRP-2</ulink>, was identified as a high-affinity binder for this sequence and the protein was shown to regulate alternative splicing through binding to UCUAUC in introns (<link linkend="bib41">Kabat et al., 2009</link><!--PMID 19706616-->).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<para>An alternative approach to discovering new alternative splicing events and their <emphasis>cis</emphasis> regulatory elements was done computationally using a support vector machine trained to identify predictive features of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> alternative cassette exons (<link linkend="bib96">Ratsch et al., 2005</link><!--PMID 15961480-->). One of the features that allowed the support vector machine to predict alternative splicing was the presence of several distinct hexamers in the introns surrounding alternative exons. In a recent approach, RNA-Seq and microarrays were used to identify developmentally-regulated alternative splicing events (<link linkend="bib95">Ramani et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21177968-->). Their analysis of the 50 intronic nucleotides on either side of the alternative cassette exons revealed enriched pentamer motifs. There is an obvious strong degree of overlap in the high scoring pentamers and hexamers identified in all three studies (<link linkend="bib40">Kabat et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16839192-->; <link linkend="bib95">Ramani et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21177968-->; <link linkend="bib96">Ratsch et al., 2005</link><!--PMID 15961480-->). It is clear that progress has been made in the past several years in identifying the most common intronic <emphasis>cis</emphasis> regulators of alternative splicing in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> shows several of the top scoring splicing regulatory hexamers and pentamers from these studies and the <emphasis>trans</emphasis>-acting proteins predicted to bind to them. The next challenge to understanding the splicing code is in deciphering how the binding of proteins to these elements regulates alternative splicing.</para>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1.</emphasis> Characterized intronic components of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> alternative splicing code. The table shows high scoring pentamer and hexamer sequences that were identified as intronic alternative splicing regulators in three different studies (<link linkend="bib40">Kabat et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16839192-->; <link linkend="bib95">Ramani et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21177968-->; <link linkend="bib96">Ratsch et al., 2005</link><!--PMID 15961480-->). Biases in the occurrence of the <emphasis>cis</emphasis> element in the intron upstream or downstream of an alternative cassette exon are indicated in the second column. Alternative splicing factors predicted to bind to the <emphasis>cis</emphasis> regulatory elements are indicated in the third column. These high-affinity binding predictions are based on the following <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> reports; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HRP-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">HRP-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib41">Kabat et al., 2009</link><!--PMID 19706616-->), ASD-2 (<link linkend="bib88">Ohno et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 18230701-->), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=FOX-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">FOX-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASD-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">ASD-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib51">Kuroyanagi et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 17060915-->), and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SUP-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUP-12</ulink> (<link linkend="bib2">Anyanful et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 15545320-->; <link linkend="bib52">Kuroyanagi et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17923701-->). The prediction for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PTB-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PTB-1</ulink> is based on the binding of its human homolog, PTB, directly to CUCUCU repeats (<link linkend="bib87">Oberstrass et al., 2005</link><!--PMID 16179478-->).</title>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="2cm"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="4cm"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="4cm"/>
<thead>
<row valign="bottom">
<entry align="center"><emphasis>cis</emphasis> element</entry>
<entry align="left">Bias of element occurrence in the intron relative to an alternative cassette exon</entry>
<entry align="center">Predicted <emphasis>trans</emphasis> splicing factor</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left">UCUAUC</entry>
<entry align="left">Upstream Intron</entry>
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HRP-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">HRP-2</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left">CUAAC</entry>
<entry align="left">No Bias</entry>
<entry align="left">ASD-2</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left">GCAUG</entry>
<entry align="left">Downstream Intron</entry>
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=FOX-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">FOX-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASD-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">ASD-1</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left">GUGUGU</entry>
<entry align="left">Downstream Intron</entry>
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SUP-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUP-12</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left">CUCUCU</entry>
<entry align="left">Upstream Intron</entry>
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PTB-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PTB-1</ulink></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>Genetic identification of alternative splicing factors in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
<para>Genetic analysis in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has led to the identification of splicing regulatory pathways. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MEC-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEC-8</ulink> is a nuclear protein that contains two RNA recognition motifs (RRMs). Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink></emphasis> lead to mechanosensory and other defects. Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink></emphasis> are synthetically lethal with viable mutations in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-52;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> gene (<link linkend="bib68">Lundquist et al., 1996</link><!--PMID 8625846-->). These viable <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-52;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> mutations occur only in exons 17 and 18, which are alternatively spliced (<link linkend="bib98">Rogalski et al., 1995</link><!--PMID 7535716-->). Skipping of exons 17 and 18 is dependent on the function of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib68">Lundquist et al., 1996</link><!--PMID 8625846-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MEC-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEC-8</ulink> protein is found in all nuclei in embryos, but expression becomes more limited to specific cell types in larvae (<link linkend="bib114">Spike et al., 2002</link><!--PMID 12397108-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-52;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> mutant alleles with stop codons in exons 17 and 18 develop a progressive paralysis at later developmental stages; in contrast, mutations in other parts of the gene are lethal. Animals containing both viable mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-52;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> and viable mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink></emphasis> have a synthetic lethal phenotype that mimics the embryonic lethality of the lethal <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-52;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> alleles (<link linkend="bib67">Lundquist and Herman, 1994</link><!--PMID 8001796-->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink>;unc-52</emphasis> double mutant animals, exons 17 and 18 (containing stop codons) cannot be skipped, and this leads to insufficient production of full-length <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-52;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink> in embryos and thus to the more severe embryonic lethality. <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link> summarizes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-52;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> alternative splicing and the specific alternative splicing events promoted by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MEC-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEC-8</ulink>. In a genetic screen based on this synthetic lethality, two <emphasis role="underline">s</emphasis>uppressors of the <emphasis><emphasis role="underline">m</emphasis>ec-8; <emphasis role="underline">u</emphasis>nc-52</emphasis> synthetic lethality (smu) were identified (<link linkend="bib67">Lundquist and Herman, 1994</link><!--PMID 8001796-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=smu-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">smu-1</ulink></emphasis> encodes a nuclear protein that contains five WD motifs, is ubiquitously expressed and is 62% identical to a human spliceosome associated protein fSAP57 (<link linkend="bib115">Spike et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11438655-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=smu-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">smu-2</ulink></emphasis> encodes a <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of the human RED protein, which has also been shown to be associated with the human spliceosome. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SMU-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMU-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SMU-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMU-2</ulink> bind to each other; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SMU-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMU-2</ulink> stabilizes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SMU-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMU-1</ulink> but <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SMU-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMU-1</ulink> does not stabilize <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SMU-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMU-2</ulink>. Based on their homology with components of the mammalian spliceosome, it is hypothesized that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SMU-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMU-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SMU-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMU-2</ulink> might interact with the spliceosome and modulate splice site choice (<link linkend="bib113">Spartz et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 15254247-->). A screen for proteins that are <emphasis role="underline">sy</emphasis>nthetic-lethal with <emphasis role="underline">m</emphasis>ec-8 mutations (sym) uncovered another splicing factor, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sym-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">sym-2</ulink></emphasis>, which is a homolog of the human alternative splicing factors hnRNP H and F (<link linkend="bib24">Davies et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 10471705-->; <link linkend="bib130">Yochem et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 15579686-->). In total, analysis of suppressors and enhancers of the viable <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-52;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> alleles has led to identification of 4 splicing regulatory factors.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 4</phrase>
</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
<para>In addition to a role in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-52;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> splicing regulation, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MEC-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEC-8</ulink> has also been identified as a regulator of alternative splicing of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-2</ulink></emphasis> transcript. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MEC-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEC-8</ulink> is required for removal of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-2</ulink></emphasis> intron 9, and the sequences required for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MEC-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEC-8</ulink> regulation are contained within the intron 9 sequence (<link linkend="bib19">Calixto et al., 2010</link><!--PMID 20364149-->). Taking advantage of the MEC-8-dependent removal of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-2</ulink></emphasis> intron 9, and the fact that there is a temperature sensitive <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink></emphasis> allele, <emphasis>mec-8(u218ts)</emphasis>, Calixto<!--PMID 20364149--> and colleagues have engineered a conditional gene expression system. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-2</ulink></emphasis> intron 9 is inserted into a gene of interest and this transgene is then transformed into a <emphasis>u218ts</emphasis> background. While the intron is removed efficiently at the permissive temperature, when these worms are raised to the restrictive temperature, intron removal ceases and the gene of interest is turned off (<link linkend="bib19">Calixto et al., 2010</link><!--PMID 20364149-->).</para>
<para>Tissue-specific expression of alternative splicing factors has been demonstrated in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SUP-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUP-12</ulink> is an RRM-containing protein that was identified in a genetic screen for suppressors of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-60;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-60</ulink></emphasis> mutations. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-60;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-60</ulink></emphasis> is alternatively spliced to yield two isoforms, UNC-60A and UNC-60B. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-60;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-60</ulink> is a homolog of the actin depolymerizing factor cofilin; UNC-60A and UNC-60B are expressed in non-muscle cells and muscle cells respectively. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sup-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">sup-12</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in muscle cells and is required for the generation of the UNC-60B isoform in those cells by alternative splicing (<link linkend="bib2">Anyanful et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 15545320-->). Loss of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sup-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">sup-12</ulink></emphasis> in <emphasis>unc-60B</emphasis> mutants allows for splicing to the UNC-60A isoform in muscle cells, and the presence of this cofilin in muscle cells can rescue the uncoordination phenotype. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SUP-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUP-12</ulink> was shown to function through interactions with GU rich elements in introns (<link linkend="bib2">Anyanful et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 15545320-->). A fluorescent reporter-based genetic screen for factors that alter <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-15</ulink></emphasis> alternative splicing also identified <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sup-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">sup-12</ulink></emphasis> as a key splicing regulator, again through interactions with GU-rich intronic elements (<link linkend="bib52">Kuroyanagi et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17923701-->).</para>
<para>Two neuronal, nuclear RNA binding proteins with a role in synaptic transmission have been identified in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. These are <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-75;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-75</ulink></emphasis>, which is an ortholog of the human CELF family of alternative splicing factors, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=exc-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">exc-7</ulink></emphasis>, which is a homolog of the <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> neuronal splicing factor ELAV (<link linkend="bib66">Loria et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 12906792-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lec-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">lec-3</ulink></emphasis> has been identified as a gene whose alternative splicing changes in both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=exc-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">exc-7</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-75;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-75</ulink></emphasis> mutant strains (<link linkend="bib7">Barberan-Soler et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 20805248-->). A <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of the human CUGBP1 splicing factor, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=etr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">etr-1</ulink></emphasis>, is expressed only in muscle cells and is essential for development (<link linkend="bib78">Milne and Hodgkin, 1999</link><!--PMID 10556089-->). These studies are strongly suggestive of an important role for alternative RNA processing in tissue specification.</para>
<para>Kuroyanagi<!--PMID 20725066--> and colleagues have engineered a creative and powerful genetic screening system with which to analyze alternative splicing. They create dual alternative splicing reporter constructs in which each alternative isoform is fused in frame to either green or red fluorescent protein (GFP or RFP). Two transgenes containing the alternatively spliced region of interest are transformed simultaneously into worms; one version of the transgene has one outcome of the alternative splicing event in frame with GFP, while the other transgene version has the other alternative isoform in frame with RFP (<link linkend="bib53">Kuroyanagi et al., 2010</link><!--PMID 20725066-->). They have used this system in forward genetic screens, screening for changes in the GFP:RFP ratio in the worms that are indicative of changes in alternative splicing. The have searched for regulators of the alternative splicing of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-15</ulink></emphasis> and of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib51">Kuroyanagi et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 17060915-->; <link linkend="bib52">Kuroyanagi et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17923701-->; <link linkend="bib88">Ohno et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 18230701-->). They have discovered <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=asd-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">asd-1</ulink></emphasis> (<emphasis role="underline">a</emphasis>lternative <emphasis role="underline">s</emphasis>plicing <emphasis role="underline">d</emphasis>efective) which is a homolog of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fox-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">fox-1</ulink></emphasis> alternative splicing factor, as a key alternative splicing regulator for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-15</ulink></emphasis> that works through UGCAUG intronic elements (<link linkend="bib51">Kuroyanagi et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 17060915-->). They demonstrated that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASD-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">ASD-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=FOX-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">FOX-1</ulink> both affect the splicing of this reporter, and that they must have overlapping function since mutations in both genes are required to see a visible phenotype in the absence of the sensitive fluorescent splicing reporters. Kuroyanagi et al.<!--PMID 17923701--> also identified <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SUP-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUP-12</ulink> as a regulator of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-15</ulink></emphasis> splicing using this screen and showed its affinity for GU-rich elements (<link linkend="bib52">Kuroyanagi et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17923701-->). A screen for regulators of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-2</ulink></emphasis> developmental alternative splicing regulation uncovered <emphasis>asd-2</emphasis>, which is a STAR family RNA binding protein (<link linkend="bib88">Ohno et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 18230701-->). They demonstrated that <emphasis>asd-2</emphasis> interacts with a CUAAC element in intron 10. This bi-color fluorescent screening system has proven powerful because it is designed to uncover genes directly responsible for splicing regulation of a specific target, and is sensitive enough to detect changes in reporter gene alternative splicing that do not otherwise cause detectable phenotypic changes in the worms. <link linkend="table2">Table 2</link> summarizes the splicing factors discussed in this chapter and indicates their closest human homologs.</para>
<table id="table2" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 2.</emphasis> <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> splicing factors described in this chapter. The closest human homolog of each is indicated in the second column.</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="2cm"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="3cm"/>
<thead>
<row valign="bottom">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Splicing Factor</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Human Homolog</emphasis></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=asd-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">asd-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">FOX1</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>asd-2 <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=star-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">star-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">QK1/Quaking</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=etr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">etr-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">CUGBP1</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=exc-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">exc-7</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">HuD/ELAV-like 4</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fox-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">fox-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">FOX2</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=hrp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">hrp-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">hnRNP A1</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=hrp-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">hrp-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">hnRNP Q/R</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>hrpf-1</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">hnRNP F/H</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>hrpf-2</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">hnRNP F/H</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">RBPMS2</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ptb-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ptb-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">PTB1</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rsp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">rsp-1</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=srp-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">srp-5</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">SRSF4/SRp75</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rsp-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">rsp-2</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=srp-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">srp-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">SRSF5/SRp40</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rsp-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">rsp-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">SRSF1/SF2/ASF/SRp30a</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rsp-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">rsp-4</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=srp-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">srp-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">SRSF2/SC35/SRp30b</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rsp-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">rsp-5</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=srp-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">srp-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">SRSF2/SC35/SRp30b</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rsp-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">rsp-6</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=srp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">srp-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">SRSF7/9G8</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rsp-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">rsp-7</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">SFRS12/SRrp86</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rsp-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">rsp-8</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">TRA2</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=smu-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">smu-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">SMU1/fSAP57</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=smu-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">smu-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">RED</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>snrp-27</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">tri-snRNP 27K</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sup-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">sup-12</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">RBMP38</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sym-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">sym-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">hnRNP F/H</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-75;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-75</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">CUGBP3</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>The combinatorial interactions of multiple protein factors with the <emphasis>cis</emphasis>-elements surrounding a given alternative splicing event lead to an integrated splicing decision. Yet the mechanism of multifactorial splicing regulation is poorly understood. Using a splicing-sensitive DNA microarray, Barberan-Soler et al. assayed 352 <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> alternative cassette exons for changes in embryonic splicing patterns between wild-type and 12 different strains carrying viable mutations in splicing factors. In addition to identifying additional substrates for regulation by splicing factors such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sup-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">sup-12</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=asd-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">asd-1</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fox-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">fox-1</ulink></emphasis>, many alternative splicing events were uncovered which are regulated by multiple splicing factors (<link linkend="bib7">Barberan-Soler et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 20805248-->). Many splicing factors were shown to have the ability to behave as splicing repressors for some alternative cassette exons and as splicing activators for others. In addition, an example was uncovered in which the ability of a given alternative splicing factor to behave as an enhancer or repressor of a specific splicing event switches during development. The observation that splicing factors can change their effects on a substrate during development supports a model in which combinatorial effects of multiple factors, both constitutive and developmentally regulated ones, contribute to the overall splicing decision.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec9">
<title>Coupling of alternative splicing to nonsense-mediated decay (AS-NMD)</title>
<para>Alternative splicing can generate isoforms with differential ability to be substrates for the NMD pathway. An alternative splicing-sensitive DNA microarray assay was used to look for changes in the steady state levels of alternative isoforms in different NMD mutant backgrounds (<link linkend="bib6">Barberan-Soler et al., 2009</link><!--PMID 19617316-->). In embryos, 73 different alternative splicing events whose isoform ratios changed in an NMD mutant background were identified. Strikingly, 59% of these NMD-sensitive alternative splicing events did not introduce a premature termination codon, and thus should not have activated the NMD pathway. These were referred to as secondary targets of the NMD pathway. In animals, splicing factors are overrepresented in the genes that are regulated by AS-NMD (<link linkend="bib55">Lareau et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 18380348-->; <link linkend="bib82">Morrison et al., 1997</link><!--PMID 9275202-->; <link linkend="bib84">Ni et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17369403-->; <link linkend="bib128">Wollerton et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 14731397-->), and 12 examples of alternatively spliced <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> alternative splicing factors regulated by AS-NMD were identified in the microarray experiments (<link linkend="bib6">Barberan-Soler et al., 2009</link><!--PMID 19617316-->). Reports in different systems have shown that several splicing factors have an autoregulatory feedback loop that links AS to NMD (<link linkend="bib118">Sureau et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11285241-->; <link linkend="bib128">Wollerton et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 14731397-->; <link linkend="bib131">Zachar et al., 1994</link><!--PMID 8056305-->). This autoregulation has been linked to regions of high sequence conservation in the pre-mRNA, stressing the evolutionary importance of this process (<link linkend="bib56">Lareau et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17361132-->; <link linkend="bib84">Ni et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17369403-->). The loss of NMD in <emphasis>C. elegans smg</emphasis> mutant strains led to stabilization, and potentially the translation, of PTC-containing isoforms of splicing factor genes. Several of these PTC-containing mRNA isoforms, stabilized in the NMD mutants, were shown to enter the polysome pool (<link linkend="bib6">Barberan-Soler et al., 2009</link><!--PMID 19617316-->). Translation of the PTC-containing isoforms of splicing factors, for example translation of the PTC isoform of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rsp-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">rsp-6</ulink></emphasis> SR protein, which would generate a protein with the N-terminal RRM but which would lack the C-terminal SR domain, could produce a dominant-negative splicing factor that could compete with the full-length SR protein for pre-mRNA binding but not activate splicing once bound. The translation of truncated splicing factor proteins in an NMD mutant background could explain the observed changes in alternative splicing of transcripts that are not predicted NMD substrates (<link linkend="bib6">Barberan-Soler et al., 2009</link><!--PMID 19617316-->).</para>
<para>Analysis of alternative splicing coupled to NMD also uncovered PTC-containing transcripts that were inefficiently degraded by NMD, as well as PTC-containing mRNAs whose NMD efficiency changed during development. Using sucrose gradient polysome analysis, it was observed that PTC-containing mRNAs isoforms that are inefficiently degraded are enriched in monosomes (<link linkend="bib6">Barberan-Soler et al., 2009</link><!--PMID 19617316-->). Three different pathways that PTC-containing transcripts could follow were proposed; strong NMD, inefficient NMD and developmentally regulated NMD. Individual representatives of these three different classes are shown in <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>. While this figure shows examples of genes that undergo AS-NMD, the features that drive the transcripts to the different NMD pathways are unknown. A role for a <emphasis>trans</emphasis>-acting factor, the RNA binding protein Pub1p, in protecting specific upstream open reading frame-containing mRNAs from the NMD pathway in yeast has been proposed (<link linkend="bib100">Ruiz-Echevarria and Peltz, 2000</link><!--PMID 10892745-->). Recent discoveries that NMD is turned off in cancer cells in their hypoxic microenvironment (<link linkend="bib124">Wang et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21730287-->), downregulated by myc oncogene overexpression (<link linkend="bib125">Wang et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21969377-->), and downregulated by expression of microRNA miR-128 in brain (<link linkend="bib13">Bruno et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21596314-->; <link linkend="bib36">Huang et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21925383-->) point to the fact the NMD regulation is likely an important mechanism for control of differentiation. Because NMD mutants are viable in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> but not in mice or flies (<link linkend="bib4">Avery et al., 2011</link><!--PMID 21317294-->; <link linkend="bib74">Medghalchi et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11152657-->), <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is a valuable model system in which to study the interconnection of alternative splicing and the regulation of NMD in animals.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 5</phrase>
</textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec10">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<para>With extensive alternative splicing and a strong degree of regulation, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> offers a tractable model system for the study of pre-mRNA splicing regulation. The available bioinformatic, genetic and biochemical approaches have led to a coordinated system with the promise to unlock the splicing code for an organism. The availability of viable mutants in splicing factors along with viable mutants in components of the NMD pathways will allow for important contributions to our understanding of pre-mRNA splicing regulation. With many of the components of the splicing code in place for this organism, the next challenges lie in understanding the mechanisms by which the interaction of these factors with the pre-mRNA regulates the assembly of the spliceosome and ultimately the choice of splice sites.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec11">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>I would like to thank Jim Kent, Massimo Caputi, Brock Roller, Sam Gu, Jennifer Kabat, MaryAnn Dassah, Sergio Barberan-Soler, Nicole Lambert and other members of my lab, past and present, who have been fantastic colleagues, and with whom I am truly fortunate to have had the privilege to work and learn. The journey of being a scientist is indeed the goal. This chapter is dedicated to the memory of David M. Prescott, 1926-2011, who taught me that valuable lesson.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec12">
<title>References</title>
&Zahler_Pre-mRNA_refs;
<para/>
</sect1>
</article>