<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'dauerfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'dauerfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'dauerfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'dauerfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY dauer_Refs SYSTEM 'dauerrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="dauer_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title>Dauer<footnote>
			<para>Edited by Donald L. Riddle. Last Revised May 21, 2007. Published August 08, 2007. This chapter should be cited as: Hu, P.J., Dauer (August 08, 2007), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.144.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2007 Patrick J. Hu. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
		<author>
			<firstname>Patrick J.</firstname>
			<surname>Hu<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Phone: (734) 615-9656; Fax: (734) 615-5493. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:pathu@umich.edu">pathu@umich.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></surname>
<affiliation><address>Life Sciences Institute, University of Michigan, Division of Hematology/Oncology, Department of Internal Medicine, and Department of Cell and Developmental Biology, University of Michigan Medical School, Ann Arbor, MI 48109, USA</address></affiliation>
</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<abstract>
		<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">In response to harsh environmental conditions,</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">larvae undergo dauer arrest at the second molt. The past decade has yielded many insights into the signaling pathways and the molecular mechanisms that govern this developmental transition. Dauer pheromone, the major physiologic signal promoting dauer arrest, has been purified, identified, and synthesized. The molecular identities of the vast majority of dauer regulatory genes isolated in initial genetic screens are now known. Physiologic ligands for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink>, a nuclear receptor that is the final common target of dauer regulatory pathways, have been identified. The discovery of the Hid (</emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">h</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="bold">igh temperature</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">i</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="bold">nduction of</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="underline">d</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="bold">auer) phenotype and the results of enhancer screens have greatly expanded the repertoire of dauer regulatory genes. Genomic analysis of dauer arrest has highlighted the role of pathway crosstalk in dauer regulation. Nonetheless, critical questions remain about the mechanistic underpinnings of dauer arrest.</emphasis></para>
	</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>In 1975, Cassada and Russell described the dauerlarva, an arrested developmental variant of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> that forms at the second molt in response to environmental duress. Dauer larvae exhibit morphological and behavioral characteristics distinct from those of larvae developing in replete environments (<link linkend="bib16">Cassada and Russell, 1975</link><!--; PMID 1183723-->). Since that discovery, the transition to dauer arrest has been a fertile area of investigation in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> field, both as a model for regulatory mechanisms governing morphological change during organismal development as well as a parallel to obligate dauer-like developmental stages in parasitic nematodes. In recent years, the molecular identities of genes mutated in various mutants exhibiting dysregulation of dauer arrest (<emphasis>daf</emphasis> mutants) have revealed the critical roles of evolutionarily conserved guanylyl cyclase, transforming growth factor-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> (TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>)-like, insulin-like, and hormonal signaling pathways in the regulation of dauer arrest.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Environmental influences on dauer arrest</title>
<para>The dauer developmental decision occurs late in the L1 larval stage and hinges on the integration of three environmental parameters: population density, food supply, and ambient temperature. Population density is the major influence on dauer arrest and is conveyed by a constitutively synthesized pheromone that induces dauer arrest and prevents dauer recovery. Conversely, a heat-stable, hydrophilic &#x201C;food signal&#x201D; that provides information about food availability inhibits dauer arrest and promotes dauer recovery. The relative amounts of pheromone and food signal, rather than absolute levels, are critical in determining whether an animal undergoes dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib33">Golden and Riddle, 1982</link><!--; PMID 6896933-->). Increased temperature enhances pheromone-induced dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib34">Golden and Riddle, 1984a</link><!--; PMID 6706004-->), and some temperature-sensitive dauer-constitutive mutants are suppressible by an amber nonsense suppressor (<link linkend="bib35">Golden and Riddle, 1984b</link><!--; PMID 6583682-->), suggesting that dauer arrest is intrinsically dependent upon ambient temperature.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Dauer morphology</title>
<para>Dauer larvae are morphologically distinct from larvae that develop in replete conditions. Dauers are radially constricted and possess a specialized cuticle with alae (<link linkend="bib16">Cassada and Russell, 1975</link><!--; PMID 1183723-->). Their oral orifices are closed by an internal plug (<link linkend="bib93">Riddle et al., 1981</link><!--; PMID 7219552-->), and their pharynxes are constricted (<link linkend="bib106">Vowels and Thomas, 1992</link><!--; PMID 1732156-->) and do not pump (<link linkend="bib16">Cassada and Russell, 1975</link><!--; PMID 1183723-->). Dauers are easily distinguishable from L3 larvae under a dissecting microscope. The dauer-specific cuticle and the lack of pharyngeal pumping confer resistance to many environmental insults, including 1% SDS (<link linkend="bib16">Cassada and Russell, 1975</link><!--; PMID 1183723-->). SDS resistance provides a convenient method for isolating dauers and has greatly facilitated the genetic analysis of dauer formation.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Dauer metabolism</title>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> undergoes a metabolic shift between L1 and L2 stages; embryos and L1 larvae use the glyoxylate cycle to generate carbohydrates from lipid stores, whereas L2 and later stages shift toward aerobic respiration and exhibit a relative increase in TCA cycle activity. Dauers do not undergo this shift toward aerobic respiration (<link linkend="bib108">Wadsworth and Riddle, 1989</link><!--; PMID 2917691-->). Relative to growing larvae, dauers also appear to be transcriptionally quiescent but have elevated levels of mRNA encoding the heat shock protein Hsp90 (<link linkend="bib21">Dalley and Golomb, 1992</link><!--; PMID 1577199-->; <link linkend="bib98">Snutch and Baillie, 1983</link><!--; PMID 6883176-->) and elevated superoxide dismutase (<link linkend="bib57">Larsen, 1993</link><!--; PMID 8415630-->; <link linkend="bib105">Vanfleteren and De Vreese, 1995</link><!--; PMID 7557026-->) and catalase (<link linkend="bib105">Vanfleteren and De Vreese, 1995</link><!--; PMID 7557026-->) activities. This suggests that dauers are adapted to resist metabolic stress and is consistent with the observation that they are long-lived (<link linkend="bib53">Klass and Hirsh, 1976</link><!--; PMID 1264206-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Pheromone</title>
<para>Dauer pheromone has recently been purified from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> extracts and molecularly characterized. Paik and colleagues first demonstrated that the ascaroside (-)-6-(3,5-dihydroxy-6-methyltetrahydropyran-2-yloxy) heptanoic acid has dauer pheromone activity (<link linkend="bib46">Jeong et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15690045-->). Recently, Jon Clardy's group has identified three distinct ascarosides in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> extracts with dauer pheromone activity (including the molecule identified by Paik&#x0027;s group). The two ascarosides distinct from that initially isolated by Paik&#x0027;s group, 5-O-ascarylosyl-5<emphasis>R</emphasis>-hydroxy-2-hexanone and an ascaroside derivative of 8<emphasis>R</emphasis>-hydroxy-2<emphasis>E</emphasis>-nonenoic acid, are two orders of magnitude more potent than (-)-6-(3,5-dihydroxy-6-methyltetrahydropyran-2-yloxy) heptanoic acid at inducing dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib15a">Butcher et al., 2007</link>). These discrepancies may be a consequence of differences in the purification steps used by the two groups (<link linkend="bib46">Jeong et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15690045-->; <link linkend="bib15a">Butcher et al., 2007</link>). Furthermore, during purification, one group followed activity using a dauer formation assay (<link linkend="bib46">Jeong et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15690045-->), whereas the other followed activity using a dauer recovery assay (<link linkend="bib15a">Butcher et al., 2007</link>).</para>
<para>Little is known about how dauer pheromone is synthesized <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> and released into the environment. Culture medium and organic extracts of a dauer-defective mutant, <emphasis>daf-22(m130)</emphasis>, do not contain dauer pheromone activity, suggesting that <emphasis>daf-22(m130)</emphasis> is defective in dauer pheromone synthesis (<link linkend="bib36">Golden and Riddle, 1985</link><!--; PMID 3859733-->). Furthermore, exogenous dauer pheromone rescues the <emphasis>daf-22(m130)</emphasis> dauer-defective phenotype (<link linkend="bib46">Jeong et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15690045-->). Interestingly, aqueous extracts of <emphasis>daf-22(m130)</emphasis> animals have measurable dauer pheromone activity (<link linkend="bib36">Golden and Riddle, 1985</link><!--; PMID 3859733-->), suggesting that these animals may have a defect in a late step in dauer pheromone synthesis that results in the accumulation of a hydrophilic precursor or precursors that possess dauer pheromone activity. The molecular identity of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-22;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-22</ulink></emphasis> is not known.</para>
<para>The mechanisms underlying direct cellular responses to dauer pheromone have not been elucidated. It has been assumed that dauer pheromone binds to a specific cell surface receptor expressed in amphid neurons; however, the molecular identity of such a receptor has remained elusive. The demonstration that active dauer pheromone consists of multiple compounds (<link linkend="bib15a">Butcher et al., 2007</link>) suggests that each compound may bind to a distinct receptor that transduces a dauer-promoting signal. This may explain why candidate dauer pheromone receptors have not emerged from the extensive genetic analysis of dauer development that has been performed to date. The availability of synthetic pheromone components should facilitate the search for their cognate receptors.</para>
<para>Consistent with the possibility that dauer pheromone binds to and activates a G-protein-coupled seven-transmembrane domain receptor, the G-protein <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>-subunits <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GPA-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GPA-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-3</ulink> promote dauer arrest when activated, suppress pheromone-induced dauer arrest when deleted, and are expressed in amphid neurons (<link linkend="bib114">Zwaal et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9055081-->). The ability of cyclic GMP (cGMP) analogs to suppress pheromone-induced dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib14">Birnby et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10790386-->) suggests that dauer pheromone may cause dauer arrest at least in part by antagonizing a guanylyl cyclase. Many transmembrane guanylyl cyclase receptors are expressed in amphid neurons (<link linkend="bib14">Birnby et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10790386-->; <link linkend="bib113">Yu et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9096403-->) and could potentially regulate responses to dauer pheromone.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Molecular characterization of signaling pathways regulating dauer arrest</title>
<para>Genetic analysis of dauer-constitutive (Daf-c) and dauer-defective (Daf-d) mutants has defined four distinct pathways that regulate dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib31">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11740945-->; <link linkend="bib37">Gottlieb and Ruvkun, 1994</link><!--; PMID 8056303-->; <link linkend="bib47">Jia et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11782415-->; <link linkend="bib93">Riddle et al., 1981</link><!--; PMID 7219552-->; <link linkend="bib104">Thomas et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8375650-->; <link linkend="bib106">Vowels and Thomas, 1992</link><!--; PMID 1732156-->). In the past decade, components of these and other pathways have been cloned and characterized, revealing the complex interplay of at least four evolutionarily conserved signal transduction pathways in regulating dauer formation.</para>
<sect2 id="sec6_1">
<title>Guanylyl cyclase pathway</title>
<para>The Daf-c gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-11</ulink></emphasis> defines a pathway that inhibits dauer arrest in parallel (at least in part) to a pathway defined by the genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-1</ulink>, 4, 7, 8,</emphasis> and <emphasis>14</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib104">Thomas et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8375650-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-11</ulink></emphasis> mutants also have defects in chemosensation (<link linkend="bib107">Vowels and Thomas, 1994</link><!--; PMID 7828815-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-11</ulink></emphasis> encodes a transmembrane guanylyl cyclase that is expressed in the chemosensory neurons ASI, ASJ, ASK, AWB, and AWC (<link linkend="bib14">Birnby et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10790386-->). 8-bromo-cGMP rescues the Daf-c phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-11</ulink></emphasis> mutants, suggesting that the Daf-c phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-11</ulink></emphasis> mutants is secondary to a reduction in cGMP synthesis. The inability of 8-bromo-cGMP to rescue dauer arrest in most other Daf-c mutants suggests that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> functions proximally in the regulation of dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib14">Birnby et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10790386-->).</para>
<para>Components of a cGMP-gated ion channel are candidate downstream effectors of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink>. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tax-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">tax-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tax-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">tax-4</ulink></emphasis> encode subunits of a cGMP-gated ion channel that regulates thermosensation, chemosensation, and neuronal development (<link linkend="bib18">Coburn and Bargmann, 1996</link><!--; PMID 8893026-->; <link linkend="bib19">Coburn et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9486798-->; <link linkend="bib55">Komatsu et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8893027-->). Both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tax-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">tax-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tax-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">tax-4</ulink></emphasis> are expressed in sensory neurons and have overlapping expression patterns with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-11</ulink></emphasis>, indicating that they may function together in the same cells. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tax-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">tax-4</ulink></emphasis> dauer arrest phenotype is not rescued by 8-bromo-cGMP (<link linkend="bib14">Birnby et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10790386-->), suggesting that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TAX-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">TAX-4</ulink> is a target of DAF-11-dependent cGMP signaling. These data suggest that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> inhibits dauer arrest at least in part by activating <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TAX-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">TAX-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TAX-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">TAX-4</ulink> through increased cGMP synthesis. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tax-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">tax-4</ulink></emphasis> mutants have a weaker Daf-c phenotype than <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-11</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib19">Coburn et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9486798-->), indicating that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> probably activates multiple downstream effectors that contribute to inhibition of dauer arrest.</para>
<para>The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-21;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-21</ulink></emphasis> gene was defined by a single allele, <emphasis>p673</emphasis>, that has genetic interactions and chemosensory pleiotropies similar to those of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-11</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib104">Thomas et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8375650-->; <link linkend="bib107">Vowels and Thomas, 1994</link><!--; PMID 7828815-->). Detailed genetic analysis of <emphasis>daf-21(p673)</emphasis> indicates that it is a recessive gain-of-function allele and that its phenotypes may be a consequence of allele-specific inhibition of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> function. Consistent with this finding, a null allele of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-21;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-21</ulink></emphasis> does not have a dauer arrest phenotype and is larval lethal. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-21;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-21</ulink></emphasis> encodes a Hsp90 homolog (<link linkend="bib14">Birnby et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10790386-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6_2">
<title>TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-like pathway</title>
<para>The TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-like pathway that regulates dauer arrest is defined by the Daf-c genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-1</ulink>, 4, 7, 8</emphasis>, and <emphasis>14</emphasis> and the Daf-d genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-5</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib86">Patterson and Padgett, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10637628-->). TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> family ligands bind to and activate heteromeric cell surface receptors with serine/threonine kinase activity, resulting in the phosphorylation and activation of SMAD transcription factors that translocate to the nucleus to regulate transcription (<link linkend="bib97">Shi and Massague, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12809600-->). Previous reviews (<link linkend="bib92">Riddle and Albert, 1997</link><!--; PMID-->) described the molecular characterization of homologs of TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>; <link linkend="bib91">Ren et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8910282-->; <link linkend="bib96">Schackwitz et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8893028-->) and Type I (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-1</ulink>; <link linkend="bib29">Georgi et al., 1990</link><!--; PMID 2160853-->) and Type II (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-4</ulink>; <link linkend="bib25">Estevez et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8413626-->) TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> receptors. Since then, cloning of the remaining genes in this pathway has defined downstream transcription factors that are targets of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-like signaling. This and other <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-like signal transduction pathways are described in detail in another section of WormBook (see <ulink url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/wormbook.1.22.1" role="_blank">TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signaling</ulink>). With the exception of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>, which is expressed primarily in the ASI amphid neuron (<link linkend="bib91">Ren et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8910282-->; <link linkend="bib96">Schackwitz et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8893028-->), all components of this pathway are widely expressed (<link linkend="bib20">Da Graca et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14681186-->; <link linkend="bib39">Gunther et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10887089-->; <link linkend="bib45">Inoue and Thomas, 2000b</link><!--; PMID 10625546-->; <link linkend="bib85">Patterson et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9334330-->; <link linkend="bib103">Tewari et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14992718-->). Mosaic analysis and rescue experiments with tissue-specific translational fusions indicate that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-4</ulink> functions non-autonomously to regulate dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib45">Inoue and Thomas, 2000b</link><!--; PMID 10625546-->).</para>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-8</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-14;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-14</ulink></emphasis> encode SMAD transcription factors (<link linkend="bib24">Estevez, 1997</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib45">Inoue and Thomas, 2000b</link><!--; PMID 10625546-->; <link linkend="bib85">Patterson et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9334330-->), and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-5</ulink></emphasis> encodes a Sno/Ski oncoprotein homolog that binds to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-3</ulink> (<link linkend="bib20">Da Graca et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14681186-->; <link linkend="bib103">Tewari et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14992718-->). Consistent with the role of mammalian SMADs as positive effectors of TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-like signaling (<link linkend="bib97">Shi and Massague, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12809600-->), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-8</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-14;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-14</ulink> are required for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-mediated inhibition of dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib45">Inoue and Thomas, 2000b</link><!--; PMID 10625546-->). However, in contrast, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-3</ulink> appears to be inhibited upon activation of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> pathway (<link linkend="bib85">Patterson et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9334330-->).</para>
<para>Recent findings indicate that the role of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-3</ulink> in the regulation of dauer arrest may be more complex than initially appreciated. Although <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-3</ulink></emphasis> loss-of-function mutations are Daf-d at 25&#x00B0;C (<link linkend="bib104">Thomas et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8375650-->), they are Daf-c at 27&#x00B0;C (<link linkend="bib2">Ailion and Thomas, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11063684-->), indicating that temperature may influence <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-3</ulink> activity. Furthermore, although <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-3</ulink></emphasis> mutants suppress 25&#x00B0;C dauer arrest in the Daf-c mutants <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-1</ulink>, 4, 7, 8</emphasis>, and <emphasis>14</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib104">Thomas et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8375650-->), they enhance the weak 25&#x00B0;C dauer arrest phenotype of some Daf-c mutants (<link linkend="bib31">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11740945-->; <link linkend="bib81">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783794-->). Thus, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-3</ulink> can function to promote or to inhibit dauer arrest depending upon environmental and genetic context. The mechanisms underlying these observations remain obscure.</para>
<para>A genetic screen to identify suppressors of the dauer arrest phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-8</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-14;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-14</ulink></emphasis> mutants identified three novel genes, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=scd-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">scd-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=scd-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">scd-2</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=scd-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">scd-3</ulink></emphasis> (Scd: <emphasis role="underline">s</emphasis>uppressors of <emphasis role="underline">c</emphasis>onstitutive <emphasis role="underline">d</emphasis>auer arrest) that have weak Daf-d phenotypes when mutated (<link linkend="bib44">Inoue and Thomas, 2000a</link><!--; PMID 11063683-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=scd-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">scd-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=scd-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">scd-2</ulink></emphasis> appear to be novel components of the TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> pathway, whereas <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=scd-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">scd-3</ulink></emphasis> suppresses both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> pathway mutants as well as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-11</ulink></emphasis> mutants and may function downstream of both pathways (<link linkend="bib44">Inoue and Thomas, 2000a</link><!--; PMID 11063683-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=scd-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">scd-1</ulink></emphasis> encodes a glutamine-rich protein, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=scd-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">scd-2</ulink></emphasis> encodes a homolog of the mammalian anaplastic lymphoma kinase (WormBase website, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org" role="_bklank">http://www.wormbase.org</ulink>, release WS170, February 10, 2007). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SCD-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">SCD-2</ulink> inhibits synaptic differentiation and is antagonized by the F-box-containing synaptic protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=FSN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">FSN-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib63">Liao et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15208641-->). The molecular identity of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=scd-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">scd-3</ulink></emphasis> is not known.</para>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-4</ulink></emphasis> encodes a cGMP-dependent protein kinase that regulates chemosensation, locomotion, and body size (<link linkend="bib22">Daniels et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10978280-->; <link linkend="bib27">Fujiwara et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12495624-->; <link linkend="bib56">L&#x0027;Etoile et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12495623-->; <link linkend="bib99">Stansberry et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11181837-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-4</ulink></emphasis> mutants are hypersensitive to dauer pheromone (<link linkend="bib35">Golden and Riddle, 1984b</link><!--; PMID 6583682-->) and have a weak dauer arrest phenotype (<link linkend="bib22">Daniels et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10978280-->). Although the molecular identity of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-4</ulink></emphasis> suggests that it may function in the guanylyl cyclase pathway to inhibit dauer arrest, genetic analysis indicates that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-4</ulink></emphasis> functions primarily in the TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> pathway to regulate dauer formation (<link linkend="bib22">Daniels et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10978280-->).</para>
<?newpage?>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=BRA-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">BRA-1</ulink>, a protein that binds to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-1</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>RI, appears to inhibit TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signaling proximally, as a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bra-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bra-1</ulink></emphasis> deletion allele partially suppresses the dauer arrest phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants but does not suppress <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-14;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-14</ulink>/SMAD</emphasis> dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib74">Morita et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11353865-->). <emphasis>kin-8</emphasis>, which encodes a homolog of the ROR family of tyrosine kinases, promotes dauer bypass and is required for full expression of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> in the ASI amphid neuron (<link linkend="bib54">Koga et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10556063-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6_3">
<title>Insulin-like pathway</title>
<para>A third pathway regulating dauer formation was originally defined by the Daf-c genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-23;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-23</ulink></emphasis> (allelic to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=age-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink></emphasis>) and the Daf-d gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> and functions in parallel to the guanylyl cyclase and TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-like pathways (<link linkend="bib37">Gottlieb and Ruvkun, 1994</link><!--; PMID 8056303-->; <link linkend="bib92">Riddle and Albert, 1997</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib104">Thomas et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8375650-->). Mutations affecting this pathway are phenotypically distinct from other Daf-c mutations in that strong alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=age-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink></emphasis> arrest as dauers non-conditionally and do not recover (<link linkend="bib28">Gems et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9725835-->; <link linkend="bib75">Morris et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8700226-->). Furthermore, unlike guanylyl cyclase pathway and TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> pathway mutants, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> pathway mutants exhibit extended lifespans (<link linkend="bib26">Friedman and Johnson, 1988</link><!--; PMID 8608934-->; <link linkend="bib40">Hertweck et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15068796-->; <link linkend="bib51">Kenyon et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8247153-->; <link linkend="bib75">Morris et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8700226-->; <link linkend="bib83">Paradis et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10364160-->; <link linkend="bib111">Wolkow et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12393910-->). The impact of this pathway on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> longevity is described in detail in another WormBook chapter and will not be discussed further here.</para>
<para>Cloning and characterization of these and other genes in this pathway have defined a conserved insulin-like pathway that inhibits dauer arrest through activation of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink> insulin receptor homolog, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AGE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AGE-1</ulink> phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K), and the protein kinases <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PDK-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PDK-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AKT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AKT-1</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AKT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">AKT-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib52">Kimura et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9252323-->; <link linkend="bib75">Morris et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8700226-->; <link linkend="bib83">Paradis et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10364160-->; <link linkend="bib84">Paradis and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--; PMID 9716402-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AKT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AKT-1</ulink> phosphorylates and inhibits the FoxO transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> by promoting its sequestration in the cytoplasm (<link linkend="bib40">Hertweck et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15068796-->; <link linkend="bib58">Lee et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11747821-->; <link linkend="bib65">Lin et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9360933-->; <link linkend="bib66">Lin et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11381260-->; <link linkend="bib79">Ogg et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9353126-->). Cytoplasmic retention of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> requires the 14-3-3 proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PAR-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-5</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=FTT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">FTT-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib13">Berdichevsky et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16777605-->; <link linkend="bib60">Li et al., 2007</link><!--; PMID 17098225-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-18;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-18</ulink>, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog of the phosphoinositide 3-phosphatase PTEN, antagonizes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AGE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AGE-1</ulink>/PI3K (<link linkend="bib32">Gil et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10077613-->; <link linkend="bib72">Mihaylova et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10377431-->; <link linkend="bib80">Ogg and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--; PMID 9885576-->; <link linkend="bib95">Rouault et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10209098-->). The E3 ubiquitin ligase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RLE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">RLE-1</ulink> catalyzes polyubiquitination and proteasomal degradation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> (<link linkend="bib61">Li et al., 2007</link><!--; PMID 17276341-->; see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). As is the case for TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> pathway components, most of these genes are expressed throughout the animal. Mosaic analysis (<link linkend="bib9">Apfeld and Kenyon, 1998</link><!--; PMID 9790527-->) and rescue experiments with tissue-specific translational fusions (<link linkend="bib110">Wolkow et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11021802-->) indicate that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink>/InsR and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AGE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AGE-1</ulink>/PI3K function non-autonomously to inhibit dauer arrest.</para>
<para>Although most mutants with reduced insulin-like signaling have both Daf-c and extended longevity phenotypes, recent studies illustrate that dauer arrest and lifespan regulation by insulin-like signaling are decoupled by spatiotemporal compartmentalization. Intriguingly, although studies on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink>/InsR suggest that it functions primarily in the nervous system to regulate lifespan as well as dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib9">Apfeld and Kenyon, 1998</link><!--; PMID 9790527-->; <link linkend="bib110">Wolkow et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11021802-->), similar studies on the major target of insulin-like signaling, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FoxO, suggest that dauer arrest and lifespan may be regulated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FoxO activity in distinct tissues. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FoxO in the nervous system has stronger influences on dauer arrest than on lifespan, whereas intestinal <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FoxO plays a greater role in regulating lifespan than in regulating dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib64">Libina et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14622602-->). Thus, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FoxO activation in different tissues may have distinct phenotypic consequences. Furthermore, insulin-like signaling during larval development regulates dauer arrest without significantly impacting lifespan, whereas insulin-like signaling during adulthood suffices to regulate longevity (<link linkend="bib23">Dillin et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12399591-->), indicating that temporal specificity also determines (at least in part) the biological output of insulin-like signaling.</para>
<para>Strikingly, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome is predicted to encode 40 insulin-like (INS) molecules (<link linkend="bib89">Pierce et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11274053-->; WormBase website, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org" role="_blank">http://www.wormbase.org</ulink>, release WS170, February 10, 2007). Studies on <emphasis>ins</emphasis> genes are complicated by the potential functional redundancy of these genes as well as the possible indirect effects of INS protein overexpression on the processing of other INS family members. Notwithstanding these caveats, there is substantial evidence to indicate that <emphasis>ins</emphasis> genes regulate dauer arrest.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="5.9in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ins-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-1</ulink></emphasis> encodes an INS protein that is most similar to human insulin among <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> INS proteins. An <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ins-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-1</ulink></emphasis> deletion mutant does not have a dauer arrest phenotype. However, overexpression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ins-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-1</ulink></emphasis> or a cDNA encoding human insulin enhances dauer arrest, both in wild-type and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/InsR</emphasis> mutant backgrounds. This suggests that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=INS-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">INS-1</ulink> and human insulin antagonize <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink>/InsR signaling. Although it remains unclear whether this effect is direct or indirect, there is some specificity among INS family members, as overexpression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ins-18;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-18</ulink></emphasis> also enhanced dauer arrest, whereas overexpression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ins-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-9</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ins-22;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-22</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ins-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-19</ulink></emphasis>, or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ins-31;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-31</ulink></emphasis> did not. It is noteworthy that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=INS-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">INS-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=INS-18;class=Protein" role="_blank">INS-18</ulink> are the only <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> INS proteins predicted to have C-peptides, which are proteolytically cleaved from proinsulin during normal insulin processing. Promoter::GFP fusions of many of these genes are expressed in amphid neurons, suggesting that dauer-regulatory environmental inputs could regulate expression and/or secretion of insulins (<link linkend="bib89">Pierce et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11274053-->).</para>
<para>The Daf-c gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-28;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-28</ulink></emphasis> encodes an INS family member that promotes insulin-like signaling. It is the only <emphasis>ins</emphasis> mutant that has emerged from forward genetic screens and is defined by a single semidominant allele (<link linkend="bib62">Li et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12654727-->; <link linkend="bib71">Malone and Thomas, 1994</link><!--; PMID 8005442-->). Strikingly, a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-28;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-28</ulink></emphasis>p::GFP transgene is expressed in the amphid neurons ASI and ASJ and is downregulated in response to pheromone and starvation. The related INS proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=INS-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">INS-4</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=INS-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">INS-6</ulink> appear to function similarly to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-28;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-28</ulink> to promote insulin-like signaling (<link linkend="bib62">Li et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12654727-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=INS-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">INS-6</ulink> can bind directly to and activate the human insulin receptor <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib42">Hua et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12654724-->). A <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-28;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-28</ulink></emphasis> deletion mutant does not undergo dauer arrest at 25&#x00B0;C (Weiqing Li, personal communication).</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=INS-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">INS-7</ulink> may also promote reproductive development, as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ins-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-7</ulink></emphasis> RNAi enhances dauer arrest in a <emphasis>daf-2(e1370)</emphasis> mutant background (<link linkend="bib78">Murphy et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12845331-->). Recently it has been shown that the ATPase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASNA-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">ASNA-1</ulink> potentiates <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink>/InsR signaling by promoting the secretion of INS peptides such as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-28;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-28</ulink> (<link linkend="bib50">Kao et al., 2007</link><!--; PMID 17289575-->). The biological role of most of the other insulin-like proteins remains to be elucidated.</para>
<para>Orthologs of components of the conserved target-of-rapamycin (TOR) pathway that is activated by insulin-like molecules (<link linkend="bib82">Oldham and Hafen, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12559758-->) also promote reproductive development in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. TOR is a protein kinase activated by insulin that couples global mRNA translation to nutrient availability. It exists in at least two heteromeric complexes, TORC1 and TORC2, which have distinct subunit compositions and biological functions. TORC1, which is sensitive to inhibition by rapamycin and contains the TOR binding partner Raptor, is required for activation of the ribosomal S6 kinase, whereas TORC2, which is insensitive to rapamycin and contains the TOR binding protein Rictor, phosphorylates and activates Akt (<link linkend="bib43">Inoki and Guan, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16516475-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-363;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-363</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-15</ulink></emphasis> encode orthologs of TOR and Raptor, respectively (<link linkend="bib48">Jia et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15253933-->; <link linkend="bib68">Long et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12225660-->). In contrast to loss-of-function mutants of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=age-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink></emphasis>, and other upstream components of insulin-like signaling, which arrest as complete dauers, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-363;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-363</ulink>/TOR</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-15</ulink>/Raptor</emphasis> mutants arrest as dauer-like larvae that lack cuticular and intestinal characteristics of full dauers (<link linkend="bib48">Jia et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15253933-->). This larval arrest phenotype is epistatic to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> loss-of-function mutations, suggesting that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LET-363;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-363</ulink>/TOR and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-15;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-15</ulink>/Raptor act downstream of or parallel to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FoxO. In replete environments, insulin-like ligands may activate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LET-363;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-363</ulink>/TOR and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-15;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-15</ulink>/Raptor to promote reproductive development. Inactivation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LET-363;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-363</ulink>/TOR and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-15;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-15</ulink>/Raptor suffices to induce developmental arrest, but other effectors of insulin-like signaling must also be inactivated in order for full dauer morphogenesis to take place.</para>
<para>Genetic evidence supports the existence of additional <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink> outputs that function in parallel to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AGE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AGE-1</ulink>/PI3K (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). Activating mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=akt-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pdk-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pdk-1</ulink></emphasis> suppress dauer arrest in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=age-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink></emphasis> null mutants but do not efficiently suppress dauer formation in <emphasis>daf-2(e1370)</emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib44">Inoue and Thomas, 2000a</link><!--; PMID 11063683-->; <link linkend="bib83">Paradis et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10364160-->; <link linkend="bib84">Paradis and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--; PMID 9716402-->), and the weak loss-of-function allele <emphasis>daf-18(e1375)</emphasis> suppresses dauer arrest in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=age-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">age-1</ulink></emphasis> null mutants but not in <emphasis>daf-2(e1370)</emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib32">Gil et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10077613-->; <link linkend="bib37">Gottlieb and Ruvkun, 1994</link><!--; PMID 8056303-->; <link linkend="bib44">Inoue and Thomas, 2000a</link><!--; PMID 11063683-->; <link linkend="bib80">Ogg and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--; PMID 9885576-->; <link linkend="bib106">Vowels and Thomas, 1992</link><!--; PMID 1732156-->). Also, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FoxO localized to the nucleus by virtue of either <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AKT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AKT-1</ulink> inactivation, inactivation of the 14-3-3 protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=FTT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">FTT-2</ulink>, or mutation of consensus <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AKT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AKT-1</ulink> phosphorylation sites is not fully active unless <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> is also mutated (<link linkend="bib13">Berdichevsky et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16777605-->; <link linkend="bib40">Hertweck et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15068796-->; <link linkend="bib66">Lin et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11381260-->). These results suggest that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink> also inhibits the activity of nuclear <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FoxO in an AKT-independent manner. Candidate components of this parallel pathway have been isolated recently (described below in the section on modifier screens).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6_4">
<title>Guanylyl cyclase regulation of TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-like and insulin-like ligand expression</title>
<para>Although genetic analysis is consistent with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> pathways functioning in parallel (<link linkend="bib104">Thomas et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8375650-->), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> likely also functions upstream of TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-like and insulin-like signaling. Ohshima and colleagues isolated a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-11</ulink></emphasis> allele in a genetic screen for mutants exhibiting enhanced dauer arrest and reduced <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink></emphasis>::GFP expression. Specific expression of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> in the ASI neuron rescued both dauer arrest as well as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink></emphasis>::GFP expression, indicating that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> functions cell autonomously to promote <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink></emphasis> transcription (<link linkend="bib77">Murakami et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11677050-->). Intriguingly, the insulin-like molecule <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-28;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-28</ulink> is also expressed in ASI, and expression of a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-28;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-28</ulink></emphasis>::GFP promoter fusion is significantly reduced in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-11</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib62">Li et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12654727-->). Thus, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> may promote reproductive growth at least in part by promoting cell-autonomous expression of insulin-like and TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-like ligands in sensory neurons.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6_5">
<title>Steroid hormone pathway</title>
<para>The Daf-c gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> and the Daf-d gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> function downstream of most other proteins that regulate dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib5">Albert and Riddle, 1988</link><!--; PMID 3350212-->; <link linkend="bib31">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11740945-->; <link linkend="bib47">Jia et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11782415-->; <link linkend="bib93">Riddle et al., 1981</link><!--; PMID 7219552-->; <link linkend="bib104">Thomas et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8375650-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> mutants have similar pleiotropies in gonadal migration that are unique among Daf mutants; alleles of both were isolated in a genetic screen for mutants with distal tip cell migration defects (<link linkend="bib7">Antebi et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9477318-->). Thus, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> define a regulatory module distinct from the guanylyl cyclase, TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-like, and insulin-like pathways.</para>
<para>Multiple lines of evidence are consistent with a model whereby <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-9</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> participate in a steroid hormone pathway that regulates dauer arrest. First, cholesterol deprivation phenocopies <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib31">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11740945-->). Furthermore, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-9</ulink> functions non-autonomously to inhibit dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib30">Gerisch and Antebi, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15084461-->; <link linkend="bib70">Mak and Ruvkun, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15084462-->), consistent with its effects being mediated by a hormone. Most strikingly, cloning of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> revealed that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> encodes a cytochrome P450 similar to steroid hydroxylases (<link linkend="bib31">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11740945-->; <link linkend="bib47">Jia et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11782415-->), and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> encodes a nuclear receptor homolog with highest similarity in its DNA binding domain to vertebrate pregnane X and vitamin D receptors and in its ligand binding domain to vertebrate thyroid hormone receptors (<link linkend="bib8">Antebi et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10859169-->). The expanded family of nuclear receptors in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is described in detail in WormBook (see <ulink url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/wormbook.1.64.1" role="_blank">Nuclear hormone receptors in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>).</para>
<para>Dauer arrest in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> mutants requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> (<link linkend="bib31">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11740945-->; <link linkend="bib47">Jia et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11782415-->), indicating that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-9</ulink> normally inhibits <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> function. Also, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> ligand binding domain mutants have a Daf-c phenotype, suggesting that these mutants are insensitive to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-9</ulink> inhibition by virtue of their reduced ability to bind ligand (<link linkend="bib8">Antebi et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10859169-->). Recently, endogenous steroids that are metabolites of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-9</ulink> and high-affinity ligands for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> have been identified. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-9</ulink> is a 3-keto-sterol-26-monooxygenase that synthesizes the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> ligands <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0394;</symbol><superscript>4</superscript>-dafachronic acid and <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0394;</symbol><superscript>7</superscript>-dafachronic acid (<link linkend="bib76">Motola et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16529801-->; see <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>).</para>
<para>Daf-c mutants whose phenotypes are exacerbated by cholesterol deprivation may define other components of this pathway (<link linkend="bib59">Li et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15509773-->; <link linkend="bib81">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783794-->; <link linkend="bib94">Rottiers et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16563875-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-36;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-36</ulink></emphasis> encodes a Rieske oxygenase that functions upstream of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-9</ulink> in dafachronic acid synthesis (<link linkend="bib94">Rottiers et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16563875-->). Intriguingly, although <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in the hypodermis, somatic gonad, and XXX cells (<link linkend="bib31">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11740945-->; <link linkend="bib47">Jia et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11782415-->; <link linkend="bib81">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783794-->), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-36;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-36</ulink></emphasis> is expressed primarily in the intestine and is not present in the XXX cells (<link linkend="bib94">Rottiers et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16563875-->). It is not clear whether intestinal <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-36;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-36</ulink> metabolites are actively transported to DAF-9-expressing tissues or whether they diffuse into neighboring tissues. Mutants of the Niemann-Pick C (NPC) homologs <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ncr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ncr-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ncr-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">ncr-2</ulink></emphasis> are weakly Daf-c, but a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ncr-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">ncr-2</ulink>;ncr-1</emphasis> double mutant has a strong Daf-c phenotype (<link linkend="bib59">Li et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15509773-->; <link linkend="bib102">Sym et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10801441-->). The NPC genes encode proteins thought to be involved in intracellular cholesterol trafficking (<link linkend="bib17">Chang et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15831488-->). NPC1 mutant mice exhibit decreased levels of neurosteroids (<link linkend="bib38">Griffin et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15208706-->). Analogously, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ncr-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">ncr-2</ulink>;ncr-1</emphasis> double mutants may undergo dauer arrest as a consequence of reduced dafachronic acid synthesis. Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sdf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">sdf-9</ulink></emphasis>, a gene identified in a synthetic dauer formation screen, cause weak dauer arrest phenotypes that are rescued by overexpression of wild-type <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib81">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783794-->).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="5.4in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>Amphid neuron mutants</title>
<para>Three mutants initially isolated based on defects in dauer arrest have structural abnormalities in the cilia of chemosensory neurons (see <ulink url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/wormbook.1.126.1" role="_blank">The sensory cilia of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>, and <ulink url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/wormbook.1.123.1" role="_blank">Chemosensation in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). These ciliary structure abnormalities prevent the amphid neurons from taking up lipophilic dyes, resulting in a Dyf (for abnormal <emphasis role="underline">dy</emphasis>e <emphasis role="underline">f</emphasis>illing) phenotype (<link linkend="bib88">Perkins et al., 1986</link><!--; PMID 2428682-->; <link linkend="bib100">Starich et al., 1995</link><!--; PMID 7705621-->). One of them, <emphasis>daf-10(e1387)</emphasis>, was originally isolated as a mutant that did not form dauers in response to starvation (<link linkend="bib4">Albert et al., 1981</link><!--; PMID 7240452-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-10;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-10</ulink></emphasis> and most other Dyf mutants suppress the dauer arrest phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-11</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib100">Starich et al., 1995</link><!--; PMID 7705621-->; <link linkend="bib106">Vowels and Thomas, 1992</link><!--; PMID 1732156-->), indicating that cilium structure abnormalities prevent sensory neurons from promoting dauer arrest in the absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> guanylyl cyclase signaling. This may be due in part to excessive activation of insulin-like signaling, as Dyf mutants exhibit enhanced <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-28;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-28</ulink></emphasis>::GFP expression (<link linkend="bib62">Li et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12654727-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-10;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-10</ulink></emphasis> encodes a protein with several WD repeats that is homologous to IFT122, a component of the intraflagellar transport particle in <emphasis>Chlamydomonas</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib12">Bell et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16648645-->; <link linkend="bib90">Qin et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11301258-->).</para>
<para><emphasis>daf-6(e1377)</emphasis> was also identified based on its inability to form dauers under starvation conditions (<link linkend="bib4">Albert et al., 1981</link><!--; PMID 7240452-->). However, in contrast to most Dyf mutants, which have primary defects in sensory neuron ciliary structure (<link linkend="bib88">Perkins et al., 1986</link><!--; PMID 2428682-->), dye-filling abnormalities in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-6</ulink></emphasis> mutants appear to be secondary to defects in the amphid channel that is formed by the glial sheath and socket cells (<link linkend="bib4">Albert et al., 1981</link><!--; PMID 7240452-->; <link linkend="bib87">Perens and Shaham, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15935778-->; <link linkend="bib88">Perkins et al., 1986</link><!--; PMID 2428682-->). These defects prevent the amphid neurons from coming into direct contact with the external environment (<link linkend="bib4">Albert et al., 1981</link><!--; PMID 7240452-->; <link linkend="bib87">Perens and Shaham, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15935778-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-6</ulink></emphasis> mutants are also unique among Dyf mutants in their inability to suppress the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-11</ulink></emphasis> dauer arrest phenotype (<link linkend="bib106">Vowels and Thomas, 1992</link><!--; PMID 1732156-->), indicating that dauer arrest due to an absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> guanylyl cyclase activity does not require proper formation of amphid channels. The observation that the amphid cilia cannot access the external environment in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-6</ulink></emphasis> mutants suggests that the Daf-d phenotype of these mutants may be a result of the inability of the amphid neurons to sense dauer pheromone. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-6</ulink></emphasis> encodes a Patched-related protein expressed in amphid sheath and socket glial cells that is required for lumen formation of the amphid channel (<link linkend="bib87">Perens and Shaham, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15935778-->).</para>
<para>All sensory neurons completely lack cilia in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-19</ulink></emphasis> mutants, the first of which was isolated in Don Riddle's lab (<link linkend="bib88">Perkins et al., 1986</link><!--; PMID 2428682-->; <link linkend="bib101">Swoboda et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10882127-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-19</ulink></emphasis> encodes a RFX-type transcription factor that directly regulates a number of cilia genes via a consensus binding site known as the X box (<link linkend="bib101">Swoboda et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10882127-->). Mutation of many of these genes individually results in a Dyf phenotype (<link linkend="bib101">Swoboda et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10882127-->). Unlike all other Dyf mutants, which are Daf-d at 25&#x00B0;C, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-19</ulink></emphasis> mutants are strongly Daf-c at 25&#x00B0;C (<link linkend="bib71">Malone and Thomas, 1994</link><!--; PMID 8005442-->; <link linkend="bib101">Swoboda et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10882127-->). The mechanisms underlying this observation are likely to be complex and are poorly understood. The severity of the cilia defect in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-19</ulink></emphasis> mutants, which affects all ciliated neurons, is probably secondary to the misregulation of many genes involved in cilia formation and maintenance and is more widespread than defects in most Dyf mutants. Indeed, laser ablation of all amphid and phasmid neurons results in a Daf-c phenotype (<link linkend="bib11">Bargmann and Horvitz, 1991</link><!--; PMID 2006412-->), suggesting that dauer arrest may be a summation phenotype resulting from complete disruption of chemosensory neuron function. Other Dyf mutants may have functional defects in subsets of sensory neurons, some of which may promote dauer arrest and others of which may inhibit dauer arrest. Furthermore, since <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-19;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-19</ulink> is the master transcriptional regulator of ciliary genes (<link linkend="bib15">Blacque et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15916950-->; <link linkend="bib101">Swoboda et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10882127-->), genes expressed in ciliated neurons whose products may transduce dauer-inhibitory signals (<link linkend="bib15">Blacque et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15916950-->) may be expressed at levels below the threshold needed to promote reproductive growth in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-19</ulink></emphasis> mutants. Finally, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> guanylyl cyclase that normally promotes reproductive growth is expressed in the cilia of the ASI and ASJ amphid neurons, and mutation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-19</ulink></emphasis> could disrupt <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> function, resulting in dauer arrest secondary to low cGMP levels in ASI and ASJ, reduced <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> expression in ASI (<link linkend="bib77">Murakami et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11677050-->), reduced <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-28;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-28</ulink>/insulin expression in ASI and ASJ (<link linkend="bib62">Li et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12654727-->), or a combination thereof. Indeed, a <emphasis>kin-8</emphasis> mutant exhibits dye-filling defects in the ASI amphid neuron and reduced expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink></emphasis>p::GFP in ASI. However, <emphasis>kin-8</emphasis> also functions in other cells to regulate dauer arrest, as expression of <emphasis>kin-8</emphasis> under the control of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink></emphasis> promoter rescues the ASI dye-filling defect but does not rescue the dauer arrest phenotype of a <emphasis>kin-8</emphasis> null mutant (<link linkend="bib54">Koga et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10556063-->). It is not known whether 8-bromo-cGMP can rescue dauer arrest or whether <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>::GFP or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-28;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-28</ulink>::GFP expression is reduced in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-19</ulink></emphasis> mutants. Although dauer arrest in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-19</ulink></emphasis> mutants is suppressed by mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis>, which encodes the major target of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink>/insulin-like signaling, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-19</ulink></emphasis> mutations are epistatic to mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-5</ulink></emphasis>, which encode the main targets of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-like signaling (Peter Swoboda, personal communication). Thus, reduction of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> expression in ASI cannot fully account for the Daf-c phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-19</ulink></emphasis> mutants.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>Regulation of dauer arrest at 27&#x00B0;C</title>
<para>A capricious incubator in Jim Thomas&#x0027; lab led to the discovery of a plethora of genes whose products function to inhibit dauer arrest at 27&#x00B0;C (<link linkend="bib2">Ailion and Thomas, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11063684-->; <link linkend="bib3">Ailion and Thomas, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14504222-->). At this temperature, wild-type animals can also arrest as dauers. Therefore, although temperature has a modest influence on dauer arrest at 25&#x00B0;C, at 27&#x00B0;C it can mobilize regulatory molecules and pathways necessary for complete dauer arrest and morphogenesis, albeit at low penetrance (<link linkend="bib2">Ailion and Thomas, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11063684-->). The discovery of this phenotype, known as the Hid phenotype (for <emphasis role="underline">h</emphasis>igh temperature <emphasis role="underline">i</emphasis>nduction of <emphasis role="underline">d</emphasis>auer), has greatly broadened the repertoire of molecules known to influence dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib2">Ailion and Thomas, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11063684-->; <link linkend="bib3">Ailion and Thomas, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14504222-->). Many Hid mutants have defects in synaptic transmission (<link linkend="bib1">Ailion et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10377425-->; <link linkend="bib2">Ailion and Thomas, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11063684-->; <link linkend="bib69">Mahoney et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16571673-->), highlighting the neuroendocrine nature of dauer regulation.</para>
<para>Intriguingly, a subset of Hid mutants that form dauers at high penetrance at 27&#x00B0;C have a Daf-d phenotype at 25&#x00B0;C, including <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-3</ulink>/SMAD</emphasis> (as described in <link linkend="sec6_2">Section 6.2</link>) and many Dyf mutants (<link linkend="bib2">Ailion and Thomas, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11063684-->; <link linkend="bib10">Apfeld and Kenyon, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10617200-->). Thus, in Dyf mutants, a mere 2&#x00B0;C elevation in ambient temperature changes the collective dauer-inhibitory output of chemosensory neurons to a dauer-promoting output. The Hid phenotype of Dyf mutants is suppressed by mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-5</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib2">Ailion and Thomas, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11063684-->; <link linkend="bib10">Apfeld and Kenyon, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10617200-->), suggesting that sensory input couples downstream to insulin-like and TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-like pathways.</para>
<para>Laser ablation experiments indicate that temperature elevations may affect the dauer regulatory functions of specific chemosensory neurons. Whereas ablation of both ADF and ASI is necessary to induce dauer arrest in wild-type animals at 20&#x00B0;C (<link linkend="bib11">Bargmann and Horvitz, 1991</link><!--; PMID 2006412-->), ablation of ASI alone suffices to induce dauer arrest at 27&#x00B0;C (<link linkend="bib2">Ailion and Thomas, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11063684-->). Therefore, high temperature may antagonize the dauer-inhibitory activity of ADF. Alternatively, sensory neurons that do not regulate dauer arrest at lower temperatures may be recruited at 27&#x00B0;C to promote dauer arrest. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>::GFP expression in ASI decreases with increasing temperature (<link linkend="bib96">Schackwitz et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8893028-->), and it is further decreased at 27&#x00B0;C (<link linkend="bib2">Ailion and Thomas, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11063684-->), suggesting a mechanism by which elevated temperature could alter the dauer regulatory output of specific sensory neurons. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-28;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-28</ulink></emphasis>::GFP expression is temperature-independent (<link linkend="bib62">Li et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12654727-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec9">
<title>Modifier screens</title>
<para>Since genetic screens for dauer arrest mutants at 25&#x00B0;C have been saturated, some groups have sought to identify mutants that exhibit dauer arrest phenotypes in specific genetic backgrounds. Similar to the Hid screen (<link linkend="bib3">Ailion and Thomas, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14504222-->), such screens allow the identification of genes with relatively subtle influences on dauer arrest.</para>
<sect2 id="sec9_1">
<title><emphasis>sdf</emphasis> (<emphasis role="underline">s</emphasis>ynthetic <emphasis role="underline">d</emphasis>auer <emphasis role="underline">f</emphasis>ormation) mutants</title>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-31;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-31</ulink></emphasis> encodes the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog of CAPS, a cytosolic protein required for calcium-triggered synaptic vesicle release (<link linkend="bib6">Ann et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9289490-->). <emphasis>unc-31(e169)</emphasis> mutants are Hid (<link linkend="bib1">Ailion et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10377425-->). In an effort to identify novel genes involved in neuronal function, Isao Katsura's group performed a screen for <emphasis role="underline">s</emphasis>ynthetic <emphasis role="underline">d</emphasis>auer <emphasis role="underline">f</emphasis>ormation (<emphasis>sdf</emphasis>) mutants that undergo dauer arrest in an <emphasis>unc-31(e169)</emphasis> mutant background. Since laser ablation of ASI suffices to induce dauer arrest in an <emphasis>unc-31(e169)</emphasis> mutant (<link linkend="bib2">Ailion and Thomas, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11063684-->), this screen would potentially identify genes required for ASI specification, development, and function.</para>
<para>Three <emphasis>sdf</emphasis> genes have been described. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sdf-13;class=Gene" role="_blank">sdf-13</ulink></emphasis> encodes a TBX2/TBX3 transcription factor homolog that is required for olfactory adaptation mediated by the AWC olfactory neuron (<link linkend="bib73">Miyahara et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14750151-->), and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sdf-14;class=Gene" role="_blank">sdf-14</ulink></emphasis> is allelic to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mrp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">mrp-1</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a multidrug resistance-associated protein that functions in multiple tissues to inhibit dauer arrest (<link linkend="bib112">Yabe et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15983401-->). Epistasis analysis did not unequivocally reveal the pathway in which <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mrp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">mrp-1</ulink></emphasis> acts. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sdf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">sdf-9</ulink></emphasis> encodes a catalytically inactive protein tyrosine phosphatase (PTP)-like molecule that may function in both steroid hormone and insulin-like pathways (<link linkend="bib41">Hu et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839187-->; <link linkend="bib81">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783794-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sdf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">sdf-9</ulink></emphasis> mutants have a weak Daf-c phenotype that is exacerbated by cholesterol deprivation (<link linkend="bib81">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783794-->). Strikingly, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sdf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">sdf-9</ulink></emphasis> is expressed specifically in the XXX cells (<link linkend="bib41">Hu et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839187-->; <link linkend="bib81">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783794-->). Laser ablation of the XXX cells causes a weak dauer arrest phenotype that requires both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink>/NR and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FoxO in the rest of the animal (<link linkend="bib81">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783794-->), indicating that the XXX cells normally inhibit <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> non-autonomously, perhaps by secreting a hormone. Since <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-9</ulink>/CYP27A1 is also expressed in the XXX cells (<link linkend="bib81">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783794-->), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SDF-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">SDF-9</ulink> may function to inhibit dauer arrest by promoting dafachronic acid synthesis in the XXX cells.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec9_2">
<title><emphasis>eak</emphasis> (<emphasis role="underline">e</emphasis>nhancer of <emphasis><emphasis role="underline">ak</emphasis>t-1</emphasis>) mutants</title>
<para>Based on the indirect evidence supporting the existence of a signaling pathway that functions in parallel to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AGE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AGE-1</ulink>/PI3K (described in <link linkend="sec6_3">Section 6.3</link>), Gary Ruvkun and his colleagues performed a genetic screen to identify mutants that <emphasis role="underline">e</emphasis>nhance the dauer arrest phenotype of an <emphasis><emphasis role="underline">ak</emphasis>t-1</emphasis> null mutant (<emphasis>eak</emphasis>). 21 independent mutants defining seven complementation groups have been isolated, and three <emphasis>eak</emphasis> genes have been molecularly characterized. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eak-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">eak-4</ulink></emphasis> encodes a novel protein with an N-myristoylation motif, <emphasis>eak-5</emphasis> is allelic to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sdf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">sdf-9</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eak-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">eak-6</ulink></emphasis> encodes a PTP-like protein similar to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SDF-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">SDF-9</ulink> (<link linkend="bib41">Hu et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839187-->). Notably, as is the case for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sdf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">sdf-9</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib81">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783794-->), transcriptional and translational GFP fusions of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eak-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">eak-4</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eak-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">eak-6</ulink></emphasis> are also specifically expressed in the XXX cells (<link linkend="bib41">Hu et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839187-->). Translational GFP fusions of all three genes localize to the plasma membrane of the XXX cells, and double mutant combinations among all three genes do not show phenotypic enhancement, suggesting that products of these three genes may function together as a complex at the plasma membrane to promote <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-9</ulink>/CYP27A1 activity and steroid hormone synthesis in the XXX cells (<link linkend="bib41">Hu et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839187-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec10">
<title>The XXX cells as a site of integration of insulin-like and steroid hormone signaling</title>
<para>Although the role of specific amphid neurons in the regulation of dauer arrest has been established for some time (<link linkend="bib11">Bargmann and Horvitz, 1991</link><!--; PMID 2006412-->; <link linkend="bib96">Schackwitz et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8893028-->), how their outputs are integrated during the dauer decision has remained a mystery. The <emphasis>sdf</emphasis> and <emphasis>eak</emphasis> modifier screens have focused attention on the XXX cells as potential sites of integration of insulin-like and steroid hormone signaling.</para>
<para>The dauer arrest phenotype caused by laser ablation of the XXX cells demonstrated their role in preventing dauer arrest and implicated them as endocrine cells (<link linkend="bib81">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783794-->). Identification of the XXX cells as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis>-expressing cells (<link linkend="bib81">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783794-->) confirmed their role in the steroid hormone pathway and suggested that they may be sites of dafachronic acid synthesis and secretion.</para>
<para>The ability of both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> loss-of-function mutations to suppress dauer arrest caused by XXX ablation (<link linkend="bib81">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783794-->) was the first indication that the XXX cells couple to both steroid hormone and insulin-like pathways. This was underscored by the discovery that three <emphasis>eak</emphasis> genes are also specifically expressed in the XXX cells and function upstream of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>/FoxO</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib41">Hu et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839187-->). Specific expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=akt-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">akt-1</ulink></emphasis> in XXX suppresses the dauer arrest phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eak-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">eak-4</ulink>;akt-1</emphasis> double mutants (<link linkend="bib41">Hu et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839187-->), suggesting that insulin-like signaling in XXX can promote dauer bypass, perhaps by potentiating the synthesis and/or secretion of dafachronic acids. Thus, in one model for how insulin-like and steroid hormone signaling are integrated in the XXX cells, insulin-like molecules secreted from amphid neurons (<link linkend="bib62">Li et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12654727-->; <link linkend="bib89">Pierce et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11274053-->) could engage <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink>/InsR on the XXX cell surface, activate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AKT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AKT-1</ulink>, and promote dafachronic acid synthesis by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-9</ulink>/CYP27A1.</para>
<para>It remains to be seen whether <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/InsR</emphasis> is expressed in the XXX cells, as well as whether <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-like signals converge on the XXX cells. Furthermore, how XXX outputs regulate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FoxO nonautonomously (<link linkend="bib81">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783794-->) is not understood. One obvious hypothesis is that the XXX cells may secrete insulin-like molecules as well as steroid hormones. It will be of great interest to determine the expression profile of the XXX cells.</para>
<para>It should be noted that, although the XXX cells clearly play a role in regulating dauer development, the relative weakness of the XXX laser ablation dauer arrest phenotype (<link linkend="bib81">Ohkura et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783794-->) compared to the dauer arrest phenotype observed in strong <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/InsR</emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol></emphasis>, and steroid hormone pathway mutants indicates that other cells and tissues besides XXX likely play major roles in the dauer decision.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec11">
<title>Expression profiling of dauers</title>
<para>Gene expression profiles have been generated using serial analysis of gene expression (SAGE; <link linkend="bib49">Jones et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11483575-->) and microarray-based profiling (<link linkend="bib109">Wang and Kim, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12620986-->) to identify gene expression changes that correlate with dauer arrest. Marra and colleagues performed SAGE on wild-type dauers generated by starvation and mixed-stage animals (both grown in liquid culture; <link linkend="bib49">Jones et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11483575-->). This mixed-stage culture was highly enriched in L1 larvae. They identified 358 dauer-specific and 533 mixed-stage-specific transcripts (P = 0.05). The most abundant dauer transcript was the non-coding transcript <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tts-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tts-1</ulink></emphasis>. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tts-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tts-1</ulink></emphasis> was enriched 20-fold in dauers compared to mixed-stage animals. The most highly expressed dauer-specific transcript corresponded to the small heat shock protein <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=hsp-12.6;class=Gene" role="_blank">hsp-12.6</ulink></emphasis>. Enrichment of the variant histone H1 <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=hil-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">hil-1</ulink></emphasis> and the nucleosome assembly protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=D2096.8;class=Gene" role="_blank">D2096.8</ulink> in dauers suggests that dauer chromatin structure may differ from that of growing animals (<link linkend="bib49">Jones et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11483575-->).</para>
<para>To obtain a picture of the dynamics of gene expression accompanying exit from dauer arrest, Wang and Kim performed a 12-hour time course of microarray-based expression profiles on dauers after recovery was triggered by refeeding on plates (<link linkend="bib109">Wang and Kim, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12620986-->). To control for gene expression changes induced by refeeding <emphasis>per se</emphasis>, they compared these profiles to those generated after refeeding of starved L1 larvae as well as to a mixed-stage sample. They clustered 2430 genes that change expression during dauer exit (P <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x2264;</symbol> 0.001) into five groups based on time course kinetics.</para>
<para>Although genes such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=hsp-12.6;class=Gene" role="_blank">hsp-12.6</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sod-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">sod-3</ulink></emphasis> were identified as dauer-enriched transcripts by both SAGE and microarray-based profiling, there was strikingly little overlap in the expression profiles generated using the two different approaches (<link linkend="bib49">Jones et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11483575-->; <link linkend="bib109">Wang and Kim, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12620986-->). The biological significance of these expression changes remains to be determined.</para>
<para>Using the same platform as Wang and Kim (<link linkend="bib109">Wang and Kim, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12620986-->), Garth Patterson and his colleagues compared gene expression profiles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol></emphasis> pathway mutants undergoing dauer arrest to profiles of wild-type early L3 larvae (<link linkend="bib67">Liu et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15380030-->). They identified over 1200 genes whose expression was regulated strongly in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol></emphasis> pathway mutants undergoing dauer arrest (P = 0.01). Notably, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>/InsR</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> are downregulated and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> is upregulated in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol></emphasis> pathway mutants, suggesting that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signaling feeds forward to promote insulin-like and steroid hormone signaling during larval development in replete environments. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> expression increases early and remains elevated during dauer exit (<link linkend="bib109">Wang and Kim, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12620986-->), suggesting that modulation of steroid hormone signaling is an important aspect of dauer recovery as well as dauer bypass in replete environments.</para>
</sect1>
<?newpage?>
<sect1 id="sec12">
<title>Functional genomic analysis of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signaling</title>
<para>In an effort to obtain a more panoramic view of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signaling landscape (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_tgfbsignal/tgfbsignal.html" role="_blank">TGF-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signaling</ulink>), Marc Vidal, Gary Ruvkun, and their colleagues combined interactome mapping with RNAi-based genetic analysis to define a dauer regulatory network (<link linkend="bib103">Tewari et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14992718-->). They performed two rounds of yeast two-hybrid screening starting with all known components of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signaling as baits, and they tested interacting proteins for roles in dauer regulation using dauer formation assays after gene-specific RNAi in wild-type and various TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> pathway mutant backgrounds. The approach was validated by their identification of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-5</ulink></emphasis>, a Sno oncogene homolog that is a major target of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signaling and that was cloned independently using classical forward genetic analysis (<link linkend="bib20">Da Graca et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14681186-->). This strategy yielded eight candidate modulators of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>/TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signaling that had not been identified in classical genetic screens for pathway components.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec13">
<title>RNAi-based analysis of dauer formation</title>
<para>Genome-wide RNAi screens for dauer arrest genes have not been reported, perhaps because RNAi of known dauer-constitutive genes does not efficiently phenocopy mutants (<link linkend="bib103">Tewari et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14992718-->). In light of the success of modifier screens in identifying new components of dauer regulatory pathways (see <link linkend="sec9">Section 9</link>), RNAi-based enhancer screens may turn out to be a fruitful strategy to identify new dauer genes.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec14">
<title>Future directions</title>
<para>Over the past decade, much has been learned about the molecular and cellular underpinnings of the regulation of dauer arrest. In particular, significant progress has been made in defining the components of signal transduction pathways that regulate dauer arrest. However, many outstanding questions remain in the field. More than twenty years ago, the fundamental influences on dauer arrest were defined (<link linkend="bib33">Golden and Riddle, 1982</link><!--; PMID 6896933-->; <link linkend="bib34">Golden and Riddle, 1984a</link><!--; PMID 6706004-->; <link linkend="bib35">Golden and Riddle, 1984b</link><!--; PMID 6583682-->). Remarkably, the mechanistic basis for the effect of pheromone, food, and temperature on dauer arrest has resisted elucidation. The availability of synthetic dauer pheromone components (<link linkend="bib46">Jeong et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15690045-->; <link linkend="bib15a">Butcher et al., 2007</link>) should facilitate the search for specific pheromone receptors. Other critical questions that remain to be answered include the molecular identity of the food signal, how it is interpreted by the animal, and how changes in ambient temperature are translated into molecular events that influence dauer arrest. It is likely that these environmental signals will function primarily by modulating signaling flux through the guanylyl cyclase, TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-like, insulin-like, and hormonal pathways described here.</para>
<para>Sequencing of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome has identified three expanded families of molecules that play critical roles in regulating dauer arrest. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome contains 40 genes encoding insulin-like molecules, 83 genes encoding cytochromes P450, and 284 genes encoding nuclear receptors. Unequivocal roles in dauer biology have been established for exactly one molecule from each family (the insulin-like molecule <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-28;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-28</ulink> (<link linkend="bib62">Li et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12654727-->), the CYP27A1 functional ortholog <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-9</ulink> (<link linkend="bib31">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11740945-->; <link linkend="bib47">Jia et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11782415-->; <link linkend="bib76">Motola et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16529801-->)), and the nuclear receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> (<link linkend="bib8">Antebi et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10859169-->; <link linkend="bib76">Motola et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16529801-->). It is likely that future research will unveil roles for other members of these families in regulating dauer arrest.</para>
<para>Finally, the interface among signal transduction pathways that regulate dauer arrest will continue to be an active area of investigation in the near future. Although epistasis analysis has contributed substantially to our understanding of how these signaling pathways interact, further studies are certain to yield greater insight into the complexities of their interdigitations. These studies are relevant not only to dauer biology but also to human health, as the evolutionary conservation of these signal transduction pathways suggests that what we learn about their interactions during <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> larval development may be germane to the interactions of similar signaling pathways in the pathogenesis of common diseases such as diabetes mellitus and cancer.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec15">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>I thank Peter Swoboda and Weiqing Li for providing unpublished results and Rebecca Butcher and Jon Clardy for providing data prior to publication. Research in my laboratory is funded by the National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases and the Michigan Diabetes Research and Training Center at the University of Michigan Medical School.</para>
</sect1>
<?newpage?>
<sect1 id="sec16">
	<title>References</title>
	&dauer_Refs;
	<para/>
</sect1>
</article>