<caption>
	<formalpara>
		<title>Figure 1. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> hermaphrodite gonad, and germline apoptosis.</title>
		<para>(A) Schematic representation of an adult hermaphrodite gonad. One of two gonad arms is shown. The basic features of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> germ cell production have been described elsewhere (see <ulink url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/wormbook.1.18.1" role="_blank">Introduction to the germline</ulink><!--, http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/wormbook.1.18.1-->, and <ulink url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/wormbook.1.13.1" role="_blank">Germline proliferation and its control</ulink><!--, http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/wormbook.1.13.1-->). Briefly, germ cells are derived from a proliferating stem cell population located at the distal end of the gonad (relative to the uterus). These germline stem cells give rise to sperm during larval stages, then switch to production of oocytes during adulthood. The somatic distal tip cell regulates germline stem cell proliferation, and entry into the transition zone and prophase of Meiosis I. Germ cells are partially enclosed by a plasma membrane, and share a common cytoplasmic core. Germ cell apoptosis occurs mainly within the gonad loop region (black line), approximately as developing oocytes exit the pachytene stage of meiotic prophase. Apoptotic nuclei are shown as solid black. Apoptosis of germ cells occurs during oogenesis, and therefore is not seen in larvae or males. After pachytene exit, the surviving germ cells grow rapidly and differentiate into individual cellularized oocytes in the proximal germline, and are fertilized in the spermatheca after they undergo maturation (see <ulink url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/wormbook.1.53.1" role="_blank">Control of oocyte meiotic maturation and fertilization</ulink><!--, http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/wormbook.1.53.1-->). (B) Cross section through the loop region, showing a single cell undergoing apoptosis. Each dying cell rapidly &#x0201C;pinches off&#x0201D; from the shared cytoplasmic core and forms a discrete cell that contains very little cytoplasm. The apoptotic cell is engulfed and removed by one of the somatic sheath cells that surround the gonad (<link linkend="bib37">Gumienny et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 9927601-->).</para>
	</formalpara>
</caption>