<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'gmSNP3pmfigch5-1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'gmSNP3pmfigch5-1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'gmSNP3pmfigch5-2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'gmSNP3pmfigch5-2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'gmSNP3pmfigch5-3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'gmSNP3pmfigch5-3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="WMgmSNP3pmch5_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<title>Genetic mapping and manipulation: Chapter 5-SNPs: Three-point mapping<footnote>
				<para>Edited by Victor Ambros. Last revised May 4, 2005. Published February 17, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Fay, D. Genetic mapping and manipulation: Chapter 5-SNPs: Three-point mapping (February 17, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.94.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 David Fay. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
<!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 5/04/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
-->
		<author>
			<firstname>David</firstname>
			<surname>Fay<remark>
					<footnote>
						<para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:davidfay@uwyo.edu">davidfay@uwyo.edu</ulink></para>
					</footnote>
				</remark>
			</surname>
			<affiliation>
				<address>Department of Molecular Biology, University of Wyoming, Laramie, Wyoming 82071-3944 USA</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
</articleinfo>
	<sect1>
		<title>The basics</title>
		<para>As described in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_SNPsintrotwopointmap/SNPsintrotwopointmap.html" role="_blank">SNPs: introduction and two-point mapping</ulink> single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) provide an exceptionally powerful means for supplementing traditional mapping practices. SNP mapping is both conceptually and practically an extension of standard three-point mapping (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_threepointmapmarkers/threepointmapmarkers.html" role="_blank">Three-point mapping with genetic markers</ulink>), and will invariably require some previous genetic mapping of the mutation of interest. The specific strategy for mapping mutations by SNP analysis will depend somewhat on the nature of your mutant phenotype. In most instances, it is advantageous to generate a chromosome containing your mutation that is flanked by two easily discernable genetic markers such as <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">dpy</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis>. The genetic distance between the flanking markers should be as small as possible, something in the range of a few map units. However, some regions of the chromosome will require that you use markers that are separated by significantly greater distances. Although not optimal, this is still workable. The issue is that the farther apart the markers are, the more recombinants that will ultimately be needed to obtain the same level of mapping refinement. Still, we have successfully used markers as far apart as 12 map units to narrow a region down to a handful of genes. Ultimately, it is more important to use easily discernable markers than to shave off a few map units of distance. Another point is that it is useful to be able to pick recombinants from both directions if at all possible. At the very least, it doubles the number of useful recombinants on the plates and can provide an added level of security, provided all your data points are in agreement.</para>
		<para>Creating strains for SNP mapping. For viable mutations, triple-mutant chromosomes can easily be obtained by generating balanced strains of the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a m/m b</emphasis></emphasis> genotype, where <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> is the mutation and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">b</emphasis></emphasis> are the marker mutations (<xref linkend="figure1" />, example #1). One then picks either <emphasis role="bold">A M</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">M B</emphasis> animals and looks for the appearance of <emphasis role="bold">A M B</emphasis> animals in some fraction of the self progeny (e.g., from a parent that was <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a m b/a m</emphasis></emphasis>), indicating the presence of a recombinant <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a m b</emphasis></emphasis> chromosome. The choice of picking <emphasis role="bold">A M</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">M B</emphasis> animals will depend on the ease of recognition of the <emphasis role="bold">A M B</emphasis> animal in either the <emphasis role="bold">A M</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">M B</emphasis> background. For example, it is somewhat easier to identify <emphasis role="bold">Dpy Unc</emphasis> animals from plates where most of other animals are <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> than the other way around.</para>
		<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="5in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject><phrase> SNPs: three-point mapping Figure 5-1</phrase></textobject> &fig1legend;
			</mediaobject>
		<para>For non-viable mutations, the construction and maintenance of the triple mutant chromosome is somewhat more involved. Here you will need to initially construct strains that are either <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a m/a b</emphasis></emphasis> or <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m b/a b</emphasis></emphasis> (<xref linkend="figure1" />, example #2). Then by blindly picking sufficient animals of the <emphasis role="bold">A B</emphasis> phenotype, it should be possible to isolate strains that throw 1/4 <emphasis role="bold">A M B</emphasis>, indicating the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a m b/a b</emphasis></emphasis> genotype. Alternatively, you could generate the strain <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m b/a c</emphasis></emphasis>, where <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">c</emphasis></emphasis> lies just to the right of <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">b</emphasis></emphasis> and confers a phenotype that is distinct from that of either <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis></emphasis> or <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">b</emphasis></emphasis>. By picking <emphasis role="bold">A-non-C</emphasis> animals, a reasonably high percentage of recombinants should be of the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a m b/a c</emphasis></emphasis> genotype (<xref linkend="figure1" />, example #3). This approach has the added advantage that the strain generated is at least partially balanced and therefore easier to maintain.</para>
		<para>On the other hand, if your mutation is inviable but you have already constructed several well-balanced strains that each carry the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a m</emphasis></emphasis> or the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m b</emphasis></emphasis> chromosomes, it is reasonable that you might want to use these strains directly for SNP mapping (also see below). <emphasis>The key here is to have two strains with markers on opposite sides, as this will allow you to move your region in from both directions</emphasis>. The same holds true for non-viable mutants when working with a triple-mutant chromosome (<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a m b</emphasis></emphasis>). This is because the only recombinants that can be propagated as homozygotes (<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a/a</emphasis></emphasis> or <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">b/b</emphasis></emphasis>) will necessarily have resulted from crossover events that lead to the loss of <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis>. Thus, in this situation, it is essential to be able to pick both <emphasis role="bold">A-non-B</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">B-non-A</emphasis> animals to narrow down your region from both sides.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Examples of SNP mapping</title>
		<para><xref linkend="figure2" /> shows the basic flowchart and potential outcomes for mapping a viable mutation that is flanked by the visible markers <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">b</emphasis></emphasis> using four regional SNPs. In this scheme, F1 heterozygous hermaphrodites are generated through crosses and allowed to self (step 1). F2 recombinants are then isolated (step 2) and sufficient self progeny are subsequently cloned such that animals homozygous for the recombinant chromosome are obtained in the F3 generation (step 3). F4 progeny can then be assayed for the presence of N2 or CB4856 sequences at an given SNP locus (step 4). For example, a <emphasis role="bold">Dpy non-Unc</emphasis> resulting from a crossover at point <emphasis role="bold">A</emphasis> would be N2 for <emphasis role="bold">SNP1</emphasis> and would not contain the mutation <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis>. Thus, <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> must lie to right of SNP1. Likewise, a <emphasis role="bold">Dpy non-Unc</emphasis> resulting from a crossover at point <emphasis role="bold">C</emphasis> would result in an <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> animal that was CB4856 for SNP3 and SNP4. Thus, <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> must reside to the left of both SNP3 and SNP4. In the examples provided in <xref linkend="figure2" />, the data from recombinants <emphasis role="bold">B</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">C</emphasis> establish the tightest endpoints on the left and right respectively. As described above, non-viable mutants may be most conveniently mapped using two strains, e.g., <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a m</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m b</emphasis></emphasis> (<xref linkend="figure3" />). By picking <emphasis role="bold">A non-M</emphasis> from one strain and <emphasis role="bold">B non-M</emphasis> from the other, both sides can effectively be pushed in.</para>
			<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
					<textobject><phrase> SNPs: three-point mapping Figure 5-2</phrase></textobject> &fig2legend;
			</mediaobject>
			<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
			<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
					<textobject><phrase> SNPs: three-point mapping Figure 5-3</phrase></textobject> &fig3legend;
			</mediaobject>
		<para>It is also worth noting that although we mostly use SNP mapping to generate progressively tighter endpoints, valuable three-point mapping data can be gleaned through this process. For example, imagine that you have assigned your mutation to the region between SNP2 and SNP3 (<xref linkend="figure2" />). In doing so, you notice that of the 20 <emphasis role="bold">Dpy non-Unc</emphasis> recombinants that experienced a crossover in this region (meaning they are all N2 for SNP2 and CB4856 for SNP3), 18 contain the mutation <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis>. This would suggest that <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> lies relatively close to SNP2, as the large majority of recombination events resulted in the retention of <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> on the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">dpy</emphasis></emphasis> chromosome. Likewise, most <emphasis role="bold">Unc non-Dpy</emphasis> recombinants isolated in this region (meaning they are N2 for SNP3 and CB4856 for SNP2) would be expected to be <emphasis role="bold">non-M</emphasis>. This may at first seem counterintuitive. This is because for normal three-point mapping (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_threepointmapmarkers/threepointmapmarkers.html" role="_blank">Three-point mapping with genetic markers</ulink>), the mutation is always on the opposite chromosome from the markers, hence a high percentage of <emphasis role="bold">Dpy-M</emphasis> animals would indicate that <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> lies closer to the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis> side of things. The difference here is that the mutation and markers all start out on the same chromosome, thus a minor revision in thinking is required. As always, if this does not make immediate sense, draw it out.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>General SNP mapping strategies</title>
		<para>The optimal strategies for efficient SNP mapping will vary somewhat depending on the nature of the mutant phenotype and on the time commitment of the researcher. We have had good success using a two-tiered approach. Initially, we isolate 75-100 recombinant animals and then in the subsequent generation isolate strains that are homozygous for the recombinant chromosome. We then begin the process of testing regional SNPs, initially being somewhat conservative in our choices of locations (meaning that we try not to overshoot). We then methodically move in our endpoints, discarding as we go those recombinants that are no longer informative. At some point, this initial pool will fail to yield any additional information and we are left with just a few recombinants holding down the left and right inner endpoints.</para>
		<para>In the second phase of SNP mapping, we go for the "mother load", where several hundred or more recombinants are isolated. The strategy is to quickly screen these recombinants using the inner-most (or near inner-most) pair of informative SNPs. For reasons described above, it is preferable that these SNPs be CB4856-specific cutters, although well-behaved N2 cutters may be workable. <emphasis>Most important is that the chosen SNPs provide consistent and easily interpretable results</emphasis>. For carrying out PCR, you can use either the initial recombinant animal (after it has had 1-2 days to lay sufficient eggs) or 5 or 6 of its L4 progeny that display the recombinant phenotype.</para>
		<para>To avert potential problems, it is advisable to stagger the growth of the recombinant animals as much as possible, either by picking recombinants over several days or by maintaining some at 20<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>C and others at 16<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>C. The idea is to avoid having just one or two "days from hell" when all the recombinants must be screened at once. Based on the position of the SNPs relative to the markers, we will test first one and then the other SNP for all of our recombinants. For example if one is testing <emphasis role="bold">Dpy non-Unc</emphasis> recombinants and the two innermost SNPs are located closer to the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis> mutation, it will be most efficient to first test the proximal SNP (relative to <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">dpy</emphasis></emphasis>) to determine if it is N2, before bothering to test the distal SNP to see if it is CB4856. Non-informative recombinants are immediately pitched, whereas the progeny from the informative recombinants are further cloned to generate homozygous lines.</para>
	</sect1>
</article>