<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig7 SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig7.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig8 SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig8.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig9 SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig9.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig10 SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig10.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig11 SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig11.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig7legend SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig7leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig8legend SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig8leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig9legend SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig9leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig10legend SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig10leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig11legend SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_fig11leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY nucreceptor_ref SYSTEM 'nucreceptor_ref.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="nucreceptor">
<articleinfo>
<title>Nuclear receptor signal transduction in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis><footnote><para>Edited by Iva Greenwald. Last revised July 23, 2014. Published June 9, 2015. This chapter should be cited as: Antebi A. Nuclear receptor signal transduction in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (June 9, 2015), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.64.2, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2015 Adam Antebi. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para></footnote></title>
<author><othername>Adam Antebi<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:AAntebi@age.mpg.de">AAntebi@age.mpg.de</ulink></para></footnote></remark></othername>
<affiliation><orgname>Max Planck Institute for Biology of Ageing and Cologne Excellence Cluster on Cellular Stress Responses in Aging Associated Diseases (CECAD), University of Cologne, Cologne, Germany; Department of Molecular and Cellular Biology, Huffington Center on Aging, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX 77030, USA</orgname></affiliation></author></articleinfo>
<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Nuclear receptors are transcription factors that often respond to small molecule metabolites and fat-soluble compounds to regulate gene expression. They broadly govern development, reproduction, metabolism, and homeostasis in diverse metazoan species and their dysregulation is associated with numerous diseases. Work in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has shed light on the seminal role of nuclear receptors in life history regulation, stem cell progression, developmental timing, cell fate specification, nutrient sensing, metabolism, and longevity. Here we highlight recent advances on the best-studied nuclear receptors in the worm, and how they illuminate metazoan biology.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Abbreviations:</emphasis></para>
<para>NR: nuclear receptor; LBD: ligand binding domain, DA: dafachronic acid; IIS: insulin/IGF signaling; AC: anchor cell; ARD: adult reproductive diapause; LC: linker cell; MUFA: monounsaturated fatty acid; PUFA: polyunsaturated fatty acid; TAG: triacyl glycerides; VU: ventral uterine; DR: Dietary restriction.</para>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction: Nuclear receptor signal transduction</title>
<para>A remarkable invention of metazoan evolution, nuclear receptors (NR) are ligand gated transcription factors that typically bind small molecule metabolites such as fatty acids, vitamins, and steroids to directly regulate gene transcription. They are well poised to coordinate multicellular metabolism, development, reproduction, and homeostasis across diverse tissues. A conserved architecture and mechanism underlies their signaling abilities (<link linkend="bib142">Mangelsdorf et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 8521507-->). The DNA binding domain consists of two zinc fingers near the N-terminus, which contact the double helix and form a dimerization interface. The ligand binding domain (LBD) resides at the C-terminus, and binds cognate ligand as well as co-activator and co-repressor complexes that instruct its activity. Typically class 1 receptors, such as the classical steroid receptors (e.g., estrogen, androgen, glucocorticoid receptors), are ligand activated, while so-called class 2 receptors (e.g., PPARs, vitamin D receptor, thyroid receptor) function as transcriptional activators in the presence of ligand, but as repressors in the absence of ligand (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). Various post-translational modifications including phosphorylation, acetylation, ubiquitylation, and sumoylation can also modulate their activities (<link linkend="bib3">Anbalagan et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22438791-->). Some NRs constitutively bind ligand (e.g., HNF4&alpha; binds fatty acids), and are instead gated by associated proteins or modifications (<link linkend="bib71">Gonzalez, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18305369-->). Other NRs have no identified ligands, and are therefore termed orphan receptors.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Humans harbor 48 NRs including the classical steroid receptors, thyroid receptors, vitamin D receptor, and retinoic acid receptors, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SF1;class=Strain" role="_blank">SF1</ulink>, GCNF, ROR, COUP, which primarily govern development, immunity, and reproduction. Major regulators of lipid, glucose, and xenobiotic metabolism include PPARs, LXR, LRH, HNF4, FXR, PXR, and CAR (<link linkend="bib148">McKenna and O&apos;Malley, 2010a</link><!--: PMID 20813267-->, <link linkend="bib149">McKenna and O&apos;Malley, 2010b</link><!--: PMID 20850017-->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> boasts a remarkable 284 receptors: 269 of them represent a vast expansion and diversification of the HNF4 family (<link linkend="bib190">Robinson-Rechavi et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15983867-->). The remaining 15 are more evolutionarily conserved, and include homologs of VITD/LXR/FXR (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003607;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-8</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003638;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-48</ulink></emphasis>), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SF1;class=Strain" role="_blank">SF1</ulink> (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis>), ROR (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003622;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-23</ulink></emphasis>), COUP (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006790;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-55</ulink></emphasis>), HNF4 (e.g., <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003654;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-64</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003659;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-69</ulink></emphasis>), Rev-Erb (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003675;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-85</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004786;class=Gene" role="_blank">sex-1</ulink></emphasis>), TLX (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis>), PNR (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001400;class=Gene" role="_blank">fax-1</ulink></emphasis>), NGF-1 (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003605;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-6</ulink></emphasis>), GCNF (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003681;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-91</ulink></emphasis>), and TR2/4 (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00022423;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-41</ulink></emphasis>) (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>, Section 6). Notably missing from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are clear structural orthologs of the classical steroid and ecdysteroid receptors, the PPARs, thyroid receptors, as well as retinoic acid and heterodimeric receptor RXR. Nevertheless evidence suggests that analogous physiologic functions have arisen through convergent evolution (<link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>, Section 6). The expanded NR superfamily is not unique to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, but also characteristic of closely related nematodes such as <emphasis>C. rameni</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib80">Haerty et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18752680-->), as well as species more evolutionarily diverged such as <emphasis>Pristionchus pacificus</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib41">Dieterich et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18806794-->), suggesting an ancestral role in nematode physiology.</para>
<para>Because of <emphasis>C. elegans&rsquo;</emphasis> cellular simplicity and powerful genetics, the study of NR signaling in the worm has provided unprecedented insights into events <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>, from the subcellular to organismal level, from synaptic remodeling to longevity&mdash;vantages not always easily achieved in mammalian models. Since our 2006 chapter, Nuclear hormone receptors in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, a wealth of information on the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> receptors has been uncovered. An emergent view is that these NRs play key roles in timers and oscillators, working as feedback regulated switches in circuits governing developmental timing, the molt cycle clock, dauer formation, longevity, and other aspects of life history. They also extensively interface with other signaling pathways to mediate fate choice and organogenesis. Finally they serve as key homeostatic regulators or switches in nutrient sensing and metabolism. In this review, we highlight the best studied of these receptors, and attempt to place them in biological context.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Nuclear receptors as switches, timers and oscillators in life history regulation</title>
<para>All animals develop through successive life stages to reproductive maturity, and ultimately age and die, collectively comprising the life history of the species. Coordinate progression through the life stages requires a precise integration of extrinsic environmental cues together with intrinsic metabolic, cellular, and physiologic processes. As ligand and nutrient responsive transcription factors, NRs play a particularly important role in orchestrating animal life history, by integrating environmental and physiologic information, coordinating metabolic and cellular events throughout the body, and triggering the succession of life stages.</para>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> life history, like many species depends very much on environment. In favorable environmental conditions, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> develops from embryo through four larval stages L1-L4 separated by molts to reproductive maturity, produces large broods of 300 animals, and then lives another 3 weeks (<link linkend="bib57">Byerly et al., 1976</link><!--: PMID 988845-->; <link linkend="bib112">Klass, 1977</link><!--: PMID 926867-->). In unfavorable conditions, such as food deprivation, animals arrest at several diapause states including the L1 diapause, the L3 dauer diapause, and an adult reproductive diapause, which are stress resistant and long lived (<link linkend="bib32">Cassada and Russell, 1975</link>; <link linkend="bib102">Johnson et al., 1984</link><!--: PMID 6542614-->; <link linkend="bib4">Angelo and Van Gilst, 2009</link><!--: PMID 19713489-->). Upon return to ample nutrients and favorable conditions, worms will resume growth and reproduction. Several conserved NRs, including <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33928;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-8</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43454;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-55</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39085;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-23</ulink>, function as key regulators of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> life history. These NRs govern diapause stages and developmental timing circuits, catalyze transitions through life stage programs, and drive the molt cycle timer. They also often influence reproduction, metabolism, and longevity. Below we highlight their roles in these circuits.</para>
<sect2 id="sec2-1">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink>/FXR, a hormone regulated switch</title>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> is the most intensively studied NR in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and has served as an important paradigm for metazoan NR signal transduction <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> is most homologous to vertebrate farnesoid-X (FXR), liver-X, and vitamin-D receptors (<link linkend="bib7">Antebi et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10859169-->), which regulate metabolism, development, and homeostasis in a wide variety of contexts (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). Vertebrate homologs are gated by cognate bile acids (<link linkend="bib141">Makishima et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10334992-->; <link linkend="bib175">Parks et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10334993-->), oxysterols (<link linkend="bib98">Janowski et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8878485-->), and vitamin-D (<link linkend="bib146">McDonnell et al., 1987</link><!--: PMID 3029866-->), respectively, but also share the ability to be regulated by bile acid-like steroids, suggesting an ancestral role of such molecules (<link linkend="bib215">Song and Liao, 2000</link><!--: PMID 11089551-->; <link linkend="bib104">Jurutka et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15578590-->; <link linkend="bib257">Zhi et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22170062-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> is also regulated by bile acid-like steroids, in this case called the dafachronic acids (DA) as well as cholestenoic acid, which activate transcription with high affinity (<link linkend="bib89">Held et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16913876-->; <link linkend="bib160">Motola et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16529801-->), and to date is the sole <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> receptor whose ligand has been unequivocally determined. Found in the nucleus of all somatic cells, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> regulates a wide swath of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> biology, including the dauer diapause, developmental timing, metabolism, and longevity, coupling environmental and physiologic information to reproductive development, detailed below (<link linkend="bib7">Antebi et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10859169-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-2">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink>/FXR and dauer formation</title>
<para>Under food scarcity, thermal stress and overcrowding, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> will arrest and enter the dauer diapause, an alternate third larval stage specialized for survival and dispersal (<link linkend="bib32">Cassada and Russell, 1975</link><!--: PMID 1183723-->; <link linkend="bib52">Fielenbach and Antebi, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18708575-->; see also the WormBook chapter Dauer). Dauer larvae are extremely stress resistant, sexually immature, and long lived. Yet when returned to ample food, will mature to reproductive adults, revealing incredible plasticity in regulation of reproduction and longevity. Genetic screens for mutants that affect dauer formation identified dauer-formation constitutive (Daf-c) and dauer-formation defective loci (Daf-d) that either always, or never, enter the dauer stage (<link linkend="bib189">Riddle et al., 1981</link><!--: PMID 7219552-->). Genetic epistasis experiments place <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> at the end of the dauer pathways (<link linkend="bib189">Riddle et al., 1981</link><!--: PMID 7219552-->; <link linkend="bib234">Vowels and Thomas, 1992</link><!--: PMID 1732156-->; <link linkend="bib224">Thomas et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID 8375650-->; <link linkend="bib72">Gottlieb and Ruvkun, 1994</link><!--: PMID 8056303-->). Various <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> mutants show opposite phenotypes: null mutants are Daf-d and somewhat short lived, whereas ligand-insensitive LBD mutants are Daf-c and modestly long lived, indicating that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> is instructive in the dauer decision (<link linkend="bib189">Riddle et al., 1981</link><!--: PMID 7219552-->; <link linkend="bib6">Antebi et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9477318-->; <link linkend="bib60">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11740945-->; <link linkend="bib54">Fisher and Lithgow, 2006</link><!--: PMID 16626392-->).</para>
<para>The molecular and cellular architecture of dauer formation reveals an intricate coupling of environmental information to a conserved endocrine network. Environmental inputs include ascarosides as signals of population density, unidentified food cues, and temperature (<link linkend="bib69">Golden and Riddle, 1984a</link><!--: PMID 6706004-->; <link linkend="bib70">Golden and Riddle, 1984b</link><!--: PMID 6583682-->; <link linkend="bib28">Butcher et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17558398-->), which are perceived and integrated by ciliated sensory neurons (<link linkend="bib179">Perkins et al., 1986</link><!--: PMID 2428682-->; <link linkend="bib16">Bargmann and Horvitz, 1991</link>) and transduced through cGMP signaling (<link linkend="bib234">Vowels and Thomas, 1992</link><!--: PMID 1732156-->; <link linkend="bib23">Birnby et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10790386-->). Sensory perception regulates production and neurosecretion of TGF-&beta; (<link linkend="bib188">Ren et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8910282-->), and insulin-like-peptides (<link linkend="bib130">Li et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12654727-->), which work through their respective signal transduction pathways to control steroidal hormone signaling (<link linkend="bib60">Gerisch and Antebi, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15084461-->; <link linkend="bib140">Mak and Ruvkun, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15084462-->). This core endocrine network is modulated by a myriad of signaling inputs including serotonin (<link linkend="bib217">Sze et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10676966-->), acetylcholine (<link linkend="bib125">Lee et al., 2014</link><!--: PMID 24219868-->), neuropeptide-Y-like (<link linkend="bib37">Cohen et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19356718-->), ALK (<link linkend="bib186">Reiner et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18674914-->), TOR (<link linkend="bib100">Jia et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15253933-->), AMPK (<link linkend="bib9">Apfeld et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15574588-->), Wnt (<link linkend="bib47">Essers et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15905404-->; <link linkend="bib67">Goh et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23019370-->), Notch (<link linkend="bib173">Ouellet et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18599512-->), ER stress signaling (<link linkend="bib120">Kulalert and Kim, 2013</link><!--: PMID 24316205-->), and others. Despite the complexity of inputs, the essential core signaling reduces to a binary decision: that in favorable circumstances, TGF-&beta; and insulin/IGF signaling (IIS) are upregulated and stimulate production of the DAs in steroidogenic cells (<link linkend="bib52">Fielenbach and Antebi, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18708575-->). Liganded <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> then prevents dauer formation, and promotes reproductive development in tissues throughout the body (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). Conversely, under adverse circumstances, TGF-&beta; and IIS are downregulated, resulting in suppression of DA production. Unliganded <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> forms a repression complex with the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45296;class=Protein" role="_blank">DIN-1</ulink>/SHARP co-repressor, thereby specifying the long-lived dauer diapause (<link linkend="bib135">Ludewig et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15314028-->; <link linkend="bib52">Fielenbach and Antebi, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18708575-->). Thus, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> functions as a hormone-regulated switch governing reproduction or survival.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Apparently the dauer endocrine network has a conserved physiologic function in regulating reproduction and longevity across taxa. Both IIS and TGF-&beta; pathways govern ecdysteroidogenesis in insect metamorphosis, and steroidogenesis in mammalian puberty (<link linkend="bib221">Tennessen and Thummel, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21959165-->) (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). TGF-&beta;, IIS, and steroidal signaling and other dauer signaling pathways have been implicated in regulation of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> adult longevity (<link linkend="bib109">Kenyon et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID 8247153-->; <link linkend="bib95">Hsin and Kenyon, 1999</link><!-- 10360574-->; <link linkend="bib61">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11740945-->; <link linkend="bib100">Jia et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11782415-->; <link linkend="bib204">Shaw et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17900898-->). IIS regulates longevity in flies, mice and humans (<link linkend="bib35">Clancy et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11292874-->; <link linkend="bib218">Tatar et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11292875-->; <link linkend="bib92">Holzenberger et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12483226-->; <link linkend="bib245">Willcox et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18765803-->), while various steroids have been implicated to affect life span in flies and perhaps mammals (<link linkend="bib108">Keisala et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19500727-->; <link linkend="bib109">Kenyon, 2010</link><!--: PMID 20336132-->; <link linkend="bib158">Mooijaart et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17452725-->; <link linkend="bib214">Simon et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12610309-->). It will be important to explore whether other pathways that govern reproduction and survival also impact mammalian longevity.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-3">
<title>Convergent evolution in steroidogenic pathways</title>
<para>Until recently relatively little was known about steroidogenic pathways in worms. Mutants were originally identified as having a similar spectrum of phenotypes as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> ligand-insensitive LBD mutants, including Daf-c and retarded gonadal migration phenotypes. Initial genetic and biochemical experiments suggested that the DAs were synthesized from cholesterol (which must be obtained through the diet) through two proposed biosynthetic branches to produce active <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> ligands, called &Delta;<superscript>7</superscript>-DA and &Delta;<superscript>4</superscript>-DA (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>) (<link linkend="bib160">Motola et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16529801-->; <link linkend="bib191">Rottiers et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16563875-->). Since then, these models have undergone revision as new activities have been revealed.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 4</phrase>
</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The &Delta;<superscript>7</superscript> branch is best understood (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>). The first step entails the conversion of cholesterol to 7-dehydrocholesterol by the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34156;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-36</ulink>/Rieske oxygenase (<link linkend="bib191">Rottiers et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16563875-->; <link linkend="bib247">Wollam et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21749634-->; <link linkend="bib252">Yoshiyama-Yanagawa et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21632547-->). A similar &Delta;<superscript>7</superscript> desaturation is catalyzed by the orthologous <emphasis>neverland</emphasis>/Rieske oxygenase in the first step of insect ecdysteroid biosynthesis (<link linkend="bib252">Yoshiyama et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16763204-->; <link linkend="bib253">Yoshiyama-Yanagawa et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21632547-->). During mammalian bile acid production, CYP7A1/cytochrome P450 hydroxylates the cholesterol backbone at the 7-position in the first step (<link linkend="bib193">Russell, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12543708-->), revealing an analogous chemistry. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, an unknown &Delta;5 reductase thereafter leads to the production of lathosterol, which is oxidized to the 3-keto steroid, lathosterone, by the short chain dehydrogenase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE08067;class=Protein" role="_blank">DHS-16</ulink>, analogous to mammalian HSD3B7 (<link linkend="bib247">Wollam et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22505847-->). The last step in the &Delta;<superscript>7</superscript> pathway involves sequential oxidation of the cholesterol side chain to the carboxylic acid moiety by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30451;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-9</ulink>/cytochrome P450 (<link linkend="bib160">Motola et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16529801-->), bearing similar chemistry to that carried out by CYP27A1 in mammalian bile acid synthetic pathways (<link linkend="bib193">Russell, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12543708-->). Indeed, a compound called dafadine, which phenocopies <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000905;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> loss of function when fed to worms, biochemically inhibits both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30451;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-9</ulink> and CYP27A1 activity (<link linkend="bib134">Luciani et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 22057127-->). These studies reveal remarkable convergence in the biochemical activities of bile acid synthetic pathways from worm to human.</para>
<para>Less is known about nematode &Delta;<superscript>4</superscript> production. Although proposed as an endogenous ligand derived from 4-cholestene-3-one, spectroscopic analysis failed to detect &Delta;<superscript>4</superscript>-DA <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>, perhaps because of vanishingly small amounts or instability (<link linkend="bib138">Mahanti et al., 2014</link><!--: PMID 24411940-->). The 3-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012394;class=Gene" role="_blank">hsd-1</ulink></emphasis>, had been proposed to work in the &Delta;<superscript>4</superscript> branch (<link linkend="bib177">Patel et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18495818-->), but available evidence argues against this hypothesis, and suggests instead that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012394;class=Gene" role="_blank">hsd-1</ulink></emphasis> may produce alternative DA-like ligands or function as a cholesterol &Delta;<superscript>7</superscript> desaturase specifically within the XXX neuroendocrine cells (<link linkend="bib247">Wollam et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22505847-->; <link linkend="bib138">Mahanti et al., 2014</link><!--: PMID 24411940-->). Accordingly, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012394;class=Gene" role="_blank">hsd-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants exhibit phenotypes and genetic interactions distinct from other hormone biosynthetic genes with respect to dauer formation, gonadal migration, and longevity (<link linkend="bib177">Patel et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18495818-->; <link linkend="bib44">Dumas et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20178781-->). More recently, several new DA-related compounds have been discovered through 2D-NMR and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink> analysis, including an abundant and potent &Delta;<superscript>1,7</superscript>-DA, as well as a less prevalent and less potent 3-alpha hydroxy DA (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>) (<link linkend="bib138">Mahanti et al., 2014</link><!--: PMID 24411940-->). In the future it will be important to determine where and how these different DAs are made, and whether the different DAs have distinct functions and transcriptomes.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-4">
<title>Hormonal amplification enforces the reproductive commitments</title>
<para>Interestingly, DA production is distributed in various tissues throughout the organism. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34156;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-36</ulink>/Rieske oxygenase is expressed primarily within the intestine (<link linkend="bib191">Rottiers et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16563875-->), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE08067;class=Protein" role="_blank">DHS-16</ulink>/3-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase is expressed in the pharynx, head neurons, and hypodermis (<link linkend="bib247">Wollam et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22505847-->), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE20185;class=Protein" role="_blank">HSD-1</ulink> in the XXX neuroendocrine cells (<link linkend="bib177">Patel et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18495818-->), and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30451;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-9</ulink>/CYP27A1 in XXX neuroendocrine cells, hypodermis, and spermatheca (<link linkend="bib61">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11740945-->; <link linkend="bib100">Jia et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11782415-->). Distributed synthesis implies that there must be mechanisms involved to transport precursors from one tissue to the other. Why hormone biosynthesis is organized in this non-autonomous fashion is unknown, but speculatively it may generate tissue-specific ligands, or help coordinate the dauer decision across the organism.</para>
<para>Indeed, the choice between dauer and reproductive development converts noisy and variable environmental information into an all-or-none binary organismal decision. Although how this is achieved is not completely understood, it seems to rely largely on tight regulation of DA production, which involves both feed forward and feedback mechanisms that ensure this decision is robust (<link linkend="bib60">Gerisch and Antebi, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15084461-->; <link linkend="bib140">Mak and Ruvkun, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15084462-->; <link linkend="bib197">Schaedel et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22505848-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000905;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink>/CYP27A1</emphasis> regulation is critical in this regard where its function in the neuroendocrine XXX cells and within the hypodermal syncitium apparently serves as a relay to coordinate the organismal response (<link linkend="bib62">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11740945-->; <link linkend="bib100">Jia et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11782415-->). It is hypothesized that the dauer pathways comprise a three state regulatory system to mediate this choice (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>) (<link linkend="bib60">Gerisch and Antebi, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15084461-->; <link linkend="bib197">Schaedel et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22505848-->). Under favorable conditions, insulin and TGF-&beta; signaling converge upon hormone production within the XXX neuroendocrine cell, which results in a DA signal that can be amplified in the hypodermis through upregulation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000905;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis>, thus locking in reproductive commitments. Moderate thermal stress, pheromone level, or modest downregulation of TGF-&beta;, IIS, or steroidal signaling, also visibly upregulate hypodermal <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000905;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis>, presumably increasing DA to sustain reproductive development. Factors required for this upregulation include <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis>, as well as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006652;class=Gene" role="_blank">ttx-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006525;class=Gene" role="_blank">tax-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004032;class=Gene" role="_blank">pkc-1</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002004;class=Gene" role="_blank">hsf-1</ulink></emphasis> genes functioning in thermotaxis neurons, revealing a complex regulatory network linked to temperature cues (<link linkend="bib127">Lee and Kenyon, 2009</link><!--: PMID 19375320-->; <link linkend="bib155">Monje et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21933341-->; <link linkend="bib17">Barna et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23116063-->). In unfavorable dauer inducing conditions, DA production falls below a threshold, hypodermal amplification is suppressed, and animals undergo dauer development. Shift experiments performed with DA (which promotes non-dauer development) and ascarosides (which oppositely promote dauer development) suggest that the dauer decision transpires within a critical time window of 12-18 hours post-hatch within the L1/early L2 stage and that sustained and elevated DA exposure is critical for rapid and complete reproductive development (<link linkend="bib69">Golden and Riddle, 1984a</link><!--: PMID 6706004-->; <link linkend="bib197">Schaedel et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22505848-->). Surprisingly, ascaroside treatment raised the threshold required for DA to implement reproductive program, implying a role of pheromone signaling pathways proximal or downstream of steroidal signaling. Critical tests of these models await accurate measurement of DA levels in various genotypes and tissues.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 5</phrase>
</textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-5">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> regulates L2/L3 transitions in developmental timing circuits</title>
<para>An important aspect of larval development is the correct specification of temporal fates. As <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> develops through the four larval stages, tissues undergo stage-specific patterns of cell division, migration, fusion, and morphogenesis. Epidermal stem cells called seams undergo asymmetric divisions at each stage, with stage-specific variations in division (<link linkend="bib216">Sulston and Horvitz, 1977</link><!--: PMID 838129-->). At the larval-to-adult transition they cease dividing, fuse, and synthesize adult alae. Vulval cells undergo stereotyped induction and division in the L3 stage, and morphogenesis during the L4 stage. The gonad undergoes cell division, outgrowth, and differentiation from L2-L4 to form two U-shaped arms harboring the maturing germ cells, spermatheca, and uterus (<link linkend="bib111">Kimble and Hirsh, 1979</link><!--: PMID 478167-->). Intestinal nuclei undergo endoreplication at each stage, with a stage-specific nuclear division in L2 (<link linkend="bib86">Hedgecock and White, 1985</link><!--: PMID 2578115-->). Motorneurons also undergo changes in synaptic connectivity (<link linkend="bib258">Zhou and Walthall, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9852581-->).</para>
<para>The so-called heterochronic genes control developmental timing, and work as temporal selectors that specify these stage appropriate patterns. Their mutation results in precocious or retarded development within specific tissues (<link linkend="bib2">Ambros and Horvitz, 1984</link><!--: PMID 6494891-->). Most of the identified heterochronic regulators are evolutionarily conserved, including the first discovered microRNAs <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002993;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-4</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002285;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-7</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib127">Lee et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID 8252621-->; <link linkend="bib243">Wightman et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID 8252622-->; <link linkend="bib187">Reinhart et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10706289-->) and components that regulate their maturation such as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24879;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-28</ulink> (<link linkend="bib159">Moss et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9054503-->; <link linkend="bib233">Viswanathan et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18292307-->). Remarkably the human <emphasis>LIN28</emphasis> has been linked to the timing of puberty (<link linkend="bib171">Ong et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19448623-->). Several NRs also play various roles in the heterochronic circuit, including <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink>/FXR, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43454;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-55</ulink>/COUP, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SF1;class=Strain" role="_blank">SF1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib6">Antebi et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9477318-->; <link linkend="bib79">Hada et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20678979-->; <link linkend="bib225">Thompson-Peer et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22325199-->).</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> functions as a switch within the heterochronic circuits, promoting L2/L3 transitions. Mutants manifest retarded phenotypes in which they repeat L2 programs inappropriately at the L3 stage in seam, gonad, and intestine (<link linkend="bib6">Antebi et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9477318-->). Such phenotypes were originally observed with high penetrance in specific LBD truncation mutants, and at low penetrance in null mutants (<link linkend="bib7">Antebi et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10859169-->). The LBD truncation mutants, though recessive in nature, are thought to interfere with redundant or overlapping functions. Indeed, double mutant combination with other heterochronic loci affecting the L2/L3 transition strongly enhance the phenotypes of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> null mutants, revealing multiple layers of regulation within the pathway (<link linkend="bib1">Abbott et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16139228-->; <link linkend="bib42">Ding et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16109369-->; <link linkend="bib53">Fielenbach et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17336909-->; <link linkend="bib91">Hochbaum et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21814518-->). Genetic epistasis experiments place <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> downstream of the novel nuclear factor, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03734;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-14</ulink>, but upstream or in parallel to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24879;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-28</ulink> (<link linkend="bib6">Antebi et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9477318-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-6">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> works in a steroid-regulated microRNA switch</title>
<para>An important clue to DAF-12&apos;s function within the heterochronic circuits came with the observation that a triple knockout of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002285;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-7</ulink></emphasis>-related microRNAs, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003039;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-48</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003312;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-84</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003335;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-241</ulink></emphasis> (collectively known as <emphasis>let-7s</emphasis>), results in phenotypes similar to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> mutation, that is, a reiteration of L2 seam cell division programs at the L3 stage (<link linkend="bib1">Abbott et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16139228-->). Moreover, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> mutation reduced expression levels of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002285;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-7</ulink></emphasis> family microRNAs as measured by Northern blots or qPCR, revealing that it works upstream (<link linkend="bib46">Esquela-Kerscher et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16217741-->; <link linkend="bib21">Bethke et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19342589-->; <link linkend="bib83">Hammell et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19828440-->). This led to the hypothesis that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> directly transcriptionally regulates these microRNAs. Indeed, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> together with the DAs, potently transactivates the promoters of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003312;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-84</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003335;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-241</ulink></emphasis> in mammalian cell culture, and expression of these two microRNAs shows <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> and DA dependence in specific tissues in the worm (<link linkend="bib21">Bethke et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19342589-->). Interestingly, ecdysone and estrogen receptors also regulate <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002285;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-7</ulink></emphasis> microRNAs in flies and mammals, respectively, revealing a possible ancestral role for steroidal control of microRNA expression by nuclear receptors (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). For example 20-hydroxy ecdysone stimulates expression of the <emphasis>Drosophila let-7C</emphasis> complex, which regulates genes required for remodeling of neuromuscular architecture during the larval-to-adult transition (<link linkend="bib22">Bhat-Nakshatri et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19528081-->; <link linkend="bib33">Chawla and Sokol, 2012</link><!--: PMID 22510985-->) and promotes temporal transitions in mushroom body neuroblast progenitors (<link linkend="bib119">Kucherenko et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23160410-->). In mammalian MCF7 cells, estradiol treatment upregulated 8 members of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002285;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-7</ulink></emphasis> family, and the related <emphasis>mir-98</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib22">Bhat-Nakshatri et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19528081-->; <link linkend="bib33">Chawla and Sokol, 2012</link><!--: PMID 22510985-->).</para>
<para>In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, the data suggest a model in which liganded <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> upregulates <emphasis>let-7s</emphasis>, which in turn downregulate their target, the L2 regulatory factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE23646;class=Protein" role="_blank">HBL-1</ulink>/hunchback Zn finger protein, allowing L3 reproductive programs to be expressed (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>) (<link linkend="bib21">Bethke et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19342589-->; <link linkend="bib83">Hammell et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19828440-->). Conversely in the absence of hormone, the unliganded receptor potently represses microRNA expression during dauer formation. Thus <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> works as a steroid-gated microRNA switch that functions to turn off earlier developmental programs to allow for later ones during reproductive growth, or to shut down the heterochronic timer altogether in the dauer stage. Interestingly, these same <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002285;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-7</ulink></emphasis>-related microRNAs also feedback inhibit <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> through its 3&rsquo;UTR, and curtail its activity for dauer formation and gonadal outgrowth (<link linkend="bib21">Bethke et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19342589-->; <link linkend="bib83">Hammell et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19828440-->). Similarly <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002285;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-7</ulink></emphasis> itself feedback inhibits <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> late in larval development to facilitate the larval-to-adult transition (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>) (<link linkend="bib76">Grosshans et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15737928-->). Such feedback control may serve to temporally dampen <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> activity, or help buffer developmental decisions in response to variable environmental and physiologic inputs.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig6" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 6</phrase>
</textobject> &fig6legend;</mediaobject>
<para>In fact, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003312;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-84</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003335;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-241</ulink></emphasis> represent only a small fraction of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> target genes relevant to developmental progression. An analysis of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> binding sites and transcriptional activity reveals that it may regulate other heterochronic genes (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003026;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-41</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00018572;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-42</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003014;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-28</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003048;class=Gene" role="_blank">lit-1</ulink></emphasis>), other microRNAs, and genes involved in microRNA activity (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015547;class=Gene" role="_blank">ain-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003598;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhl-2</ulink></emphasis>), putative coregulators (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008549;class=Gene" role="_blank">din-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000366;class=Gene" role="_blank">cbp-1</ulink></emphasis>), as well as dauer transcription factors (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000899;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis>) (<link linkend="bib208">Shostak et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15489294-->; <link linkend="bib54">Fisher and Lithgow, 2006</link><!--: PMID 16626392-->; <link linkend="bib83">Hammell et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19828440-->; <link linkend="bib91">Hochbaum et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21814518-->), demonstrating that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> regulates key components in these circuits.</para>
<para>By lying at the confluence of dauer and heterochronic pathways, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> coordinates L2/L3 transitions, including the L3 dauer diapause, in response to environmental and physiologic inputs. In this capacity, it works intimately with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29325;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-42</ulink>/Period, another heterochronic regulator that also affects dauer formation, developmental timing in epidermis, gonad, and other tissues, as well as molting (<link linkend="bib99">Jeon et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10550049-->; <link linkend="bib221">Tennessen et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16300753-->; <link linkend="bib222">Tennessen et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20843862-->; <link linkend="bib156">Monsalve et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 22137474-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29325;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-42</ulink> is a homolog of Period, the circadian regulator, and is expressed in an oscillating pattern in concert with the molt cycle (<link linkend="bib99">Jeon et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10550049-->; <link linkend="bib157">Monsalve et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 22137474-->), suggesting a clocklike function similar to its mammalian counterpart (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link> and <link linkend="figure7">Figure 7</link>). Notably, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29325;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-42</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> appear to mutually antagonize one another&apos;s activity. For example, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> retarded heterochronic phenotypes are suppressed by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00018572;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-42</ulink></emphasis> mutation, and <emphasis>lin-42&rsquo;s</emphasis> precocious phenotypes are often suppressed by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> mutation (<link linkend="bib221">Tennessen et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16300753-->). <emphasis>lin-42(+)</emphasis> opposes dauer formation under mild stress and works at the same step as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> during the dauer decision. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00018572;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-42</ulink></emphasis> mutants are Daf-c at elevated temperatures, and <emphasis>lin-42(+)</emphasis> overexpression prevents dauer formation even in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> LBD Daf-c mutants, suggesting a close association with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> (<link linkend="bib222">Tennessen et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20843862-->). These interactions could be direct, as the two proteins physically interact in yeast two-hybrid experiments, or indirect, reflect opposing regulatory activities on target processes. It is noteworthy that several mammalian NRs bind to and are inhibited by PER2, suggesting a conserved interaction between NRs and components of the circadian clock (<link linkend="bib75">Grimaldi et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 21035761-->; <link linkend="bib199">Schmutz et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20159955-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure7" xreflabel="Figure 7">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig7" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 7</phrase>
</textobject> &fig7legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Many of the observed <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> heterochronic phenotypes are modulated by environmental conditions or dauer signaling (<link linkend="bib21">Bethke et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19342589-->; <link linkend="bib91">Hochbaum et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21814518-->; <link linkend="bib97">Huang and Zhang, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21471153-->), revealing plastic and modulatory inputs into developmental timing pathways. Other processes influenced by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> include the specification of chemoreceptors in sensory neurons (<link linkend="bib166">Nolan et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12464635-->), male mate search behavior (<link linkend="bib113">Kleemann et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18854588-->), foregut remodeling (<link linkend="bib8">Ao et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15375261-->), and muscle arm extension (<link linkend="bib43">Dixon et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18436204-->). These functions may be related to its roles in dauer or developmental timing. In particular extra muscle arms are induced by downregulation of DA, IIS, and TGF-&beta; signaling (<link linkend="bib43">Dixon et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18436204-->). Interestingly this phenotype depends specifically on a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> isoform consisting of LBD only, revealing a novel previously unknown role for this protein. Altogether these processes imply substantial plasticity in remodeling of neural and neuromuscular architecture in response to environmental and hormonal cues.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-7">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> regulates life span in response to signals from the reproductive system</title>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has served as a premier model for the study of aging, and at least four major pathways have been shown to extend life span across taxa including reduced insulin/IGF, mitochondrial function, dietary restriction, and signaling from the reproductive system (<link linkend="bib109">Kenyon, 2010</link><!--: PMID 20336132-->). Notably, removal of germline stem cells by laser microsurgery or genetic ablation results in an extension of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> adult life span by 60% (<link linkend="bib95">Hsin and Kenyon, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10360574-->; <link linkend="bib10">Arantes-Oliveira et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11799246-->). Further removal of the somatic gonad abolishes this life span extension, suggesting that the germline makes life-shortening signals that antagonize life-lengthening signals from the somatic gonad. Regulation of life span by the reproductive system is also seen in fruit flies (<link linkend="bib55">Flatt et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18434551-->) and perhaps even in humans (<link linkend="bib152">Min et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23017989-->).</para>
<para>Regulation of longevity by the reproductive system requires the activity of at least five transcription factors, including <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink>/FXR, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15998;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHA-4</ulink>/FOXA, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE19488;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-80</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33715;class=Protein" role="_blank">HLH-30</ulink>/TFEB, which regulate lipid metabolism, fatty acid desaturation, lipolysis, autophagy, and proteasome activity to influence longevity (<link linkend="figure8">Figure 8</link>) (<link linkend="bib95">Hsin and Kenyon, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10360574-->; <link linkend="bib235">Wang et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18988854-->; <link linkend="bib73">Goudeau et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21423649-->; <link linkend="bib123">Lapierre et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21906946-->; <link linkend="bib232">Vilchez et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22922647-->; <link linkend="bib123">Lapierre et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23925298-->; <link linkend="bib167">O&apos;Rourke and Ruvkun, 2013</link><!--: PMID 23604316-->). Communication between tissues suggests a hormonal mechanism is at work, and indeed, long life requires the activity of DA and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> signaling (<link linkend="bib95">Hsin and Kenyon, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10360574-->; <link linkend="bib61">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11740945-->; <link linkend="bib191">Rottiers et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16563875-->; <link linkend="bib61">Gerisch et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17360327-->; <link linkend="bib247">Wollam et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22505847-->). In fact, life extending signals from the somatic gonad may be the DAs themselves since gonadless animals, which have normal life span, exhibit robust life span extension upon <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30451;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-9</ulink> overexpression or DA supplementation (<link linkend="bib249">Yamawaki et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20824162-->). Moreover, this extension is <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> dependent. Another key regulator in this pathway is the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO transcription factor, which mediates IIS (<link linkend="bib95">Hsin and Kenyon, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10360574-->). Evidence indicates that DA/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> facilitates <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO nuclear localization and activity (Berman and Kenyon, 2006 <!--: PMID 16530050-->; <link linkend="bib61">Gerisch et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17360327-->), and that the two transcription factors cooperate to regulate longevity assurance genes in germlineless animals. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> may contribute to longevity by regulating expression of a fatty acid reductase, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00022200;class=Gene" role="_blank">fard-1</ulink></emphasis>, as well as the lipase <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00019939;class=Gene" role="_blank">lips-17</ulink></emphasis>, which are required for longevity (<link linkend="bib144">McCormick et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22081913-->). Surprisingly genetic manipulation of these molecules as well as the lipase <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00019376;class=Gene" role="_blank">lipl-4</ulink></emphasis> (which is transactivated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO) have little effect on bulk fat levels, and therefore may instead produce fatty acid signaling molecules that could work through additional nuclear receptors such as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE19488;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-80</ulink> (see Section 4.8).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure8" xreflabel="Figure 8">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig8" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 8</phrase>
</textobject> &fig8legend;</mediaobject>
<para>How might <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> cooperate to regulate longevity? Recent evidence suggests that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> regulation of <emphasis>let-7-</emphasis>related microRNAs mediates crosstalk between the two transcription factors (<link linkend="bib205">Shen et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23239738-->). Studies by Shen and colleagues showed that germline removal results in upregulation of DA production, triggering <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> dependent activation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003312;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-84</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003335;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-241</ulink></emphasis>, previously implicated in developmental timing circuits (Section 2.6) (<link linkend="bib21">Bethke et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19342589-->). Importantly, these microRNAs, too, are required for the longevity of germlineless animals, as their deletion abolishes life span extension. Further molecular analysis reveals that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003312;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-84</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003335;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-241</ulink></emphasis> downregulate two inhibitors of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO, namely the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05274;class=Protein" role="_blank">AKT-1</ulink> kinase (<link linkend="bib174">Paradis and Ruvkun, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9716402-->) and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03734;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-14</ulink> heterochronic nuclear factor (<link linkend="bib24">Boehm and Slack, 2005</link><!--: PMID 16373574-->), and thereby promote <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO nuclear localization and activity (<link linkend="figure8">Figure 8</link>) (<link linkend="bib205">Shen et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23239738-->). Remarkably then, components of the developmental timing switch used during L2/L3 temporal transitions are co-opted to trigger a long lived adult mode. This discovery and others support the idea that components of developmental clocks are used to regulate animal life span (<link linkend="bib62">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11740945-->; <link linkend="bib24">Boehm and Slack, 2005</link><!--: PMID 16373574-->; <link linkend="bib205">Shen et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23239738-->). Conceivably developmental timing components synchronize signaling between gonad and soma to ensure coordinate maturation under environmental or physiologic stress.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-8">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> and longevity continued</title>
<para>In ectotherms, longevity varies inversely with temperature, with animals living shorter at higher temperatures. Thermal effects on life span and other processes are ascribed to passive changes in metabolic rate, but recent evidence also suggests a regulated process that links thermotaxis and steroidal signaling (<link linkend="bib128">Lee and Kenyon, 2009</link><!--: PMID 19375320-->). Thermotaxis genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006652;class=Gene" role="_blank">ttx-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006654;class=Gene" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis> encode transcription factors that specify the fates of the temperature sensing neurons (<link linkend="bib90">Hobert et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9292724-->; <link linkend="bib122">Lanjuin et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14536063-->). Unexpectedly, loss of AFD thermosensory neurons through mutation or laser ablation, results in short life span at elevated temperatures (25&deg; C), which is restored by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> loss of function (<link linkend="bib128">Lee and Kenyon, 2009</link><!--: PMID 19375320-->). Similar observations are seen with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000905;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> hypomorphs that reduce but do not abolish DA production; such mutants are short lived at 25 &deg;C, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> mutation suppresses this phenotype, suggesting that the unliganded receptor is life shortening in this context. Overexpression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000905;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> also restores normal life span to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006652;class=Gene" role="_blank">ttx-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant animals. Altogether these observations suggest that a boost of DA production and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> activity at elevated temperatures is essential to maintain normal life. Conceivably this physiologic function is related to the activity of heat shock factor, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002004;class=Gene" role="_blank">hsf-1</ulink></emphasis>, which, similar to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006652;class=Gene" role="_blank">ttx-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib128">Lee and Kenyon, 2009</link><!--: PMID 19375320-->), regulates <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000905;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis> levels in response to temperature in feedback circuits described above (<link linkend="bib17">Barna et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23116063-->), suggesting that thermal responses are coordinated hormonally.</para>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> mutants also show complex interactions with IIS for life span regulation. So-called <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> class 1 mutants robustly extend life span in a manner that is partially abrogated upon <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> loss, while <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> class 2 mutants, which are more pleiotropic, show synergistic life span extension upon <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> depletion (<link linkend="bib59">Gems et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9725835-->), an interaction that is hermaphrodite specific (<link linkend="bib145">McCulloch and Gems, 2007</link><!--: PMID 18056973-->). Several other loci, such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002335;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-60</ulink></emphasis>/Ras and hormone biosynthetic genes evoke a similar complex interaction, but the underlying molecular mechanism remains obscure (<link linkend="bib163">Nanji et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16164423-->; <link linkend="bib44">Dumas et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23550118-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> also functions in hormesis-induced longevity. When animals are subjected to moderate brief pulses of heat stress, they acquire subsequent thermotolerance and longevity, which depends on the activity of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000913;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-18</ulink>,</emphasis> and other factors (<link linkend="bib39">Cypser et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 17067771-->). Lastly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> has been shown to contribute to precocious aging and somatic collapse of hermaphrodites that have been mated by males (<link linkend="bib206">Shi and Murphy, 2013</link><!--: PMID 24356112-->). Mated hermaphrodites shrink and die early due to signals from sperm and seminal fluid: the shrinkage phenotype is mediated by DA/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> pathways, while the short-lived phenotype largely arises from induction of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47202;class=Protein" role="_blank">INS-7</ulink> and inhibition of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-9">
<title>DA/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> signaling in parasitic and other nematodes</title>
<para>Remarkably, DA/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> signaling has been conserved in nematodes that are diverged from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> by over 150 million years, and functions similarly as an important regulator of life history traits and phenotypic plasticity. The free-living nematode <emphasis>Pristionchus pacificus</emphasis> has co-opted the DA/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> module, not only to regulate dauer formation, but also to select alternative mouth dimorphisms involved in predatory feeding (<link linkend="bib170">Ogawa et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19110431-->; <link linkend="bib20">Bento et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20592728-->). As with <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, germline elimination extends <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> life span, and in addition enhances innate immunity in a manner dependent upon <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib183">Rae et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22912581-->). The DA/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> module has also been deployed to regulate the infective stage of parasitic nematodes, which is comparable to dauer. Treatment of the parasites <emphasis>Strongyloides stercoralis, Acylostoma spp,</emphasis> and <emphasis>Strongyloides papillosus</emphasis> with &Delta;<superscript>7</superscript>-DA variously prevents formation of the L3 infective stage or promotes exit from the infective stage, much like DA prevents dauer formation or promotes dauer exit (<link linkend="bib170">Ogawa et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19110431-->; <link linkend="bib239">Wang et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19497877-->). Several nematode DAF-12s are transactivated by DA and cholestenoic acid in cell culture. Such activity is confirmed in the crystal structure of &Delta;<superscript>7</superscript>-DA bound to the LBD of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> from <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis>, which reveals that the receptor forms a canonical three layered sandwich comprised of 13 alpha helical regions and three beta strands typical of NRs (<link linkend="bib239">Wang et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19497877-->). The orientation of ligand and contact residues within the LBD pocket most resembles the way in which bile acids bind to FXR, implying that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> and FXR are biochemical orthologs (<link linkend="bib257">Zhi et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22170062-->). Significantly, many of the parasitic nematodes lack endogenous DAs as well as a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000905;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink></emphasis>/CYP27A1, suggesting they rely on host-produced bile acid-like steroids to stimulate exit from the infective stage.</para>
<para>Altogether these studies indicate the vast potential for exploiting the DA/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> axis to combat parasitic disease. For example, DA-like molecules could be used to trigger precocious exit from the infective stage in the wrong environment, or DA-inhibitors could be used to prevent exit in compatible hosts.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-10">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33928;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-8</ulink>/LXR regulates cholesterol, bile acid, and fatty acid metabolism</title>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33928;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-8</ulink> is the closest relative to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, and homologous to vertebrate LXR, FXR, PXR, and VITD receptors. Expressed primarily in the gut, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33928;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-8</ulink> controls production of the bile-acid like DAs and thereby <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> activity through regulation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34156;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-36</ulink>/Rieske oxygenase and cholesterol disposition (<link linkend="bib137">Magner et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23931753-->). Mutants display lower levels of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007536;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-36</ulink></emphasis> mRNA and protein, and make less of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34156;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-36</ulink> metabolic product, 7-dehydrocholesterol, as well as DA itself. Consistent with a role in DA metabolism, mutants enter the dauer diapause constitutively on low cholesterol or at elevated temperature (27 &deg;C), and have reduced expression of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> target gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003335;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-241</ulink></emphasis>. By controlling the first step in DA production, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33928;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-8</ulink> may thereby regulate cholesterol, bile acid flux, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> activity. These functions are analogous to its vertebrate relative, LXR, which regulates the first step of bile acid synthesis and affects activity of FXR (<link linkend="bib30">Calkin and Tontonoz, 2012</link><!--: PMID 22414897-->), the homolog of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>). Steady state levels of cholesterol are lower in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003607;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-8</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos as measured by uptake of NBD-cholesterol, suggesting a deficiency in transport or metabolism in the germline. Indeed, several phenotypes manifest under low cholesterol (e.g., shortened life span, FA desaturation defects) or no cholesterol conditions (larval arrest). Transcriptome analysis of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003607;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-8</ulink></emphasis> mutants under low cholesterol conditions reveals altered expression of genes involved in fatty acid desaturation, lipolysis, transport and vitellogenesis, as well as those functioning in host defense and life span regulation (<link linkend="bib137">Magner et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23931753-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003607;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-8</ulink></emphasis> mutants have reduced mRNA expression of the fatty acid desaturases, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001397;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis>, and correspondingly higher levels of saturated and lower levels of mono- and polyunsaturated FA. Regulation of FA desaturation and apolipoprotein production are also features of the vertebrate LXR (<link linkend="bib30">Calkin and Tontonoz, 2012</link><!--: PMID 22414897-->). Interestingly, the <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> DHR96, a close relative of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33928;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-8</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink>, also regulates fatty acid and cholesterol metabolism (<link linkend="bib84">Horner et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19952106-->; <link linkend="bib209">Sieber and Thummel, 2012</link><!--: PMID 22197324-->). Mutants are sensitive to cholesterol deprivation, and have dysregulated cholesterol balance. DHR96 has been shown to bind to cholesterol, although it is not known if this serves as an activating ligand, inverse agonist, or competency factor (<link linkend="bib84">Horner et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19952106-->). Although the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33928;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-8</ulink> ligand is unknown, it is surmised to be a sterol derivative based on its sterol dependent phenotypes.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-11">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43454;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-55</ulink>/COUP, a switch in neuronal developmental timing circuits</title>
<para>The NR COUP is highly conserved in evolution and functions in neural and cardiovascular development, pituitary and reproductive function, and metabolism (<link linkend="bib133">Lin et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21257780-->). The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006790;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-55</ulink></emphasis> regulates synaptic remodeling of GABAergic motoneurons during the L1 stage, through conserved developmental timing pathways (<link linkend="bib258">Zhou and Walthall, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9852581-->; <link linkend="bib225">Thompson-Peer et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22325199-->). Specifically, embryonically born DD motoneurons switch their synaptic outputs from ventral onto dorsal muscles during the L1 stage, while larval-born VD neurons do not. Normally, <emphasis>unc-55(+)</emphasis> prevents VD neurons from undergoing synaptic remodeling; in null mutants larval VD neurons remodel inappropriately, similar to the embryonic DDs. Consistent with a cell autonomous role, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006790;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-55</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in the VDs during larval development. Additionally, it resides in AS and other motor neurons (<link linkend="bib258">Zhou and Walthall, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9852581-->), suggesting that other roles remain to be discovered.</para>
<para>How might <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006790;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-55</ulink></emphasis> regulate synaptic switching? Apparently DD switching is driven by the heterochronic regulator <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001824;class=Gene" role="_blank">hbl-1</ulink></emphasis>/hunchback, which is repressed by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006790;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-55</ulink></emphasis> in the VDs (<link linkend="bib225">Thompson-Peer et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22325199-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001824;class=Gene" role="_blank">hbl-1</ulink></emphasis> loss-of-function mutants, DD remodeling is delayed, whereas in microRNA <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003312;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-84</ulink></emphasis> mutants, which conversely cause <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001824;class=Gene" role="_blank">hbl-1</ulink></emphasis> overexpression, DD remodeling is precocious. Given the regulatory relationships of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003312;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-84</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001824;class=Gene" role="_blank">hbl-1</ulink></emphasis> in seam cells described above, it seems plausible that steroid signaling too might function in synaptic remodeling. Transcriptional profiling of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006790;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-55</ulink></emphasis> reveals differential expression in a large number of genes compared to wild type, including the Iroquois homeodomain protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE42075#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">IRX-1</ulink>, which also regulates DD remodeling (<link linkend="bib180">Petersen et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 22031882-->). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE43454#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-55</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE23646#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">HBL-1</ulink> regulatory interaction strikingly resembles those seen in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> where <emphasis>seven-up</emphasis>/COUP temporally regulates <emphasis>hb</emphasis>/hunchback during neurogenesis (<link linkend="bib105">Kanai et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15691762-->; <link linkend="bib19">Benito-Sipos et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 22071101-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-12">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink>/SF-1 and the molting clock</title>
<para>We now turn our attention to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink><emphasis>,</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39085;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-23</ulink>, and other receptors that function in another type of timing device, the molting clock. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> is a highly conserved NR that plays critical roles in development and metabolism. Its closest relative in <emphasis>Drosophila,</emphasis> Ftz-F1, is involved in early embryonic patterning, larval molting, and metamorphosis (<link linkend="bib172">Ou and King-Jones, 2013</link><!--: PMID 23347515-->). The mammalian homolog, SF-1, is implicated in steroidogenesis, hypothalamic, adrenal and gonadal development, and sex determination (<link linkend="bib51">Ferraz-de-Souza et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21078366-->). Another homolog, LRH, functions in cholesterol, bile acid, glucose, and fatty acid metabolism. It also modulates pluripotentency of embryonic stem cells, and has a role in inflammation and stem cell renewal in the gut (<link linkend="bib50">Fernandez-Marcos et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21194563-->)</para>
<para>Like its fly counterpart, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink>/SF-1 coordinates epidermal morphogenesis, differentiation, and molting. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> is expressed early in embryogenesis first within the E lineage, which gives rise to the gut, and thereafter in hypodermal cells, pharyngeal and rectal epithelial cells, somatic gonad, and germline. During embryogenesis, mutation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> or knockdown by RNAi results in lethality at the two-fold stage at the initiation of elongation (<link linkend="bib12">Asahina et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10971653-->; <link linkend="bib63">Gissendanner and Sluder, 2000</link><!--: PMID 10772806-->). Although epidermal cells are specified and divide normally, they fail to fuse properly during epidermal morphogenesis resulting in ventral closure defects. During larval development, the epidermal seam cells fail to reestablish contacts at the lateral midline and lose their spindle shape, possibly leading to ectopic cell division in the adult and poor alae formation (<link linkend="bib34">Chen et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15314147-->; <link linkend="bib212">Silhankova et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15615786-->). Knockdown of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> within the seam cells is sufficient to recapitulate these defects, suggesting a cell autonomous role (<link linkend="bib82">Hajduskova et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19654209-->; <link linkend="bib79">Hada et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20678979-->). Mutants also have additional defects in vulva division, fusion, and morphogenesis (<link linkend="bib34">Chen et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15314147-->). In this context, correct vulval specification depends on dampening of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> transcriptional activity by sumoylation (<link linkend="bib240">Ward et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 24348269-->).</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> functions most prominently within the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> molt cycle (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link> and <link linkend="figure7">Figure 7</link>). Each of the four successive larval stages (L1-L4) is punctuated by molts. The molt cycle begins with synthesis of the new cuticle, an intermolt period characterized by feeding, activity, and growth, followed by a brief hiatus of sleep-like inactivity, termed lethargus, during which the new cuticle is deposited and the old one shed, and then emergence into the new intermolt. This process takes approximately 8-10 hours for each stage (<link linkend="bib156">Monsalve and Frand, 2012</link><!--: PMID 24058853-->). During the larval molts, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> mutants are unable to shed the old cuticle and often bear residual cuticle stuck to mouth, vulva, and rectal areas (<link linkend="bib12">Asahina et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10971653-->; <link linkend="bib63">Gissendanner and Sluder, 2000</link><!--: PMID 10772806-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> mRNA and protein levels oscillate, with peak mRNA levels at the molt (<link linkend="figure7">Figure 7</link>) (<link linkend="bib64">Gissendanner et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14738886-->; M. Horn and A. Antebi, unpublished). Several key genes implicated in ecdysis and epidermal differentiation are regulated by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis>, including the angiotensin converting enzyme homolog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000039;class=Gene" role="_blank">acn-1</ulink></emphasis>, the nematode-specific gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015646;class=Gene" role="_blank">mlt-10</ulink></emphasis>, the collagenase <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003553;class=Gene" role="_blank">nas-37</ulink></emphasis>, and the amyloid precursor protein homolog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000149;class=Gene" role="_blank">apl-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib26">Brooks et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14559923-->; <link linkend="bib40">Davis et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15539494-->; <link linkend="bib56">Frand et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16122351-->; <link linkend="bib94">Hornsten et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17267616-->; <link linkend="bib79">Hada et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20678979-->; <link linkend="bib150">Meli et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20335506-->; <link linkend="bib242">Wiese et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20862215-->).</para>
<para>Recently, it has been suggested that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> also acts in the heterochronic circuit. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> mutants display defects reminiscent of retarded heterochrony, including shallow adult alae formation and delayed male tail retraction (<link linkend="bib79">Hada et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20678979-->; <link linkend="bib164">Nelson et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21408209-->). Moreover, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> depletion suppresses the precocious heterochronic phenotypes of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001824;class=Gene" role="_blank">hbl-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003026;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-41</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00018572;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-42</ulink></emphasis> mutants, although its interactions with other heterochronic mutants suggest a more complex network (<link linkend="bib79">Hada et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20678979-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> RNAi also suppresses the supernumerary molt phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002285;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-7</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003312;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-84</ulink></emphasis> double mutants, suggesting that <emphasis>let-7s</emphasis> downregulate <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> at the L4/adult transition, leading to a cessation of molting (<link linkend="bib85">Hayes et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 17065234-->; <link linkend="bib79">Hada et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20678979-->). In accord with this idea, the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> 3&rsquo;UTR contains predicted <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002285;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-7</ulink></emphasis> binding sites, but it remains to be seen whether regulation is direct. The observation that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> works at the convergence of the molt cycle and the developmental timer strongly suggests intimate interactions with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00018572;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-42</ulink></emphasis>/period, a gene that also affects both processes (see Section 2.14) (<link linkend="bib99">Jeon et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10550049-->; <link linkend="bib157">Monsalve et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 22137474-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-13">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39085;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-23</ulink>/ROR regulates the molt cycle</title>
<para>Molting is also controlled by another key nuclear hormone receptor, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE24775#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-23</ulink>, a homolog of <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> DHR3 and the mammalian ROR (<link linkend="figure7">Figure 7</link>), which are all components of biological clocks. During the <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> larval molt cycle and prepupal to pupal transition, the ecdysone receptor stimulates Ftz-F1&beta;, which in turn regulate DHR3 within ecdysone signaling cascades (<link linkend="bib172">Ou and King-Jones, 2013</link><!--: PMID 23347515-->). The mammalian ROR&alpha; is a central component of the circadian clock, positively regulating BMAL and the NR REV-ERB (<link linkend="bib185">Ranhotra, 2012</link><!--: PMID 22686165-->). In turn, REV-ERB feedback inhibits ROR, contributing to the periodicity of circadian rhythms. ROR also functions in cerebellum development, immunity, and lipid, cholesterol, and glucose metabolism.</para>
<para>Similar to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003622;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-23</ulink></emphasis> null mutants arrest at the comma or three-fold stage of embryogenesis (<link linkend="bib115">Kostrouchova et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9521900-->; <link linkend="bib116">Kostrouchova et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11416209-->). Hatched L1 larvae are dumpy, indicating morphologic or elongation defects. Also similar to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003622;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-23</ulink></emphasis> RNAi knockdown in larvae results in defects in molting and alae formation (<link linkend="bib116">Kostrouchova et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11416209-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003622;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-23</ulink></emphasis> is expressed predominately in epidermal tissues, including seam cells, P-ectoblasts, and hypodermal cells. Expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003622;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-23</ulink></emphasis> mRNA oscillates with the molt cycle, but with opposite phase to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis>, peaking during the intermolt (<link linkend="figure7">Figure 7</link>) (<link linkend="bib64">Gissendanner et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14738886-->), though whether protein expression also oscillates has yet to be determined. The reciprocal relationship between <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003622;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-23</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> expression suggests that they could regulate one another in a feedback loop, but this has not been directly tested. Surprisingly, the reciprocal regulatory relationship of ROR and REV-ERB seen in the mammalian circadian clock is not seen in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> counterparts<emphasis>,</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39085;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-23</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26023;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-85</ulink>. Although <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003675;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-85</ulink></emphasis> expression varies with the molt cycle, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003675;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-85</ulink></emphasis> depletion does not result in molting defects except at the dauer molt. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003675;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-85</ulink></emphasis> also affects egg laying (<link linkend="bib64">Gissendanner et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14738886-->). Another REV-ERB homolog, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004786;class=Gene" role="_blank">sex-1</ulink>,</emphasis> specifies the hermaphrodite sexual fate. It serves as a dose dependent X chromosome signaling element that antagonizes autosomal signaling elements in the promoter of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006962;class=Gene" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis>, a key sex determination gene (<link linkend="bib31">Carmi et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9823896-->; <link linkend="bib48">Farboud et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23666922-->).</para>
<para>Transcriptome profiling reveals that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39085;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-23</ulink> regulates expression of various genes implicated in molting including, cuticle collagens (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001064;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-2</ulink>,-3,-5,-7,-8,-10</emphasis>), hedgehog-related genes (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006947;class=Gene" role="_blank">wrt-1</ulink>,-2,-3, grd</emphasis> genes), patch-related genes (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004210;class=Gene" role="_blank">ptc-3</ulink></emphasis>), and molting genes (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021095;class=Gene" role="_blank">mlt-8</ulink>,-9,-10,-11</emphasis>) (<link linkend="bib117">Kouns et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21910973-->). Similar to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003622;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-23</ulink></emphasis> also affects expression of a number of genes functionally implicated in molting, including <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000039;class=Gene" role="_blank">acn-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015646;class=Gene" role="_blank">mlt-10</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib56">Frand et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16122351-->; <link linkend="bib117">Kouns et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21910973-->). Curiously, several genes involved in DA biosynthesis, including <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000979;class=Gene" role="_blank">dhs-16</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000905;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-9</ulink>,</emphasis> also appear to be <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003622;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-23</ulink></emphasis> regulated, perhaps relevant to a role in the dauer molt (<link linkend="bib64">Gissendanner et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14738886-->; <link linkend="bib117">Kouns et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21910973-->).</para>
<para>Other NRs may also be tied to the molt cycle. The HNF4-like family member, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003650;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-60</ulink></emphasis>, is regulated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39085;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-23</ulink> within seam cells (<link linkend="bib213">Simeckova et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17579999-->). RNAi knockdown of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003650;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-60</ulink></emphasis> results in embryonic lethality, poor ventral closure, and seam cell defects similar to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003622;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-23</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> mutants, suggesting <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003650;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-60</ulink></emphasis> could work in transcriptional cascades driving early morphogenetic events. The <emphasis>DHR78/TR2</emphasis> homolog, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00022423;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-41</ulink>,</emphasis> and possibly <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink>,</emphasis> are expressed in a cyclical pattern along with the molt cycle, as measured by mRNA (<link linkend="figure7">Figure 7</link>) (<link linkend="bib64">Gissendanner et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14738886-->; <link linkend="bib76">Merris et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17277379-->). However, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/protein/DAF-12" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink>::GFP does not overtly oscillate at the protein level, and mutation of these receptors does not explicitly affect molting per se, though both affect the dauer molt and fat accumulation (<link linkend="bib62">Gerisch et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11740945-->; <link linkend="bib64">Gissendanner et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14738886-->; <link linkend="bib11">Arda et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20461074-->).</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE31227#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-40</ulink> is another receptor required for late embryonic morphogenesis, elongation, and proper muscle formation and motility. Accordingly, it is expressed primarily in the pharyngeal, body wall, and sex muscles, but also in a handful of neurons (<link linkend="bib27">Brozova et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16920335-->). Proteomic analysis of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003630;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-40</ulink></emphasis> mutants reveals changes in the level of proteins enriched in muscle function and metabolism (<link linkend="bib181">Pohludka et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18616929-->). Given its phenotypes and expression pattern, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003630;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-40</ulink></emphasis> will likely strongly interact with genes involved in muscle biogenesis, morphogenesis, and attachment, such as the paralyzed at two-fold (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000053;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Pat</ulink>) mutants (<link linkend="bib246">Williamsa and Waterston, 1994</link><!--: PMID 8106547-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-14">
<title>Molting and beyond</title>
<para>Although the molt cycle is apparently an adaptation of the <emphasis>Ecdysoa</emphasis> clade of animals, the study of its circuitry could very well shed light on mammalian circadian rhythms and sleep. As mentioned earlier, components of the molt cycle include those implicated in circadian rhythms in mammals, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39085;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-23</ulink>/ROR and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29325;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-42</ulink><emphasis>/</emphasis>Period, suggesting an ancient origin for these clocks (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link> and <link linkend="figure7">Figure 7</link>). The short C-terminal <emphasis>lin-42a</emphasis> isoform is specifically implicated in molting. It affects the length of lethargus and the molt cycle, the execution of the molt, the expression of molting genes, and seam cell morphology, functionally resembling <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003622;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-23</ulink>/25.</emphasis> Accordingly, <emphasis>lin-42a</emphasis> is expressed cyclically with peaks at the molt, while the longer <emphasis>lin-42bc</emphasis> isoforms, which specifically affect developmental timing, peak during the intermolt (<link linkend="bib99">Jeon et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10550049-->; <link linkend="bib221">Tennessen et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16300753-->; <link linkend="bib157">Monsalve et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 22137474-->). Thus regulatory cascades used in mammalian circadian timers may have been co-opted by the molt cycle, and components identified in either pathway may inform the other. Another interesting aspect of the molt cycle that resembles sleep of mammalian circadian rhythms is lethargus, a quiescent sleep-like state, during which the animal lays down the new cuticle and sheds the old (<link linkend="bib184">Raizen et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18185515-->). A molecular genetic dissection of genes that affect lethargus in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> so far include <emphasis>lin-42a</emphasis>/period, cGMP (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001173;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-4</ulink></emphasis>/protein kinase G), EGF, Notch signaling, and others (<link linkend="bib228">Van Buskirk and Sternberg, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17891142-->; <link linkend="bib184">Raizen et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18185515-->; <link linkend="bib157">Monsalve et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 22137474-->; <link linkend="bib201">Schwarz et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 22192827-->). Study of such molecules may help illuminate related conserved pathways involved in metazoan sleep.</para>
<para>A major unresolved question is whether the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> molt cycle is hormonally regulated. The broad synchronization of events across tissues suggests so, but no hormone has yet been found. Although homologs of DA hormone biosynthetic genes have been implicated in insect ecdysteroid metabolism (<link linkend="bib252">Yoshiyama et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16763204-->; <link linkend="bib78">Guittard et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 20932968-->), the worm genes do not obviously affect molting. Moreover, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> lacks ecdysteroids and the ecdysteroid receptor. Nor have high throughput RNAi screens for molting defects identified obvious steroidogenic enzymes (<link linkend="bib56">Frand et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16122351-->). Nevertheless, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> molting is contingent upon dietary cholesterol, and several genes inferred to be involved in cholesterol transport, including the megalin homolog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003071;class=Gene" role="_blank">lrp-1</ulink></emphasis>, hedgehog-related and patch-related receptors, and the APP homolog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000149;class=Gene" role="_blank">apl-1</ulink>,</emphasis> affect molting (<link linkend="bib251">Yochem et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 9876188-->; <link linkend="bib260">Zugasti et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16204193-->; <link linkend="bib94">Hornsten et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17267616-->; <link linkend="bib242">Wiese et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20862215-->). Intriguingly, various 7-oxysterols reportedly bind mammalian ROR as inverse agonists (<link linkend="bib238">Wang et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 19965867-->); conceivably similar molecules could regulate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39085;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-23</ulink>. Alternately <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> molting may be regulated by other lipids, since mammalian SF-1 binds phospho- and sphingolipids (<link linkend="bib118">Krylova et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15707893-->; <link linkend="bib227">Urs et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17196738-->; <link linkend="bib126">Lee et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21614002-->), and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> reportedly binds to fatty acid-phosphoinositides (<link linkend="bib162">Mullaney et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20889131-->). These could also serve as molting hormones that link fatty acid availability to developmental advance. Clearly identifying molting hormones will remain a major important challenge for the future.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Nuclear receptors as regulators of cell fate and organogenesis</title>
<para>During development, multipotent cells progress through a succession of states to build cell types, organs, tissues, and integrated systems. Cells choose between alternate fates of more restricted potential in response to intrinsic and extrinsic cues. These fate choices often entail integrating inputs from growth and signal transduction pathways that impart positional and temporal information. Signaling inputs also serve to detect, quantify, and relay information about the state of the system, and often work combinatorially to specify fate choice. Ultimately, these converge on a coterie of transcription factors whose transcriptional output determines cell type. As key transcriptional regulators responding to physiologic and environmental input, NRs also function as important modulators of cell fate and organogenesis. Below, we highlight the interactions of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003605;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-6</ulink></emphasis> with various signaling pathways during morphogenesis.</para>
<sect2 id="sec3-1">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink>/SF-1 and wingless signaling</title>
<para>The wingless signaling pathway (<emphasis>Wnt</emphasis>) is used at various points in development to specify asymmetric patterns of division and differentiation. In <emphasis>C. elegans, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> both antagonizes and enhances non-canonical <emphasis>Wnt</emphasis> signaling in the somatic gonad and epidermis, respectively (<link linkend="bib13">Asahina et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16890160-->; <link linkend="bib82">Hajduskova et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19654209-->). During <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> gonadogenesis, two primordial somatic gonadoblasts each give rise to distal and proximal blast cells that organize the bilobed arms of the gonad along the distal-proximal axis. Migratory distal tip cells coordinate outgrowth of the gonad, while proximal gonadal cells give rise to spermatheca and uterine tissues (<link linkend="bib111">Kimble and Hirsh, 1979</link><!--: PMID 478167-->). <emphasis>Wnt</emphasis> signaling components primarily help specify the gonadal distal fate. Reduction of function mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004077;class=Gene" role="_blank">pop-1</ulink></emphasis>/TCF, the &beta;-catenin homologs <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006379;class=Gene" role="_blank">sys-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006943;class=Gene" role="_blank">wrm-1</ulink></emphasis>, and the map kinase homolog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003048;class=Gene" role="_blank">lit-1</ulink></emphasis> result in loss of the distal tip cells, resulting in a stunted gonad and sterility (<link linkend="bib153">Miskowski et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11161562-->; <link linkend="bib210">Siegfried and Kimble, 2002</link><!--: PMID 11807036-->; <link linkend="bib210">Siegfried et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15020416-->). Conversely, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> loss results in a defect in the specification of proximal fate and inappropriate promotion of the distal fate, resulting in improperly formed spermatheca and uterine tissues, excess distal tip cells, and a tumorous germline (<link linkend="bib13">Asahina et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16890160-->). Consistent with antagonistic behavior between <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis>wnt</emphasis> signaling, double mutant combinations result in mutual suppression and more normal gonadal development.</para>
<para>This genetic interaction corresponds to physical and functional interactions of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> with the &beta;&minus;catenin homologs controlling transcriptional events. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26743;class=Protein" role="_blank">WRM-1</ulink> protein inhibits the transcriptional activity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> in cell culture, while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27209;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYS-1</ulink> enhances it (<link linkend="bib13">Asahina et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16890160-->). Moreover, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> inhibits the transcriptional activity of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46967;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27209;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYS-1</ulink> complex. This has led to a model in which <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> in presumptive proximal cells inhibits the activity of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46967;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27209;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYS-1</ulink> complex to suppress distal fates, and works together with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27209;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYS-1</ulink> to promote proximal fates (<link linkend="figure9">Figure 9</link>) (<link linkend="bib13">Asahina et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16890160-->). Conversely, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> in presumptive distal cells is inhibited by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26743;class=Protein" role="_blank">WRM-1</ulink>, where the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46967;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27209;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYS-1</ulink> complex can then specify distal fates. The antagonistic interaction with <emphasis>Wnt</emphasis> signaling appears to be tissue specific, since <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> works synergistically with <emphasis>Wnt</emphasis> signaling to specify asymmetric cell fates in the epidermal T cells (<link linkend="bib82">Hajduskova et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19654209-->). This behavior fits with observations in mammals where SF-1 works in concert with <emphasis>Wnt</emphasis> signaling to regulate target gene expression (<link linkend="bib194">Salisbury et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17244763-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure9" xreflabel="Figure 9">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig9" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 9</phrase>
</textobject> &fig9legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Evidence suggests that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> also physically and functionally interacts with other transcription factors for epidermal phenotypes. These include the homeobox proteins, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05026;class=Protein" role="_blank">CEH-39</ulink>, involved in regulating Pn.p fusion events, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29010;class=Protein" role="_blank">NOB-1</ulink>, involved in specification of posterior regions of the animal (<link linkend="bib34">Chen et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15314147-->), as well as the NR <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27779;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-91</ulink><emphasis>/</emphasis>GCNF (<link linkend="bib240">Ward et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 24348269-->). These observations suggest that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> may serve as a competency factor for other transcription factors in a number of contexts.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-2">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18491;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-67</ulink>/TLL controls cell fate through EGF, FGF, and Notch signaling</title>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18491;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-67</ulink> is an ortholog of the highly conserved TLL/TLX tailess NR. During <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> embryogenesis tailless inhibits segmentation, and promotes terminal fates in the posterior of the embryo (<link linkend="bib77">Gui et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21124006-->). Later in development it regulates neurogenesis and neural stem cell renewal. Similarly, mammalian TLX affects nervous system and visual development, embryonic and adult neural stem maintenance, and prevents glial differentiation. It is thought that TLX/TLL are orphan receptors working principally as transcriptional repressors (<link linkend="bib77">Gui et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21124006-->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in late stage embryos, in epidermal cells including hyp7 and vulval cells, the excretory cell, somatic gonadal cells including the hermaphrodite anchor cell, uterine cells, and the male linker cell, as well as the male tail, and a handful of head neurons. Null mutations result in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000081;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">L1 arrest</ulink> and lethality along with cuticle malformations and bulges, suggesting a role in embryonic morphogenesis (<link linkend="bib64">Gissendanner et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14738886-->; <link linkend="bib231">Verghese et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21718694-->). Additionally, animals exhibit cystic canal defects, which may be another cause of lethality (<link linkend="bib195">Sarin et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19641012-->). RNAi knockdown or partial loss of function in larvae results in egg laying and protruding vulva phenotypes at the gross level (<link linkend="bib64">Gissendanner et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14738886-->; <link linkend="bib231">Verghese et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21718694-->). Detailed examination of egg-laying (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000640;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Egl</ulink>) and protruding vulval (Pvul) defects reveals that they arise from altered fate specification in vulva and somatic gonad, suggesting a coordinate role in late stage aspects of reproductive maturation (<link linkend="bib49">Fernandes and Sternberg, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17465684-->; <link linkend="bib231">Verghese et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21718694-->).</para>
<para>Specific <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> regulatory interactions and phenotypes suggest a complex late larval role in vulval morphogenesis in which the receptor regulates key growth factor signaling pathways. Although vulval cell lineages are grossly normal in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> RNAi treated animals, specific fusion events in primary derived (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink>) vulE and vulF cells are aberrant (<link linkend="bib49">Fernandes and Sternberg, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17465684-->). In vulF cells, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> positively regulates the primary fate marker <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002992;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-3</ulink></emphasis>/EGF and simultaneously inhibits secondary fate markers, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001185;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-17</ulink></emphasis>/FGF and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001193;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-26</ulink>/</emphasis>LRAT. In secondary vulval cell derivatives, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> positively regulates <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006987;class=Gene" role="_blank">zmp-1</ulink>/</emphasis>zinc matrix metalloproteinase in vulA and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003938;class=Gene" role="_blank">pax-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001185;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-17</ulink>/</emphasis>FGF in vulD cells. Thus <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> can activate or repress the same gene (e.g., <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001185;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-17</ulink></emphasis>/FGF) depending on cell type. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in a dynamic pattern during vulval morphogenesis and exhibits complex genetic and regulatory interactions with a number of other transcription factors in these tissues, namely <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003000;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-11</ulink></emphasis>/LIM, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000584;class=Gene" role="_blank">cog-1</ulink></emphasis>/NKX6.1/6.2, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001204;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-38</ulink></emphasis>/PAX2. In particular, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000584;class=Gene" role="_blank">cog-1</ulink></emphasis> appear to have mutually antagonistic inhibitory interactions in this context (<link linkend="bib49">Fernandes and Sternberg, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17465684-->). Further understanding of such interrelationships may give insight into the complex regulatory networks governing organ morphogenesis.</para>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> also functions in uterine morphogenesis, which is closely coordinated with vulval morphogenesis. Again <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in a highly dynamic pattern within various cells of somatic gonad and uterus (<link linkend="bib231">Verghese et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21718694-->). An important insight into <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> function came from the realization that it affects several binary fate decisions governed by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003001;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis>/Notch and its ligand <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002246;class=Gene" role="_blank">lag-2</ulink></emphasis>/delta, including the anchor cell (AC)/ventral uterine (VU) blast cell decision, and the fates of uterine <emphasis>pi</emphasis> and uterine seam junction cell fusions (<link linkend="bib231">Verghese et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21718694-->). Consistent with a role in regulating Notch, expression of both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00274;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>/Notch and its ligand are down in various uterine cell types in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> mutants. Consequently, mutant animals have two AC cells, that is, VU cells are transformed to AC, a phenotype similar to Notch loss of function (<link linkend="bib203">Seydoux and Greenwald, 1989</link><!--: PMID 2736627-->). The AC fate is nevertheless weakly determined, since several AC markers such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006987;class=Gene" role="_blank">zmp-1</ulink></emphasis> are not expressed. Because the AC further induces fates amongst vulva precursor cells, it seems likely that some of the observed vulval defects are a secondary consequence of the AC/VU decision. Interestingly, mammalian tailless regulates neural stem cell cycling, which also is influenced by Notch (<link linkend="bib77">Gui et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21124006-->). Conceivably this regulatory circuitry is conserved throughout evolution.</para>
<para>A related gonadal function of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> lies in the developmental timing of male gonadal morphogenesis (<link linkend="bib107">Kato and Sternberg, 2009</link><!--: PMID 19906858-->). During larval development the male somatic gonadal linker cell (LC) leads a column of proliferating germ cells through stereotyped outgrowth. Shortly after its birth, the LC migrates anteriorly during the L2 stage, dorsally by the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000756;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">L2 molt</ulink>, posteriorly and then ventrally during the L3, and back to the tail tip during L4 (<link linkend="bib111">Kimble and Hirsh, 1979</link><!--: PMID 478167-->). These migrations are subject to both positional guidance cues as well as temporal control. Several transcription factors regulate various segments of the migratory path. In particular, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in the LC and responsible for promoting ventral and posterior migrations during the L4 stage (<link linkend="bib107">Kato and Sternberg, 2009</link><!--: PMID 19906858-->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> RNAi treated animals, these migrations fail, and the LC often remains dorsal. Ventral migration depends on expression of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006776;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-40</ulink></emphasis> and repression of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006745;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-5</ulink></emphasis> guidance receptors, which are respectively attracted to or repelled by ventral netrin cues (<link linkend="bib86">Hedgecock et al., 1990</link><!--: PMID 2310575-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> functions to repress <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006745;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-5</ulink></emphasis> expression in the LC, and activate <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006987;class=Gene" role="_blank">zmp-1</ulink></emphasis> at the same time. The general role of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> seems primarily to affect the temporal aspects of the LC migration program, including the timed polarization of the LC in the L4 stage. Surprisingly, the corresponding migratory cell in hermaphrodites, the distal tip cell, does not express <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis>, nor does it show a phenotype in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> knockdown, suggesting a male specific role. Null mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> also affect late stage migrations of the LC (<link linkend="bib6">Antebi et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9477318-->). It would be of interest to understand the regulatory relationship between <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000908;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis> in this context.</para>
<para>Expression profiling of microdissected male LCs, comparing <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> mutants to wild type, reveals that a remarkable number of genes are expressed within the migrating cell, including a multiplicity of transcription factors, cytoskeletal elements, and ion channels (<link linkend="bib201">Schwarz et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22991463-->). Upon knockdown, several of these genes perturb migration, including <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001953;class=Gene" role="_blank">hlh-8</ulink></emphasis>/Twist homolog, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016162;class=Gene" role="_blank">crh-2</ulink></emphasis>/CREB homolog, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007918;class=Gene" role="_blank">sphk-1</ulink></emphasis>/sphingosine kinase, the conserved transmembrane mechano- and cold sensor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007801;class=Gene" role="_blank">trpa-1</ulink></emphasis>, and tandem pore potassium ion channels. Future exploration of the mechanism underlying the activity of these various genes in the migration program should prove interesting.</para>
<para>Like its vertebrate relatives, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> has a prominent role in the specification of neuronal cell fates. The best-studied case involves the specification of the bilateral <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink>/L neurons, a pair of head chemosensory neurons responsive to soluble attractants. Their fates are first specified by the zinc finger transcription factor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000483;class=Gene" role="_blank">che-1</ulink></emphasis>, which turns on genes specific for ASE function (<link linkend="bib226">Uchida et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12588839-->). Thereafter <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASEL</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink> become asymmetric and functionally distinct, by virtue of an elaborate bi-stable feedback loop that restricts expression of left/right markers (<link linkend="bib103">Johnston and Hobert, 2003</link><!--: PMID 14685240-->; <link linkend="bib196">Sarin et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17717195-->). Among the many players, the <emphasis>nkx6.1/6.2</emphasis> transcription factor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000584;class=Gene" role="_blank">cog-1</ulink></emphasis> specifies the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink> fate, while its downregulation by the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003088;class=Gene" role="_blank">lsy-6</ulink></emphasis> microRNA species the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASEL</ulink> fate.</para>
<para>Notably <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> functions at both steps to specify <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASEL</ulink>/R fate. First, it regulates expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000483;class=Gene" role="_blank">che-1</ulink></emphasis>, thereby functioning in the initial specification of the ASE cell. Second, it regulates asymmetry by promoting the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink> fate and repressing the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASEL</ulink> fate (<link linkend="bib195">Sarin et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19641012-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> facilitates <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink> by direct transcriptional activation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000584;class=Gene" role="_blank">cog-1</ulink></emphasis>. Consequently, mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> often result in the expression of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASEL</ulink> markers in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink> cell, and loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink> markers in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink> (<link linkend="bib195">Sarin et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19641012-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> also regulates the fate of a number of other amphid neurons, including ASK and ASJ but its role in these cells is less well defined. Interestingly, L/R symmetry breaking events in the nervous system deploy Notch signaling at distinct points earlier in embryogenesis (<link linkend="bib36">Cochella and Hobert, 2012</link><!--: PMID 23201143-->). It remains to be seen whether <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003657;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-67</ulink></emphasis> regulates Notch signaling in this context.</para>
<para>A close relative of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18491;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-67</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04670;class=Protein" role="_blank">FAX-1</ulink> is a conserved homolog of the vertebrate PNR implicated in the specification of photoreceptor rods and cones of the retina. Mutations in this receptor lead to night blindness and eye degeneration (<link linkend="bib200">Schorderet and Escher, 2009</link><!--: PMID 19718767-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001400;class=Gene" role="_blank">fax-1</ulink></emphasis> is responsible for axon pathfinding and neurotransmitter expression in the AVK interneurons, and helps specify various terminal interneuron identities in conjunction with the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE48350;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-42</ulink> homeodomain protein (<link linkend="bib161">Much et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10648229-->; <link linkend="bib243">Wightman et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16183052-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-3">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24859;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-6</ulink>/NGF-1 regulates spermatheca organogenesis</title>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24859;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-6</ulink> is a homolog of the highly conserved NOR1/Nurr77/Nurr1 subgroup of receptors. In mammals the three paralogs function in diverse processes including immediate early response, neural development, specification of midbrain dopaminergic neurons, immunity and inflammation, atherogenesis, adrenal steroidogenesis, and glucose and mitochondrial metabolism (<link linkend="bib255">Zhao and Bruemmer, 2010</link><!--: PMID 20631354-->). <emphasis>DHR38</emphasis> is the <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> homolog and functions in molting and metamorphosis, as well as glycogen storage and carbohydrate metabolism (<link linkend="bib192">Ruaud et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21084378-->). These receptors are thought to work in a ligand independent fashion.</para>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003605;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-6</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in a single pair of neurons in the head, possibly the ASI, as well as within dorsal somatic gonadal cells that later give rise to the hermaphrodite spermatheca (<link linkend="bib64">Gissendanner et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14738886-->; <link linkend="bib64">Gissendanner et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18096150-->). Consistent with a role in this organ, mutants have abnormal spermathecal morphogenesis, resulting in an <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000640;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Egl</ulink> phenotype and ovulation defects. Spermathecae lack about half their cells, and are missing the uterine/spermathecal valve, suggesting cell lineage defects arising from various gonadoblasts (<link linkend="bib64">Gissendanner et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18096150-->). Accordingly, various spermathecal markers are misexpressed or down, including <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000584;class=Gene" role="_blank">cog-1</ulink>/nkx6.1</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002694;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-502</ulink>/</emphasis>rho associated kinase. The neuronal function of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003605;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-6</ulink></emphasis> remains unknown, but possible localization in ASI may suggest a role in dauer formation, sensory signal transduction, or endocrine control. Recently <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24859;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-6</ulink> has been shown to physically and functionally interact with c-jun during spermathecal development. (<link linkend="bib63">Gissendanner et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 24178943-->). Moreover, two-hybrid data suggest physical interaction with several components of wingless signaling (<link linkend="bib129">Li et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14704431-->). It would be of interest to investigate the <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> relevance of such interactions in the future, as well as possible interaction with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE03191#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE18491#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-67</ulink>. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003605;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-6</ulink></emphasis> also varies with the molt cycle, but the significance of this is not clear (<link linkend="figure7">Figure 7</link>) (<link linkend="bib12">Asahina et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10971653-->; <link linkend="bib65">Gissendanner and Sluder, 2000</link><!--: PMID 10772806-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Nuclear receptors in nutrient sensing, metabolism, and energy homeostasis</title>
<para>From juvenile stages to adult, animals must sense nutrient levels and modulate growth rates, maturation, and reproductive output accordingly. Nutrient levels must be closely monitored, balanced, and coordinated with biosynthetic and energy demands of the organism. NRs are crucial nutrient sensors involved in detecting key metabolites and coupling their flux to metabolism, energy homeostasis, growth, and reproduction. They play a particularly important role in lipid and carbohydrate metabolism, and function in circuits governing their synthesis, transport, storage, and breakdown. Several <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> receptors are implicated in coupling nutrient levels to growth, and metabolism, including <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003681;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-91</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003652;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-62</ulink>,</emphasis> <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003622;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-23</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis>. Other NRs may more specifically regulate fat and glucose metabolism, including <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003654;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-64</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003659;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-69</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015497;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-76</ulink>,</emphasis> and others. Finally, some NRs, such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003704;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-114</ulink></emphasis>, are also involved in maintaining metabolic balance, and detoxifying endo- and xenobiotics to preserve organismal homeostasis. Below we discuss the role of the various NRs in these circuits.</para>
<sect2 id="sec4-1">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27779;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-91</ulink> regulates blast cell progression in response to nutrients</title>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27779;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-91</ulink> is a homolog of the mammalian GCNF (germ cell nuclear factor), a transcriptional repressor that restricts pluripotency gene expression during stem cell differentiation in embyrogenesis (<link linkend="bib237">Wang and Cooney, 2013</link><!--: PMID 23696363-->). Although little is known about <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003681;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-91</ulink></emphasis> function in the worm, recent studies suggest a connection between nutrient sensing and stem cell quiescence and progression during the L1 diapause (<link linkend="bib106">Kasuga et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23644454-->). When L1 larvae are starved, they arrest development and shut down blast cell division, entering a stress and starvation resistant L1 diapause (<link linkend="bib102">Johnson et al., 1984</link><!--: PMID 6542614-->). A number of loci have been found that inappropriately stimulate L1 progression of blast cells (M mesoblast, P ectoblasts) under nutrient deprivation (<link linkend="bib18">Baugh and Sternberg, 2006</link><!--: PMID 16631585-->; <link linkend="bib58">Fukuyama et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16631584-->), including loss of function of microRNA <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003328;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-235</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib106">Kasuga et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23644454-->). Evidently, one of the targets of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003328;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-235</ulink></emphasis> downregulation during starvation is <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003681;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-91</ulink></emphasis>, which harbors <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003328;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-235</ulink></emphasis> binding sites in its 3&rsquo;UTR. Consistent with a role in this pathway, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003681;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-91</ulink></emphasis> expression is downregulated in the L1 diapause, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003681;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-91</ulink></emphasis> loss alleviates <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003328;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-235</ulink></emphasis> mutant defects, thereby preventing P ectoblast migration, and halting the onset of markers of molting and developmental progression under starvation (<link linkend="bib106">Kasuga et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23644454-->). These studies suggest that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003681;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-91</ulink></emphasis> downregulation is important for blast cell quiescence under nutrient limitation, and conversely, that its upregulation is associated with stem cell progression. Knockdown of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003681;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-91</ulink></emphasis> by RNAi also reportedly gives rise to molting and vulval defects, although it is unclear if these phenotypes are seen in the deletion mutant (<link linkend="bib256">Zhao et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15351708-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-2">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27305;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-62</ulink> regulates dietary restriction mediated longevity</title>
<para>Dietary restriction (DR), a modest reduction of food intake without malnutrition, leads to health benefits and extends the life span of yeast, worms, flies, rodents, and perhaps primates (<link linkend="bib139">Mair and Dillin, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18373439-->; <link linkend="bib143">Mattison et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22932268-->; <link linkend="bib38">Colman et al., 2014</link><!--: PMID 24691430-->). Several paradigms of DR in the worm extend life span, including bacterial dilution (<link linkend="bib112">Klass, 1977</link><!--: PMID 926867-->) and mutation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001133;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib121">Lakowski and Hekimi, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9789046-->), which affects a nicotinic acetylcholine receptor subunit causing worms to ingest less food (<link linkend="bib147">McKay et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15020415-->). Recently, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> HNF4&alpha; related receptor, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27305;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-62</ulink>, has been shown to extend lifespan under DR, providing the first causal evidence of NR control of DR-induced longevity (<link linkend="bib88">Heestand et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23935515-->). Deletion of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003652;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-62</ulink></emphasis> largely abolished the longevity of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001133;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants, and dampened life extension by bacterial dilution at lower nutrient ranges. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003652;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-62</ulink></emphasis> mutants also perturbed DR-induced changes in triglyceride accumulation, fat metabolism, and autophagy. In particular, autophagy&mdash;the turnover of cytosolic and organellar components through engulfment and lysosomal degradation&mdash;is induced under nutrient limitation and has been shown to be required for DR induced longevity (<link linkend="bib84">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18282106-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27305;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-62</ulink> affects autophagy, since mRNA levels of the LC3 homolog, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002980;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-1</ulink></emphasis>, as well as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01849;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGG-1</ulink>::GFP puncta are down in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003652;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-62</ulink></emphasis> mutants under DR. Transcriptome analysis reveals approximately 600 genes regulated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27305;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-62</ulink> under DR, including various kinases, phosphatases, genes involved in lipid transport and metabolism, amine metabolism, and chromatin structure (<link linkend="bib88">Heestand et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23935515-->). These findings raise the possibility that DR mediated longevity could be modulated by a NHR-62-dependent metabolite or ligand, and suggest various biological processes that could contribute to the health and longevity benefits of DR. Notably HNF4&alpha; itself constitutively binds fatty acids and is known to regulate lipid and glucose metabolism (<link linkend="bib71">Gonzalez, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18305369-->), raising the prospect that this NR could influence DR in mammals.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-3">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39085;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-23</ulink> regulates nutrient dependent maturational time</title>
<para>Recently, the molting NR, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39085;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-23</ulink>/ROR, has been tied to nutrient-dependent regulation of life history. Walhout and co-workers found that propagation of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> on an alternative bacterial food source, <emphasis>Comomonas</emphasis>, results in developmental acceleration, reduced brood size, and shortened life span (<link linkend="bib136">MacNeil et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23540701-->). Remarkably, this physiological response is observed even if trace amounts of <emphasis>Comomonas</emphasis> are mixed in with the normal food source, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP50;class=Strain" role="_blank">OP50</ulink>, suggesting a nutrient sensing mechanism. However, these physiologic phenotypes appear independent of major nutrient sensing pathways such as TOR and IIS, and were instead associated with a dampening of gene expression of molt-cycle oscillatory as well as critical nutrient responsive genes such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016943;class=Gene" role="_blank">acdh-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib136">MacNeil et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23540701-->). Transcriptome analysis further suggests that major expression changes could be mediated by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003622;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-23</ulink></emphasis>, although a definitive functional role for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003622;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-23</ulink></emphasis> in regulating these life history traits remains to be seen (<link linkend="bib136">MacNeil et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23540701-->). Additionally, the HNF-4 related NRs, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003609;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-10</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003658;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-68</ulink></emphasis>, also mediate major changes in metabolic gene expression in response to <emphasis>Comomonas</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib241">Watson et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23540702-->). These studies suggest that diet and metabolism are intimately linked with temporal regulation of development and that food quality as well as quantity can affect life history traits.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-4">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SF1;class=Strain" role="_blank">SF1</ulink> and fat metabolism</title>
<para>Interestingly, the molting NR, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink><emphasis>/</emphasis>SF-1, also plays a role in fat metabolism. It was identified in a genetic screen for suppressors of the acyl-coA synthase gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020343;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-3</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib162">Mullaney et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20889131-->). Acyl-CoA synthases condense fatty acids of various lengths with acyl-CoA, and function in &beta;&minus;oxidation and other fat metabolic processes. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020343;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-3</ulink></emphasis> in particular has a preference for working on C18 fatty acids. Loss of function mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020343;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-3</ulink></emphasis> result in increased fatty acid uptake, greater rates of <emphasis>de novo</emphasis> fatty acid synthesis, and accumulation of Nile red and bodipy-labeled fatty acids in large neutral lipid compartments in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestine (<link linkend="bib162">Mullaney et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20889131-->). Surprisingly, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020343;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-3</ulink></emphasis> expression in epidermal seam cells triggers these metabolic effects in the gut, suggesting action at a distance. Suppressors of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020343;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-3</ulink></emphasis> mutant include several other fatty acid metabolic genes, as well as hypomorphic mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib162">Mullaney et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20889131-->). Conversely, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020343;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-3</ulink></emphasis> loss partially suppressed egg-laying and sterility phenotypes of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> hypomorphs, suggesting an antagonistic interaction. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> and its mammalian homologs SF-1 and LRH can accommodate fatty acyl-phosphoinositides in the LBD (<link linkend="bib118">Krylova et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15707893-->; <link linkend="bib227">Urs et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17196738-->; <link linkend="bib162">Mullaney et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20889131-->; <link linkend="bib126">Lee et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21614002-->). It is therefore surmised that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020343;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-3</ulink></emphasis> loss results in a depletion of long chain fatty acid-CoA inhibitory ligands for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink>, with the result that overactive <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> provokes the observed changes in fat metabolism (<link linkend="figure10">Figure 10</link>) (<link linkend="bib162">Mullaney et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20889131-->). Because of mutual suppression, however, it is unclear whether <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003623;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-25</ulink></emphasis> acts upstream or downstream in these pathways. Curiously <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020343;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-3</ulink></emphasis> mutants do not have a reported molting defect, presumably because <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> still retains activity. Other genes implicated in fatty acid synthesis, however, do impact cuticle formation and expression of molting genes<emphasis>,</emphasis> namely <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004076;class=Gene" role="_blank">pod-2</ulink>,</emphasis> encoding acetyl-CoA carboxylase, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009342;class=Gene" role="_blank">fasn-1</ulink>,</emphasis> encoding fatty acid synthase (<link linkend="bib131">Li and Paik, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21524356-->). Conceivably, fatty acid molecules could affect molting by modulating NR activity, or could provide mechanical integrity to the cuticle.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure10" xreflabel="Figure 10">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig10" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 10</phrase>
</textobject> &fig10legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-5">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE12084;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-49</ulink>/PPAR regulates fat metabolism and the nutrient response</title>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE12084;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-49</ulink> has emerged as one of the most important HNF4-like NRs, which coordinates fat metabolism in response to nutrient conditions, and whose responsibilities resemble that of mammalian lipid-sensing NRs, PPAR&alpha; or PPAR&delta;. Among other things, PPAR&alpha; regulates expression of &beta;&minus;oxidation and fatty acid desaturase genes, and manages energy balance in response to starvation (<link linkend="bib229">Van Gilst et al., 2005a</link><!--: PMID 15719061-->; <link linkend="bib230">Van Gilst et al., 2005b</link><!--: PMID 16157872-->).</para>
<para>Consistent with a broad role in coordinating metabolism, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE12084;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-49</ulink> resides in multiple tissues including intestine, hypodermis, body wall muscle, and pharynx (<link linkend="bib229">Van Gilst et al., 2005a</link><!--: PMID 15719061-->). Among genes activated by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> in the fed state are those involved in mitochondrial &beta;&minus;oxidation of fatty acids (<link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>, <link linkend="figure10">Figure 10</link>) (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001150;class=Gene" role="_blank">ech-1</ulink></emphasis> enoyl-CoA-hydratase, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009221;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-2</ulink></emphasis> acyl-CoA synthase, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008629;class=Gene" role="_blank">cpt-5</ulink></emphasis> carnitine palmitoyl transferase) the monodesaturation of fatty acids by &Delta;-9 fatty acid-CoA desaturases (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001397;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis>), and lipid transport (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002260;class=Gene" role="_blank">lbp-8</ulink></emphasis>) (<link linkend="bib229">Van Gilst et al., 2005a</link><!--: PMID 15719061-->; <link linkend="bib230">Van Gilst et al., 2005b</link><!--: PMID 16157872-->). Additionally, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> promotes expression of genes in the glyoxylate cycle (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001564;class=Gene" role="_blank">gei-7</ulink></emphasis>, malate synthase; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015391;class=Gene" role="_blank">sdha-1</ulink></emphasis>, succinate dehydrogenase), which are involved in the conversion of fat to glucose. By contrast <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> represses genes involved in peroxisomal &beta;&minus;oxidation (two acyl-CoA oxidases, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001158;class=Gene" role="_blank">ech-9</ulink></emphasis>) and lipid binding (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002259;class=Gene" role="_blank">lbp-7</ulink>)</emphasis>. It also inhibits expression of genes involved in sphingolipid processing, (acid ceramidase, glycosyl hydrolase, and sphingosine phosphate lyase) and lipid remodeling (a triacylglycerol lipase, an o-acyl transferase, two phospholipases) (<link linkend="bib178">Pathare et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22511885-->). Ligands for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> remain unidentified but are hypothesized to be fatty acids or derivatives.</para>
<para>In support of the notion that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> coordinates fat usage, mutants exhibit lower levels of &beta;-oxidation and oxygen consumption, and accumulate the vital dye Nile red, which stains a lysosomal-like acidic fat compartment (<link linkend="bib178">Pathare et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22511885-->; <link linkend="bib229">Van Gilst et al., 2005a</link><!--: PMID 15719061-->). As a result of a deficiency in &Delta;-9 fatty acid-CoA desaturase activity, they accumulate the saturated fatty acids C16:0 palmitic acid and C18:0 stearic acid (<link linkend="bib229">Van Gilst et al., 2005a</link><!--: PMID 15719061-->). Accordingly, they have reduced C16:1n7 palmitoleic and C18:1n9 oleic monounsaturated fatty acids (MUFAs). Little change is seen in measured polyunsaturated fatty acid (PUFA) levels, although enzymes involved in their production (e.g., <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001393;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001394;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-2</ulink></emphasis>) are also changed in quantitative proteomic experiments (<link linkend="bib57">Fredens et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21874006-->).</para>
<para>The transcriptional response of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> very much depends on nutrient status. Notably, starvation induces a number of genes, some of which show <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> dependence. These include acyl Co-A synthase genes, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009221;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00018269;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-11</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00019978;class=Gene" role="_blank">hacd-1</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001564;class=Gene" role="_blank">gei-7</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib230">Van Gilst et al., 2005b</link><!--: PMID 16157872-->)<emphasis>.</emphasis> Surprisingly, starvation also results in <emphasis>nhr-49(+)</emphasis> dependent suppression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00019644;class=Gene" role="_blank">cpt-4</ulink>,</emphasis> revealing a complex regulation of genes involved in &beta;-oxidation. Proteomic analysis confirms that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> plays a major role in fat metabolism, although its role in peroxisomal &beta;-oxidation may be more important than that in mitochondrial &beta;-oxidation, since many proteins reduced in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> mutants contain a peroxisomal localization signal (<link linkend="bib57">Fredens et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21874006-->). <emphasis>nhr-49(+)</emphasis> may more broadly coordinate nutrient sensing systems since analyses of transcriptome, proteome, and metabolome data also reveals changes in amino acid, protein and xenobiotic metabolism (<link linkend="bib15">Atherton et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18435929-->; <link linkend="bib57">Fredens et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21874006-->; <link linkend="bib178">Pathare et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22511885-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-6">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE12084;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-49</ulink>/PPAR affects life span and the adult reproductive diapause</title>
<para>One of the most striking phenotypes of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> is its effect on life span. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> mutants are dramatically short lived compared to wild type (mean life span 9 days vs. 17 days) (<link linkend="bib229">Van Gilst et al., 2005a</link><!--: PMID 15719061-->). Short life span is ascribed to lower expression of the fatty acid desaturases, and the higher ratios of saturated to unsaturated fatty acids, which can be lipotoxic in higher animals. In fact, several studies suggest an inverse correlation between the accumulation of saturated fat and longevity (<link linkend="bib73">Goudeau et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21423649-->; <link linkend="bib207">Shmookler Reis et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21386131-->), but the molecular basis of this correlation is unknown.</para>
<para>Although <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> has no known role in dauer formation, it plays a critical role in a similar long-lived quiescent state termed the adult reproductive diapause (ARD), in which animals cease reproductive activities under starvation (<link linkend="bib4">Angelo and Van Gilst, 2009</link><!--: PMID 19713489-->). Worms shifted to no food during the L4 stage stop embryo production and trim back germline stem cells through apoptosis or necrosis. A subset of animals retains arrested embryos for a week or so. Even after several weeks of starvation, animals sustain expression of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002246;class=Gene" role="_blank">lag-2</ulink></emphasis> Notch ligand, whose expression in the niche (gonadal distal tip cells) prevents meiotic progression and maintains the germline stem cells. When returned to ample food, animals will reconstitute their germline and other tissues, produce viable progeny, and live a normal life span, revealing protective mechanisms for soma and germline in response to nutrient deprivation, and robust rejuvenation in response to a return to food. Evidently <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> is important for ARD, since fewer mutant animals enter the adult reproductive diapause (<link linkend="bib4">Angelo and Van Gilst, 2009</link><!--: PMID 19713489-->). For those animals that successfully enter ARD, however, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> did not play an obvious role in the recovery of germline stem cells. Presumably <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> promotes ARD by mobilizing metabolic genes important for energy homeostasis, stress, and turnover.</para>
<para>Interestingly, mammalian PPAR&alpha; is also implicated in the response to fasting. PPAR&alpha; transgenic mice massively upregulate expression of the fasting hormone FGF21, which turns on genes involved in hepatic &beta;-oxidation, ketogenesis, and gluconeogenesis (<link linkend="bib182">Potthoff et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22302876-->). Remarkably, FGF21 overexpression has been recently shown to be sufficient to improve insulin sensitivity and extend murine life span (<link linkend="bib254">Zhang et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23066506-->). It does so by suppressing production of hepatic IGF-1, mimicking a state of growth hormone deficiency. Whether similar downstream pathways operate to regulate starvation induced longevity in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> remains to be seen.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-7">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE12084;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-49</ulink>/PPAR transcriptional complexes</title>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE12084;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-49</ulink> works in a number of transcriptional complexes to regulate metabolism. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> acts in conjunction with the co-activator <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007016;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink></emphasis> to impact fatty acid metabolism (<link linkend="figure10">Figure 10</link>). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007016;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink></emphasis> was found in yeast two-hybrid screens with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> as bait, and encodes a homolog of the mediator subunit 15, a multisubunit complex that functions as a transcriptional coregulator (<link linkend="bib219">Taubert et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16651656-->). Consistent with the idea that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007016;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> act together, both gene products are found in the intestine, the major metabolic and endocrine organ in the worm. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007016;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink></emphasis> loss of function results in a failure to accumulate <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis>-dependent fasting induced genes, including <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001564;class=Gene" role="_blank">gei-7</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009221;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00018269;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-11</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00019978;class=Gene" role="_blank">hacd-1</ulink></emphasis>, as well as reduced expression of genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001397;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002260;class=Gene" role="_blank">lbp-8</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008629;class=Gene" role="_blank">cpt-5</ulink></emphasis> in the fed state. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007016;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink></emphasis> mutants have perturbed fatty acid composition, increased saturated FA, reduced MUFAs and PUFAs, and are short lived. In fact, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007016;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink></emphasis> plays a broad role in the fatty acid/fasting response since it is required for regulation of additional genes, such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001394;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016943;class=Gene" role="_blank">acdh-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015894;class=Gene" role="_blank">acdh-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001158;class=Gene" role="_blank">ech-9</ulink>, F08A8.2-4</emphasis> acyl-CoA-oxidase and others, which are relatively unaffected by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis>. Accordingly <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007016;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink></emphasis> physically interacts with a number of other NRs as well as the SREBP homolog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004735;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib250">Yang et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16799563-->; <link linkend="bib11">Arda et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20461074-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007016;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink></emphasis> also has other <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> independent roles including in PUFA production, as well as oxidative, xenobiotic and heavy metal metabolism (<link linkend="bib219">Taubert et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18454197-->; <link linkend="bib67">Goh et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23957350-->), and affects longevity in a number of contexts (<link linkend="bib220">Taubert et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16651656-->; <link linkend="bib198">Schleit et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 22132200-->; <link linkend="bib144">McCormick et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22081913-->).</para>
<para>In analogy to the mammalian heterodimeric partner RXR, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE12084;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-49</ulink> also complexes directly with various other NRs (<link linkend="figure10">Figure 10</link>). Namely <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> interacts with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003656;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-66</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003612;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-13</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003621;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-22</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003695;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-105</ulink></emphasis>, as measured through yeast two-hybrid interactions and/or GST-pulldowns (<link linkend="bib178">Pathare et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22511885-->). Genetic and biochemical analysis reveals that these NRs execute separable aspects of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> function. For example, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003612;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-13</ulink></emphasis> specifically affect expression of fatty acid desaturase genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001397;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis>. Similar to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis> mutants accumulate saturated fats, have reduced monounsaturated fats, and are somewhat short lived. Although <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003612;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-13</ulink></emphasis> has no discernible change in fatty acid composition, mutants are also short lived. By contrast, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003656;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-66</ulink></emphasis> functions specifically in the repression of genes involved in sphingolipid processing and lipid remodeling, and displays normal lifespan, suggesting that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003656;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-66</ulink></emphasis> may carry out repressive aspects of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> function. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003656;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-66</ulink></emphasis> mutants have reduced &beta;-oxidation, oxygen consumption, and altered mitochondrial morphology (<link linkend="bib178">Pathare et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22511885-->). Altogether, these studies reveal that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> works in a combinatorial fashion in distinct complexes to carry out its diverse functions. It seems plausible that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003639;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> may interact with additional NRs.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-8">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE19488;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-80</ulink>/HNF4 regulates fatty acid desaturation and longevity</title>
<para>Levels of saturated and desaturated fatty acids must be precisely controlled, and importantly, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis> functions in homeostatic circuits that serve to regulate fatty acid desaturation gene expression and balance (<link linkend="bib25">Brock et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16839188-->). As mentioned above, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis> promotes expression of the &Delta;-9 fatty acid desaturases, particularly <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001397;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink>,</emphasis> and to a lesser extent <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink></emphasis>, under well-fed conditions (<link linkend="figure10">Figure 10</link>). Correlatively, mutants accumulate C18:0 stearic acid and have reduced levels of C18:1n9 monounsaturated oleic acid (<link linkend="bib25">Brock et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16839188-->; <link linkend="bib178">Pathare et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22511885-->). Whereas the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001397;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink></emphasis> triple mutant is lethal, single and double mutants are viable due to compensatory upregulation of the remaining intact genes by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis>. For example, when the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink></emphasis> gene is mutated, the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001397;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> genes are substantially upregulated. This upregulation depends largely on <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis>(+): in the absence of the receptor, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> induction is abrogated. As might be predicted, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis> RNAi combined with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink></emphasis> mutation exacerbates the imbalance in fatty acid composition. Moreover, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis>; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink></emphasis> double mutants are synthetically lethal and only survive if provided with exogenous desaturated fatty acids (<link linkend="bib25">Brock et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16839188-->).</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE19488;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-80</ulink> is also required for longevity in response to signals from the reproductive system (<link linkend="bib73">Goudeau et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21423649-->) (<link linkend="figure8">Figure 8</link>). As mentioned above, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> life span is extended considerably by removal of germline stem cells. Germline loss results in induction of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink>::gfp</emphasis> expression in the intestine, and deletion of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis> suppresses the longevity of germlineless <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001609;class=Gene" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants. One of the major transcriptional outputs of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis> is the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink></emphasis>/&Delta;9 desaturase, which is strongly induced in germlineless animals in an <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis>-dependent manner. Accordingly, germlineless animals exhibit elevated levels of C18:1n9 oleic acid, the metabolic product of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44710;class=Protein" role="_blank">FAT-6</ulink> activity. Consistent with an important physiological role, a double knockout of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> desaturases abrogates gonadal longevity, yet long life is restored by supplementation with oleic acid (<link linkend="bib73">Goudeau et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21423649-->). These studies point to the importance of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003670;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis> and fatty acid desaturation in extending life in response to germline signals. Germline removal also results in an upregulation of the lipase <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00019376;class=Gene" role="_blank">lipl-4</ulink></emphasis> via <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO (<link linkend="bib235">Wang et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18988854-->) (<link linkend="figure8">Figure 8</link>). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00019376;class=Gene" role="_blank">lipl-4</ulink></emphasis> overexpression is sufficient to extend life span in gonad-intact animals, while <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00019376;class=Gene" role="_blank">lipl-4</ulink></emphasis> loss abrogates life span extension in germlineless <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001609;class=Gene" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants, presumably due to FA released upon lipolysis. Interestingly <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00019376;class=Gene" role="_blank">lipl-4</ulink></emphasis> overexpression has been shown to induce autophagy, and knockdown of autophagy gene function abrogates longevity (<link linkend="bib123">Lapierre et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21906946-->). Omega-6 polyunsaturated fatty acids stimulate autophagy and longevity, revealing an important connection between fatty acid desaturation, autophagy, and longevity (<link linkend="bib167">O&apos;Rourke et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23392608-->). Conceivably oleic acid, omega-6 PUFAs, or their derivatives could stimulate longevity by altering fatty acid metabolism, directly stimulating autophagy, or working through nuclear receptor signal transduction.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-9">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39696;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-64</ulink>/HNF4 and fat metabolism</title>
<para>Another HNF4-like receptor implicated in fat metabolism is <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39696;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-64</ulink> (<link linkend="bib132">Liang et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20360843-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003654;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-64</ulink></emphasis> was identified in RNAi screens as a suppressor of the reduced Nile red staining and decreased fat storage phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> double mutants. Additionally, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003654;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-64</ulink></emphasis> RNAi partially restores the low triacylglyceride levels, brood size and slow growth rates seen in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> mutants. As in mammals, the sterol regulatory element binding protein homolog, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004735;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink></emphasis> regulates &Delta;-9 desaturase expression, and levels of fatty acid desaturation (<link linkend="bib250">Yang et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16799563-->). Like <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> mutants, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004735;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant animals fail to accumulate TAGs and exhibit slow growth phenotypes; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003654;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-64</ulink></emphasis> RNAi also suppresses these phenotypes (<link linkend="bib132">Liang et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20360843-->). An analysis of FA composition reveals that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003654;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-64</ulink></emphasis> knockdown results in a reduction of saturated fatty acids, and an increase in monomethyl branched-chain fatty acids, which are important signals for cellular growth (<link linkend="bib114">Kniazeva et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15340492-->; <link linkend="bib259">Zhu et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23705068-->). In addition, several fatty acid metabolic genes show dysregulation upon <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003654;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-64</ulink></emphasis> knockdown. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004076;class=Gene" role="_blank">pod-2</ulink></emphasis> fatty acetyl-CoA carboxylase gene is substantially upregulated, revealing that fatty acid synthesis is increased. At the same time, the acyl-CoA-oxidase, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F08A8.4;class=Gene" role="_blank"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008567;class=Gene" role="_blank">F08A8.4</ulink></ulink></emphasis>, is decreased, suggesting that peroxisomal &beta;-oxidation may be down (<link linkend="figure10">Figure 10</link>). Accordingly, RNAi of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F08A8.4;class=Gene" role="_blank"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008567;class=Gene" role="_blank">F08A8.4</ulink></ulink></emphasis> itself suppresses the slow growth phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> double mutants. Taken altogether, these results suggest that <emphasis>nhr-64(+)</emphasis> normally functions to remove fatty acids through oxidation and suppression of synthesis, and to thwart growth signaling. In this view, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003654;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-64</ulink></emphasis> knockdown tempers fatty acid catabolism, and permits a more balanced metabolism in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> double mutants. Alternately, high levels of C18:0 stearic acid seen in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> mutants could overstimulate <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003654;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-64</ulink></emphasis> towards fatty acid catabolism and away from storage. In this view <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003654;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-64</ulink></emphasis> knockdown would decrease these activities. In the future it will be important to actually measure &beta;-oxidation and other metabolic processes directly to interpret these observations.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-10">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37476;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-76</ulink> integrates biogenic amine signaling to mediate lipolysis</title>
<para>The neurally produced biogenic amines, serotonin (5-HT) and octopamine, play an important role in regulating metabolism, feeding and behavior. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> they have been shown to synergistically induce fat loss in the intestine analogous to mammals where serotonin and beta-adrenergic signaling also cooperate (<link linkend="bib165">Noble et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 24120942-->). One of the prominent outputs of 5-HT treatment is the induction the major triacylglycerol lipase 1, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015484;class=Gene" role="_blank">atgl-1</ulink></emphasis>, expressed in the intestine. Interestingly, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015484;class=Gene" role="_blank">atgl-1</ulink></emphasis> expression in this context is dependent on the NR <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37476;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-76</ulink> (<link linkend="figure10">Figure 10</link>) (<link linkend="bib165">Noble et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 24120942-->). Mutation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015484;class=Gene" role="_blank">atgl-1</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015497;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-76</ulink></emphasis> prevents 5-HT-induced fat loss. Evidently this relay is indirect. Serotonin appears to first impinge upon the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003386;class=Gene" role="_blank">mod-1</ulink></emphasis> serotonin-gated Cl-channel within <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=URXR;class=Cell" role="_blank">URXR</ulink>/L neurons, which are exposed to the body cavity and pseudocoelem. Presumably thereafter, unidentified molecules secreted from URX impinge on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37476;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-76</ulink> in the intestine, which promotes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015484;class=Gene" role="_blank">atgl-1</ulink></emphasis> transcription, thus catalyzing FA lipolysis and breakdown. Interestingly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37476;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-76</ulink> bears significant homology to RXR, which works as a heterodimeric partner with multiple nuclear receptors, and binds to retinoic acid derivatives. It will be especially interesting to see whether <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37476;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-76</ulink> is ligand gated and whether it functions similar to RXR.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-11">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32501;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-69</ulink>/HNF4 regulates insulin secretion and dauer formation</title>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32501;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-69</ulink> is one among the HNF4-like receptors that has been recently shown to function in glucose sensing, insulin signaling, dauer formation, and longevity (<link linkend="bib175">Park et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22359515-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32501;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-69</ulink> protein was found associated in pulldown experiments with the R-smad homolog <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06236;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-8</ulink>, a component of TGF-&beta; signaling that functions in dauer formation. Consistent with a role in dauer formation, mutation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003659;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-69</ulink></emphasis> mildly enhances the Daf-c phenotypes of mutants in TGF-&beta; signaling. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003659;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-69</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in the ASI, an important sensory neuron governing dauer formation and longevity. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000904;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-8</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003659;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-69</ulink></emphasis> double mutants synergize for a number of phenotypes indicative of reduced IIS, including increased life span and upregulated <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO target gene expression. Most interestingly, double mutants exhibit decreased neuropeptide secretion, resulting from derepression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001374;class=Gene" role="_blank">exp-2</ulink></emphasis>, an <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32501;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-69</ulink> target gene encoding a conserved potassium channel (<link linkend="bib175">Park et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22359515-->). This ion channel inhibits secretion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25720;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-28</ulink>, an insulin-like peptide expressed in ASI. Conversely, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001374;class=Gene" role="_blank">exp-2</ulink></emphasis> loss of function results in insulin hypersecretion, and short life span. Genetic epistasis experiments suggest that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001374;class=Gene" role="_blank">exp-2</ulink></emphasis> works downstream of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003659;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-69</ulink></emphasis>, but upstream of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000898;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis>/insulin receptor with respect to longevity. Additionally, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003659;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-69</ulink></emphasis> expression in ASI is upregulated by IIS, presumably through positive feedback. Altogether these data suggest a model whereby an NHR-69-DAF-8 complex inhibits <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001374;class=Gene" role="_blank">exp-2</ulink></emphasis> expression, which results in insulin secretion and normal life (<link linkend="figure11">Figure 11</link>). Upon downregulation of these transcription factors, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001374;class=Gene" role="_blank">exp-2</ulink></emphasis> expression is elevated, thereby inhibiting insulin secretion, and leading to dauer formation and long life. Finally <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003659;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-69</ulink></emphasis> overexpression in the ASI neuron leads to a lethargic phenotype that is rescued by exogenous glucose. Thus <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32501;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-69</ulink> behaves much like HNF4&alpha; in regulating glucose metabolism, insulin signaling, and metabolic homeostasis. Mammalian HNF4 and SMAD3 physically interact and evidence suggests conserved crosstalk between the pathways (<link linkend="bib154">Mizutani et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21646355-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure11" xreflabel="Figure 11">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig11" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 11</phrase>
</textobject> &fig11legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-12">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17474;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-31</ulink>/HNF4 controls fluid balance</title>
<para>The HNF4&alpha;-like NR, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17474;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-31</ulink>, has an extraordinarily specific role in tubulogenesis of the worm excretory cell (<link linkend="bib81">Hahn-Windgassen and Van Gilst, 2009</link><!--: PMID 19668342-->), which functions analogously to the kidney tubule mediating ion and water balance in mammals. During larval development a single excretory cell in the head sends out paired tubular processes anteriorly and posteriorly which extend the length of the animal. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003625;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-31</ulink></emphasis> is expressed within the excretory cell, as well as in the intestine and in unidentified tail cells. Deletion of the gene results in early embryonic lethality, presumably due to excretory cell dysfunction. RNAi knockdown of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003625;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-31</ulink></emphasis> late in larval development results in sensitivity to high salt challenge (<link linkend="bib81">Hahn-Windgassen and Van Gilst, 2009</link><!--: PMID 19668342-->). The excretory cell tubules in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003625;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-31</ulink></emphasis> depleted animals harbor large varicosities, which contain a surplus of endoplasmic reticulum, mitochondria, and vacuole-like vesicles, as visualized by electron microscopy, which could be interpreted as regions of unregulated membrane growth or failure to turnover such organelles. Analysis of the transcriptional profile comparing <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003625;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-31</ulink></emphasis> RNAi to wild-type reveals a striking reduction in the expression of 16 subunits of the vacuolar ATPase, a proton pumping ATPase involved in lysosomal function and vesicle trafficking. Notably knockdown of these subunits induces a swelling of tubule varicosities similar to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003625;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-31</ulink></emphasis> knockdown. The promoters of these V-ATPase genes are enriched in a putative binding site for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE17474#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-31</ulink>. Similarly, the mammalian HNF4&alpha; binding site is also enriched in the promoters of genes for the V-ATPase subunits, suggesting a possible related role for this receptor in kidney function.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-13">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35803;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-114</ulink> affects germ cell integrity in response to diet</title>
<para>Organisms in the wild encounter unpredictable food sources with differing levels of nutrients. The somatically expressed HNF4&gamma;-like NR, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35803;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-114</ulink>, affects the survival of germ cells in response to nutrient imbalance (<link linkend="bib74">Gracida and Eckmann, 2013</link><!--: PMID 23499532-->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003704;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-114</ulink></emphasis> deletion mutants, germ cells fail to proliferate normally, rendering the animal sterile. Curiously, this phenotype is observed on an <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> B food source (e.g., <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP50;class=Strain" role="_blank">OP50</ulink>), but not with an <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> K12 food source (e.g., <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HT115;class=Strain" role="_blank">HT115</ulink>). This phenotype could in part be attributed to levels of dietary tryptophan, as supplementation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP50;class=Strain" role="_blank">OP50</ulink> with tryptophan restored fertility. Moreover, rescue depended on live <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> suggesting that tryptophan metabolites produced by the microbiome contribute to the response. An analysis of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35803;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-114</ulink> transcriptome in response to tryptophan revealed changes in various xenobiotic and detoxifying genes. This suggests a role for HNF4&gamma; in buffering tissue damage against dietary or metabolic insults, and a protective role of chemical defense in this response.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-14">
<title>Other NR regulators of metabolism</title>
<para>Several other less well-characterized NRs that affect various aspects of metabolism have emerged from genetic screens. Some have been identified through altered Nile red accumulation (<link linkend="bib14">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12529643-->), which marks a lysosomal-like organelle (<link linkend="bib168">O&apos;Rourke et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19883620-->). Others have been identified through stimulated Raman microscopy to visualize fat levels <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib235">Wang et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21240281-->). The yeast one hybrid approach was used to systematically identify transcriptional regulators of defined sets of metabolic genes (<link linkend="bib11">Arda et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20461074-->), and NRs emerged as an overrepresented transcription factor class, strongly implicating them in metabolic control. A network model of the interactions further revealed that multiple NRs converge on specific target genes, or regulate other NRs. Moreover, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE25078#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-15</ulink> co-activator was shown to interact with at least 12 such receptors. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31110;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-86</ulink> in particular emerged as a hub with 12 NRs converging on its promoter, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31110;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-86</ulink> itself regulating several downstream NRs in this network. Consistent with a role in metabolism RNAi knockdown of these receptors resulted in alterations in Nile red accumulation, and some (e.g., <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00017510;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-178</ulink>,</emphasis> <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003635;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-45</ulink></emphasis>) showed nutrient dependent regulation, as well as predicted regulatory interactions <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib11">Arda et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20461074-->). Clearly this powerful approach should be further exploited to expand the links in such networks, and used to elucidate the underlying physiology.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Future perspectives</title>
<para>Studies in the worm demonstrate that NRs are key regulators of cellular fate, stage structure, metabolism, and longevity that can illuminate fundamental aspect of metazoan biology. Several challenges lie ahead for the future and many questions remains. What is the molecular architecture of the molt cycle and how does this integrate with sleep, metabolism, and developmental timing? What is the interrelationship between developmental timing components and longevity? How are the various NRs integrated into signal transduction pathways controlling cell fate and morphogenesis? What is the nature of metabolic networks and function of NRs in these circuits? What are the transcriptional regulatory networks in which NRs are embedded? What roles might NRs play in other physiologic functions, such as innate immunity, xenobiotic metabolism, behavior, and stress response? Beyond these physiologic questions are nuts and bolts issues of identifying the ligands, direct target genes, and coregulatory molecules that interface with the various NRs. Finally, what are the functional homologs of the diversified <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> NRs? The answers to these questions and many more are bound to yield important insights into evolutionarily conserved facets of metazoan NRs.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Tables 1 and 2</title>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title>Table 1. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> NRs</title>
<tgroup cols="8">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5"/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6"/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7"/>
<colspec colnum="8" colname="col8"/>
<thead>
<row valign="bottom" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Ce receptor</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Expression</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Function</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Regulated Genes</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Dm receptor</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Function</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Hs/Mm receptor</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Function</emphasis></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">neurons, intestine, hypodermis, vulva, pharynx, muscle, somatic gonad</entry>
<entry align="center">dauer formation, developmental timing, fat metabolism, longevity regulated by dafachronic acid ligands</entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003335;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-241</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003312;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-84</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003048;class=Gene" role="_blank">lit-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003026;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-41</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00018572;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-42</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003014;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-28</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015547;class=Gene" role="_blank">ain-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003598;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhl-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008549;class=Gene" role="_blank">din-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000366;class=Gene" role="_blank">cbp-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000899;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00022200;class=Gene" role="_blank">fard-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00010471;class=Gene" role="_blank">cdr-6</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">DHR96</entry>
<entry align="center">cholesterol, TAG, xenobiotic metabolism, binds cholesterol</entry>
<entry align="center">FXR/ NR1H3</entry>
<entry align="center">cholesterol, fat, bile acid metabolism</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33928;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-8</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">intestine</entry>
<entry align="center">dauer formation, fat metabolism, cholesterol metabolism, xenobiotic metabolism</entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007536;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-36</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001397;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006925;class=Gene" role="_blank">vit-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006926;class=Gene" role="_blank">vit-2</ulink>,</emphasis> lipases, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001239;class=Gene" role="_blank">elo-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001394;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry align="center">LXR&alpha;/ NR1H2, LXR&beta;/ NR1H1</entry>
<entry align="center">glucose, cholesterol, fat, bile acid metabolism, neural development, immune function, skin barrier function and protection</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry align="center">PXR/ NR1I2, CAR/ NR1I3</entry>
<entry align="center">xenobiotic and bile acid metabolism</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry align="center">VDR/NR11</entry>
<entry align="center">bone development and homeostasis, phosphate and calcium homeostasis, cellular differentiation</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43454;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-55</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">motor-neurons</entry>
<entry align="center">regulates remodeling of VD motoneuron synapses</entry>
<entry align="center">represses <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001824;class=Gene" role="_blank">hbl-1</ulink>, Irx-1</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">Seven Up</entry>
<entry align="center">neurogenesis, cardiac development</entry>
<entry align="center">COUP-TF1/ NR2F1 COUP-TF2/ NR2F2</entry>
<entry align="center">cardiovascular development, angiogenesis, neural development, pituitary and reproductive function, metabolism</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03191;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">intestine, hypodermis, vulva, pharyngeal and rectal epithelial cells, somatic gonad, germline</entry>
<entry align="center">molting, epidermal differentiation, developmental timing, fat metabolism</entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000149;class=Gene" role="_blank">apl-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000039;class=Gene" role="_blank">acn-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015646;class=Gene" role="_blank">mlt-10</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003553;class=Gene" role="_blank">nas-37</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">FTZ-F1</entry>
<entry align="center">early embryonic patterning and larval molting and metamorphosis</entry>
<entry align="center">SF-1/ NR5A1</entry>
<entry align="center">regulates sexual development &amp; development of steroidogenic tissues</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry align="center">LRH/ NR5A2</entry>
<entry align="center">cholesterol, bile acid, glucose and fatty acid metabolism, inflammation, pluripotentency of embryonic stem cells, gut stem cell renewal</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39085;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-23</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">hypodermis, pharynx, germline, intestine?</entry>
<entry align="center">molting, maturational timing in response to nutrients</entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001064;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-2</ulink>,3,5,7,8,10, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006947;class=Gene" role="_blank">wrt-1</ulink>,2, 3, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021095;class=Gene" role="_blank">mlt-8</ulink>,9,10, 11, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004210;class=Gene" role="_blank">ptc-3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000039;class=Gene" role="_blank">acn-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003650;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-60</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">DHR3</entry>
<entry align="center">ecdysone inducible, prepupal to pupal transition, metamorphosis, adult differentiation, molting, cellular growth</entry>
<entry align="center">ROR&alpha;/ NR1F1, ROR&beta;/ NR1F2, ROR&gamma;/ NR1F3</entry>
<entry align="center">circadian clock, cerebellum development, immunity, lipid, cholesterol, and glucose metabolism</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37054;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-41</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">seam cell, hyodermis, rectal epithelium, excretory cell, head neuron, excretory cell, vulva</entry>
<entry align="center">Dauer molt</entry>
<entry/>
<entry align="center">DHR78</entry>
<entry align="center">ecdysone inducible, larval growth, metamorphosis, tracheal development</entry>
<entry align="center">TR2/ NR2C1, TR4/ NR2C2</entry>
<entry align="center">recruits corepressors, role in early embryonic development, and stem cells</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26023;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-85</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">excretory duct cell, hypodermis, rectal epithelium, vulva</entry>
<entry align="center">dauer molt, egg laying,</entry>
<entry/>
<entry align="center">E75</entry>
<entry align="center">ecdysone inducible, covalently modified by heme and regulated by nitic oxide which regulates association with DHR3</entry>
<entry align="center">REV-ERB&alpha;/ NR1D1, REV-ERB&beta; NR1D2</entry>
<entry align="center">heme binding, circadian rhythm, adipogenesis</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03323;class=Protein" role="_blank">SEX-1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">ubiquitous nuclear staining in embryo</entry>
<entry align="center">sex determination</entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006962;class=Gene" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">E78</entry>
<entry align="center">Ecdysone inducible, Repressed by DHR3</entry>
<entry align="center">&ldquo;</entry>
<entry align="center">&ldquo;</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18491;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-67</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">head neurons, hypodermis, vulva, somatic gonad, excretory cell</entry>
<entry align="center">epidermal morphogenesis, vulval and gonadal development, neuronal cell fate, excretory canal morphogenesis</entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001185;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-17</ulink></emphasis>/FGF, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001193;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-26</ulink>/</emphasis> LRAT, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003938;class=Gene" role="_blank">pax-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006987;class=Gene" role="_blank">zmp-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006745;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-5</ulink></emphasis> (LC), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001953;class=Gene" role="_blank">hlh-8</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016162;class=Gene" role="_blank">crh-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007918;class=Gene" role="_blank">sphk-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007801;class=Gene" role="_blank">trpa-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000483;class=Gene" role="_blank">che-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">Tailless</entry>
<entry align="center">inhibits embryonic segmentation, promotes terminal fates, neurogenesis</entry>
<entry align="center">TLX/ NR2E1, TLL/ NR2E2</entry>
<entry align="center">nervous system and visual development, embryonic and adult neural stem maintenance</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04670;class=Protein" role="_blank">FAX-1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">AVK, various interneurons</entry>
<entry align="center">interneuron fate specification, axon outgrowth, neurotransmitter expression</entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001444;class=Gene" role="_blank">flp-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003878;class=Gene" role="_blank">opt-3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003563;class=Gene" role="_blank">ncs-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">DHR51</entry>
<entry align="center">mushroom body development, wing expansion fertility</entry>
<entry align="center">PNR/ NR2E3</entry>
<entry align="center">photoreceptor rods and cones</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24859;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-6</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">ASI, spermatheca</entry>
<entry align="center">spermathecal organogenesis</entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000584;class=Gene" role="_blank">cog-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002694;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-502</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">DHR38</entry>
<entry align="center">molting and metamorphosis, glycogen storage, carbohydrate metabolism</entry>
<entry align="center">Nurr77/NR4A1, Nurr1/NR4A2, NOR1/NR4A3</entry>
<entry align="center">immediate early response, neural development, specification of midbrain dopaminergic neurons, immunity and inflammation, atherogenesis, adrenal steroidogenesis, and glucose and mitochondrial metabolism</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27779;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-91</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">neurons, seam cells, vulva, excretory cell, spermatheca,</entry>
<entry align="center">regulates stem blast cell quiescence and progression in response to nutrients</entry>
<entry/>
<entry align="center">DHR4</entry>
<entry align="center">controls the timing of ecdysone pulses and larval maturation, through negative feedback</entry>
<entry align="center">GCNF/NR6A1</entry>
<entry align="center">transcriptional repressor required for vertebrate stem cell differentiation, embryogenesis and neural differentiation</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<table id="table2" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title>Table 2. Spotlight on functionally characterized HNF4-related receptors.</title>
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<thead>
<row valign="bottom" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Receptor</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Tissue Expression</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Function</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Regulated genes</emphasis></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27305;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-62</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">neurons, intestine, hypodermis, pharynx, spermatheca, excretory cell</entry>
<entry align="left">Promotes: dietary restriction mediated longevity</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015894;class=Gene" role="_blank">acdh-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002260;class=Gene" role="_blank">lbp-8</ulink>, vit-1-6 <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000666;class=Gene" role="_blank">col-91</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001769;class=Gene" role="_blank">gst-21</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002980;class=Gene" role="_blank">lgg-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE12084;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-49</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">neurons, intestine, hypodermis, pharynx, body muscle</entry>
<entry align="left">Promotes: FA &beta; oxidation, FA desaturation, transport, adult reproductive diapause</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001397;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002260;class=Gene" role="_blank">lbp-8</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008629;class=Gene" role="_blank">cpt-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001150;class=Gene" role="_blank">ech-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009221;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00018269;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-11</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00019978;class=Gene" role="_blank">hacd-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001564;class=Gene" role="_blank">gei-7</ulink>, acid ceramidase F27e5.1, glycosylhydrolase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E02H9.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">E02H9.5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004981;class=Gene" role="_blank">spl</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B0222.4;class=Gene" role="_blank">B0222.4</ulink>, ZK167.2 lipase, W02b12.1 lipase</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE19488;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-80</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">neurons, intestine, head muscle</entry>
<entry align="left">Promotes: FA desaturation, &beta;&ndash;oxidation, gonadal longevity</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001397;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008629;class=Gene" role="_blank">cpt-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001150;class=Gene" role="_blank">ech-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49570;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-66</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">neurons in anterior, lateral, retrovesicular ganglia, seam cells, hypodermis, intestine, body muscle</entry>
<entry align="left">&beta; oxidation, Represses: sphingolipid metabolism</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis>ceramidase F27e5.1, glycosylhydrolase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E02H9.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">E02H9.5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004981;class=Gene" role="_blank">spl</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B0222.4;class=Gene" role="_blank">B0222.4</ulink>, ZK167.2 lipase, W02b12.1 lipase</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26221;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-13</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">ubiquitous, intestine</entry>
<entry align="left">Promotes: FA desaturation</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001397;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001398;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001399;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001150;class=Gene" role="_blank">ech-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37476;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-76</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">body muscle, vulval muscle, excretory gland, intestine, seam cell</entry>
<entry align="left">Promotes: FA lipolysis in response to serotonin</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015484;class=Gene" role="_blank">atgl-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39696;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-64</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">neurons of head, tail, ventral cord, intestine, hypodermis, pharynx</entry>
<entry align="left">Promotes: FA synthesis Prevents: FA catabolism</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis>acs-1-5, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001243;class=Gene" role="_blank">elo-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001244;class=Gene" role="_blank">elo-6</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004076;class=Gene" role="_blank">pod-2</ulink></emphasis> up, acyl-CoA-oxidase <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F08A8.4;class=Gene" role="_blank"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008567;class=Gene" role="_blank">F08A8.4</ulink></ulink> down</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32501;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-69</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">ASI neuron, tail neurons, Intestine, hypodermis, pharynx, uterus, rectal epithelium</entry>
<entry align="left">Glucose metabolism, TGF-&beta; &amp; Insulin signaling, Dauer formation, longevity</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001374;class=Gene" role="_blank">exp-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17474;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-31</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">excretory cell</entry>
<entry align="left">Excretory cell morphogenesis, Fluid Balance</entry>
<entry align="left">Vacuolar-ATPase subunits</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35803;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-114</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">intestine, hypodermis, germline</entry>
<entry align="left">Germ Cell Maintenance, Xenobiotic Metabolism</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis>cyp-35b2, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00019472;class=Gene" role="_blank">cyp-35B1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00014047;class=Gene" role="_blank">clec-61</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009526;class=Gene" role="_blank">clec-169</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001756;class=Gene" role="_blank">gst-8</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007082;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-10</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015449;class=Gene" role="_blank">ugt-63</ulink></emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31982;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-40</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">neurons, body muscle, pharynx, vulval muscle, rectal glands, P ectoblasts</entry>
<entry align="left">Embryonic muscle development</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003514;class=Gene" role="_blank">myo-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000063;class=Gene" role="_blank">act-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006787;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE16151;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-60</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=VC4;class=Cell" role="_blank">VC4</ulink> -, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=VC5;class=Cell" role="_blank"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=VC5;class=Clone" role="_blank">VC5</ulink></ulink> -motor-neurons, pharyngeal gland, seam cell, male ray <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UV1;class=Strain" role="_blank">UV1</ulink> uterine cells</entry>
<entry align="left">Ventral closure, embryogenesis</entry>
<entry/>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>I thank Dan Magner and Philipp J&auml;ger for critical reading of the manuscript and Moritz Horn, Christoph Geisen, and Sabine Finkler for help with figures. I thank the Max Planck Society, Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (SFB635 &amp; Cluster of Excellence: Cellular Stress Responses in Aging-Associated Diseases (CECAD)), and the German Bundesministerium f&uuml;r Bildung und Forschung (Gerontosys; Sybacol) for their generous support.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>References</title>
<para/>
&nucreceptor_ref;
</sect1>
</article>