<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 2. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> works at the convergence of the dauer pathways to mediate the choice between dauer arrest versus reproductive development.</title>
<para>In favorable environments, cues detected by ciliated sensory neurons (grey lines) result in the activation of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42996;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink>/guanylyl cyclase and the production of cGMP. Thereafter, TGF-&beta; and insulin-like peptides are secreted from neurons and impinge on their respective signal transduction pathways in target tissues and steroidogenic cells. Inactivation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO by the PI3K/AKT kinase cascade as well as inhibition of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30963;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-3</ulink>/Smad-DAF-5/Ski complexes by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06236;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-8</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45907;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-14</ulink> SMADs stimulate biosynthesis of the DAs from cholesterol. Liganded <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> assembles putative co-activator complexes, bypassing dauer, and allowing L3 and later programs.</para>
</formalpara>
<simpara>In unfavorable environments, cues detected by ciliated sensory neurons result in the inactivation of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42996;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink>/guanylyl cyclase and decreased synthesis of cGMP. Consequently, production of TGF-&beta; and Insulin-like peptides is suppressed, as are their respective signal transduction pathways in target tissues. Activation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>/FOXO as well <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30963;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-3</ulink>/Smad and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18985;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-5</ulink>/Ski complexes inhibit production of the DAs. Unliganded <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> together with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45296;class=Protein" role="_blank">DIN-1</ulink> form a co-repressor complex, promoting the dauer diapause, and preventing reproductive programs.</simpara>
</caption>
