<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'strongyloides.2_fig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'strongyloides.2_fig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'strongyloides.2_fig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'strongyloides.2_fig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'strongyloides.2_fig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'strongyloides.2_fig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'strongyloides.2_fig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'strongyloides.2_fig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'strongyloides.2_fig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'strongyloides.2_fig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'strongyloides.2_fig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'strongyloides.2_fig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY strongyloides.2_ref SYSTEM 'strongyloides.2_ref.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="strongyloides.2_body">
<articleinfo>
<title>The biology of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides spp.</emphasis><footnote><para>Edited by Marie-Anne F&eacute;lix, Robin B. Gasser, and David Bird Last revised September 20, 2013. Published July 16, 2015. This chapter should be cited as: Viney M.E., Lok J.B. The biology of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides spp.</emphasis> (July 16, 2015), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.141.2, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2015 Mark E. Viney and James B. Lok. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para></footnote></title>
<author><othername>Mark E. Viney<superscript>1</superscript><remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:Mark.Viney@bristol.ac.uk">Mark.Viney@bristol.ac.uk</ulink></para></footnote></remark> and James B. Lok<superscript>2</superscript></othername>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>1</superscript>School of Biological Sciences, University of Bristol, Bristol, BS8 1TQ, UK</orgname></affiliation>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>2</superscript>Department of Pathobiology, School of Veterinary Medicine, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA 19104-6008, USA</orgname></affiliation></author></articleinfo>
<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> is a genus of parasitic nematodes that, unusually, has a free-living adult generation. Here we introduce the biology of this genus, especially the fascinating but complex life-cycle, together with an overview of the taxonomy, morphology, genetics, and genomics of this genus.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title><emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> is a genus of parasitic nematodes</title>
<para><emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> is a genus containing some 50 species of obligate gastrointestinal parasites of vertebrates (<link linkend="bib79">Speare, 1989</link>). <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> infects mammals, birds, reptiles and amphibians. Where investigated, most species appear to be able to infect one, or at most a very few, host species. Indeed, in many cases the specific designation may have been attributed largely by the host species in which the parasite was found. This degree of host-species specificity is not unusual among animal parasitic nematodes.</para>
<para>For most nematodes that parasitise the vertebrate gastrointestinal tract, male and female worms live in the host gut and the females lay eggs that pass out of the host in faeces. Depending on the species, these eggs, or infective larvae that develop from them, are eaten (eggs or larvae) or penetrate host skin (larvae) to achieve transmission to a new host. There is then often a period of larval migration within the new host before new adults establish in the gut. <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> follows this basic plan, but with significant differences. Female-only adult worms form the parasitic stages of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis>. In addition, there is a dioecious adult generation that occurs outside of the host (<link linkend="bib75">Schad, 1989</link>). This free-living adult generation is almost unique among nematode parasites of vertebrates. Originally the parasitic and free-living adult generations of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> were described as distinct species of <emphasis role="italic">Anguillula</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib10">Bavay, 1876</link>; <link linkend="bib11">Bavay, 1877</link>) until they were discovered to be separate stages of one life-cycle when they were brought together as <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib35">Grassi, 1879</link>).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title><emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> infection of humans</title>
<para>Two species of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> infect humans, <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">S. fuelleborni</emphasis>. <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> has a cosmopolitan distribution in tropical and subtropical regions (<link linkend="bib75">Schad, 1989</link>). <emphasis role="italic">S. fuelleborni</emphasis> occurs in African primates where infection can be shared with humans (<link linkend="bib70">Pampiglione and Ricciardi, 1972</link>; <link linkend="bib43">Hira and Patel, 1980</link><!-- PMID: 7394891-->). <emphasis role="italic">S. fuelleborni kellyi</emphasis> occurs exclusively in humans in New Guinea (<link linkend="bib5">Ashford and Barnish 1989</link><!-- PMID: 15463651-->; <link linkend="bib6">Ashford et al., 1992</link><!-- PMID: 15463651-->). It is estimated that some 100-200 million individuals are infected worldwide with <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis>, however these infections can be difficult to detect, so these may be underestimates (<link linkend="bib20">Crompton, 1987</link>; <link linkend="bib1">Albonico et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID: 10050275-->; <link linkend="bib73">Requena-Mendez et al., 2013</link><!-- PMID: 23350004-->). For comparison, global human infection with the gastro-intestinal nematodes <emphasis role="italic">Ascaris lumbricoides, Trichuris trichiura,</emphasis> and hookworms (<emphasis role="italic">Ancylostoma duodenale</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Necator americanus</emphasis>) are 1.4, 1.0, and 1.4 billion, respectively (<link linkend="bib1">Albonico et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID: 10050275-->).</para>
<para>In normal, healthy individuals infection with <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> causes rather little overt pathology (<link linkend="bib30">Genta and Caymmi Gomes, 1989</link>; <link linkend="bib36">Grove, 1989a</link>), but may compromise an individual&apos;s nutritional status (<link linkend="bib81">Stephenson et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID: 11386688-->). However, <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> infection in immunocompromised individuals (particularly following the administration of steroids, for example following transplant surgery) can result in disseminated strongyloidiasis, in which worms, particularly larvae, move beyond the confines of the gut into other organs (<link linkend="bib36">Grove 1989a</link>; <link linkend="bib15">Buonfrate et al., 2013</link><!-- PMID: 23394259-->) (see <link linkend="sec5">Section 5</link>). This is fatal unless anti-<emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> therapy is given. <emphasis role="italic">S. fuelleborni kellyi</emphasis> is also the aetiological agent of swollen baby (or belly) syndrome in New Guinea, in which neo-natal infants acquire overwhelming intestinal infections that can also disseminate (<link linkend="bib5">Ashford and Barnish, 1989</link><!-- PMID: 15463651-->). This is also fatal in the absence of anti-<emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> therapy.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title><emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> in the wild</title>
<para><emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> is a relatively common infection of wild and domestic animals. Although it is difficult to generalise, the prevalence (i.e., the proportion of a population that is infected) of <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> infections of humans is often up to 5% in endemic areas with this typically concentrated in younger individuals (which is common for many soil transmitted helminths), with the occasional occurrence of higher prevalence. In a study of rats in the UK the prevalence of <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> was 62% (<link linkend="bib26">Fisher and Viney, 1998</link><!-- PMID: 9608730-->). The relative difficulty of detection of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> infections affects the accuracy of reported estimates of prevalence (<link linkend="bib73">Requena-Mendez et al., 2013</link><!-- PMID: 23350004-->).</para>
<para><emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> infections can be detected by examination of host faeces for <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> eggs or larvae, or by examination of the small intestine of a host for parasitic females.</para>
<para><emphasis role="italic">Faeces.</emphasis> In freshly isolated faeces direct examination of a thick smear will reveal eggs and/or L1 stages. The eggs are ellipsoid, 40&ndash;85 &mu;m in length, with a thin wall containing a larva (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). This morphology identifies the eggs as <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis>; the presence of larvae in fresh faeces is also diagnostic of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> infection. The stage (eggs or larvae) present in faeces is a species-specific character (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). In this way, for example, <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">S. fuelleborni</emphasis> infections can be differentiated by the presence of larvae or eggs, respectively.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Faeces can be sampled by collection of fresh faeces from the ground, by collection directly from the rectum (of large domestic animals) or, for humans, from volunteered stool samples. Direct examination of faeces can diagnose relatively high intensity (i.e., a large number of worms per host) <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> infections. For lower intensity infections larvae can be collected from a greater faecal mass by the use of a Baermann funnel (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strongyloides/strongyloides.html"><emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides stercoralis</emphasis>: a model for translational research on parasitic nematode biology</ulink>) or by nematode egg concentration techniques on formalin preserved stool samples (<link linkend="bib73">Requena-Mendez et al., 2013</link><!-- PMID: 23350004-->). Faecal samples can also be grown in faecal cultures from which infective L3s can be obtained (see <link linkend="sec8">Section 8</link>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strongyloides/strongyloides.html"><emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides stercoralis</emphasis>: a model for translational research on parasitic nematode biology</ulink>). The infective L3 morphology (see <link linkend="sec4">Section 4</link>) will identify <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> larvae.</para>
<para>It is important to examine fresh faeces for two reasons (<link linkend="bib5">Ashford and Barnish, 1989</link><!-- PMID: 15463651-->). First, <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> eggs rapidly hatch to release larvae and so examination of fresh faeces allows proper determination of the stage passed in faeces. Second, faeces collected from the ground can be rapidly contaminated by free-living nematodes, making the subsequent identification and collection of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> larvae more difficult.</para>
<para><emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> parasitic females can be observed in the small intestine of infected hosts. This, obviously, requires the sacrifice of the host. <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> parasitic females are, in general, concentrated in the upper half-to-third of the small intestine. Direct microscopical examination can reveal parasitic females or, more usually, the trails of dark eggs left behind the female as she migrates through the intestinal mucosa (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). To do this the intestine is opened longitudinally and the luminal contents removed; easier viewing can be achieved by squashing the open small intestine between two glass plates, which are then examined microscopically (<link linkend="bib105">Wilkes et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID: 15206469-->). Live parasitic females can be obtained by vertically suspending longitudinally opened intestines in media (<link linkend="bib105">Wilkes et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID: 15206469-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Phylogeny, morphology and taxonomy</title>
<para>Nematode phylogenetic reconstruction based on rRNA SSU places <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> (Rhabditida, Strongyloididae) (<link linkend="bib3">Anderson, 2000</link>) in clade IVa, which is a sister clade to plant parasitic and invertebrate parasitic nematodes (clade IVb) (<link linkend="bib13">Blaxter et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID: 9510248-->). <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> (Rhabditida, Rhabditidae) is in clade V together with other parasitic nematodes (order Strongylida). Therefore the taxonomic arrangement of <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> is not consistent with the reconstructed phylogeny. Note the difference between the taxonomic order Strongylida and its superfamily Strongyloidea, which contains Clade V parasites such as the true strongyles of equids, and the family Strongyloididae (order Rhabditida, Clade IVa), which contains <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> spp. Similarities in naming of these divergent taxa are potential sources of great confusion. Furthermore, note that this chapter is about the genus <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis>, but that there is a quite different genus of nematodes, <emphasis role="italic">Strongylus.</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis role="italic">Parastrongyloides</emphasis> is the sister genus to <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib24">Dorris et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID: 12392916-->). <emphasis role="italic">Parastrongyloides</emphasis> has a similar life-cycle to <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> except that there are parasitic males as well as females, and the free-living forms are able to go through multiple, sequential generations outside of the host, apparently indefinitely (see <link linkend="sec5">Section 5</link>) (<link linkend="bib33">Grant et al., 2006a</link><!-- PMID: 16500655-->). <emphasis role="italic">Parastrongyloides</emphasis> was first described from moles but is more widely known from Australasian marsupials (<link linkend="bib62">Morgan, 1928</link>; <link linkend="bib55">Mackerras, 1959</link>).</para>
<para>Molecular phylogenetic analysis of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> has suggested the existence of two clades within the genus (<link linkend="bib24">Dorris et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID: 12392916-->). This analysis has not been able to separate morphologically defined species, including <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">S. fuelleborni.</emphasis></para>
<para>The morphology of the parasitic and free-living phases of the life-cycle differs. The parasitic females for many species are approximately 2 mm in length (some species are larger, up to 5 mm), with blunt-ended tails, and an elongated, straight-sided (filariform) oesophagus, occupying approximately one third of the body length (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>) (<link linkend="bib79">Speare, 1989</link>). The ovary is didelphic and opens at the vulva, which is positioned approximately two thirds along the body length. The free-living adult stages are approximately 1 mm in length, with the female slightly larger than the male (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>). Both sexes have a rhabditiform oesophagus; the free-living female has a didelphic ovary and a vulva at the mid-point of the body (<link linkend="bib79">Speare, 1989</link>). The general structure, organization, and appearance of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> free-living females and <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> hermaphrodites are similar. Infective L3s, the hypothesised analogue of dauer larvae of free-living nematodes (<link linkend="bib44">Hotez et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID: 15463660-->) are, like <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> dauer larvae, radially constricted with a filariform oesophagus approximately half the length of the larva (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>). These larvae have a tripartite pointed tail which, when viewed with a dissecting microscope, appears like a simple fork (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>); these larvae are highly active in liquid following gentle agitation.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 4</phrase>
</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 5</phrase>
</textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
<para>There are a number of characters used for species identification. For the parasitic females these are the disposition of the ovaries (parallel to or spiralled around the intestine); the <emphasis role="italic">en face</emphasis> view of the stoma (<link linkend="bib53">Little, 1966</link><!-- PMID: 5929983-->); the stage passed in host faeces (i.e., eggs, larvae, or eggs and larvae), and more recently, the morphology of the peri-vulval lateral cuticle (<link linkend="bib79">Speare, 1989</link>; <link linkend="bib95">Viney and Ashford, 1990</link><!-- PMID: 2338480-->). Morphometric comparison of body size and the relative position of various structures is also used extensively. The means of recovery of these parasitic stages (e.g., collection from intestine or from faeces following host anthelminthic therapy), as well as the effects of the host immune response on the morphology of <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> parasitic females (e.g., <link linkend="bib48">Kimura et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID: 10466130-->), will reduce the utility of these morphometric approaches.</para>
<para>For the free-living adult males and females morphometrics are also important, as too is the arrangement of the peri-cloacal papillae of the male (<link linkend="bib79">Speare, 1989</link>). The forked tail of the infective L3s is a particularly clear diagnostic character for <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> (see <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>), which allows easy allows differentiation from other nematodes that may contaminate faecal samples.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>The life-cycle</title>
<para>The life-cycle of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> is both complicated and somewhat tricky to understand, but also one part of the fascination of the genus. This description is primarily based on the life-cycle of <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> (a parasite of the rat), which has been extensively studied; some of these details are likely to vary in other species.</para>
<para>Hosts become infected when free-living infective L3s penetrate the skin. Naturally this occurs by the chance coming together of host skin and larvae, though this is facilitated by dispersal and nictation behaviours of the larvae. In the laboratory this comes about by the deliberate application of infective L3s to host skin or by subcutaneous injection (<link linkend="bib90">Tindall and Wilson, 1988</link><!-- PMID: 3405640-->). These larvae migrate through the host body such that from 24 hours post infection (p.i.) they are found in the naso-frontal region of the host from where they are, presumably, swallowed to reach the small intestine (<link linkend="bib90">Tindall and Wilson, 1988</link><!-- PMID: 3405640-->). This naso-frontal route of migration has been most thoroughly determined in <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis>; in other species of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> (and other genera of skin-penetrating nematodes) migration through the lungs is also thought to be important. During this migration they moult via an L4 stage so that there are adult parasitic female worms present in the gut from approximately 4 days p.i., with reproduction commencing shortly thereafter, detected by the presence of eggs and/or larvae in the faeces (<link linkend="bib48">Kimura et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID: 10466130-->).</para>
<para>In the host faeces the eggs hatch to release first-stage larvae (L1) (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>). Larvae are either male or female. Male larvae develop via L2-L4 stages into rhabditiform males. Analogously, female larvae can develop into rhabditiform females. Together, this type of development is known as indirect, sexual, or heterogonic development. The free-living adults mate and the female lays eggs that hatch to release L1s that moult via an L2 into infective filariform L3 stages. All the progeny of the free-living adult generation are female. These infective L3 stages are long lived and can persist in the environment until they encounter a suitable host. Their behaviour is to move away from the host faeces in which they have developed, a behaviour likely to enhance their probability of finding a host. In addition, female L1s that hatch from eggs passed in faeces have an alternative fate, to moult via an L2 into infective L3s. This type of development is known as direct, asexual, or homogonic development. Infective L3s that have developed via the direct or indirect route are, apparently, the same.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig6" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 6</phrase>
</textobject> &fig6legend;</mediaobject>
<para>For most <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> species only one free-living adult generation occurs. However, up to nine (decreasingly fecund) free-living generations have been observed for <emphasis role="italic">S. planiceps</emphasis>, though in the same study <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> had only one free-living adult generation (<link linkend="bib107">Yamada et al., 1991</link><!-- PMID: 1865267-->). <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> therefore differs from its relative <emphasis role="italic">Parastrongyloides</emphasis> which has apparently unlimited successive free-living generations (<link linkend="bib33">Grant et al., 2006a</link><!-- PMID: 16500655-->).</para>
<para>The free-living adult generation of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> (and <emphasis role="italic">Parastrongyloides</emphasis>) is therefore rather similar to the life-cycle of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, that is, L1-L4 stages that develop into free-living adults that mate to produce eggs and L1 progeny. However, the major difference is that the progeny of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> spp. free-living adults develop into infective L3s, the hypothesised analogue of dauer larvae (<link linkend="bib44">Hotez et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID: 15463660-->).</para>
<para><emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> can undergo autoinfection, that is, repeated generations of development in the same host individual. Autoinfection appears to be unique to <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> within the genus (and also essentially unique among other genera of gastrointestinal parasites of vertebrates; only <emphasis role="italic">Enterobius</emphasis> spp. and <emphasis role="italic">Capillaria</emphasis> spp. also have this phenomenon) and largely accounts for it being a serious pathogen of humans. Autoinfection involves accelerated development by larval progeny of parasitic females such that they develop into infective L3s within the gut, which then penetrate directly into the tissues of the primary host. Thus here, the entire life cycle is completed within a host and there are no stages external to the host. Autoinfection may result in dissemination of L3 through many organs and tissues of the host, as well as the establishment of new parasitic females in the gut. In the absence of treatment, subsequent rounds of autoinfection are possible, resulting in fulminant expansion of parasite populations and multi-organ involvement with potentially fatal consequences for the host (<link linkend="bib46">Igra-Siegman et al., 1981</link><!-- PMID: 7025145-->). Groups at risk of such so-called disseminated <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> infections include patients who are immunocompromised as a result of corticosteroid therapy, various neoplasms, or infection with the human T lymphotropic virus-1 (<link linkend="bib16">Carvalho and Da Fonseca Porta, 2004</link><!-- PMID: 15771684-->; <link linkend="bib52">Lim et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID: 15337730-->; <link linkend="bib15">Buofrate et al., 2013</link><!-- PMID: 23394259-->).</para>
<para>A prominent and intriguing subgroup of disseminated strongyloidiasis cases are of former far-east prisoners of war (World War II) who now reside in Europe, Australasia, or North America and present with the disease as much as 50 years after leaving the endemic area. Corticosteroid therapy and/or concurrent cancer treatment are common features of these cases (<link linkend="bib31">Gill and Bell, 1979</link><!-- PMID: 497706-->; <link linkend="bib32">Gill et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID: 15099996-->). The onset of disseminated strongyloidiasis decades after the last possible exposure to the parasite is extremely serious for elderly patients. But, this also makes clear a salient feature of the infection biology of <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis>, namely the capacity to maintain exceedingly chronic infections in hosts. Such hyperchronic infections usually go undiagnosed due to the paucity or absence of larvae in the faeces. Alternative hypotheses for the chronicity of these infections are that either there are dormant larvae in the tissues or senescent non-reproductive female worms in the intestine, with immunosuppression triggering either reactivation of dormant larvae or resumption of egg laying by barren parasitic females. Data from studies conducted over a relatively short time frame (77 days) in experimentally infected dogs favour the latter mechanism involving resumed oviposition by barren female worms (<link linkend="bib56">Mansfield et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID: 9025687-->). The importance of people with chronic asymptomatic strongyloidiasis as a group at risk of disseminated hyperinfection has recently been emphasised (<link linkend="bib18">Caumes and Keystone, 2011</link><!-- PMID: 21366788-->).</para>
<para>Hypobiosis or dormancy of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> L3s may or may not be central to the maintenance of chronic infections, but it is key to another mode of transmission: transmammary transmission. There is evidence of transmammary transmission in <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">S. venezuelensis</emphasis> in rats (<link linkend="bib67">Nolan and Katz, 1981</link>; <link linkend="bib47">Kawanabe et al., 1988</link><!-- PMID: 3205871-->), <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> in dogs (<link linkend="bib78">Shoop et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID: 12099422-->), <emphasis role="italic">S. fuelleborni kellyi</emphasis> in humans (<link linkend="bib6">Ashford et al., 1992</link><!-- PMID: 15463651-->), and several species affecting livestock including <emphasis role="italic">S. ransomi</emphasis> in swine (<link linkend="bib82">Stewart et al., 1976</link><!-- PMID: 1275338-->), <emphasis role="italic">S. westeri</emphasis> in horses (<link linkend="bib54">Lyons, 1994</link>), and <emphasis role="italic">S. papillosus</emphasis> in ruminants (<link linkend="bib60">Moncol and Grice, 1974</link>). Infective L3s transmitted by the transmammary route presumably arrest their development and migration in the mammary glands, and then re-activate at lactation. Transmammary transmission also occurs in other parasitic nematodes that have a phase of within-host tissue migration during their life cycles, including ascarid roundworms and hookworms (<link linkend="bib85">Stone and Smith, 1973</link><!-- PMID: 4598107-->; <link linkend="bib77">Shoop and Corkum, 1987</link><!-- PMID: 3572644-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Sex determination and genetics of the life-cycle</title>
<para>Sex determination in <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> is an XX/X0, female/male system. XX parasitic females produce XX female and X0 male larvae (<link linkend="bib42">Harvey and Viney, 2001</link><!-- PMID: 11514444-->). It is not known whether this system of sex determination relies on the ratio of X chromosomes to autosomes, as occurs in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, or whether it relies simply on the absolute number of X chromosomes. The male larvae develop into free-living males only. The XX female larvae have an environmentally determined choice, between developing into free living adult females or into infective L3s. These XX infective L3s develop into parasitic females directly. XX free-living females and X0 free-living males mate and produce XX, female-only infective L3 progeny, which can develop into parasitic females (<link linkend="bib42">Harvey and Viney, 2001</link><!-- PMID: 11514444-->). Therefore, as a consequence of some process acting either during male gametogenesis or at fertilisation, all progeny inherit the paternal X chromosome (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>). In <emphasis role="italic">S. papillosus</emphasis> there is a male-specific chromatin diminution event, which functionally generates an XX/XO system in this species too (<link linkend="bib65">Nemetschke et al., 2010a</link><!-- PMID: 20832309-->).</para>
<para>The sex ratio of <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> is highly variable between different isolates, ranging from apparently nearly all female to 20-50 % male and this can change over time (see <link linkend="sec7">Section 7</link>) (<link linkend="bib97">Viney et al., 1992</link><!-- PMID: 1469259-->; <link linkend="bib41">Harvey et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID: 11416909-->). This is in contrast to the generally highly hermaphrodite-biased sex ratio of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> (in the absence of matng with males), which perhaps suggests that the mechanisms that control the sex ratio in these two genera are different (<link linkend="bib42">Harvey and Viney, 2001</link><!-- PMID: 11514444-->).</para>
<para>The parasitic females of <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> reproduce parthenogenetically (<link linkend="bib93">Viney, 1994</link><!-- PMID: 7800419-->). This parthenogenesis is genetically mitotic, as shown by the absence of allelic segregation. Thus, the female progeny of a parasitic female are identical to each and to their mother. Formally, this parthenogenesis may occur either by mitotic parthenogenesis or by types of meiotic parthenogenesis (in which meiosis is modified to restore the diploid state) in which allelic segregation does not occur (<link linkend="bib45">Hughes, 1989</link>). Single parasitic female infections can therefore give rise to isofemale lines (<link linkend="bib97">Viney et al., 1992</link><!-- PMID: 1469259-->). The free-living adult generation of <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">S. papillosus</emphasis> reproduces by conventional sexual reproduction (<link linkend="bib98">Viney et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID: 8108454-->; <link linkend="bib25">Eberhardt et al., 2007</link><!-- PMID: 17324432-->). The maximum life-time fecundity of <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> free-living females is less than 40 (<link linkend="bib27">Gardner et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID: 15489049-->).</para>
<para>There has been extensive cytological investigation of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis>, investigating both sex determination and means of reproduction of the parasitic and free-living adult generations (e.g., <link linkend="bib91">Triantaphyllou and Moncol, 1977</link><!-- PMID: 592051-->; <link linkend="bib2">Albertson et al., 1979</link><!-- PMID: 533664-->). The genetic analysis of <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">S. papillosus</emphasis> and the cytological analyses of many species do not agree. This suggests that the carefully observed and recorded cytology may not reliably reveal the genetics of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis>.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>Controlling the life-cycle</title>
<para>The extent to which indirect (or heterogonic) and direct (or homogonic) development occur in the free-living phases of the <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> life-cycle depends on the sex ratio of the free-living generation and on a range of environmental conditions. Again, these phenomena are most thoroughly understood for <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti.</emphasis> For <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis>, the developmental choice of XX female larvae is affected by environmental conditions. For example, the temperature at which faeces containing developing larvae is held external to the host affects development, such that female larvae preferentially develop into free-living adult females (indirect development) at higher temperatures (<link linkend="bib94">Viney, 1996</link><!-- PMID: 8728983-->). It is probable that many other environmental factors (e.g., food quantity and quality) may have similar effects. There has been extensive investigation of a wide range of factors for a number of species (<link linkend="bib4">Arizono, 1976</link>; <link linkend="bib61">Moncol and Triantaphyllou, 1978</link><!-- PMID: 25317-->; <link linkend="bib58">Minematsu et al., 1989</link><!-- PMID: 2738378-->) (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>). These phenomena have been investigated in the related genus <emphasis role="italic">Parastrongyloides</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib33">Grant et al., 2006a</link><!-- PMID: 16500655-->).</para>
<para>For <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis>, the immune status of the host from which developing larvae are passed also affects the development of the free-living larvae. This occurs in two ways. First, XX female larvae preferentially develop into adult free-living females (indirect development) when passed from hosts mounting an anti-<emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> immune response (<link linkend="bib29">Gemmill et al., 1997</link>; <link linkend="bib41">Harvey et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID: 11416909-->). In addition, the sex ratio of larvae passed from hosts mounting such an immune response becomes more male biased (<link linkend="bib41">Harvey et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID: 11416909-->). The combined effect of the host immune response is therefore that comparatively more free-living adult males and females develop. In <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> infections of humans co-infected with HIV, there is also a relationship between an individual&apos;s immune status and the developmental route of their <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> infection (<link linkend="bib100">Viney et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID: 15551217-->).</para>
<para>There is yet further complexity. XX female larvae are comparatively more sensitive to environmental temperature (measured as their developmental response) when passed from hosts mounting an anti-<emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> response. The effect of the host immune response and its interaction with environmental conditions is that indirect development is favoured by larvae passed from hosts mounting an anti-<emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> immune response (<link linkend="bib41">Harvey et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID: 11416909-->).</para>
<para>There are some interesting implications of this sophisticated control of these developmental choices. Firstly, the mechanism by which an apparently environmental feature (the host immune response) affects the sex ratio of the progeny is not known. It is also not clear how developing larvae measure the host immune response and/or how this measurement is &lsquo;remembered&rsquo; through time, since the host immune response is, presumably, measured within the host, yet the developmental consequences occur later and outside of the host (<link linkend="bib99">Viney, 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib21">Crook and Viney, 2005</link><!-- PMID: 16178360-->).</para>
<para>For <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis>, there is extensive inter-isolate variation in the predominant nature of the development of the free-living generation. For example, isolates of <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> from the UK show an almost 100% homogonic development (<link linkend="bib97">Viney et al., 1992</link><!-- PMID: 1469259-->). Such inter-isolate variation implies that there is extensive variation in the sex ratio of the progeny of the parasitic female generation and/or in the sensitivity of larvae to environmental conditions. The degree of direct and indirect development can be artificially selected (<link linkend="bib94">Viney, 1996</link><!-- PMID: 8728983-->).</para>
<para>The hypothesised homology between the dauer larvae of free-living nematodes and infective L3 stages of parasitic nematodes has been noted before (<link linkend="bib44">Hotez et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID: 15463660-->; <link linkend="bib74">Riddle and Albert, 1997</link>). The homology is particularly attractive with <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis>, because of the similarity between the free-living life-cycle of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> and that of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. This analogy has been investigated. For <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis>, laser ablation of amphidial neurons has identified the two that are necessary to control the female developmental decision. These amphidial neurons were identified by analogy with <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib8">Ashton et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID: 7665730-->; <link linkend="bib7">Ashton and Schad, 1996</link><!-- PMID: 15275212-->; <link linkend="bib9">Ashton et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID: 9714195-->).</para>
<para>The role of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000903;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink></emphasis> in controlling the dauer-formation decision of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib72">Ren et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID: 8910282-->) has promoted investigation of putative homologous genes in parasitic nematodes, including <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis>. However, based on comparison of the life-cycle stage expression pattern, this has not directly supported the parasitic nematode infective L3 vs<emphasis role="italic">.</emphasis> free-living nematode dauer larvae analogy (<link linkend="bib21">Crook et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID: 15664656-->; <link linkend="bib57">Massey et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID: 15907565-->; <link linkend="bib101">Viney et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID: 16139836-->). Insulin-like signalling also influences dauer larval development in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans,</emphasis> and evidence from genetic (<link linkend="bib17">Castelletto et al., 2009</link><!-- PMID: 19360119-->) and pharmacological (<link linkend="bib83">Stoltzfus et al., 2012a</link><!-- PMID: 22701676-->) studies indicates that it may similarly regulate the development of infective larvae in <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis>. In regulating dauer larva development in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, both insulin-like and TGF-&beta;-like (<emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000903;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink></emphasis>) signalling converge on a steroid nuclear hormone (NHR) signalling system involving the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27584;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink> NHR and its steroid ligands the dafachronic acids (<link linkend="bib63">Motola et al., 2006</link><!-- PMID: 16529801-->). Recent findings support a similar NHR-regulated system affecting formation and development of infective larvae in <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib104">Wang et al., 2009</link><!-- PMID: 19497877-->) and <emphasis role="italic">S. papillosus</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib69">Ogawa et al., 2009</link><!-- PMID: 19110431-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>Maintaining the life-cycle</title>
<para><emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> is surprisingly easy to maintain in the laboratory. To grow the free-living generation, faeces (collected from an infected laboratory animal) simply need to be maintained damp and at a slightly elevated temperature. For some host species (carnivores, primates, or anything with particularly smelly faeces) the faecal material should be mixed with wetted activated charcoal. There are many different ways in which the faeces can be cultured, with the &lsquo;sophistication&rsquo; of these different methods simply seeking to allow the larval and adult stages to separate themselves from faecal material. The methods for <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> are given in detail in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strongyloides/strongyloides.html"><emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides stercoralis</emphasis>: a model for translational research on parasitic nematode biology</ulink>. Larvae recovered from faecal cultures can also be maintained on modified NGM agar plates (<link linkend="bib27">Gardner et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID: 15489049-->; <link linkend="bib50">Li et al., 2006</link><!-- PMID: 16500658-->).</para>
<para>Infective L3s recovered from faecal cultures can be used to infect host animals. This can be done &lsquo;naturally&rsquo; by applying larvae to dampened skin or fur (<link linkend="bib90">Tindall and Wilson, 1988</link><!-- PMID: 3405640-->). More routinely, infective L3s can be inoculated subcutaneously by injection (e.g., <link linkend="bib105">Wilkes et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID: 15206469-->). The eggs and larvae of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> passed in faeces are susceptible to desiccation. This has two consequences. First, if infected hosts are maintained in dry conditions, then between-animal transmission within an animal house will not occur. Second, when collecting faeces with which to initiate faecal cultures, either freshly deposited faeces must be collected or cages must be arranged so that faeces collect onto a damp surface.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec9">
<title>The parasitic phase of the life-cycle</title>
<para>The biology of the parasitic phase, principally the parasitic females, is the least well known, largely because of the relative difficulty of working with these stages. The females are embedded in the mucosa of the small intestine, often close to the crypts of Lieberk&uuml;hn (<link linkend="bib23">Dawkins et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID: 6880343-->). The females migrate through the mucosa, leaving trails of eggs (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>) (<link linkend="bib39">Grove et al., 1987</link><!-- PMID: 3429117-->). These eggs then, presumably passively, make their way to the gut lumen, before being passed out of the host in faeces either before and/or shortly after hatching depending on the species. Parasitic females are usually concentrated in the proximal part of the small intestine.</para>
<para>Infected hosts make an anti-<emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> immune response against both larvae migrating from the site of infection to the intestine, and against intestinal parasitic females. The nature of this response differs between these sites and stages of <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib12">Bell et al., 1981</link><!-- PMID: 7318985-->; <link linkend="bib49">Korenaga et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID: 6827449-->). The host immune response has deleterious effects on the parasitic females. Parasitic females become shorter, their fecundity is reduced, and they become more posteriorly positioned in the host intestine as an anti-<emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> immune response develops (<link linkend="bib48">Kimura et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID: 10466130-->; <link linkend="bib105">Wilkes et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID: 15206469-->). These effects either do not occur in immunodeficient hosts (e.g., in nude rats which are athymic and, hence, have no T-cell arm of the immune system) or are reversible if the host is immunosuppressed (<link linkend="bib29">Gemmill et al., 1997</link>; <link linkend="bib102">Viney et al., 2006</link><!-- PMID: 16817996-->). In <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> infections the host immune response brings about density-dependent effects on the survival and reproduction of the parasitic stages (<link linkend="bib71">Paterson and Viney, 2002</link><!-- PMID: 12358425-->), which is ultimately due to a parasite dose-dependent change in the quality of the host immune response (<link linkend="bib14">Bleay et al., 2007</link><!-- PMID: 17597133-->; <link linkend="bib105">Wilkes et al., 2007</link><!-- PMID: 17576363-->).</para>
<para>Ultimately these effects of the host immune response result in most experimental animals losing their infections after a period of time. For <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> in rats, readily detectable patent infections last for approximately a month, though some worms persist for up to about 10 weeks (<link linkend="bib48">Kimura et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID: 10466130-->; <link linkend="bib105">Wilkes et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID: 15206469-->). <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> infections of nude rats last for approximately a year (403 days), with the parasitic females dying of senescence (<link linkend="bib28">Gardner et al., 2006</link><!-- PMID: 16913877-->). The maximum lifespan of <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> free-living females is five days (<link linkend="bib27">Gardner et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID: 15489049-->); thus, the two female forms of the <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> life-cycle have an 80-fold difference in their maximum lifespan (<link linkend="bib28">Gardner et al., 2006</link><!-- PMID: 16913877-->).</para>
<para>A common strategy by which parasitic nematodes enhance their own survival in hosts is to, in some way, immunomodulate their host immune responses. This phenomenon has now also been found for <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> spp. in rodent models (<link linkend="bib64">Negrao-Correa et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID: 12704135-->; <link linkend="bib40">Hartmann et al., 2012</link><!-- PMID: 21723282-->).</para>
<para>For <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis>, host immunosuppression is used both to enhance the longevity and intensity of infection, and to facilitate experimental autoinfection (<link linkend="bib38">Grove et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID: 6642862-->; <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides stercoralis</emphasis>: a model for translational research on parasitic nematode biology).</para>
<para><emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> infections can readily be treated with anthelminthic drugs both therapeutically and experimentally. The drug of choice is thiabendazole, though ivermectin is also effective, especially for disseminated infection (<link linkend="bib36">Grove, 1989b</link>; <link linkend="bib20">Conway et al., 1995</link>; <link linkend="bib92">Turner et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID: 16282302-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec10">
<title>Life-cycle plasticity</title>
<para>A common feature of the life-cycle of parasitic nematodes is that there are phases of the life-cycle in one host species that alternate with phases either outside of a host or in a second (or third) host species. This means that parasitic nematodes live multi-facetted lives. Life-cycle stages that are specific to one host species, or to the external environment, differ by the very fact that they are adapted to these different niches (<link linkend="bib96">Viney and Cable, 2011</link><!-- PMID: 21959167-->; <link linkend="bib103">Viney and Diaz, 2012</link><!-- PMID: 24058831-->). <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> spp. is no different in this respect. However, the genetics of its life-cycle gives an unrivaled opportunity to address questions of the mechanism of these processes. Thus, the parasitic adult female stage is genetically identical to the free-living adult female stage, such that differences between these two stages can be used as a model to understand the basis of parasitism. Such a comparison in this life-cycle is particularly powerful, especially compared to other parasitic nematode life-cycles where, typically, a parasitic phase of the life-cycle consists of adult worms, whereas free-living stages consist of larval stages. Thus, in these settings any comparison of parasitic and free-living stages is also confounded by an adult and larval comparison. The recent interrogation of the <emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides</emphasis> spp. genome (<link linkend="sec11">Section 11</link>), including the construction of a genetic map for <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib66">Nemetschke et al., 2010b</link><!-- PMID: 19887089-->), is now facilitating these analyses (e.g., <link linkend="bib80">Spinner et al., 2012</link><!-- PMID: 22717055-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec11">
<title>Genomics</title>
<para>The genome sequences of <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">S. venezuelensis</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">S. papillosus</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> (and of the relative <emphasis role="italic">Parastrongyloides trichosuri</emphasis>) have been determined. The availability of isofemale lines of some of these species (or other approaches to inbreeding) has been very important in efficiently assembling these genomes. For <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> (for which the genome sequence is most complete and has the best annotation) the genome is 43 Mbp (thus, less than half the size of the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genome) with a high (79%) AT content, predicted to code for approximately 12,000 genes. Large scale transcriptomic approaches with <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> have been used, particularly aimed at discovering genes used in the developmental control of the <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> life-cycle (<link linkend="bib84">Stoltzfus et al., 2012b</link><!-- PMID: 23145190-->).</para>
<para>This genomic work has built on previous expressed sequence tag (EST) analyses of <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis> (free-living L1 and infective L3s) and <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> (free-living L1, L2, mixed free-living adults and infective L3s, parasitic females) (<link linkend="bib59">Mitreva et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID: 14762059-->; <link linkend="bib86">Thompson et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID: 15907559-->). For <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> there has been fairly extensive microarray analysis, comparing different life-cycle stages, different immune environments and differently selected lines (e.g., <link linkend="bib87">Thompson et al., 2006</link><!-- PMID: 16784522-->; <link linkend="bib88">Thompson et al., 2008</link><!-- PMID: 18234359-->; <link linkend="bib89">Thompson et al., 2009</link><!-- PMID: 19056418-->; <link linkend="bib68">O&apos;Meara et al., 2010</link><!-- PMID: 20673765-->).</para>
<para>While determining the genome sequence of these species is a key step, further exploitation of the genome also requires genetic tools. To this end transgenic methods have very recently been developed for <emphasis role="italic">S. stercoralis</emphasis>, and for the related nematode <emphasis role="italic">P. trichosuri</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib34">Grant et al., 2006b</link><!-- PMID: 16500659-->; <link linkend="bib50">Li et al., 2006</link><!-- PMID: 16500658-->; <link linkend="bib51">Li et al., 2011</link><!-- PMID: 21723330-->; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strongyloides/strongyloides.html"><emphasis role="italic">Strongyloides stercoralis</emphasis>: a model for translational research on parasitic nematode biology</ulink>). Chromosomal integration of transgenes by the <emphasis role="italic">piggyBac</emphasis> transposon system has enabled derivation of the first stable, transgene expressing lines of <emphasis role="italic">S. ratti</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib76">Shao et al., 2012</link><!-- PMID: 22912584-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec12">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<para>We would like to thank Simon Harvey, Gerhard Schad and Fiona Thompson for their comments on earlier versions of this chapter, David Tricker with the figures and Matt Berriman, Nancy Holroyd, and Vicky Hunt for access to unpublished genomic sequence. MEV would like to thank MRC, NERC, BBSRC and The Wellcome Trust for financial support. JBL gratefully acknowledges financial support from the US National Institutes of Health (grants AI50688, AI22662 and RR02512) and the Ellison Medical Foundation (ID-IA-0037-02).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec13">
<title>References</title>
<para/>
&strongyloides.2_ref;
</sect1>
</article>