<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'BrockieGlutfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'BrockieGlutfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'BrockieGlutfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'BrockieGlutfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'BrockieGlutfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'BrockieGlutfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'BrockieGlutfig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'BrockieGlutfig4leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY BrockieGlut_Refs SYSTEM 'BrockieGlutrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="BrockieGlut_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title>Ionotropic glutamate receptors: genetics, behavior and electrophysiology<footnote>
		<para>Edited by Erik M. Jorgensen and Joshua M. Kaplan. Last revised April 23, 2005. Published January 19, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Brockie, P. J. and Maricq, A. V. Ionotropic glutamate receptors: genetics, behavior and electrophysiology (January 19, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.61.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 Penelope J. Brockie and Andres V. Maricq. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
		</footnote>
		</title>
        <author>
			<othername>Penelope J. Brockie, Andres V. Maricq
				<remark>
					<footnote>
						<para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:maricq@biology.utah.edu">maricq@biology.utah.edu</ulink></para>
					</footnote>
				</remark>
			</othername>
			<affiliation>
				<address>Department of Biology, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0840 USA</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
				</articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Most rapid excitatory synaptic signaling is mediated by glutamatergic neurotransmission. An important challenge in neurobiology is to understand the molecular architecture of functional glutamatergic synapses. By combining the techniques of genetics, molecular biology and electrophysiology in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">we have the potential to identify and characterize the molecules that contribute to the function of glutamatergic synapses. In</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">both excitatory and inhibitory ionotropic glutamate receptors are linked to neural circuits and behavior. Genetic analysis has identified genes required for receptor expression, trafficking, localization, stabilization and function at synapses. Significantly, novel proteins required for glutamate receptor function have been discovered in the worm. These advances may also lead to a better understanding of glutamatergic signaling in vertebrates.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
<?newpage?>
        <sect1 id="sec1">
            <title>Ionotropic glutamate receptors</title>
            <para>Ionotropic glutamate receptors (iGluRs) are a major class of heteromeric ligand-gated ion channels and mediate the majority of the excitatory neurotransmission in the vertebrate central nervous system (CNS). Following the cloning of the first subunit from rat in 1989 (<link linkend="bib38">Hollmann et al., 1989</link><!--: PMID 2480522-->), a large family of iGluR subunits was discovered. These transmembrane proteins can be crudely classified on the basis of pharmacological specificity as belonging to the N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) class or the non-NMDA class. The molecular cloning of receptor subunits revealed that classes defined by molecular criteria were the same as those defined earlier by pharmacological criteria (<link linkend="bib37">Hollmann and Heinemann, 1994</link><!--: PMID 8210177-->; <link linkend="bib22">Dingledine et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10049997-->).</para>
            <para>Of the eighteen receptor subunits identified in rat, 7 belong to the NMDA class (NR1, NR2A-D, NR3A-B). The remaining subunits are members of the non-NMDA class, which can be further subdivided into those preferentially gated by the drugs <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>-amino-3-hydroxy-5-methyl-4-isoxazole propionic acid (AMPA; GluR1-4/GluRA-D), or kainate (KA; GluR5-7, KA1-2). Two other subunits, <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B4;</symbol>1 and <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B4;</symbol>2, which share high sequence similarity with other iGluR subunits, are termed orphan receptors because there is no evidence that they form functional glutamate-gated receptors. A functional ligand-gated receptor is formed by the heteromeric assembly of four subunits from a single class, e.g., AMPA subunits assemble with other members of the AMPA subfamily (<link linkend="bib46">Laube et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9526012-->; <link linkend="bib54">Mano and Teichberg, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9507977-->; <link linkend="bib73">Rosenmund et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9616121-->).</para>
            <para>At least 10 putative iGluR subunits are expressed in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib5">Brockie et al., 2001a</link><!--: PMID 11222641-->; <link linkend="bib7">Brockie and Maricq, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12904685-->). Members of the non-NMDA class (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> - <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-8;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-8</ulink>) include subunits most similar to either the AMPA or kainate subfamilies. The 2 NMDA subunits, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">NMR-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMR-2</ulink>, belong to the NR1 and NR2A subfamilies, respectively (<xref linkend="figure1" />). The large number of receptor subunits identified in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> suggests that the worm has the potential to express a diverse number of functional iGluRs.</para>
            <para>The amino acid sequence of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> subunits reveals many similarities between <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and vertebrate iGluR subunits (<link linkend="bib5">Brockie et al., 2001a</link><!--: PMID 11222641-->). Regions that encode the extracellular ligand binding domains, S1 and S2, the 4 hydrophobic domains, TM1-TM3 and the pore region, are conserved in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Amino acid residues that influence the properties of vertebrate iGluRs are also present in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> subunits, including the "Q/R" site of non-NMDA receptors (<link linkend="bib75">Seeburg et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9651532-->) and a conserved asparagine (N) residue in NMDA receptors (<link linkend="bib10">Burnashev et al., 1992b</link><!--: PMID 1382314-->) that regulate calcium permeability. The iGluR signature SYTANLAA amino acid sequence at the C-terminus of TM2 is also conserved in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> subunits and appears to be important for receptor gating. A point mutation in this region was identified in an iGluR subunit in the mouse mutant strain called <emphasis>lurcher</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib91">Zuo et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9285588-->). The mutation changed an alanine (A) to threonine (T) in the <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B4;</symbol>2 subunit that appeared to cause the receptor to remain constitutively open. This same A to T mutation, when introduced into the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> subunit in a transgenic <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> strain, causes a dramatic change in locomotion presumably due to increased ion flow through the receptor channel (<link linkend="bib89">Zheng et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10571229-->).</para>
            <para>In addition to the cation selective iGluRs, a small family of glutamate-gated chloride channels (GluCl) has been identified in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. The inhibitory GluCls form channels that are permeant to chloride ions and are sensitive to the anthelmintic drug avermectin (<link linkend="bib18">Cully et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID 7935817-->). The GluCl channels appear unique to invertebrates and members of this family have also been isolated from <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>, and the parasitic nematodes <emphasis>Haemonchus contortus</emphasis>, <emphasis>Ascaris suum</emphasis> and <emphasis>Dirofilaria immitis</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib17">Cully et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8702744-->; <link linkend="bib23">Forrester et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 9920773-->; <link linkend="bib40">Jagannathan et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10551358-->; <link linkend="bib12">Cheeseman et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11378196-->; <link linkend="bib24">Forrester et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11931838-->; <link linkend="bib87">Yates and Wolstenholme, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15313134-->). There are at least 6 genes that encode GluCl subunits in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> - <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glc-1" role="_blank">glc-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glc-2" role="_blank">glc-2</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glc-3" role="_blank">glc-3</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glc-4" role="_blank">glc-4</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=avr-14" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink>/gbr-2</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=avr-15" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib18">Cully et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID 7935817-->; <link linkend="bib20">Dent et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9312045-->; <link linkend="bib84">Vassilatis et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9407104-->; <link linkend="bib47">Laughton et al., 1997a</link><!--: PMID 9409779-->; <link linkend="bib21">Dent et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10716995-->; <link linkend="bib39">Horoszok et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11250875-->). Multiple splice variants are encoded by a subset of these genes (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=avr-14" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=avr-15" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis>; <link linkend="bib20">Dent et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9312045-->; <link linkend="bib84">Vassilatis et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9407104-->; <link linkend="bib47">Laughton et al., 1997a</link><!--: PMID 9409779-->) and the subunit membrane topology places them in the ligand-gated ion channel superfamily (LGICS) that includes the excitatory acetylcholine and serotonin receptors and the inhibitory GABA and glycine receptors (<link linkend="bib63">Ortells and Lunt, 1995</link><!--: PMID 7754520-->).</para>
            <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata width="5in" entityref="fig1" align="center"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        <textobject>
							<phrase>WormBook Ionotropic Glutamate Receptors: Genetics, Behavior and Electrophysiology figure 1</phrase>
					</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="sec2">
            <title>Glutamate-gated chloride channels: distribution and function in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
            <para>The first genes encoding GluCl subunits, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glc-1" role="_blank">glc-1</ulink></emphasis> (GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>1) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glc-2" role="_blank">glc-2</ulink></emphasis> (GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>), were identified in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> by functional expression in <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes (<link linkend="bib18">Cully et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID 7935817-->). GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>1 and GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol> associate in oocytes to form a heteromeric glutamate-gated chloride channel that is also sensitive to the anti-parasitic drug ivermectin, a derivative of avermectin. Although less is known about this unique class of glutamate-gated channels compared to the cationic iGluRs, genetic and electrophysiological analyses have provided some insight into their role in worm behavior (<link linkend="bib86">Yates et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 13678634-->).</para>
            <para>The cellular distribution of a subset of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> GluCl subunits has been described using the reporter molecule GFP. GluCls are expressed in both pharyngeal muscle cells and neurons providing insight into the possible roles of GluCls in worm behavior. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=avr-14" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink></emphasis> (GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>3) is exclusively expressed in the extrapharyngeal nervous system, including motor neurons and the mechanosensory neurons ALM, PLM and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PVD;class=Cell" role="_blank">PVD</ulink> (<link linkend="bib21">Dent et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10716995-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=avr-15" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> (GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>2) is expressed in the extrapharyngeal nervous system and the pm4 (metacorpus) and pm5 (isthmus) pharyngeal muscle cells (<link linkend="bib20">Dent et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9312045-->). Unlike <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=avr-14" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=avr-15" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis>, which are widely expressed, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glc-2" role="_blank">glc-2</ulink></emphasis> (GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>) expression is limited to the pm4 muscle cells (<link linkend="bib48">Laughton et al., 1997b</link><!--: PMID 9192499-->) where it is likely to form functional heteromeric channels with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AVR-15;class=protein" role="_blank">AVR-15</ulink>/GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>2 (<link linkend="bib84">Vassilatis et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9407104-->).</para>
            <para>As the distribution of GluCl subunits suggests, GluCls are involved in pharyngeal pumping, sensory perception and locomotion. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AVR-15;class=protein" role="_blank">AVR-15</ulink>/GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>2 subunit functions to inhibit pharyngeal muscle contractions during pharyngeal pumping (<link linkend="bib20">Dent et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9312045-->; <link linkend="bib65">Pemberton et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11306685-->). The glutamatergic <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M3;class=Cell" role="_blank">M3</ulink> motor neurons primarily synapse onto the pm4 muscle cells (<link linkend="bib1">Albertson and Thomson, 1976</link><!--: PMID 8805-->) and regulate the timing of muscle relaxation during pharyngeal pumping (<link linkend="bib3">Avery, 1993</link><!--: PMID 8440973-->). The M3s generate inhibitory post synaptic potentials (IPSPs) in contracted pharyngeal muscle, which result in muscle relaxation (<link linkend="bib3">Avery, 1993</link><!--: PMID 8440973-->; <link linkend="bib67">Raizen and Avery, 1994</link><!--: PMID 8155316-->). Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=avr-15" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> eliminate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M3;class=Cell" role="_blank">M3</ulink> mediated IPSPs (<link linkend="bib20">Dent et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9312045-->). Interestingly, intracellular recordings from pharyngeal muscle cells revealed that exogenously applied glutamate elicits a chloride-dependent depolarizing current that is dependent on <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=avr-15" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib65">Pemberton et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11306685-->).</para>
            <para>In the extrapharyngeal nervous system, the <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>-type subunits, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AVR-14;class=protein" role="_blank">AVR-14</ulink>/GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>3, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AVR-15;class=protein" role="_blank">AVR-15</ulink>/GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLC-1</ulink>/GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>1, are responsible for sensitivity to ivermectin (<link linkend="bib21">Dent et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10716995-->). In addition to inhibiting pharyngeal pumping, ivermectin reduces mobility due to paralysis of the mid-body region. GluCl channels might also function in opposition to the excitatory iGluR subunits <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">NMR-1</ulink> in the command interneurons to drive forward rather than backward movement. A small glutamate-gated chloride current is evident in the AVA command interneurons in the absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">NMR-1</ulink> mediated cationic currents (<link linkend="bib57">Mellem et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12467596-->); however, the GluCl subunits responsible for this current have not been identified. Conversely, mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=avr-15" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> dramatically reduce the response to anterior body touch in worms in which the AVD command interneurons have been laser ablated (<link linkend="bib49">Lee et al., 1999</link>), suggesting that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AVR-15;class=protein" role="_blank">AVR-15</ulink>/GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>2 might also function to inhibit forward movement in response to mechanical stimuli. Interestingly, mechanical stimulation of the tail slows the rate of pharyngeal pumping in adult worms; and mutations in both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=avr-14" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=avr-15" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> reduce these inhibitory effects (<link linkend="bib43">Keane and Avery, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12750328-->). This suggests a flow of information from the extrapharyngeal nervous system to the pharynx. This idea is supported by the observation that ivermectin inhibits pharyngeal pumping in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=avr-15" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> mutants; however, pumping resumes when the pharynx is dissected out (<link linkend="bib21">Dent et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10716995-->).</para>
         </sect1>
         <sect1 id="sec3">
            <title>Distribution of iGluRs in the nervous system</title>
            <para>By expressing GFP-tagged iGluRs in transgenic worms, we now have a detailed map of the neurons that express iGluRs (<link linkend="bib34">Hart et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7477294-->; <link linkend="bib55">Maricq et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7477293-->; <link linkend="bib5">Brockie et al., 2001a</link><!--: PMID 11222641-->). Given the caveats associated with GFP expression, we know which iGluR subunits are expressed in any given neuron. Six of the subunits, including 4 non-NMDA (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-2" role="_blank">glr-2</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-4" role="_blank">glr-4</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-5" role="_blank">glr-5</ulink></emphasis>) and 2 NMDA (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nmr-1" role="_blank">nmr-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nmr-2" role="_blank">nmr-2</ulink></emphasis>), are expressed in many of the command interneurons - AVA, AVB, AVD, AVE and PVC - which control forward and backward movement (<xref linkend="figure2" />). The distribution of NMDA receptors is almost exclusive to these interneurons. Both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-3" role="_blank">glr-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-6" role="_blank">glr-6</ulink></emphasis> are expressed in a single interneuron pair, the RIA neurons (<xref linkend="figure3" />A-C). Laser ablation studies have placed RIA in the neural circuit that controls thermotaxis (<link linkend="bib58">Mori and Ohshima, 1995</link><!--: PMID 7630402-->). The remaining subunits, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-7" role="_blank">glr-7</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-8" role="_blank">glr-8</ulink></emphasis>, are expressed in partially overlapping sets of neurons in the pharyngeal nervous system (<xref linkend="figure3" />D-I). The distribution of iGluR subunits suggests that iGluRs might be involved in behaviors as diverse as the avoidance of noxious stimuli to the control of pharyngeal activity. To address these possibilities, mutations in a number of the genes encoding iGluR subunits have been generated.</para>
<para>&#x000A0;</para>
                <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata entityref="fig2" width="6.5in" align="center"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            <textobject>
								<phrase>WormBook Ionotropic Glutamate Receptors: Genetics, Behavior and Electrophysiology figure 2</phrase>
							</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
                <mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata entityref="fig3" width="6.5in" align="center"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        <textobject>
							<phrase>WormBook Ionotropic Glutamate Receptors: Genetics, Behavior and Electrophysiology figure 3</phrase>
						</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="sec4">
            <title>Electrophysiological analysis of iGluRs in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
            <para>Until recently, a comprehensive approach to the study of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> nervous system had not been possible due to a lack of electrophysiological techniques to directly study synaptic function. Analysis of synaptic function was facilitated by the "slit worm" preparation first described by Lockery and Goodman (<link linkend="bib50">Lockery and Goodman, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9711611-->). Over the past 5 years, the technique has been applied to the study of muscle cells (<link linkend="bib68">Richmond and Jorgensen, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10461217-->), and extended to the characterization of glutamate-gated currents in identified neurons, including AVA and AVD (<link linkend="bib6">Brockie et al., 2001b</link><!--: PMID 11545720-->; <link linkend="bib57">Mellem et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12467596-->; <link linkend="bib90">Zheng et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14749834-->). <emphasis>In vivo</emphasis> patch-clamp recordings from these neurons reveal robust NMDA and non-NMDA dependent glutamate-gated currents.</para>
            <para>The AVA interneurons are a central component of the withdrawal response to noxious stimuli. The glutamate-gated current in AVA can be divided into two major components, a large and rapid current component that is dependent on the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-2</ulink> non-NMDA subunits (<link linkend="bib57">Mellem et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12467596-->), and a smaller yet longer-lasting current. The fast, GLR-1-dependent current mediates the backing response to nose touch and hyperosmotic stimuli (see &#x0201C;<link linkend="sec5">The Role of iGluRs in Worm Behavior</link>&#x0201D;). The slower current is activated by the agonist NMDA and is abolished by a deletion mutation in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">NMR-1</ulink> subunit (<link linkend="bib6">Brockie et al., 2001b</link><!--: PMID 11545720-->). The kinetic properties of the non-NMDA and NMDA channels are consistent with iGluR currents observed in vertebrate systems. Interestingly, while mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis> appear to completely eliminate the fast glutamate-gated current, in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-2" role="_blank">glr-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants, a small yet rapid current is still present, indicating that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> might form a homomeric receptor or heteromeric receptors with other iGluR subunits (<link linkend="bib57">Mellem et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12467596-->). The different electrophysiological properties of the AVA neurons in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-2" role="_blank">glr-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants parallel the subtle differences in behavior, demonstrating that receptor function can be correlated with neuron excitability and worm behavior.</para>
            <para>NMDA-gated currents recorded from AVA exhibit the voltage dependence that is characteristic of NMDA receptor mediated currents (<link linkend="bib6">Brockie et al., 2001b</link><!--: PMID 11545720-->). The slow kinetics of the NMDA receptor may provide a temporal window during which small currents resulting from multiple, independent sensory inputs are summated to generate a membrane depolarization sufficient to initiate backward movement. The absence of these long-lasting currents appears to be responsible for the reduced frequency of backward movements observed in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nmr-1" role="_blank">nmr-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib6">Brockie et al., 2001b</link><!--: PMID 11545720-->). These results demonstrate the advantage of combining genetic, molecular, behavioral and electrophysiological analyses of nervous system function.</para>
            <para>Electrophysiological analysis of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> neuronal function is still in its infancy. Although it is now straightforward to record ligand-gated and voltage-gated currents from identified neurons, it is much more difficult to study nerve-evoked currents in neurons or endogenous, spontaneous synaptic activity. Two technical hurdles prevent more rapid progress. First, electrical, mechanical or optical techniques need to be developed to selectively activate neural inputs to identified neurons. Some progress has been made. Recently, the receptor potential in touch neurons was analyzed using electrophysiological techniques. Worms avoid mechanical stimulation but habituate to repeated taps. However, the receptor potential in sensory neurons showed no evidence of decay indicating that habituation probably does not occur at the level of the sensory neurons (<link linkend="bib62">O'Hagan et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15580270-->). Continued development of new stimulation techniques and their application to interneurons and motor neurons bodes well for a mechanistic understanding of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> nervous system. The second major hurdle is the lack of a well-developed pharmacology. Specific drugs &#x02014; agonists and antagonists &#x02014; are required to acutely perturb synaptic function. These drugs are slowly being developed and a combination of genetics and pharmacology has led to major advances in our understanding of the neuromuscular junction (<link linkend="bib68">Richmond and Jorgensen, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10461217-->; <link linkend="bib25">Francis et al., 2005</link>).</para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="sec5">
            <title>The role of iGluRs in worm behavior</title>
            <para>The first iGluR subunit to be characterized in the worm was the AMPA-subtype encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis>. Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis> disrupt the backing response to nose touch stimulation (<link linkend="bib34">Hart et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7477294-->; <link linkend="bib55">Maricq et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7477293-->). This defect is a result of faulty glutamatergic neurotransmission between sensory neurons (primarily the ASH polymodal sensory neurons) and the command interneurons that express <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib57">Mellem et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12467596-->). Since the initial characterization of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants, additional behavioral paradigms were developed, which now link <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> to the avoidance of hyperosmotic stimuli (<link linkend="bib57">Mellem et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12467596-->) and the volatile repellent octanol (<link linkend="bib33">Hart et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10066248-->; <link linkend="bib11">Chao et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15492222-->), the "spontaneous" switch from forward to backward movement (<link linkend="bib89">Zheng et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10571229-->; <link linkend="bib6">Brockie et al., 2001b</link><!--: PMID 11545720-->), foraging behavior (<link linkend="bib36">Hills et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14762140-->) and long-term memory (<link linkend="bib72">Rose et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14573539-->; <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>).</para>
            <para>
                <table id="table1" frame='all'>
				<title>Table 1. Phenotype of iGluR mutants</title>
                <tgroup cols='7' align='center' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                <colspec colname='c1' align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname='c2' align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname='c3' align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname='c4' align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname='c5' align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname='c6' align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname='c7' align="left" colwidth="3*"/>
                <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Gene</entry>
                  <entry>Not</entry>
                  <entry>Osm</entry>
                  <entry>Octanol avoidance</entry>
                  <entry>Learning</entry>
                  <entry>Forward movement</entry>
                  <entry align="center">Glutamate- gated current</entry>
                </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                  <entry>+</entry>
                  <entry>++</entry>
                  <entry>Defective</entry>
                  <entry>Defective</entry>
                  <entry>Increased</entry>
                  <entry>Non-NMDA- component absent</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-2" role="_blank">glr-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                  <entry>++</entry>
                  <entry>++</entry>
                  <entry>ND</entry>
                  <entry>ND</entry>
                  <entry>ND</entry>
                  <entry>Non-NMDA- component reduced</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nmr-1" role="_blank">nmr-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                  <entry>++++</entry>
                  <entry>+++</entry>
                  <entry>ND</entry>
                  <entry>ND</entry>
                  <entry>Increased</entry>
                  <entry>NMDA- component absent</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry namest="c1" nameend="c7" align="left">Phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-2" role="_blank">glr-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nmr-1" role="_blank">nmr-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants. + indicates the response to nose touch (Not) or osmotic stimuli (Osm) compared to wild-type where ++++ represents wild-type behavior. ND, not determined.</entry>
                </row>
                </tbody>
                </tgroup>
                </table></para>
           <para>The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-2</ulink> subunit is expressed in many of the neurons that express <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>, including the command interneurons. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-2" role="_blank">glr-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants share the same behavior defects, although some are less severe in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-2" role="_blank">glr-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib57">Mellem et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12467596-->). Interestingly, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-2" role="_blank">glr-2</ulink></emphasis> transcription, but not <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis>, is induced in response to ethanol exposure (<link linkend="bib45">Kwon et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15028283-->); however the behavior of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-2" role="_blank">glr-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants in response to ethanol has not been characterized. The small differences in mutant behaviors are paralleled in the electrophysiological profiles of each mutant (see &#x0201C;<link linkend="sec4">Electrophysiological Analysis of iGluRs in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></link>&#x0201D;). Together, the electrophysiological and behavioral data suggest that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-2</ulink> form functional heteromeric ligand-gated channels required for the avoidance of noxious stimuli.</para>
           <para>The mechanisms that regulate avoidance behaviors associated with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-2</ulink> channels were further elucidated by an analysis of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nmr-1" role="_blank">nmr-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nmr-1" role="_blank">nmr-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nmr-2" role="_blank">nmr-2</ulink></emphasis> are co-expressed in a small subset of neurons, including a majority of the command interneurons (<link linkend="bib5">Brockie et al., 2001a</link><!--: PMID 11222641-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nmr-1" role="_blank">nmr-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants are normal for the nose touch response (<link linkend="bib6">Brockie et al., 2001b</link><!--: PMID 11545720-->); however, a subtle defect in osmotic avoidance was revealed (<link linkend="bib57">Mellem et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12467596-->) using a technique first described by Hilliard, et al. (<link linkend="bib35">Hilliard et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12007416-->). The requirement for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nmr-1" role="_blank">nmr-1</ulink></emphasis> in osmotic avoidance and not the nose touch response might be due to differential release of glutamate from the ASH neurons dependent on the sensory modality. This hypothesis was supported by characterizing the role of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-3" role="_blank">egl-3</ulink></emphasis> in both nose touch and osmotic avoidance (<link linkend="bib42">Kass et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11717360-->; <link linkend="bib57">Mellem et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12467596-->).</para>
            <para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-3" role="_blank">egl-3</ulink></emphasis> encodes an orthologue of the PC2 family of proprotein convertases that process proneuropeptides into active signaling molecules (<link linkend="bib42">Kass et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11717360-->). Genetic and electrophysiological analyses are consistent with the idea that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-3;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-3</ulink> normally downregulates glutamate release; however, proof of this hypothesis will require more direct measures of glutamate release in these mutants (<link linkend="bib57">Mellem et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12467596-->). In one model, glutamate release due to nose touch stimulation is upregulated in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-3" role="_blank">egl-3</ulink></emphasis>; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis> double mutants thus activating NMDA receptors and partially compensating for the loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>. NMDA receptors might also participate in the response to hyperosmotic stimuli, but not nose touch stimuli, due to increased glutamate release compared to that induced by tactile stimulation, although this hypothesis has not been directly tested. In this model, the polymodal ASH sensory neurons might decode tactile and hyperosmotic sensory modalities by differential release of glutamate, which in turn leads to differential activation of non-NMDA and NMDA receptors. In vertebrates, non-NMDA and NMDA receptors appear to be differentially distributed at a subset of glutamatergic synapses with NMDA receptors located at extrasynaptic sites (<link linkend="bib14">Chen and Diamond, 2002</link><!--: PMID 11896156-->). A similar distribution of receptors might also exist in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">NMR-1</ulink> subunits do not appear to co-localize at synapses along the ventral cord (<link linkend="bib6">Brockie et al., 2001b</link><!--: PMID 11545720-->).</para>
            <para>In addition to their role in avoidance behaviors, NMDA receptors in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are also required for sensitivity to the anesthetic nitrous oxide (N<subscript>2</subscript>O) otherwise known as laughing gas (<link linkend="bib60">Nagele et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15159532-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nmr-1" role="_blank">nmr-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants are resistant to the effects of N<subscript>2</subscript>O, whereas <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants are not. Furthermore, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nmr-1" role="_blank">nmr-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants have similar behavioral defects as wild-type worms exposed to N<subscript>2</subscript>O suggesting that N<subscript>2</subscript>O disrupts NMDA receptor function. Thus, NMDA receptors are hypothesized to be the major molecular target of N<subscript>2</subscript>O. This study shed light on the mechanism of action of N<subscript>2</subscript>O and showed that its mechanism of action was distinct from that of volatile anesthetics; the most commonly used general anesthetics.</para>
            <para>In vertebrates, iGluRs play an important role in synaptic plasticity - the cellular mechanism thought to underlie learning and memory formation (<link linkend="bib52">Malenka and Bear, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15450156-->). Although it has proved difficult to assess learning and memory in the worm, there are a number of behavioral paradigms used to characterize these behaviors. A relatively simple learning protocol that tests the habituation response to tap vibrations has linked the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EAT-4;class=protein" role="_blank">EAT-4</ulink> vesicular glutamate transporter and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> subunit to habituation behavior (<link linkend="bib71">Rose et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12075001-->; <link linkend="bib72">Rose et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14573539-->). Furthermore, in certain paradigms worms can learn to associate paired stimuli and this association is dependent on <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib59">Morrison and van der Kooy, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11439453-->).</para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="sec6">
            <title>Mechanisms of iGluR localization, stabilization and function at the synapse</title>
            <para>The subcellular localization of iGluRs can be characterized using functional fusion proteins between iGluRs and GFP (<link linkend="bib70">Rongo et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9753322-->; <link linkend="bib6">Brockie et al., 2001b</link><!--: PMID 11545720-->; <link linkend="bib57">Mellem et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12467596-->). These iGluR::GFP chimeras are distributed in a punctate pattern along the neural processes of transgenic worms. The puncta align with presynaptic markers and are likely to represent postsynaptic sites (<link linkend="bib70">Rongo et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9753322-->). Functional <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>::GFP proteins have proven an extremely valuable reagent for assessing the trafficking, membrane insertion and stabilization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> containing receptors (<xref linkend="figure4" />). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>::GFP was first used to describe the role of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-10;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-10</ulink> PDZ-domain protein in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> localization (<link linkend="bib70">Rongo et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9753322-->). In vertebrates, PDZ-domain proteins interact with select NMDA and non-NMDA subunits and are proposed to be required for the proper localization and stabilization of iGluRs at the postsynaptic density (<link linkend="bib76">Sheng and Sala, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11283303-->; <link linkend="bib4">Bredt and Nicoll, 2003</link><!--: PMID 14556714-->; <link linkend="bib44">Kim and Sheng, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15378037-->). Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-10" role="_blank">lin-10</ulink></emphasis> change the punctate distribution of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>::GFP to one that appears more uniformly distributed. Like <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-10" role="_blank">lin-10</ulink></emphasis> mutants are nose touch defective lending further support to the hypothesis that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-10;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-10</ulink> is required for the synaptic localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> subunits (<link linkend="bib70">Rongo et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9753322-->). Interestingly, the vertebrate homologue, mLin-10, has also been implicated in the regulation of AMPA receptor trafficking and surface expression (<link linkend="bib79">Stricker and Huganir, 2003</link><!--: PMID 14529721-->).</para>
            <para>During development, the density of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>::GFP puncta along the ventral cord remains the same even though the length of the worm increases approximate 10-fold. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-43" role="_blank">unc-43</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes calcium and calmodulin-dependent protein kinase II (CaMKII), has an important role in maintaining the density of receptors at synapses (<link linkend="bib69">Rongo and Kaplan, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10647013-->). An <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-43" role="_blank">unc-43</ulink></emphasis> loss-of-function mutation disrupts trafficking leading to an accumulation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>::GFP in cell bodies and a reduction in the density of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> synapses. Paradoxically, an <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-43" role="_blank">unc-43</ulink></emphasis> gain-of-function mutation, that renders <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-43;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-43</ulink> constitutively active, also reduces the number of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> synapses; however, the mutation does not affect receptor trafficking. Interestingly, the constitutively active form of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-43;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-43</ulink> fails to localize to synaptic clusters in the ventral cord. Together, these findings suggested that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-43;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-43</ulink> activity during development is required to traffick <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> from the cell body for the formation of new synapses. Once the appropriate synaptic density has been established, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-43;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-43</ulink> might function at synapses to maintain <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> density (<link linkend="bib69">Rongo and Kaplan, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10647013-->).</para>
            <mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
                            <imageobject>
                                <imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4.5in" align="center"/>
                            </imageobject>
                        <textobject>
							<phrase>WormBook Ionotropic Glutamate Receptors: Genetics, Behavior and Electrophysiology figure 4</phrase>
						</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
            <para>What other molecules are required to traffick iGluR subunits from the cell body to the appropriate postsynaptic sites? Recently, the unfolded protein response (UPR) has been implicated in the export of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> iGluR subunits from the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) (<link linkend="bib77">Shim et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15317844-->). Various stress factors can lead to the accumulation of improperly folded proteins in the ER, and the UPR is a mechanism used by eukaryotic cells to cope with this accumulation of protein (<link linkend="bib74">Rutkowski and Kaufman, 2004</link><!--: PMID 14729177-->; <link linkend="bib88">Zhang and Kaufman, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15070890-->). Activation of the UPR results in the overall attenuation of protein translation with the exception of increased synthesis of targeted proteins such as ER chaperones. Homologues of key proteins of the vertebrate UPR, IRE1 and XBP1, are found in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Interestingly, mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ire-1" role="_blank">ire-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xbp-1" role="_blank">xbp-1</ulink></emphasis> prevent <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> export from the ER even in the absence of ER stress (<link linkend="bib77">Shim et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15317844-->). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-5;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-5</ulink> iGluR subunits also accumulate in the ER of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ire-1" role="_blank">ire-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xbp-1" role="_blank">xbp-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants suggesting that the UPR is a critical component of the trafficking pathway that ultimately leads to the formation of functional glutamatergic synapses. These findings were supported by recent studies of the GluR1 vertebrate AMPA subunit (<link linkend="bib83">Vandenberghe et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15689545-->). GluR1 is poorly expressed on the surface of transfected COS7 cells and instead accumulates in the ER. Upregulation of the UPR boosts surface expression in transfected cells. These effects are also seen when GluR1 is co-expressed with the transmembrane protein stargazin, the founding member of the transmembrane regulators of AMPA receptor function (TARP) family (<link linkend="bib80">Tomita et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12771129-->). In addition to its role in AMPA receptor trafficking, stargazin also appears to regulate the levels of functional receptors at both the plasma membrane and at synapses (<link linkend="bib13">Chen et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 11140673-->; <link linkend="bib4">Bredt and Nicoll, 2003</link><!--: PMID 14556714-->).</para>
           <para>In addition to the UPR, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> exit from the ER is regulated by a quality control mechanism that prevents defective receptors from reaching the synapse. Thus, mutations in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> that are predicted to disrupt glutamate-binding or modify ion permeability increase retention of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> in the ER (<link linkend="bib30">Grunwald and Kaplan, 2003</link><!--: PMID 14529715-->). Similarly, mutations in the vertebrate GluR6 kainate subunit that dramatically reduce ligand-binding also result in ER retention of the receptor (<link linkend="bib51">Mah et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15745947-->). Interestingly, the mutated subunits can still form multimeric complexes suggesting that ER retention is not due to gross errors in protein folding.</para>
            <para>The Q/R site, located in the pore region of the vertebrate GluR2 subunit, also acts as an ER retention signal (<link linkend="bib29">Greger et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12062022-->). A subset of vertebrate AMPA subunits undergo a process of RNA editing, which substitutes a glutamine (Q) codon for arginine (R) in the pore region (<link linkend="bib78">Sommer et al., 1991</link><!--: PMID 1717158-->; <link linkend="bib75">Seeburg et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9651532-->). Editing is most apparent in vertebrate GluR2 and receptors that contain the edited R form show a decrease in Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> permeability and a change in channel rectification compared to those that contain the unedited Q form (<link linkend="bib9">Burnashev et al., 1992a</link><!--: PMID 1370372-->). The majority of edited GluR2(R) subunits do not form tetrameric complexes and are therefore retained in the ER whereas the unedited GluR2(Q) subunits tetramerize, exit the ER and localize to synapses (<link linkend="bib28">Greger et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14622580-->). Retaining GluR2(R) in the ER therefore controls the abundance of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ca;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ca</ulink><superscript>2+</superscript> permeant AMPA receptors at the synapse, thus regulating synaptic strength. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-2" role="_blank">glr-2</ulink></emphasis> genomic sequence encodes glutamine at the Q/R site (<link linkend="bib5">Brockie et al., 2001a</link><!--: PMID 11222641-->; <link linkend="bib57">Mellem et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12467596-->). When R is substituted for Q, transgenic worms that express the modified GLR-2(R) subunit exhibit, at low penetrance, uncoordination, neuronal degeneration, developmental arrest, and lethality (<link linkend="bib2">Aronoff et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15371514-->) - phenotypes that are not caused by a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-2" role="_blank">glr-2</ulink></emphasis> deletion mutation alone (<link linkend="bib57">Mellem et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12467596-->).</para>
            <para>Synaptic AMPA iGluRs are not static, but rapidly cycle between a subcellular pool and the postsynaptic membrane. This dynamic process is of central importance for synaptic plasticity (<link linkend="bib53">Malinow and Malenka, 2002</link><!--: PMID 12052905-->; <link linkend="bib56">McGee and Bredt, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12593989-->; <link linkend="bib16">Contractor and Heinemann, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15494562-->). Agonist-induced endocytosis of vertebrate AMPA receptors has been linked to the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway (<link linkend="bib15">Colledge et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14642282-->; <link linkend="bib64">Patrick et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14653997-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, iGluR ubiquitination together with clathrin-mediated endocytosis regulate the levels of synaptic iGluRs (<link linkend="bib8">Burbea et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12123612-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-11" role="_blank">unc-11</ulink></emphasis> encodes an orthologue of the AP180 clathrin adaptin protein, mutations in which cause endocytotic defects (<link linkend="bib61">Nonet et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10397769-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-11;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-11</ulink> is required for clathrin-mediated endocytosis of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> containing receptors as mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-11" role="_blank">unc-11</ulink></emphasis> increase the levels of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>::GFP at ventral cord puncta. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>::GFP also accumulates when ubiquitination of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> is blocked, thus ubiquitination leads to clathrin-mediated endocytosis of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> via an <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-11;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-11</ulink> dependent mechanism (<link linkend="bib8">Burbea et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12123612-->).</para>
            <para>The anaphase-promoting complex (APC) also regulates the abundance of iGluRs at both <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib82">van Roessel et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15550251-->) and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib41">Juo and Kaplan, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15556870-->) synapses. The APC is a multisubunit ubiquitin ligase that assembles ubiquitin chains on substrate molecules thereby regulating their degradation (<link linkend="bib32">Harper et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12208841-->; <link linkend="bib66">Peters, 2002</link><!--: PMID 12049731-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mat-1" role="_blank">mat-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mat-2" role="_blank">mat-2</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mat-3" role="_blank">mat-3</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=emb-30" role="_blank">emb-30</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=emb-27" role="_blank">emb-27</ulink></emphasis>, which encode subunits of the APC (<link linkend="bib26">Furuta et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10749938-->; <link linkend="bib27">Golden et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 11134076-->; <link linkend="bib85">Wallenfang and Seydoux, 2000</link><!--: PMID 11081513-->; <link linkend="bib19">Davis et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11861581-->), result in an accumulation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>::GFP at ventral cord puncta (<link linkend="bib41">Juo and Kaplan, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15556870-->). Furthermore, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>::GFP puncta size is also increased in transgenic worms that overexpress the amino terminal of the APC subunit CDH1, which acts as a dominant negative. Interestingly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> does not appear to be a direct target of the APC as mutations in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> that block ubiquitination further increase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>::GFP puncta size in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=emb-27" role="_blank">emb-27</ulink></emphasis> mutants. Instead, the APC might target scaffold proteins that associate with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>. The accumulation of synaptic <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>::GFP that is associated with a decrease in APC activity results in a predicted change in worm behavior. Thus, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mat-1" role="_blank">mat-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib41">Juo and Kaplan, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15556870-->) have locomotion defects similar to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis> gain-of-function mutants (<link linkend="bib89">Zheng et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10571229-->; <link linkend="bib41">Juo and Kaplan, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15556870-->). The data suggest that both ubiquitination of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> and the APC modulate the strength of glutamatergic signaling thus maintaining plasticity of the nervous system.</para>
            <para>Homeostatic regulation of iGluR abundance at synapses, termed synaptic scaling, is a proposed compensatory mechanism by which neurons maintain a normal level of synaptic input (<link linkend="bib81">Turrigiano and Nelson, 2004</link><!--: PMID 14735113-->). Manipulations that chronically suppress synaptic transmission increase AMPA receptor abundance at synapses, whereas those that enhance activity decrease their synaptic abundance. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> a mutation in either <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-2" role="_blank">unc-2</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a voltage-dependent calcium channel, or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=eat-4" role="_blank">eat-4</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a vesicular glutamate transporter, are predicted to suppress activity at glutamatergic synapses. Both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-2" role="_blank">unc-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=eat-4" role="_blank">eat-4</ulink></emphasis> mutants display an increased abundance of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>::GFP at ventral cord puncta that parallels an increase in the amplitude of glutamate-gated currents in response to exogenously applied glutamate (<link linkend="bib31">Grunwald et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14981253-->). The abundance of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink>::GFP at synapses of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-11" role="_blank">unc-11</ulink></emphasis>; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=eat-4" role="_blank">eat-4</ulink></emphasis> double mutants is not further increased, suggesting that synaptic scaling in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> depends on clathrin-mediated endocytosis.</para>
            <para>Once localized to the appropriate postsynaptic sites iGluRs must be competent to gate open in response to ligand binding. Are additional gene products required for iGluR synaptic function? The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SOL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SOL-1</ulink> CUB-domain transmembrane protein was identified in a genetic screen for modifiers of a constitutively active variant of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib90">Zheng et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14749834-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SOL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SOL-1</ulink> is required for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> dependent glutamate-gated currents, and for behaviors that are dependent on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> mediated synaptic transmission. Formally, the loss of glutamate-gated currents in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sol-1" role="_blank">sol-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants can be explained by loss of membrane iGluRs, loss of ligand binding, loss of ligand-dependent gating, or altered desensitization. Although the data suggest that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SOL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SOL-1</ulink> affects the properties of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> receptor gating or desensitization, the mechanism of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SOL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SOL-1</ulink> function still remains to be determined. Nonetheless, the identification of this novel protein in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> shows that iGluRs are not simply stand-alone molecules and suggests that glutamatergic signaling in other organisms may be similarly dependent on SOL-1-like accessory subunits.</para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="sec7">
            <title>Glutamatergic signaling: what questions still remain?</title>
            <para>The analysis of iGluRs in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has progressed rapidly in the past decade. Genetic and electrophysiological studies have provided new insights into how iGluRs contribute to animal behavior and demonstrated that the molecular, pharmacological and electrophysiological properties of iGluRs in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> parallel those of vertebrate receptors. This implies that what we learn from the worm will lead to a better understanding of this receptor family in more complex vertebrate systems.</para>
            <para>Although our knowledge of iGluR signaling has advanced considerably since the first subunit was cloned in 1989 (<link linkend="bib38">Hollmann et al., 1989</link><!--: PMID 2480522-->), many outstanding questions still remain. Current efforts are largely focused on understanding the molecular mechanisms that assemble functional glutamatergic synapses, the regulation of synaptic plasticity, and how plasticity contributes to behavior. Although these questions can be addressed in vertebrate systems, the studies can be difficult due to the immense complexity of the nervous system. An obvious advantage of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is the relative ease of identifying and cloning new and novel genes required for glutamatergic signaling, such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sol-1" role="_blank">sol-1</ulink></emphasis> and components of the UPR and APC (see &#x0201C;<link linkend="sec6">Mechanisms of iGluR Localization, Stabilization and Function at the Synapse</link>&#x0201D;). Identifying new molecules can challenge and refine prevailing models of iGluR mediated synaptic signaling. To this end, ongoing genetic studies in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are expected to make important contributions to the understanding of this important class of neurotransmitter receptors.</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1 id="sec8">
            <title>Acknowledgements</title>
            <para>We thank The Society for Neuroscience for permission to reproduce Figures 1, 2, and 3, and members of the Maricq laboratory for their cited research. A.V.M. is supported by grants from the National Institutes of Health, and the National Science Foundation, and is an independent investigator of the National Alliance for Research on Schizophrenia and Depression.</para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1 id="sec9">
                <title>References</title>
				<para/>
				&BrockieGlut_Refs;</sect1>
</article>