<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 7. CeHD remodelling.</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">(A)</emphasis> Schematized section of an embryo at three different stages, reflecting the evolution of CeHD and FO organisation (green). <emphasis role="bold">(B)</emphasis> Respective distribution of the CeHD protein VAB-10A and of a muscle component to illustrate those changes with time as muscles become active. Scale bar, 10 &mu;m. <emphasis role="bold">(C)</emphasis> Illustration of FO and CeHD maturation. The trapezoidal shape of the epidermal cell represents that the epidermis becomes thinner along the apico-basal axis at the level of CeHDs during this process. First, CeHD components assemble apically and basally and progressively form puncta above muscles (I); muscle twitching induces a mechanotransduction process in the epidermis (II) whereby the proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31478;class=Protein" role="_blank">GIT-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45486;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIX-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE16832;class=Protein" role="_blank">CED-10</ulink> induce <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27670;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAK-1</ulink> kinase activity and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34875;class=Protein" role="_blank">IFA-3</ulink> phosphorylation to promote FO maturation into short regularly-spaced circumferential bands above muscles (III). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31478;class=Protein" role="_blank">GIT-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45486;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIX-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27670;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAK-1</ulink> are associated with CeHDs. <emphasis role="bold">(D)</emphasis> Affecting the mechanotransduction pathway in a weak <emphasis>vab-10A</emphasis> mutant induces the aggregation of ectopic IFs (orange arrow) and a weakening of CeHDs (sagittal view). <emphasis role="bold">(E)</emphasis> Remodelling of CeHDs is sensitive to the amount of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26978;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-805</ulink> receptor and of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47156;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink>/Perlecan. The E3-ubiquitin ligase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE48619;class=Protein" role="_blank">EEL-1</ulink> regulates the levels of some unknown nuclear factor (TF) that regulates <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002915;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-805</ulink></emphasis> expression; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21562;class=Protein" role="_blank">CRT-1</ulink>/calreticulin helps fold and/or export <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47156;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink>. <emphasis role="bold">(F)</emphasis> A two-fold increase of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26978;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-805</ulink> as observed in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00022069;class=Gene" role="_blank">eel-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants, or a two-fold decrease of the ECM protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47156;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink>/Perlecan levels as observed in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000802;class=Gene" role="_blank">crt-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants compromises CeHD remodelling when in addition the VAB-10A protein is partially functional.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>