<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 6. Intermediate filament assembly and Fibrous Organelle (FO) structure.</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">(A)</emphasis> Sagittal view of the epidermis showing the structure of FOs. FOs correspond to two adhesion complexes each related to vertebrate hemidesmosomes and called CeHD (<emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> hemidesmosome), which can be visualized as electron dense spots (<emphasis role="bold">A&rsquo;</emphasis>; scale bar, 1 &mu;m) bridged by intermediate filaments. (<emphasis role="bold">A&Prime;</emphasis>; scale bar, 10 &mu;m) Adult stained with MH5 mAb, showing the VAB-10A (FO component) pattern in adults. CeHDs are formed basally by the myotactin/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26978;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-805</ulink> receptor or apically by the homologous <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28049;class=Protein" role="_blank">MUA-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29511;class=Protein" role="_blank">MUP-4</ulink> receptors, the plectin/BPAG1e-like VAB-10A, the ankyrin-repeat protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34375;class=Protein" role="_blank">VAB-19</ulink>/Kank, and the intermediate filament (IF) heterodimers <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02619;class=Protein" role="_blank">IFB-1</ulink>/IFA-2 or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02619;class=Protein" role="_blank">IFB-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34875;class=Protein" role="_blank">IFA-3</ulink>. <emphasis role="bold">(B)</emphasis> Sagittal view showing that IF assembly requires their sumoylation by the SUMO protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18056;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMO-1</ulink> to regulate the balance between short IF squiggles and longer IFs recruited to FOs. In a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004888;class=Gene" role="_blank">smo-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant, squiggles predominate, reducing IF recruitment to FOs, leading to FO weakening. <emphasis role="bold">(C-C&rsquo;)</emphasis> Sagittal view (<emphasis role="bold">C</emphasis>) and cross-section view (<emphasis role="bold">C&rsquo;</emphasis>; see <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4B&Prime;</link> and <link linkend="figure7">7A</link> for wild-type reference) of a <emphasis>vab-10A</emphasis> mutant showing strongly disorganized/absent CeHDs; IFs, myotactin and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34375;class=Protein" role="_blank">VAB-19</ulink> have a very abnormal distribution or form aggregates. As a consequence, the epidermis can detach from the embryonic sheath (or the cuticle at later stages), muscles detach from the epidermis and collapse in the embryo. <emphasis role="bold">(D-D&rsquo;)</emphasis> Sagittal view (<emphasis role="bold">D</emphasis>) and cross-section view (<emphasis role="bold">D&rsquo;</emphasis>) showing a similar phenotype, albeit slightly less severe, in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002915;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-805</ulink></emphasis>/myotactin. CeHDs fail to evolve from foci to circumferential lines (left), or they stretch from much more along the circumference (right) inducing mis-localization of some CeHD components such as VAB-19.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>