<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 2. The CeAJ (<emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> apical junction) and cell adhesion.</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">(A)</emphasis> Schematic representation of known CeAJ components. As in vertebrates and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> epithelial cells contain several adhesion complexes, the cadherin-catenin (CCC) and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34261;class=Protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27085;class=Protein" role="_blank">AJM-1</ulink> (DAC) complexes. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is unique in three respects: (1) there is a single electron-dense area in the CeAJ (shown in <emphasis role="bold">A&rsquo;</emphasis>; scale bar, 100 nm), (2) <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29778;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-413</ulink> does not colocalize with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34261;class=Protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink> (as its homologue Scribble in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>), and (3) <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49486;class=Protein" role="_blank">SAX-7</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43754;class=Protein" role="_blank">MAGI-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49686;class=Protein" role="_blank">AFD-1</ulink>, defining the SMAC, whose vertebrate homologues are part of the zonula adherens like the CCC, may have a yet distinct position from the CCC in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (it is shown at two positions). CeAJs from different epithelia contain the same set of proteins, although the classical claudin-like protein might differ in different tissues (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE08040;class=Protein" role="_blank">CLC-1</ulink> in the pharynx, vulva and spermatheca; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28881;class=Protein" role="_blank">CLC-2</ulink> in the lateral epidermis). The DAC complex is likely to correspond to the electron-dense area of the CeAJ since immunogold staining experiments localize <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27085;class=Protein" role="_blank">AJM-1</ulink> at the electron density, and removal of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34261;class=Protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27085;class=Protein" role="_blank">AJM-1</ulink> compromises the electron dense area of the CeAJ (<link linkend="bib74">Koppen et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11715019-->; <link linkend="bib93">McMahon et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11493666-->). Note that the CCC mutants have not been examined by electron microscopy. <emphasis role="bold">(B)</emphasis> During ventral enclosure (facing arrows), ventral epidermal cells extend actin-rich filopodial extensions towards the ventral midline, where they must assemble a new CeAJ with their countralateral homologues through a cadherin/HMR-1-dependent recruitment of other CCC, and presumably DAC, components. <emphasis role="bold">(C)</emphasis> Ventral cells in zygotic <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001980;class=Gene" role="_blank">hmr-1</ulink></emphasis>, maternal and zygotic <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001979;class=Gene" role="_blank">hmp-2</ulink>,</emphasis> or maternal and zygotic <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001978;class=Gene" role="_blank">hmp-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants can extend towards the ventral midline but fail to establish junctions. Adhesion between other cells remains normal in the absence of CCC components. <emphasis role="bold">(D)</emphasis> Cell-cell adhesion is not impaired in mutants lacking the DAC. Paracellular gate function is defective in animals lacking the claudin-like protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE08040;class=Protein" role="_blank">CLC-1</ulink>, a putative DAC component in the pharynx, since pharyngeal cells fail to prevent a small fluorescent dye to leak between adjacent cells (grey material infiltrating between cells). <emphasis role="bold">(E)</emphasis> In animals lacking a CCC and a DAC protein (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40995;class=Protein" role="_blank">HMP-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34261;class=Protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink>, or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32938;class=Protein" role="_blank">VAB-9</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34261;class=Protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink>), cell adhesion is not maintained, causing epithelial cells to round up.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>