<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 4. General anatomy of the epidermis.</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">(A-B)</emphasis> Epidermal actin, as visualized with a GFP fused to the actin-binding domain of the protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35150;class=Protein" role="_blank">VAB-10</ulink>, <emphasis role="bold">(C-D)</emphasis> myosin II, as visualized with a GFP fused to the myosin regulatory chain <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01531;class=Protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink>, and <emphasis role="bold">(E-F)</emphasis> microtubules (in green, visualized with GFP) and apical junctions (in red, visualized with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34261;class=Protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink>::RFP) at the 1.5-fold (<emphasis role="bold">E</emphasis>) and 3.5-fold stage (<emphasis role="bold">F</emphasis>), respectively. <emphasis role="bold">(A, C, E)</emphasis> 1.5-fold and <emphasis role="bold">(B, D, F)</emphasis> 3.5-fold stage embryos. <emphasis role="bold">(A&rsquo;-F&rsquo;)</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">(A&rsquo;&rsquo;-F&rsquo;&rsquo;)</emphasis> correspond to enlargements area boxed in red (seam cell) and white (non-seam cell), respectively. Note the regular actin organisation in the non-seam cell, the myosin II enrichment in seam cells, the regular distribution of microtubules in non-seam cells, and their comparatively disorganized distribution in seam cells. Scale bar, 10 &mu;m. Images are a courtesy from (<link linkend="bib44">Gally et al., 2009</link>).<!--: PMID 19675126--> <emphasis role="bold">(G)</emphasis> 2-fold stage embryo carrying <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34261;class=Protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink>::RFP, a fluorescent reporter to visualize the DAC. Scale bar, 10 &mu;m. <emphasis role="bold">(G&rsquo;)</emphasis> Camera lucida drawing of the CeAJ pattern represented in (<emphasis role="bold">G</emphasis>), and (<emphasis role="bold">G&rsquo;&rsquo;</emphasis>) cross-section through the embryo to highlight the positions of muscles (pink bars) and of CeHDs in the overlying part of the epidermis (green dots). <emphasis role="bold">(H)</emphasis> 3D representation of the epidermis (area boxed in brown on <emphasis role="bold">G&rdquo;</emphasis>, then flattened). All epidermal cells contain actin microfilaments and microtubules, but only dorsal and ventral epidermal cells contain intermediate filaments. In the dorsal and ventral epidermis, actin filaments form circumferential bundles, which are intermingled with MTs. Colocalisation experiments suggest that IFs overlap with MFs. Dorsal and ventral cells establish CeHDs (<emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> hemidesmosomes, also called fibrous organelles or FOs), which are junctions with the extracellular matrix that mechanically couple muscles to the cuticle. For the sake of clarity, several FO components were not drawn.  Orientation on the compass: D=dorsal, V=ventral, A=anterior, P=posterior, L=left, R=right</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>