<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 5. Anchoring of actin microfilaments.</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">(A)</emphasis> Flat-mount representation of the dorsal half of an embryo, with seam cells (light blue) and the main dorsal epidermal syncytium hyp7 (dark yellow; anterior to the left, posterior to the right). Circumferential actin bundles in dorsal cells (vertical green lines) are anchored to the CCC (black lines); note the exaggerated interruption at the expected position of CeHDs (arrows), which has been observed only in certain conditions (<link linkend="bib87">Maiden et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23271732-->). In seam cells, actin filaments look less organized and are probably not anchored to the CeAJ (see <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link><emphasis role="bold">A-B</emphasis>). <emphasis role="bold">(B)</emphasis> In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001978;class=Gene" role="_blank">hmp-1</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001979;class=Gene" role="_blank">hmp-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants, actin bundles are not attached to the CeAJ; due to morphogenetic forces, they snap back to the middle of hyp7. <emphasis role="bold">(C)</emphasis> Actin filaments are significantly disorganized in mutants for the CCC component <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32938;class=Protein" role="_blank">VAB-9</ulink>, the apical spectrin <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46456;class=Protein" role="_blank">SPC-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46252;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMA-1</ulink>, the FO components <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34375;class=Protein" role="_blank">VAB-19</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35150;class=Protein" role="_blank">VAB-10</ulink>, the regulatory actomyosin proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE08098;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-502</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01531;class=Protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink>; however the extent of disorganization appears more severe after phalloidin staining (left moiety), compared to when seen with an actin-binding protein fused to GFP (right moiety). <emphasis role="bold">(D)</emphasis> Enlarged view of the intestinal lumen and brush border in wild-type animals (left), showing the localization of EPS-8A (red), which binds actin barbed ends through a novel domain found at its C-terminus, and of the actin-rich and IFB-2-rich terminal web at the basis of microvilli. In larvae lacking the EPS-8A isoform (middle), microvilli have irregular sizes and orientations or can be missing. In larvae lacking the intermediate filament and actin organizer <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28393;class=Protein" role="_blank">IFO-1</ulink>, the terminal web is strongly affected leading to lumen narrowing (not represented), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE48309;class=Protein" role="_blank">IFB-2</ulink> aggregates and partial actin loss. <emphasis role="bold">(E)</emphasis> Representation of the excretory canal longitudinal section, with its so-called terminal web electron dense structure enriched in actin, actin-anchoring proteins (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07805;class=Protein" role="_blank">ERM-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46252;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMA-1</ulink>) and intermediate filaments (IFA-2/3 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02619;class=Protein" role="_blank">IFB-1</ulink>). In the absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07805;class=Protein" role="_blank">ERM-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46252;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMA-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE16463;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACT-5</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02619;class=Protein" role="_blank">IFB-1</ulink>, cysts develop, highlighting the importance of a terminal web in maintaining a regular lumen diameter in tubular organs.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>