<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 3. The establishment and maintenance of epithelial cell polarity.</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">(A)</emphasis> Once born, epidermal cells rapidly establish CeAJs in a process that involves coalescence of junctional elements initially more spread along the lateral junction. Top, view at the apical surface; bottom, lateral view along the apico-basal axis. <emphasis role="bold">(B)</emphasis> In the epidermis and intestine of a maternal/zygotic <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003921;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-6</ulink></emphasis> mutant, junctions remain fragmented in the plane of the epithelium; it appears normal in the intestine along the apico-basal axis but has not been described for the epidermis (a lateral view was omitted due to the lack of the relevant information for the epidermis) <emphasis role="bold">(C)</emphasis> In a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002632;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-413</ulink></emphasis> mutant, ectopic electron dense junctions are found along the lateral membrane, suggesting that apical coalescence of CeAJ components is defective. Furthermore, apical markers of the epidermis (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28468;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHE-14</ulink>) and the intestine (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49082;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40130;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE48309;class=Protein" role="_blank">IFB-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07805;class=Protein" role="_blank">ERM-1</ulink>) become gradually mislocalized along the lateral membrane. <emphasis role="bold">(D)</emphasis> In the intestine, the establishment of epithelial polarity involves a handover of MTOC material from the centrosome to the apical surface in a process involving <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49082;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink>. <emphasis role="bold">(E)</emphasis> In a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003918;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-3</ulink></emphasis> mutant, this handover process is defective, and cell polarity is not established. <emphasis role="bold">(F)</emphasis> The establishment of epithelial polarity is also defective in the arcade cells of a zygotic <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006974;class=Gene" role="_blank">zen-4</ulink></emphasis> mutant. <emphasis role="bold">(G-H)</emphasis> Expansion of the intestine at later stages of development requires glycosphingolipids and the presence of the AP-1 clathrin adaptor; RAB-11<superscript>+</superscript>-endosomes play a key role in this process. Absence of sphingolipids or of AP-1 induces the formation of multiple lumens (asterisks), loss of the RAB-11<superscript>+</superscript>-endosomes and partial loss of cell polarity. <emphasis role="bold">(I)</emphasis> A separate trafficking pathway, involving the Cdc42 effector <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27939;class=Protein" role="_blank">TOCA-1</ulink>/2 and the WAVE and Arp2/3 complexes, negatively regulates the amount of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07805;class=Protein" role="_blank">ERM-1</ulink> and indirectly controls junction homeostasis; in their absence, the lumen expands, in part due to a reduction of the DAC component <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34261;class=Protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink>. <emphasis role="bold">(K)</emphasis> Loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07805;class=Protein" role="_blank">ERM-1</ulink> induces an opposite phenotype characterized by strong reduction of the lumen, loss of actin, and more <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34261;class=Protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink> at the CeAJ.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>