<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'geneticsuppressionfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'geneticsuppressionfig1leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY geneticsuppression_Refs SYSTEM 'geneticsuppressionrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="geneticsuppression_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Genetic suppression<footnote>
                <para>Edited by Philip Anderson. Last revised March 29, 2005. Published December 27, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Hodgkin, J. Genetic suppression (December 27, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.59.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 Jonathan Hodgkin. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
            </footnote>
        </title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 3/29/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
-->
        <author>
            <firstname>Jonathan</firstname>
            <surname>Hodgkin<remark>
                    <footnote>
                        <para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:jah@bioch.ox.ac.uk">jah@bioch.ox.ac.uk</ulink></para>
                    </footnote>
                </remark>
            </surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Genetics Unit, Department of Biochemistry, University of Oxford, Oxford OX1 3QU, UK</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Genetic suppression has provided a very powerful tool for analyzing</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans.</emphasis></emphasis>
            <emphasis role="bold">Suppression experiments are facilitated by the ability to handle very large numbers of
            individuals and to apply powerful selections. Because the animal grows as a
            self-fertilizing diploid, both dominant and recessive suppressors can be recovered. Many
            different kinds of suppression have been reported. These are discussed by category, with
            examples, together with discussion of how suppressors can be used to interpret the
            underlying biology, and to enable further experimentation. Suppression phenomena can be
            divided into intragenic and extragenic classes, depending on whether the suppressor lies
            in the same gene as the starting mutation, or in a different gene. Intragenic types
            include same-site replacement, compensatory mutation, alteration in splicing, and
            reversion of dominant mutations by</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">cis-</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="bold">knockout. Extragenic suppression can occur by a
            variety of informational mechanisms, such as alterations in splicing, translation or
            nonsense-mediated decay. In addition, extragenic suppression can occur by bypass, dosage
            effects, product interaction, or removal of toxic products. Within signaling pathways,
            suppression can occur by modulating the strength of signal transmission, or by epistatic
            interactions that can reveal the underlying regulatory hierarchies. In</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis>
            <emphasis role="bold">biology, the processes of muscle development, vulva formation and sex determination have
            provided remarkably rich arenas for the investigation and exploitation of suppression.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
    <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>Genetic suppressors provide some of the most powerful tools available for exploring
            gene expression, function and interaction. A suppressor mutation can be defined as a
            second mutation, at a site distinct from the mutation under study, that suppresses the
            phenotypic effect of the first mutation. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is especially suited for suppression
            analysis, for several practical reasons: <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
                <listitem>
                    <para>Very large numbers of individuals can be handled, so that extremely rare
                        mutational events can occur within a single experimental population.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Strong selections can be applied, which may permit the detection and
                        recovery of a single individual from a population of one hundred thousand or more.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Mutations are easily generated, particularly by the chemical mutagen EMS.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The predominant mode of reproduction is by self-fertilization, so that
                        both recessive and dominant suppressors can be recovered readily.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>Genetic suppression can arise in a variety of ways, which are described in the
            sections below. Depending on the nature of the suppressive interaction, different kinds
            of information can be obtained about the initial gene studied.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Intragenic suppression by same site replacement</title>
        <para>In the simplest and least informative scenario, if a mutant carries a single base
            change difference from wildtype, then reversion can occur simply by mutating the
            sequence back to wildtype. However, intracodonic suppression can also occur, if a
            different base change can result in a functional coding sequence. An example is
            provided by a Gln-to-Pro mutant of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dpy-31" role="_blank">dpy-31</ulink></emphasis>, encoding a collagen-processing protease,
            which has been repeatedly reverted either by back mutation, Pro-to-Gln (CCT -&gt;
            CTT), or by the only other acceptable change in this codon, Pro-to-Ser (CCT -&gt;
            TCT) (<link linkend="bib42">Novelli et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15579684-->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Intragenic suppression by compensatory second site mutation</title>
        <para>In principle, missense mutations that result in a non-functional protein can sometimes
            be suppressed by introducing another change elsewhere in the protein. Relatively few
            cases of this effect have been studied so far in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. An example is provided by
            the reversion of temperature-sensitive missense mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a cell
            interaction protein; this experiment yielded a variety of second-site missense changes
            that are able to correct the original defect (<link linkend="bib34">Lissemore et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID 8307320-->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Intragenic suppression by altered splicing</title>
        <para>Sometimes intragenic reversion can be achieved by a second mutation that leads to
            omission of a deleterious mutation by means of exon skipping. This is particularly
            likely to happen with genes that produce multiple splice variants, as illustrated by
            studies of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-52" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis>. This gene encodes multiple isoforms of perlecan, which are proteins
            required for myofilament anchorage to the basement membrane underlying muscle cells.
            Nonsense mutations located in some of the alternatively spliced exons can be suppressed
            by a G-to-A change in the acceptor site adjoining the mutant exon, which leads to its
            omission; the resulting RNA remains in frame and produces a functional protein (<link linkend="bib46">Rogalski
            et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7535716-->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Intragenic suppression of dominant mutations by loss-of-function in <emphasis>cis</emphasis>.</title>
        <para>Most genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are haplo-sufficient, so the majority of dominant mutations
            are associated with gain-of-function effects, which result in a toxic or inappropriately
            expressed gene product (<link linkend="bib43">Park and Horvitz, 1986</link><!--: PMID 3744028-->). The dominant effect of
            such a mutation can be suppressed by introducing a second mutation elsewhere in the
            mutated gene that results in partial or complete loss-of-function in its product.</para>
        <para>An early example was provided by studies of the myosin gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-54" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis>. Some dominant
            mutations of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-54" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis> cause slow movement or paralysis in single dose, by poisoning thick
            filament assembly. These mutations, such as the allele <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1152;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1152</ulink></emphasis>, can be reverted by
            introducing null or partial loss-of-function mutations in <emphasis>cis</emphasis>. Heterozygotes carrying
            just the dominant allele <emphasis>(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1152;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1152</ulink>/+)</emphasis> are slow, whereas <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1152;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1152</ulink> null / +</emphasis> heterozygotes are
            wildtype. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-54" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis> gene is essential for movement, so <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1152;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1152</ulink> null</emphasis> double homozygotes
            are paralysed, but the mutations are initially recovered in healthy heterozygotes with
            normal movement. Selection for improved movement of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1152;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1152</ulink>/+</emphasis> heterozygotes therefore
            provided an efficient means of recovering many mutations in this gene (<link linkend="bib1">Anderson and
            Brenner, 1984</link><!--: PMID 6589606-->).</para>
        <para>Similar strategies have been used frequently and effectively to generate multiple
            loss-of-function mutations in important or essential genes.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Extragenic suppression &#x02014; overview</title>
        <para>Suppressing the effects of a mutant gene by changes elsewhere in the genome can occur
            in a number of ways. Extragenic suppression is usually revealed by crossing a revertant
            line with wildtype, and observing the re-appearance of the original mutant after
            Mendelian segregation. Numerous cases of extragenic suppression have now been identified
            and analysed in greater or lesser depth. Many different phenomena are involved in the
            various cases. About 40 genes in the <emphasis>sup</emphasis> class have been defined thus far, and in
            addition separate gene classes have been established for many of the more specific
            processes that have been studied. As shown in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>, research on 21 suppressor gene
            classes has been published. At least 20 further classes have been established (see
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/" role="_blank">Wormbase</ulink>) but their properties are as yet unpublished. It should be noted that
            suppressor mutations frequently turn out to be special alleles of genes that have
            already been well studied and given more informative names, so the names of suppressor
            loci are more transient than most.</para>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="100%">
<title>Table 1. Suppressor gene classes</title>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c2" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c3" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Gene name</entry>
<entry>Explanation</entry>
<entry>Initial references</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>cps</emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CED-3;class=protein" role="_blank">CED-3</ulink> Protease Suppressor</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib56">Wang et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12446902--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>des</emphasis></entry>
<entry>DEgeneration Suppressor</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib55">Treinin et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9860996--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>eor</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Egl-1 suppressor/DiO uptake defect/Raf enhancer</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib19">Howard and Sundaram, 2002</link><!--: PMID 12130541--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>ksr</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Kinase Suppressor of activated Ras</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib53">Sundaram and Han, 1995</link><!--: PMID 8521513-->; <link linkend="bib27">Kornfeld et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 8521514--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>scd</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Suppressor of Constitutive Dauer formation</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib21">Inoue and Thomas, 2000</link><!--: PMID 11063683--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sel</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Suppressor/Enhancer of Lin-12</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib52">Sundaram and Greenwald, 1993</link><!--: PMID 8293978--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>seu</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Suppressor of Ectopic Unc-5</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib6">Colavita and Culotti, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9473333--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sgs</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Suppressor of G protein S defect</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib28">Korswagen et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9724641--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sli</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Suppressor of LIneage defect</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib23">Jongeward et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7789760--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>smg</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Suppressor, Morphological effect on Genitalia</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib18">Hodgkin et al., 1989</link><!--: PMID 2583479--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>smu</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Suppressor of Mec and Unc defects</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib36">Lundquist and Herman, 1994</link><!--: PMID 8001796--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>soc</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Suppressor Of Clr</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib49">Selfors et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9618511--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sog</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Suppressor Of Glp</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib38">Maine and Kimble, 1993</link><!--: PMID 8307319--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sol</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Suppressor Of Lurcher movement defect</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib65">Zheng et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14749834--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sop</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Suppressor Of Pal</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib64">Zhang and Emmons, 2000</link><!--: PMID 10970880--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>spr</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Suppressor of PResenilin defect</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib60">Wen et al. 2000</link><!--: PMID 11114162--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>srl</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Suppressor of Roller Lethality</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib3">Barbazuk et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID 8138151--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sup</emphasis></entry>
<entry>SUPpressor</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib45">Riddle and Brenner, 1978</link><!--: PMID 669254-->; <link linkend="bib58">Waterston and Brenner, 1978</link><!--: PMID 703836--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sur</emphasis></entry>
<entry>SUppressor of activated Ras</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib29">Lackner et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID 8299936-->; <link linkend="bib62">Wu and Han, 1994</link><!--: PMID 8299935--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sus</emphasis></entry>
<entry>SUppressor of Suppressor</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib5">Brown and Riddle, 1985</link><!--: PMID 4018568--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>suv</emphasis></entry>
<entry>SUppressor of Vulvaless</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib15">Hajnal et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9334333--></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
        <para>Space does not permit a full description of all the classes listed in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>, but
		some of the major types of suppression that have been encountered are discussed below,
            using particular examples.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Informational suppression &#x02014; overview</title>
        <para>Alteration of the general machinery for transcription, RNA processing and translation
            can sometimes ameliorate or suppress certain kinds of mutation in many different genes.
            The hallmarks of informational suppression, as this phenomenon is known, are
            allele-specificity and gene-non-specificity. Three kinds of informational suppression
            have been described so far in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>: nonsense suppression; suppression by modified
            splicing; suppression by loss of nonsense-mediated decay (NMD).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Nonsense suppression</title>
        <para>A large fraction of point mutations identified in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are changes from sense to
            nonsense codons, either UAG (amber), UAA (ochre) or UGA (opal), resulting in polypeptide
            chain termination and (usually) complete or almost complete loss of gene function. These
            nonsense mutants can potentially be suppressed by nonsense suppressor tRNAs, in which a
            sense codon has been changed to be able to decode the nonsense triplet. In practice,
            only amber suppressors have been recovered. Early work identified two suppressor loci,
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-5" role="_blank">sup-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-7" role="_blank">sup-7</ulink></emphasis>, which could act to suppress certain mutations in a wide variety of
            genes (<link linkend="bib58">Waterston and Brenner, 1978</link><!--: PMID 703836-->; <link linkend="bib57">Waterston, 1981</link><!--: PMID 7274656-->). These
            were subsequently shown to be amber suppressor mutations of two Trp tRNA genes, carrying
            alterations in their anticodons from CCA to CTA (<link linkend="bib61">Wills, et al., 1983</link><!--: PMID 6571695-->;
            <link linkend="bib4">Bolten et al., 1984</link><!--: PMID 6093119-->).</para>
        <para>There are twelve members of the Trp tRNA family in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, but only two can be
            mutated to yield strong amber suppressors. The same two mutations, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-5" role="_blank">sup-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-7" role="_blank">sup-7</ulink></emphasis>, were
            isolated repeatedly in independent experiments (<link linkend="bib57">Waterston, 1981</link><!--: PMID 7274656-->). Weak
            amber suppressors were subsequently obtained for six additional members of the set (see
            <link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>), by selecting for suppressors using amber mutants that are very easily
            suppressed such as several in the sex determination gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-3" role="_blank">tra-3</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib16">Hodgkin, 1985</link>;
            <link linkend="bib25">Kondo et al., 1988</link><!--: PMID 3221861-->; <link linkend="bib26">Kondo et al., 1990</link><!--: PMID 2398498-->). Probably only a
            trace of full length <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-3;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-3</ulink> protein is sufficient to provide enough activity for normal
            sexual development, so weak suppressors can be recovered. As indicated in <link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>, the
            eight identified amber suppressors appear to be expressed at different levels, and they
            also exhibit some differences between tissues in the strength of suppression (<link linkend="bib26">Kondo et
            al., 1990</link><!--: PMID 2398498-->). In vitro observations on the transcription of these genes
            that are consistent with these different strengths have been reported (Li et al, 1988<!--:
            PMID 9447966-->). The differences in strength show that flanking sequences can exert a
            strong influence on expression level of these tRNAs, despite the fact that all eight are
            identical in the internal promoter sequences believed to be sufficient for Pol III
            transcription of tRNA genes.</para>
<table id="table2" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="100%">
<title>Table 2. Amber nonsense suppressors</title>
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c2" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c3" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c4" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Gene name (allele)</entry>
<entry>Class (other name)</entry>
<entry>Approximate relative strength</entry>
<entry>Reference</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sup-5(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1464;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1464</ulink>)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Trp (<emphasis>rtw-1</emphasis>)</entry>
<entry>7</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib58">Waterston and Brenner (1978)</link></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sup-7(st5)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Trp (<emphasis>rtw-2</emphasis>)</entry>
<entry>8</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib57">Waterston (1981)</link></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sup-21(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1957;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1957</ulink>)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Trp (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rtw-10" role="_blank">rtw-10</ulink></emphasis>)</entry>
<entry>3</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib16">Hodgkin (1985)</link></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sup-24(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=st354;class=Variation" role="_blank">st354</ulink>)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Trp (<emphasis>rtw-4</emphasis>)</entry>
<entry>4</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib25">Kondo et al. (1988)</link></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sup-28(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e2058;class=Variation" role="_blank">e2058</ulink>)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Trp (<emphasis>rtw-8</emphasis>)</entry>
<entry>2</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib25">Kondo et al. (1988)</link></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sup-29(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1986;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1986</ulink>)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Trp (<emphasis>rtw-9</emphasis>)</entry>
<entry>1</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib25">Kondo et al. (1988)</link></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sup-33(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=st389;class=Variation" role="_blank">st389</ulink>)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Trp (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rtw-11" role="_blank">rtw-11</ulink></emphasis>)</entry>
<entry>4</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib26">Kondo et al. (1990)</link></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sup-34(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e2227;class=Variation" role="_blank">e2227</ulink>)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Trp (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rtw-12" role="_blank">rtw-12</ulink></emphasis>)</entry>
<entry>3</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib26">Kondo et al. (1990)</link></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sup-22(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e2057;class=Variation" role="_blank">e2057</ulink>)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Non-Trp</entry>
<entry>2</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib16">Hodgkin (1985)</link></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sup-23(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e2059;class=Variation" role="_blank">e2059</ulink>)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>?Non-Trp</entry>
<entry>2</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib16">Hodgkin (1985)</link></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sup-32(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1958;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1958</ulink>)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Non-Trp</entry>
<entry>2</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib16">Hodgkin (1985)</link></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sup-?(st402)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Non-Trp</entry>
<entry>3</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib26">Kondo et al. (1990)</link></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis>sup-?(st414)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Non-Trp</entry>
<entry>2</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib26">Kondo et al. (1990)</link></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
        <para>Too much suppression is clearly deleterious, because animals carrying two doses of
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-7" role="_blank">sup-7</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-5" role="_blank">sup-5</ulink></emphasis> are inviable or subviable, especially at low temperature (<link linkend="bib57">Waterston,
            1981</link><!--: PMID 7274656-->). Presumably the deleterious effects result from too much
            readthrough of natural stop codons. Selection for improved low-temperature viability of
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-7" role="_blank">sup-7</ulink></emphasis> animals was used to generate deletions or loss-of-function mutations of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-7" role="_blank">sup-7</ulink></emphasis>,
            suggesting that the inviability is due to readthrough rather than loss of the normal
            function of the gene. The same effect may explain why ochre or opal suppressors have not
            been recovered.</para>
        <para>Additional weak amber suppressors have been isolated, which do not correspond to Trp
            tRNA genes, but they have not yet been identified at the molecular level (<link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>). Some
            of these are likely to be Gln tRNA genes, because a Gln CTG anticodon can be readily
            mutated to read amber codons. Suppression by an amber-suppressing Ser tRNA from
            Drosophila, introduced as a transgene, has been reported (<link linkend="bib44">Pilgrim and Bell, 1993</link><!--: PMID 8232208-->), demonstrating that endogenous Ser tRNA genes might also yield amber
        suppressors. As well as providing valuable tools for examining mutations in
        particular genes and for studying tRNA gene expression, amber suppressors have been useful
        in the development of methods for microinjection and transformation of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib24">Kimble et
        al., 1982</link><!--: PMID 7121584-->; <link linkend="bib9">Fire, 1986</link><!--: PMID -->) The dose-sensitivity of strong amber
    suppressors also allows selection of single-copy transformants (<link linkend="bib10">Fire et al., 1990</link><!--: PMID 2377476-->).</para>
	</sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Extragenic suppression by modified splicing</title>
        <para>Two kinds of suppression by modified splicing have been reported. The first kind
            depends on compensatory mutations in splice-site recognition machinery, and the second
            is associated with mutations that affect alternative splicing.</para>
        <para>The first kind involves allele-specific suppression of mutations that change the
            conserved and essential GU donor sequence at the 5’ end of an intron, by means of
            compensatory changes in the sequence of a U1 snRNA gene. In the case of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-6" role="_blank">sup-6</ulink></emphasis>, a donor
            site mutation (AGgu --&gt; AGau) in allele <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e309;class=Variation" role="_blank">e309</ulink></emphasis> of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-13" role="_blank">unc-13</ulink></emphasis> is suppressed by a change
            in one of the U1 snRNA genes (…UCCAUU… --&gt; UCUAUU) (<link linkend="bib63">Zahler et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15342508-->). In a related case, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-39" role="_blank">sup-39</ulink></emphasis>, a donor site mutation (AGgu --&gt; AGuu) in
            allele <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e936;class=Variation" role="_blank">e936</ulink></emphasis> of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-73" role="_blank">unc-73</ulink></emphasis> is suppressed by a change in a different U1 snRNA gene (…UCCAUU…
            --&gt;… UCAAUU…) (<link linkend="bib48">Run et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8722777-->; <link linkend="bib47">Roller et al., 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib63">Zahler et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 10757761-->). These effects are consistent with the proposed role of U1 in pairing at the
            donor site during splicing.</para>
        <para>In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, there are 12 genes encoding U1 snRNA, yet only two have yielded
            suppressors of this type (<link linkend="bib63">Zahler et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15342508-->). As with the failure to
            find ochre or opal suppressors discussed above, it is possible that most U1 suppressor
            mutations will be either too weak, because of redundancy, or too deleterious, because of
            effects on normal genes. In support of the latter possibility, both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-6" role="_blank">sup-6</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-39" role="_blank">sup-39</ulink></emphasis>
            exhibit defects when homozygous: <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-6" role="_blank">sup-6</ulink></emphasis> homozygotes arrest in late-larval development,
            and 50<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-39" role="_blank">sup-39</ulink></emphasis> homozygotes die as embryos. In addition, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-39" role="_blank">sup-39</ulink></emphasis> animals that escape
            this embryonic lethality frequently exhibit two rows of oocytes rather than one in adult
            hermaphrodites, an unusual and unexplained phenotype (<link linkend="bib48">Run et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8722777-->).</para>
        <para>The second kind of extragenic suppression by altered splicing involves the regulation
            of alternative splicing. As described above, some mutations of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-52" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> perlecan gene
            are located in alternatively spliced exons and can be suppressed by intragenic mutations
            that cause exon-skipping. A subset of these, those located in exon 17, can also be
            suppressed by loss-of-function mutations in two genes, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=smu-1" role="_blank">smu-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=smu-2" role="_blank">smu-2</ulink></emphasis>, which encode
            proteins homologous to mammalian spliceosome-associated factors (<link linkend="bib50">Spartz et al., 2004</link><!--:
            PMID 15254247-->). Loss of these factors leads to enhanced skipping of exon 17, and
            consequently to suppression of mutations affecting this exon. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=smu-1" role="_blank">smu-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=smu-2" role="_blank">smu-2</ulink></emphasis>
            mutations also weakly suppress the pleiotropic effects of mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mec-8" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink></emphasis>, which
            encodes another regulator of alternative splicing (<link linkend="bib36">Lundquist and Herman, 1994</link><!--: PMID 8001796-->). This suggests that the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMU-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SMU-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMU-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SMU-2</ulink> factors can affect the splicing of
            multiple genes, although neither is essential for viability. It seems very likely that
            further cases of suppression by modified splicing will be encountered in the future.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Suppression by loss of NMD (Nonsense Mediated Decay)</title>
        <para>Mutations resulting in a premature stop codon trigger the NMD system of message
            degradation. If the
            NMD system is absent, then mRNAs with such codons have longer lifetimes, increasing the
            chance of readthrough at the stop codon and the production of a functional protein.
            Alternatively, if the stop codon is located close to the end of the message, the
            truncated polypeptide produced after translation of the stabilized message may be long
            enough to have substantial activity. Nonsense mutations are frequently generated in <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> forward mutagenesis screens, so a variety of suppressor screens have yielded
            mutations in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> NMD genes (<link linkend="bib18">Hodgkin et al., 1989</link><!--: PMID 2583479-->). Seven genes
            required for NMD have been identified in this way, which are called <emphasis>smg</emphasis> (for Suppressor
            with Morphogenetic effect on Genitalia). Loss of NMD does not lead to inviability in <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis>, but does result in an abnormal morphology of the hermaphrodite vulva and of the
            male tail, hence the name. Suppression is generally weaker than with amber suppression.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Extragenic suppression by non-specific physiological effects</title>
        <para>Some cases of suppression probably result from general effects on the physiology of
            the animal, which can alter the expression of a variety of different genes. An example
            is provided by the recovery of mutations in eight or more cuticle collagen genes, all of
            which cause a ‘dumpy left roller’ phenotype, as weak suppressors of two quite different
            mutant defects: germline proliferation, in the case of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib37">Maine and Kimble, 1989</link><!--:
            PMID 2627884-->), and embryonic gastrulation, in the case of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=emb-5" role="_blank">emb-5</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib41">Nishiwaki and Miwa,
            1998</link><!--: PMID 9738874-->). The mechanism involved is unknown, but indirect effects via
            alteration of extracellular matrix or of stress response have been suggested as possible explanations.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Suppression by altered gene dosage</title>
        <para>Sometimes the lack of a particular protein can be compensated for by increasing the
            amount of an alternative, related protein. This is illustrated by the analysis of a gene
            initially called <emphasis>sup-3</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib45">Riddle and Brenner, 1978</link><!--: PMID 669254-->), identified by mutations
            that acted to suppress <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-54" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-15" role="_blank">unc-15</ulink></emphasis> mutants; these lack either the major body wall
            myosin (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-54;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-54</ulink>) or another thick filament component, paramyosin (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-15;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-15</ulink>). Molecular
            analysis of <emphasis>sup-3</emphasis> showed that its mutant alleles are duplications or triplications of
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=myo-3" role="_blank">myo-3</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a minor myosin. Normally <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MYO-3;class=protein" role="_blank">MYO-3</ulink> accounts for only 15<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of the body
            wall myosin, but its level is increased in the duplication alleles, and can thereby
            compensate for the lack of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-54;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-54</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-15;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-15</ulink> (<link linkend="bib39">Maruyama et al., 1989</link><!--: PMID 2575705-->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Bypass suppression</title>
        <para>Suppression by increased dosage can be regarded as a special case of bypass
            suppression, wherein an alternative protein or pathway is up-regulated or de-regulated
            to remove the need for a defective component. Mutations that activate alternative
            pathways are often encountered as a result of suppressor analysis. Screens for
            suppressors of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pal-1" role="_blank">pal-1</ulink></emphasis>, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of the developmental regulator caudal,
            illustrate this effect (<link linkend="bib64">Zhang and Emmons, 2000</link><!--: PMID 10970880-->). In normal development,
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pal-1" role="_blank">pal-1</ulink></emphasis> expression in certain tail cells depends on a positive regulatory element located
            in one of its introns. A screen was carried out for suppressors of a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pal-1" role="_blank">pal-1</ulink></emphasis> mutation
            affecting this intronic element, which led to the identification of three <emphasis>sop</emphasis>
            (Suppressor Of Pal) genes. These encode factors that act as general repressors of an
            alternative mode of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pal-1" role="_blank">pal-1</ulink></emphasis> transcription. Two of the <emphasis>sop</emphasis> genes encode components of the
            transcriptional Mediator complex. Loss of these factors results in expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pal-1" role="_blank">pal-1</ulink></emphasis>
            in the tail cells, and hence to suppression by bypassing the need for the intronic
            regulatory element.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Extragenic suppression by interacting components</title>
        <para>An abnormal protein can sometimes be restored to greater functionality by changes in
            an interacting protein. Suppression by such a mechanism is usually allele-specific, and
            provides <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> evidence for protein interaction. An example is provided by mutations
            of the muscle protein gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-22" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink></emphasis>, which cause a ‘twitcher’ abnormal movement phenotype.
            Some revertants of certain <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-22" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink></emphasis> alleles were found to be unusual missense alleles of
            the body wall myosin gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-54" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis>, suggesting that the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-22;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-22</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-54;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-54</ulink> proteins
            interact directly (<link linkend="bib40">Moerman et al., 1982</link><!--: PMID 7151169-->). Both these proteins are,
            indeed, located in the thick filaments of the myofilament lattice (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_SarcomereAssembCelegansmusc/SarcomereAssembCelegansmusc.html" role="_blank">Sarcomere assembly in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> muscle</ulink>).</para>
        <para>Another example is provided by suppression of certain dominant mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-105" role="_blank">unc-105</ulink></emphasis>,
            a gene encoding a putative mechanosensory channel in muscle cells, by a specific
            missense alteration in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-2" role="_blank">let-2</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a basement membrane collagen (<link linkend="bib35">Liu et al.,
            1996</link><!--: PMID 8662524-->). A plausible interpretation is that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-105;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-105</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-2;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-2</ulink> interact
            directly, providing anchorage for the sensory channel and allowing it to act as a
            stretch sensor.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Suppression by removal of a toxic protein or protein complex</title>
        <para>A situation sometimes encountered in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genetics is the appearance of an
            abnormal phenotype as the result of a neomorphic change in a gene, resulting in the
            production of a toxic protein. Such mutations are usually but not always dominant
            (sometimes they are recessive because in heterozygotes the abnormal protein is
            outcompeted by normal protein). Suppression studies have been carried out with such
            mutations in a variety of different genes. Any alteration that removes the toxic
            protein, or prevents it from acting, will behave as a suppressor.</para>
        <para>The simplest situation involves the introduction of a second inactivating mutation in
            <emphasis>cis</emphasis> to the dominant allele. This is exemplified by dominant mutations of the myosin gene
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-54" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis>, as already described.</para>
        <para>A more complex situation was encountered with the gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-93" role="_blank">unc-93</ulink></emphasis>, which has been
            subjected to extensive suppression analysis. A rare mutation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-93" role="_blank">unc-93</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1500;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1500</ulink></emphasis>, causes a
            distinctive movement and egg-laying defect referred to as the ‘rubber-band’ phenotype.
            This phenotype is almost completely recessive, although genetic tests indicate that
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1500;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1500</ulink></emphasis> is neomorphic in character. Null mutations introduced in <emphasis>cis</emphasis> to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1500;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1500</ulink></emphasis> result in
            normally moving animals, when homozygous. Therefore, the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-93" role="_blank">unc-93</ulink></emphasis> gene is dispensable, but
            can be mutated to generate a product that is able to poison muscle contraction
            (<link linkend="bib12">Greenwald and Horvitz, 1980</link><!--: PMID 6894129-->). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1500;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1500</ulink></emphasis> phenotype can also be suppressed
            by null mutations in three unlinked genes, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-9" role="_blank">sup-9</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-10" role="_blank">sup-10</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-18" role="_blank">sup-18</ulink></emphasis>, which act as
            recessive suppressors, as well as by specific dominant mutations of another gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-11" role="_blank">sup-11</ulink></emphasis>
            (<link linkend="bib13">Greenwald and Horvitz, 1982</link><!--: PMID 7173602-->). Moreover, ‘rubber-band’ alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-9" role="_blank">sup-9</ulink></emphasis>
            and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-10" role="_blank">sup-10</ulink></emphasis> were subsequently found, which can be suppressed by null alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-93" role="_blank">unc-93</ulink></emphasis>
            (<link linkend="bib14">Greenwald and Horvitz, 1986</link><!--: PMID 3710144-->; <link linkend="bib30">Levin and Horvitz, 1992</link><!--: PMID 1313436-->).
            Molecular analysis indicates that these genes encode components of a muscle-specific
            potassium channel: the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SUP-9;class=protein" role="_blank">SUP-9</ulink> sequence reveals that it belongs to the family of two-pore
            K<superscript>+</superscript> channel proteins, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SUP-10;class=protein" role="_blank">SUP-10</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-93;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-93</ulink> are membrane proteins that co-localize with
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SUP-9;class=protein" role="_blank">SUP-9</ulink> in muscle cells (<link linkend="bib31">Levin and Horvitz, 1993</link><!--: PMID 8224828-->; <link linkend="bib7">de la Cruz et al., 2003</link><!--:
            PMID 14534247-->). The current interpretation is therefore that this multi-protein channel
            complex is dispensable for normal muscle function, but it can be mutated so as to
            interfere severely with contraction, presumably by affecting K<superscript>+</superscript> flux. The other two
            interacting genes, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-11" role="_blank">sup-11</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-18" role="_blank">sup-18</ulink></emphasis>, likely encode additional components, but <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-11" role="_blank">sup-11</ulink></emphasis> is
            known to be an essential gene, in contrast to the other four (because null mutations of
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-11" role="_blank">sup-11</ulink></emphasis> are embryonic lethal), so it must be involved in other processes as well.</para>
        <para>A comparable situation was found in the case of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=deg-3" role="_blank">deg-3</ulink></emphasis> gene, which encodes a
            nicotinic acetylcholine receptor subunit. Rare dominant alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=deg-3" role="_blank">deg-3</ulink></emphasis> cause neuronal
            degeneration (hence the name), but the degeneration can be suppressed by
            loss-of-function mutations of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=des-2" role="_blank">des-2</ulink></emphasis> (DEgeneration Suppressor). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=des-2" role="_blank">des-2</ulink></emphasis> gene was found
            to encode another receptor subunit, and co-expression of wildtype <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DEG-3;class=protein" role="_blank">DEG-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DES-2;class=protein" role="_blank">DES-2</ulink> in
          <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes resulted in formation of a functional acetylcholine-gated channel.
            Co-expression of mutant <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DEG-3;class=protein" role="_blank">DEG-3</ulink> with wildtype <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DES-2;class=protein" role="_blank">DES-2</ulink> resulted in an abnormal channel.
            Expression of either subunit alone, however, does not allow formation of a channel,
            thereby explaining the mechanism of suppression (<link linkend="bib55">Treinin et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9860996-->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Suppression by modulators of activity</title>
        <para>The efficiency of a signal transduction pathway is usually modulated by interacting
            components that can increase or decrease the strength of a signal. This is especially
            true in multicellular organisms, where the same pathway may be used for multiple
            purposes in different tissues, and can be fine-tuned by these modulators so as to allow
            optimal function in each context. The presence of modulators is often revealed by
            suppression analysis. Good illustrations of this type of suppression are provided by
            extensive work on the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>/NOTCH receptor, which is involved in numerous important
            signaling events during development (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_lin12Notch/lin12notch.html" role="_blank">LIN-12/Notch signaling in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). Suppression experiments
            have been carried out using both hypomorphic, partial loss-of-function alleles (<link linkend="bib52">Sundaram
            and Greenwald, 1993</link><!--: PMID 8293978-->) and hypermorphic, gain-of-function alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis>
            (<link linkend="bib32">Levitan and Greenwald, 1995</link><!--: PMID 7566091-->; <link linkend="bib54">Tax et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9409830-->). The first
            kind of experiment yielded mutations in negative regulators of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> activity, such as
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sel-1" role="_blank">sel-1</ulink></emphasis>, encoding an extracellular protein (<link linkend="bib11">Grant and Greenwald, 1996</link><!--: PMID 8722778-->), and
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sel-10" role="_blank">sel-10</ulink></emphasis>, encoding an F-box protein predicted to be involved in ubiquitin-mediated
            turnover of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> (<link linkend="bib20">Hubbard et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9389650-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SEL-10;class=protein" role="_blank">SEL-10</ulink> was independently
            identified as a factor affecting sex determination, again partly as a result of
            suppressor analysis (<link linkend="bib22">Jager et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15306688-->).</para>
        <para>The second kind of experiment, suppressing dominant gain-of-function alleles of
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis>, generated mutations in positive regulators. These included <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SUP-17;class=protein" role="_blank">SUP-17</ulink>, a protein
            belonging to the ADAM protease family, which perhaps acts by cleaving and activating the
            extracellular domain of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> receptor (<link linkend="bib59">Wen et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9428412-->). Also
            identified were <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SEL-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SEL-5</ulink>, a serine/threonine kinase (<link linkend="bib8">Fares and Greenwald, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10581273-->) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SEL-12;class=protein" role="_blank">SEL-12</ulink>, which is related to mammalian presenilin proteins and therefore
            of great medical interest (<link linkend="bib32">Levitan and Greenwald, 1995</link><!--: PMID 7566091-->). Not
            surprisingly, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sel-12" role="_blank">sel-12</ulink></emphasis> mutations have an egg-laying defect in a <emphasis>lin-12(+)</emphasis> background; this
            in turn has allowed further suppressor screens for mutations correcting this defect, and
            the identification of <emphasis>spr</emphasis> (Suppressor of Presenilin) genes (<link linkend="bib60">Wen et al. 2000</link><!--: PMID 11114162-->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Suppression by epistasis</title>
        <para>Suppression analysis has been invaluable in unraveling regulatory pathways in <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis>. Many important events in development depend on signal transduction events,
            whereby an inductive signal emanating from one cell leads to a transcriptional response
            in target cells or tissues. The transduction of the signal involves a chain of
            interactions, with receptors, second messengers and transcription factors, and the
            interactions may be either positive or negative at each step. Mutations that decrease or
            increase signaling at one step can be epistatically suppressed by antagonistic mutations
            acting at a downstream step, which in turn can be subjected to further analysis. If the
            pathway involves a linear series of interactions, then the epistatic relationships of
            mutations in the different genes can be used to deduce the order and nature of the steps
            involved. More detailed discussion of the rules and interpretation of epistasis can be
            found elsewhere (<link linkend="bib2">Avery and Wasserman 1992</link><!--: PMID 1365397-->).</para>
        <para>Two good examples are provided by the vulval induction pathway (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RTKRasMAPKsignaling/RTKRasMAPKsignaling.html" role="_blank">RTKRas/MAP kinase signaling</ulink > and the sex determination pathway (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_somaticsexdeterm/somaticsexdeterm.html" role="_blank">Somatic sex determination</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_sexgermline/sexgermline.html" role="_blank">Sex-determination in the germ line</ulink>). In
            the first case, opposite mutant phenotypes result from either too little or too much
            activation of the ERK MAP kinase pathway in the vulval precursor cells. These phenotypes
            are called Vul (vulvaless, failure to induce or complete vulval differentation) and Muv
            (multivulva, excess vulval differentiation) respectively. Both kinds of phenotype are
            very conspicuous in adult hermaphrodites, and both are associated with egg-laying
            defects and reduced fertility, so suppressors are easily detected. Mutations that
            suppress a Vul phenotype often lead to a Muv phenotype on their own, and vice versa. For
            example, screens for suppressors of a loss-of-function Vul mutation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-23" role="_blank">let-23</ulink></emphasis>, encoding
            the EGF receptor required for vulval induction, yielded a gain-of-function in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-60" role="_blank">let-60</ulink></emphasis>,
            encoding the downstream Ras protein in this signal transduction pathway. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-60" role="_blank">let-60</ulink>(gf)</emphasis>
            mutation has a Muv phenotype on its own, and screens for suppressors of the Muv
            phenotype led to the isolation of mutations in ten or more genes encoding further
            downstream components or modifiers of the pathway, most of which have a Vul phenotype on
            their own. This kind of analysis has led to the identification of thirty or more genes
            involved in EGF signaling, and has played a major role in the very detailed elucidation
            of its properties and function (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RTKRasMAPKsignaling/RTKRasMAPKsignaling.html">RTKRas/MAP kinase signaling</ulink>). For a summary of the
            suppressor screens that have been carried out, see <link linkend="bib51">Sternberg and Han (1998</link><!--: PMID 9825675-->).</para>
        <para>In the case of sex determination, the opposite phenotypes caused by mutation are
            Masculinized and Feminized. It is frequently possible (for example by use of
            temperature-sensitive mutants) to set up a situation in which a large population of
            worms develops only along one sexual path. Such a pure male or pure female population
            will yield no progeny, so there is extremely effective selection for any suppressor
            mutation that reverts or ameliorates the phenotype, and thereby allows cross- or
            self-fertilization, and the production of progeny. An extensive series of experiments of
            this type has been carried out in a number of different laboratories, as summarized in
            <xref linkend="figure1" />. Both loss-of-function and gain-of-function mutations have been isolated at
            each of four regulatory steps, largely as a result of this approach. For example,
            selections for suppressors of the masculinizing mutations of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-3" role="_blank">tra-3</ulink></emphasis> yielded feminizing
            (loss-of-function) alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-1" role="_blank">fem-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-2" role="_blank">fem-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-3" role="_blank">fem-3</ulink></emphasis>, as well as gain-of-function
            alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib17">Hodgkin, 1986</link><!--: PMID 3770465-->). Amber alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-3" role="_blank">tra-3</ulink></emphasis> were used in
            some of these selections, which consequently also yielded many nonsense suppressors and
            NMD (smg) suppressors (<link linkend="bib16">Hodgkin, 1985</link><!--: PMID ?-->; <link linkend="bib17">Hodgkin, 1986</link><!--: PMID 3770465-->).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
			<imageobject>
			<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="5.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Suppressor mutations figure 1</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>Almost every known control pathway in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has been subjected to some kind of
            suppressor analysis, and the results have frequently been critical in elucidating
            properties and testing models. Genetic suppression must also happen naturally, and is
            certain to play an important role in evolution. Whether new kinds of suppression will
            become apparent, as further genes and processes are subjected to investigation, remains
        to be seen.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
		<para/>
		&geneticsuppression_Refs;</sect1>
</article>