<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 2: CoIP-MS schematic for analysis of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> protein complexes.</title>
<para>A preparative growth of animals is lysed in a protein complex-compatible buffer with a dounce on ice, bead beater at 4&deg;C, or in liquid nitrogen with a mortar and pestle. The POI is CoIPed and eluted for proteomic analysis. Quality control, gel-based analysis is performed on 10% of CoIP (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>). Shotgun proteomic analysis is performed on the remaining 90% of the CoIP. Proteins are precipitated with tricholoracetic acid (TCA)/acetone or methanol/chloroform to remove lipids and surfactants. Proteins are resolubilized, primarily with 8 M urea, then alkylated, reduced, and digested to peptides with trypsin. Tryptic peptides are analyzed using MudPIT, consisting of online nLC/LC-MS/MS. Peptides are fractionated by charge with strong cation exchange (SCX) chromatography and then further separated by hydrophobicity with reverse-phase high performance liquid chromatography (RP-HPLC). Separated peptides are transferred into the mass spectrometer by electrospray ionization (ESI) where their intact and fragment ion masses can be measured with either high or low mass accuracy and resolution using the LTQ or the Orbitrap, respectively. Bioinformatic analysis is performed on the MS/MS data. A SEQUEST protein database search is used to match experimental and theoretical peptide spectra and to localize PTMs. Spectra can be manually annotated to validate peptide identification or PTM localization. In this case, the blue and green annotations are sequence informative ions while the red ions are phosphorylation site-specific ions that localize the PTMs. DTASelect is used to filter confident peptide matches and reassemble the peptides into proteins. Further analysis can be performed between replicate and comparative runs with Venn diagrams or more sophisticated statistical software (see <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>).</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>
