<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 4</title><para>Anatomy and study of the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> nervous system. (A) Diagram of the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> nervous system identifying some major nerve bundles and ganglia. Major nerve tracts include the ventral nerve cord (VNC), dorsal nerve cord (DNC), and nerve ring. Major ganglia include the ring ganglia, retrovesicular ganglion (RVG), pre-anal ganglion (PAG), and dorsal-root ganglion (DRG). Image produced using the OpenWorm browser utility (openworm.org). (B) Visualization of anterior sensory neurons and their neurite projections by expression of a GFP reporter transgene. The <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/tools/genome/gbrowse/c_elegans_PRJNA13758/?name=gene%3AWBGene00000241" role="_blank">Y105E8A.5</ulink>::GFP</emphasis> fusion transgene is expressed in amphid, OL, and IL sensory neurons of the head (R. Newbury and D. Moerman, Wormatlas; wormatlas.org). (C) Use of cameleon reporter transgene to detect calcium transients in the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> pharynx. The animal carries a transgene with <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003514;class=Gene" role="_blank">myo-2</ulink></emphasis>, a pharynx-specific myosin gene, fused to YC2.1, a calcium-sensitive fluorescent detector. False-color red in the pharyngeal bulb reflects real-time calcium releases in the cell of the living animal. Image adapted from <link linkend="bib102">Kerr et al. (2000)</link><!-- PMID: 10896155-->. (D) Electronic microscopic section showing synapses. Collections of densely-staining vesicles can be seen in neuron 1 at point of synaptic connection to neurons 2 and 3 (arrows). Synaptic varicosities (V) that contain vesicles can be seen clustered around the active zone. DCV identifies a dense-core vesicle. Image from D. Hall (Wormatlas; wormatlas.org). (E) Worm behavior on a bacterial plate. Left image shows the standard laboratory <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=N2;class=Strain" role="_blank">N2</ulink> strain foraging as individuals evenly dispersed across the bacterial food. Right image shows an <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003807;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant strain foraging in grouped masses (sometimes called a &ldquo;social&rdquo; feeding phenotype). Image from M. de Bono, taken from <link linkend="bib154">Schafer (2005)</link><!-- PMID: 16139205-->.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>
