<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'celegansintro_fig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'celegansintro_fig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'celegansintro_fig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'celegansintro_fig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'celegansintro_fig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'celegansintro_fig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig7 SYSTEM 'celegansintro_fig7.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'celegansintro_fig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'celegansintro_fig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'celegansintro_fig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'celegansintro_fig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'celegansintro_fig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'celegansintro_fig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig7legend SYSTEM 'celegansintro_fig7leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY celegansintro_ref SYSTEM 'celegansintro_ref.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="celegansintro_text">
<articleinfo>
<title>A Transparent window into biology: A primer on <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis><footnote><para>Edited by E. A. De Stasio. Published June 18, 2015. This chapter should be cited as: Corsi A.K., Wightman B., and Chalfie M. A Transparent window into biology: A primer on <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> (June 18, 2015), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.177.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2015 Ann K. Corsi, Bruce Wightman, and Martin Chalfie. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para></footnote></title>
<author><othername>Ann K. Corsi<superscript>1</superscript><remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:corsi@cua.edu">corsi@cua.edu</ulink>, <ulink url="mailto:wightman@muhlenberg.edu">wightman@muhlenberg.edu</ulink>, or <ulink url="mailto:mc21@columbia.edu">mc21@columbia.edu</ulink>.</para></footnote></remark>, Bruce Wightman<superscript>2<emphasis role="italic">&sect;</emphasis></superscript>, and Martin Chalfie<superscript>3<emphasis role="italic">&sect;</emphasis></superscript></othername>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>1</superscript>Biology Department, The Catholic University of America, Washington, DC 20064</orgname></affiliation>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>2</superscript>Biology Department, Muhlenberg College, Allentown, PA 18104</orgname></affiliation>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>3</superscript>Department of Biological Sciences, Columbia University, New York, NY 10027</orgname></affiliation></author></articleinfo>
<para><emphasis role="italic">Here for the first time, WormBook and GENETICS co-publish an article. We wish to thank Tracey DePellegrin, Ruth Isaacson, and Elizabeth De Stasio of GENETICS for their dedication to this collaboration, as well as Editor-in-Chief Mark Johnston for his support of the project.</emphasis></para>
<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Summary</emphasis></title>
<para>A little over 50 years ago, Sydney Brenner had the foresight to develop the nematode (round worm) <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> as a genetic model for understanding questions of developmental biology and neurobiology. Over time, research on <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has expanded to explore a wealth of diverse areas in modern biology including studies of the basic functions and interactions of eukaryotic cells, host-parasite interactions, and evolution. <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has also become an important organism in which to study processes that go awry in human diseases. This primer introduces the organism and the many features that make it an outstanding experimental system, including its small size, rapid life cycle, transparency, and well-annotated genome. We survey the basic anatomical features, common technical approaches, and important discoveries in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> research. Key to studying <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has been the ability to address biological problems genetically, using both forward and reverse genetics, both at the level of the entire organism and at the level of the single, identified cell. These possibilities make <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> useful not only in research laboratories, but also in the classroom where it can be used to excite students who actually can see what is happening inside live cells and tissues.</para>
</abstract>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Keywords</emphasis> <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>; nematodes; Primer; single-cell analysis; transparent genetic system</para>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>In 1963, Sydney Brenner sent a letter to Max Perutz, the chairman of the Medical Research Council&apos;s Laboratory of Molecular Biology (LMB), detailing his concerns that the &ldquo;classical problems of molecular biology have either been solved or will be solved in the next decade&rdquo; and proposing that the future of molecular biology lies in the extension to other fields, &ldquo;notably development and the nervous system&rdquo; (<link linkend="bib24">Brenner 1988</link>; <link linkend="bib25">Brenner 2002</link><!-- PMID: 12419193-->). With the simplicity and power of prokaryotic genetics in mind, he proposed that a nematode (round worm), <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis briggsae,</emphasis> would be an ideal system in which to tackle these problems. Later, he settled on the related nematode <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> as the focus of his efforts because the <emphasis role="italic">elegans</emphasis> strain grew better than the <emphasis role="italic">briggsae</emphasis> isolate in Brenner&apos;s laboratory (<link linkend="bib54">F&eacute;lix 2008</link><!-- PMID: 19014674-->). Today, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> is actively studied in over a thousand laboratories worldwide (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org">www.wormbase.org</ulink>) with over 1200 <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> research articles published each year for the last 5 years.</para>
<para><emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> is a tiny, free-living nematode found worldwide. Newly hatched larvae are 0.25 millimeters long and adults are 1 millimeter long. Their small size means that the animals are usually observed with either dissecting microscopes, which generally allow up to 100X magnification, or compound microscopes, which allow up to 1000X magnification. The dissecting microscope is used to observe worms on Petri dishes (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1, A and B</link>) as they move, eat, develop, mate, and lay eggs (for movies showing these features, see <ulink url="http://labs.bio.unc.edu/Goldstein/movies.html">http://labs.bio.unc.edu/Goldstein/movies.html</ulink>). A compound or confocal microscope allows observation at much finer resolution (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1C</link>), permitting researchers to perform experiments that address questions related to cell development and function at single-cell resolution. Because <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> is transparent, individual cells and subcellular details are easily visualized using Nomarski (differential interference contrast, DIC) optics (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1C</link>). Enhanced detail can be discerned by using fluorescent proteins to tag proteins or subcellular compartments (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1D</link>). Fluorescent proteins can also be used to study developmental processes, screen for mutants affecting cell development and function, isolate cells, and characterize protein interactions <emphasis role="italic">in vivo</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib32">Chalfie <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1994</link><!-- PMID: 8303295-->; <link linkend="bib21">Boulin <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050449-->; <link linkend="bib53">Feinberg <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2008</link><!-- PMID: 18255029-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<para><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has a rapid life cycle (3 days at 25&deg; from egg to egg-laying adult) and exists primarily as a self-fertilizing hermaphrodite, although males arise at a frequency of &lt;0.2% (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). These features have helped to make <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> a powerful model of choice for eukaryotic genetic studies. In addition, because the animal has an invariant number of somatic cells, researchers have been able to track the fate of every cell between fertilization and adulthood in live animals and to generate a complete cell lineage (<link linkend="bib168">Sulston and Horvitz 1977</link><!-- PMID: 838129-->; <link linkend="bib104">Kimble and Hirsh 1979</link><!-- PMID: 478167-->; <link linkend="bib172">Sulston <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1983</link><!-- PMID: 6684600-->). Researchers have also reconstructed the shape of all <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> cells from electron micrographs, including each of the 302 neurons of the adult hermaphrodite (<link linkend="bib188">White <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1986</link><!-- PMID: 22462104-->) and the posterior mating circuit in the adult male (<link linkend="bib94">Jarrell <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2012</link><!-- PMID: 22837521-->). These reconstructions have provided the most complete &ldquo;wiring diagrams&rdquo; of any nervous system and have helped to explain how sexual dimorphism affects neuronal circuits. Moreover, because of the invariant wild-type cell lineage and neuroanatomy of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, mutations that give rise to developmental and behavioral defects are readily identified in genetic screens. Finally, because <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> was the first multicellular organism with a complete genome sequence (<emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> Sequencing Consortium 1998<!-- PMID: 9851916-->), forward and reverse genetics have led to the molecular identification of many key genes in developmental and cell biological processes.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The experimental strengths and the similarities between the cellular and molecular processes present in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> and other animals across evolutionary time (metabolism, organelle structure and function, gene regulation, protein biology, etc.) have made <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> an excellent organism with which to study general metazoan biology. At least 38% of the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> protein-coding genes have predicted orthologs in the human genome (<link linkend="bib159">Shaye and Greenwald 2011</link><!-- PMID: 21647448-->), 60-80% of human genes have an ortholog in the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genome (<link linkend="bib96">Kaletta and Hengartner, 2006</link><!-- PMID: 16672925-->), and 40% of genes known to be associated with human diseases have clear orthologs in the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genome (<link linkend="bib40">Culetto and Satelle 2000</link><!-- PMID: 10767309-->). Thus, many discoveries in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> have relevance to the study of human health and disease.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> basics</title>
<sect2 id="sec2.1">
<title>Growth and maintenance</title>
<para><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, although often mischaracterized as a soil nematode, can most easily be isolated from rotting vegetable matter, which contains an ample supply of their bacterial food source (<link linkend="bib15">Barri&egrave;re and F&eacute;lix 2014</link><!-- PMID: 24803426-->). In the laboratory, animals are normally grown on agar plates containing a lawn of the bacterium <emphasis role="italic">Escherichia coli</emphasis>. Once the animals deplete the bacteria, they utilize their fat supply. Without food, the development of young larval stage animals is arrested. As a result of entering this stasis, animals can survive for at least a month (often starved plates can be usefully kept for up to six months at 15&deg;), and as stocks, they do not require constant feeding. Whenever healthy, growing animals are needed, a piece of the agar from the old plate can be transferred to a new plate with bacteria. The animals move to the new bacteria and resume their development.</para>
<para>Several other features greatly facilitate the maintenance of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> stocks and their experimental use. First, because <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> is a self-fertilizing hermaphrodite (see the following section), a single animal can populate a plate. Second, animal populations can be frozen for years and revived when needed. Third, the animal&apos;s small size means that many can be grown in a small space. Fourth, animals can be grown at temperatures ranging from 12&deg; to 25&deg;; their Q<subscript>10</subscript> for growth is ~2 (that is, an increase of 10&deg; speeds up growth twofold). Growth at different temperatures makes it possible to control the rate of animal development and assists in the isolation and use of temperature-sensitive mutants. Continual growth above 25&deg; is not possible because the animals become <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000688;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">sterile</ulink>. The upper temperature limit can be a problem if animals are kept on bench tops (instead of temperature-controlled incubators) in rooms that are too warm. Shorter exposures to higher temperatures are possible for heat shock experiments and to increase production of males (<link linkend="bib169">Sulston and Hodgkin 1998</link>). Fifth, animals can be synchronized by isolating newly hatched larvae or by treating gravid adults with bleach (which decontaminates by killing everything but embryos) and isolating eggs, which are resistant to bleach treatment. Sixth, to facilitate biochemical studies animals can be grown in bulk in liquid medium. &rdquo;Worm sorters&rdquo; such as the COPAS Biosorter are also available to quickly select large quantities of individual worms with desired characteristics. Finally, one does not need especially expensive equipment beyond a good dissecting microscope and a compound microscope to work with this animal. Overall, the animals are inexpensive and convenient to maintain.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2.2">
<title>Sexual forms and their importance</title>
<para>Wild-type <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has two sexual forms: self-fertilizing hermaphrodites and males (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link> and <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3, A and B</link>). The gonad of hermaphrodites forms an ovotestis that first produces haploid amoeboid sperm that are stored in the spermatheca in the L4 stage and then near adulthood the germ line switches fate to produce much larger oocytes. Essentially hermaphrodites are females whose gonads temporarily produce sperm before they produce oocytes. Hermaphrodites can produce up to 300 self-progeny that are fertilized by the stored sperm. If mated with males, hermaphrodites are capable of producing ~1000 offspring, indicating that hermaphrodite-produced sperm is a limiting factor in self-fertilization. Both sexes are diploid for the five autosomal chromosomes. The sexes differ in that hermaphrodites have two X chromosomes and males have a single X chromosome&mdash;<emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has no Y chromosome&mdash;and the genotype of males is referred to as XO. Sex is determined by the X to autosome (X:A) ratio (<link linkend="bib193">Zarkower 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050479-->). The majority of offspring produced by self-fertilization are hermaphrodites; only 0.1-0.2% of the progeny are males due to rare meiotic non-disjunction of the X chromosome. Because hermaphrodites make their own sperm, in genetic crosses self-progeny (oocytes fertilized by the hermaphrodite&apos;s sperm) need to be distinguished from cross-progeny. For example, when hermaphrodites homozygous for a recessive mutation causing a visible mutant phenotype are mated to wild-type males, the self-progeny hermaphrodites show the mutant phenotype and the cross-progeny hermaphrodites do not.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Self-fertilizing hermaphrodites provide several advantages for genetic analysis. First, self- fertilization (often referred to as selfing) simplifies maintaining stocks because a single animal can give rise to an entire population. Second, as Sydney <link linkend="bib23">Brenner (1974)</link><!-- PMID: 4366476--> has written, &ldquo;the animals are driven to homozygosity,&rdquo; <emphasis role="italic">i.e.,</emphasis> populations of hermaphrodites tend to lose heterozygotes (because hermaphrodites cannot mate with other hermaphrodites). Thus, strains that are mutagenized are essentially isogenic. Third, selfing follows the standard Mendelian rules of segregation, so a parent that is heterozygous for a recessive trait will produce the standard 1:2:1 pattern of segregation, such that 25% of the progeny will be homozygous for the mutant allele and display the autosomal recessive trait. Thus, selfing reduces greatly the effort needed to find such mutants. Fourth, mutants with neuromuscular defects that impair the ability to mate can still be maintained in the laboratory. In fact, only eleven of the 302 nerve cells of the hermaphrodite: eight <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005660#01--10" role="_blank">ADF</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005664#01--10" role="_blank">ASG</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005666#01--10" role="_blank">ASI</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005667#01--10" role="_blank">ASJ</ulink> neurons, which when killed as a group cause the animals to become dauer larvae (<link linkend="bib12">Bargmann and Horvitz 1991</link><!-- PMID: 2006412-->), the two CAN cells (<link linkend="bib61">Forrester and Garriga 1997</link><!-- PMID: 9165130-->), and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0004467#01--10" role="_blank">M4</ulink> neuron in the pharynx (<link linkend="bib6">Avery and Horvitz 1989</link><!-- PMID: 2642006-->) are known to be essential to support development to the reproductive adult stage. Fifth, the viability of even severely defective mutants and their ability to self-fertilize allows for easy screens for modifier (enhancer and suppressor) mutations. Such screens have been exceptionally useful and informative. For example, <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003001;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> nomenclature is outlined in <link linkend="box1">Box 1</link>) are defective in vulval development and components of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00274;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>/Notch signaling pathway have been identified with both suppressor and enhancer screens (<link linkend="bib70">Greenwald and Kovall 2013</link><!-- PMID: 23355521-->).</para>
<table id="box1" frame="box" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title>Box 1. <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> Nomenclature</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">Genetic nomenclature differs from species to species. Here, we describe the major terms used in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> research. A more complete description can be found at <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/about/userguide/nomenclature">http://www.wormbase.org/about/userguide/nomenclature</ulink>.</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Nomenclature at a glance</emphasis><superscript>1</superscript>:</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ZK154.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">ZK154.3</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Systematic gene identification (3<superscript>rd</superscript> ORF on cosmid <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/cds/ZK154.3#04--10" role="_blank">ZK154</ulink>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003171;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-7</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Gene name (the 7<superscript>th</superscript> &ldquo;mechanosensory abnormality&rdquo; gene named)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="italic">mec-7(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00144057;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1506</ulink>)</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Allele name (from the MRC Laboratory of Molecular Biology - <emphasis role="italic">e</emphasis>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15257;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEC-7</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Protein name (product of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003171;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-7</ulink></emphasis> gene)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000315;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Mec</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Phenotype (Mechanosensory abnormal phenotype)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00144057;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1506</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Homozygous allele</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00144057;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1506</ulink>/+</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Heterozygous allele</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/rearrangement/mnDp30#0--10" role="_blank">mnDp30</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Duplication (from the Herman Lab - <emphasis role="italic">mn</emphasis>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/rearrangement/nDf6#0--10" role="_blank">nDf6</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Deficiency/Deletion (from the Horvitz Lab - <emphasis role="italic">n</emphasis>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBTransgene00001043;class=Transgene" role="_blank">muIs35</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Integrated transgene (from the Kenyon Lab - <emphasis role="italic">mu</emphasis>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBTransgene00016364;class=Transgene" role="_blank">evEx1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Extrachromosomal transgene array (from the Culotti Lab - <emphasis role="italic">ev</emphasis>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CB3270;class=Strain" role="_blank">CB3270</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Strain name (from MRC Laboratory of Molecular Biology - CB)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="italic">mec-7p::gfp</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">GFP transcriptional fusion (using only the promoter of the gene)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003171;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-7</ulink>::gfp</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">GFP translational fusion (in which <emphasis role="italic">gfp</emphasis> is inserted in the coding sequence of the gene)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="italic">ceh-6(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00239175;class=Variation" role="_blank">pk33</ulink>::Tc1)</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Transposon (Tc1) insertion in <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000431;class=Gene" role="_blank">ceh-6</ulink></emphasis> gene</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"><superscript>1</superscript>All C. elegans gene names, allele designations, and reporter genes are written in italics. Cosmids, proteins, phenotypes, and strain names are not written in italics.</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"><emphasis role="bold">Mutation (allele) names</emphasis>: The wild-type allele of any gene is designated by an italicized plus sign, +<emphasis role="italic">.</emphasis> Mutant alleles are represented by 1-3 lowercase letters, which indicate specific laboratories, followed by a number. All gene and allele symbols are italicized, <emphasis role="italic">e.g.,</emphasis> <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006789;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143398;class=Variation" role="_blank">e678</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis role="italic">mn5</emphasis>. The homozygous genotype is represented by a single copy of the allele name (<emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143398;class=Variation" role="_blank">e678</ulink></emphasis>). A heterozygous condition is indicated with a slash, <emphasis role="italic">e.g.,</emphasis> <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143150;class=Variation" role="_blank">e364</ulink>/+</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143150;class=Variation" role="_blank">e364</ulink>/e1099.</emphasis> Chromosomal abnormalities are indicated by one or two letters after the lab code, <emphasis role="italic">e.g.,</emphasis> <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/rearrangement/mnDp30#0--10" role="_blank">mnDp30</ulink></emphasis> is a duplication, <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/rearrangement/nDf6#0--10" role="_blank">nDf6</ulink></emphasis> is a deletion (called a deficiency), and <emphasis role="italic">szT1</emphasis> is a translocation. One or two letters may be added after the allele name to indicate particular properties conveyed by the mutation <emphasis role="italic">e.g.</emphasis> temperature-sensitivity (ts), amber (am), revertant (r), dominant (d), and semidominant (sd). When a gene has more than one mutation, such as could result from the intragenic reversion of a mutant allele, both the old and new mutations are indicated, <emphasis role="italic">e.g.,</emphasis> intragenic reversion of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00144046;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1498</ulink></emphasis> could yield <emphasis role="italic">e1498<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/variation/WBVar00266549#02-45-3" role="_blank">u124</ulink>r</emphasis>.</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"><emphasis role="bold">Gene names</emphasis>: Genes are designated by 3 or 4 lower case letters, a dash, and a number (all italicized), <emphasis role="italic">e.g.</emphasis> <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003056;class=Gene" role="_blank">lon-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">ensh-1</emphasis>. To distinguish alleles of the same gene, the allele names are placed in parenthesis with no space between the gene and allele name, <emphasis role="italic">e.g.,</emphasis> <emphasis role="italic">mec-7(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143933;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1343</ulink>)</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">mec-7(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00144057;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1506</ulink>)</emphasis>. Genes that have been identified as an open reading frame (ORF) through bioinformatics approaches get a systematic gene identification (<emphasis role="italic">e.g.</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/cds/ZK154.3#04--10" role="_blank">ZK154.3</ulink>) until subsequent studies prompts them to be given a gene name. The upstream promoter region of a gene is indicated by the gene name followed by a &ldquo;p.&rdquo; The promoter and the protein-coding names are separated by two colons as are parts of fusion proteins. Thus, a gene encoding a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15257;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEC-7</ulink>::GFP translational fusion driven from the <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003171;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-7</ulink></emphasis> promoter would be <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003171;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-7</ulink>::gfp</emphasis>, whereas a <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003102;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> transcriptional fusion would be <emphasis role="italic">mab-5p::gfp</emphasis>. A transposon insertion into a gene is similarly shown using the transposon name and two colons, e.g., <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006759;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink>::Tc1</emphasis> [most <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> transposons are labeled Tc (transposon, <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis</emphasis>) and a number].</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"><emphasis role="bold">Phenotypes</emphasis>: Mutant phenotypes are designated by the non-italicized gene name without the dash and number and with the first letter capitalized, e.g., <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000643;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Unc</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000229;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Sma</ulink> animals are Uncoordinated or Small in body size.</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"><emphasis role="bold">Gene products</emphasis>: RNAs are designated by the italicized gene name; proteins are designated by the gene name in all caps and not italicized (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15257;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEC-7</ulink>). Sometimes specific amino acid changes are indicated.</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"><emphasis role="bold">Strain names</emphasis>: Two capital letters and a number, <emphasis role="italic">e.g.</emphasis> CB429 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TU38;class=Strain" role="_blank">TU38</ulink>, designate a strain containing one or more genetic differences. The letters indicate the laboratory that constructed the strain (<ulink url="http://www.cbs.umn.edu/research/resources/cgc/lab-head">http://www.cbs.umn.edu/research/resources/cgc/lab-head</ulink>). None of these symbols are italicized. Because a given strain can carry more than one mutation, strain names can be thought of as shorthand to describe animals carrying complicated genotypes. Genes (and/or alleles) in strains with several mutations are listed in chromosome and then map order with genes on the same chromosome separated by spaces and genes on different chromosomes separated by semi-colons. The italicized name of the chromosome can also be included, <emphasis role="italic">e.g.,</emphasis> <emphasis role="italic">lon-2(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143398;class=Variation" role="_blank">e678</ulink>) mec-7(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00144057;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1506</ulink>) X</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006789;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003515;class=Gene" role="_blank">myo-3</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00143150;class=Variation" role="_blank">e364</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00142944;class=Variation" role="_blank">e66</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00266506;class=Variation" role="_blank">u38</ulink>/szT1</emphasis>. <emphasis role="italic">szT1</emphasis> is one of many balancer chromosomes that are often used to maintain mutations that are <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000062;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">lethal</ulink> as homozygotes but viable as heterozygotes. For strains that contain reporter genes, there are two typical designations. The reporters are named for specific laboratories similar to mutant alleles, and they are further named according to whether the reporter gene is maintained extrachromosomally on a multicopy array using an &ldquo;Ex&rdquo; label (<emphasis role="italic">e.g. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBTransgene00016364;class=Transgene" role="_blank">evEx1</ulink>)</emphasis> or is maintained by integrating the sequence (in most cases randomly) into the genome using an &ldquo;Is&rdquo; label (<emphasis role="italic">e.g. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBTransgene00001043;class=Transgene" role="_blank">muIs35</ulink></emphasis>).</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>Males are important because they allow the exchange of genetic material needed to generate animals with different genetic compositions and to map genes. Indeed, the animal has evolved to take advantage of the genetic contribution of rare males by using male (outcross) sperm before using hermaphrodite (self) sperm (<link linkend="bib182">Ward and Carrel 1979</link><!-- PMID: 499670-->). Thus, if males are capable of mating, cross progeny prevail (to help males find hermaphrodites, researchers use Petri plates with a small spot of bacteria).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2.3">
<title>Life cycle</title>
<para><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> embryogenesis takes approximately 16 hours at 20&deg; (all of the subsequent times are also for development at 20&deg;) (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). A virtually impermeable eggshell is made after fertilization, allowing the embryo to develop completely independent of the mother. However, embryos are usually retained within the hermaphrodite until about the 24-cell stage at which time they are laid. The hermaphrodite embryo hatches with 558 nuclei (some nuclei are in multi-nuclear syncytia, so the cell count is lower) and becomes a first stage (L1) larva. The animals begin to eat and develop through four larval stages (L1-L4). The L1 stage is ~16 hr long; the other stages are ~12 hr long. Each stage ends with a sleep-like period of inactivity called lethargus (<link linkend="bib144">Raizen <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2008</link><!-- PMID: 18185515-->) in which a new cuticle (outer collagenous layer) is made. Lethargus ends with the molting of the old cuticle. Approximately 12 hr after the L4 molt, adult hermaphrodites begin producing progeny for a period of 2-3 days until they have utilized all of their self-produced sperm; additional progeny can be generated if the sperm-depleted hermaphrodite mates with a male. After the reproductive period, hermaphrodites can live several more weeks before dying of senescence.</para>
<para>When bacteria are depleted and the animals are crowded, L2 larvae activate an alternative life cycle (<link linkend="bib91">Hu 2007</link><!-- PMID: 17988074-->) and molt into an alternative L3 larval stage called the &ldquo;dauer&rdquo; larva (&ldquo;dauer&rdquo; in German means &ldquo;lasting"; the signal is actually processed by L1 animals, but its results are not seen until the so-called &ldquo;L2d&rdquo; stage; <link linkend="bib66">Golden and Riddle 1984</link><!-- PMID: 6706004-->). The dauer larva cuticle completely surrounds the animal and plugs the mouth preventing the animal from eating and thereby arresting development. The dauer cuticle has enhanced resistance to chemicals, so it provides the dauer with greater protection against environmental stresses and caustic agents. Dauer larvae can survive for many months and are the dispersal form most commonly encountered in the wild. When the dauer larvae are transferred onto plates with bacteria, they shed their mouth plugs, molt, and continue their development as slightly different L4 larvae.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genetics</title>
<para>A major reason Sydney Brenner (<link linkend="bib23">Brenner, 1974</link>)<!-- PMID: 4366476--> chose to study <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> was the ease of genetic manipulation. Self-fertilization means that after hermaphrodites (P0s) are mutagenized, any mutant alleles (except dominant lethals) can be maintained through self-propagation in first-generation (F1) progeny, second-generation (F2) progeny, etc. without mating. This property makes obtaining these progeny easy. In practice, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> researchers screen for mutations anywhere in the genome (instead of using balanced strains to mutagenize single chromosomes) in a single mutagenesis and determine linkage afterward. A second genetic advantage of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> is that it grows quickly. Since animals take ~3 days at 25&deg; (~3.5 days at 20&deg;) to develop from fertilized eggs to adults producing their own fertilized eggs, mutant homozygotes can be detected two generations (~1 week) after mutagenesis. In addition, the ability to freeze and recover <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> makes it possible to preserve mutant strains without worrying that they have acquired unwanted suppressors, other modifiers, or additional background mutations or have lost important mutations, particularly if they are maintained as heterozygotes. Therefore, much less effort needs to be devoted to strain maintenance.</para>
<para>The traditional use of genetics in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> (often referred to as &ldquo;forward genetics&rdquo;) begins with a screen or selection to find mutants with a particular phenotype followed by inference of the wild-type role of the gene from the nature of the mutant phenotype. <link linkend="bib95">Jorgensen and Mango (2002)</link><!-- PMID: 11988761-->have reviewed the many types of screens and selections used in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> to identify mutations resulting in novel phenotypes (including conditional phenotypes) and mutations that modify (either enhancing or suppressing) existing phenotypes. A variety of mutagens have been used (<link linkend="bib110">Kutscher and Shaham 2014</link><!-- PMID: 24449699-->), including ethane methylsulfonate (EMS), an alkylating reagent that causes principally GC-to-AT transition mutations and small deletions, used by Brenner in his initial studies (<link linkend="bib23">Brenner 1974</link>).</para>
<para>Once mutant strains have been obtained and shown to be true-breeding, <emphasis role="italic">i.e.,</emphasis> give mutant individuals in the next generation, they can be mapped using classical genetic tools (<link linkend="bib23">Brenner 1974</link><!-- PMID: 4366476-->). Originally, mapping involved linkage crosses to identify the chromosome containing the mutation followed by multiple three-factor crosses to refine its map position. Once a map position had been determined, the mutated gene could be identified molecularly (using the physical map of overlapping genomic clones) by transformation rescue of the mutant phenotype by the wild-type gene (<link linkend="bib52">Evans 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050410-->; <link linkend="bib127">Merritt <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2010</link><!-- PMID: 20169625-->; <link linkend="bib156">Schweinsberg and Grant 2013</link><!-- PMID: 24395815-->). Transformation requires injection of DNA into the syncytial (multi-nucleated) gonad, where it is incorporated into the nucleus of some developing gametes (<link linkend="bib126">Mello and Fire 1995</link>). Transposon-tagged mutations were also used to isolate the DNA of the mutated gene, allowing for its molecular identification (<emphasis role="italic">e.g.,</emphasis> <link linkend="bib71">Greenwald 1985</link><!-- PMID: 3000611-->). The entire process of cloning a gene could easily take a year.</para>
<para>Today, however, the process of connecting a mutant phenotype to a gene is much more rapid due to advances in whole-genome sequencing (<link linkend="bib46">Doitsidou <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2010</link><!-- PMID: 21079745-->; <link linkend="bib195">Zuryn <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2010</link><!-- PMID: 20610404-->; <link linkend="bib130">Minevich <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2012</link><!-- PMID: 23051646-->). Mutants derived from the standard wild-type strain (called <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=N2;class=Strain" role="_blank">N2</ulink>) are crossed to a wild-type strain obtained in Hawaii (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CB4856;class=Strain" role="_blank">CB4856</ulink>), whose sequence differs from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=N2;class=Strain" role="_blank">N2</ulink> at many positions [one single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) per 91 +/- 56 kb; <link linkend="bib174">Swan <emphasis role="italic">et al</emphasis>. 2002</link><!-- PMID: 12097347-->]. Mutants re-isolated after the cross have retained <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=N2;class=Strain" role="_blank">N2</ulink> sequences in the vicinity of the mutation, whereas <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=N2;class=Strain" role="_blank">N2</ulink> and Hawaiian sequences randomly segregate at other loci. Whole-genome sequencing can reveal the location of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=N2;class=Strain" role="_blank">N2</ulink> DNA and lead, hopefully, to a small number of candidate genes that can be tested as above. This process can be done in a number of weeks and, as before, transformation rescue (or complementation testing) provides evidence that the correct gene has been identified.</para>
<para>Researchers can also use a known gene sequence to obtain mutant strains, a process called &ldquo;reverse genetics&rdquo; (<link linkend="bib1">Ahringer 2006</link>). One of the first ways to do such reverse genetics was the generation of strains that deleted all or part of a target gene (<link linkend="bib113">Lesa 2006</link><!-- PMID: 17406462-->). Animals were mutagenized with trimethylpsoralen to cause deletions and large numbers of individual F2 animals were used to establish lines. Pooling DNA from these strains and amplifying the several pools of DNA with PCR primers, designed to amplify a deleted but not wild-type gene, could identify which line had a deletion mutation (a process called sibling-selection). Further selection within the line could establish a homozygous strain containing the deletion mutation.</para>
<para>Whole-genome sequencing has enabled a very rapid way of obtaining mutations. In a study dubbed the &ldquo;million mutation project&rdquo; (<link linkend="bib176">Thompson et al. 2013</link><!-- PMID: 23800452-->), animals were mutated by EMS and/or N-ethyl-N-nitrosourea (ENU) and F2 progeny (from different P0 parents) were grown. Over 2000 healthy strains were established from these mutageneses. Whole-genome sequencing of each strain showed that, on average, there were 400 mutations per strain. Altogether these strains had over 800,000 unique mutations. Since the genome contains ~20,000 genes, each gene has been mutated an average of 8 times. The results are available in WormBase and the strains can be obtained from the <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis</emphasis> Genetics Center (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). Recent advances in efficient genome-editing methods (TALEN and CRISPR/Cas9) in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> now allow investigators to create targeted mutations in nearly any location in the genome in any genetic background (<link linkend="bib64">Fr&oslash;kj&aelig;r-Jensen 2013</link><!-- PMID: 24190921-->, <link linkend="bib180">Waaijers and Boxem 2014</link><!-- PMID: 24685391-->). These gene editing techniques, particularly CRISPR/Cas9, enable rapid methods to mutate and interrogate <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genes, and new approaches based on them are being introduced<emphasis role="italic">.</emphasis></para>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title>TABLE 1 <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> resources</title>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<thead>
<row valign="bottom" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Resource</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Website Address</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">WormBase</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/">http://www.wormbase.org/</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Genes, expression, resources, phenotypes, metadata, and publications</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">WormBook</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/">http://www.wormbook.org/</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Basic information about the biology of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> and other nematodes, including methods</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">WormAtlas</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormatlas.org/">http://www.wormatlas.org/</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Worm anatomy, including neurons and wiring, EM sections, and cell lineage</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis</emphasis> Genetics Center</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="https://www.cbs.umn.edu/research/resources/cgc">https://www.cbs.umn.edu/research/resources/cgc</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Stocks of wild-type and mutant nematode strains</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">National Bioresource Project</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.shigen.nig.ac.jp/c.elegans/index.jsp">http://www.shigen.nig.ac.jp/c.elegans/index.jsp</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Collection of deletions of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genes</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">Million Mutation Project</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://genome.sfu.ca/mmp/">http://genome.sfu.ca/mmp/</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Fully sequenced genomes of strains carrying multiple mutations</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">Expression patterns database</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://gfpweb.aecom.yu.edu/index">http://gfpweb.aecom.yu.edu/index</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Expression patterns for promoter::gfp transgenes</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">TransgeneOme</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="https://transgeneome.mpi-cbg.de/transgeneomics/index.html">https://transgeneome.mpi-cbg.de/transgeneomics/index.html</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Resource for tagged gene constructs and expression patterns</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">modENCODE</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.modencode.org">www.modencode.org</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Model organism database of DNA elements</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">UCSC Genome Browser</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="https://genome.ucsc.edu/">https://genome.ucsc.edu/</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Multiple alignments of conserved nematode genome sequences</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> Interactive Network</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormweb.org/">http://www.wormweb.org/</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Interactive neuron wiring diagram and gene expression information with direct links to published supporting data</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">OpenWorm Science</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.openworm.org/">http://www.openworm.org/</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Various on-line resources for <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> research.</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> Behavioral Database</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://wormbehavior.mrc-lmb.cam.ac.uk/">http://wormbehavior.mrc-lmb.cam.ac.uk/</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Detailed traces of worm movement and posture for different strains and mutants</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis briggsae</emphasis> Research Resource</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.briggsae.org/">http://www.briggsae.org/</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Resource for research on <emphasis role="italic">C. briggsae</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">Nematode and Neglected Genomics</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.nematodes.org/">http://www.nematodes.org/</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Database of genomics for other nematode species</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">Rhabditina Taxonomy</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://128.122.60.136/fmi/iwp/cgi?-db=RhabditinaDB&amp;-loadframes">http://128.122.60.136/fmi/iwp/cgi?-db=RhabditinaDB&amp;-loadframes</ulink> or <ulink url="http://wormtails.bio.nyu.edu/Databases.html">http://wormtails.bio.nyu.edu/Databases.html</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Nematode phylogeny, morphology, literature, ecology, and geographical information</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">WormClassroom</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://wormclassroom.org/">http://wormclassroom.org/</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Resource for education using <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>Mutant-like phenotypes can also be obtained using RNA interference (RNAi), the use of double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) to reduce gene activity (<link linkend="bib59">Fire <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1998</link><!-- PMID: 9486653-->; see <link linkend="bib1">Ahringer 2006</link>). The added discovery that RNAi can be produced by soaking the animals in a solution of dsRNA (<link linkend="bib175">Tabara <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1998</link>)<!-- PMID: 9841401-->or by feeding the animals bacteria that generate specific dsRNA (<link linkend="bib177">Timmons and Fire, 1998</link>)<!-- PMID: 9804418-->means the entire genome can be easily and systematically interrogated for genes needed for specific functions. Such genome-wide screens using libraries of bacterial strains are common and easily done.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Why choose <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>?</title>
<para>In addition to being a powerful system for genetic studies, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has many inherent advantages as a model for eukaryotic biology. These features include its small size, large brood size, ease of cultivation, low maintenance expense, long-term cryopreservation, quick generation time, transparency, invariant cell number and development, and the ability to reduce gene activity using feeding RNAi. Although not usually mentioned, another favorable feature of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> is the organisms are quite benign to humans. In fact, because they cannot grow at body temperatures, they cannot grow in humans. Some nematodes, <emphasis role="italic">e.g</emphasis>., <emphasis role="italic">Ascaris suum</emphasis>, induce a debilitating allergic reaction and must be studied in ventilated hoods (<link linkend="bib100">Kennedy 2013</link>; A.O. Stretton, personal communication). As far as we are aware, allergic reactions to <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> have not been documented.</para>
<para>Studies of cell and developmental biology that use <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> are greatly aided by the transparency of the animal, which allows researchers to examine development and changes due to mutations or altered environments at the level of a single, identified cell within the context of the entire living organism. Thus, many biological problems can be studied &ldquo;in miniature&rdquo; at the single-cell level, instead of large numbers of cells in heterogeneous tissues. Transparency also enables a wealth of studies in living animals utilizing fluorescent protein reporters (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1D</link> and <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4B</link>). By labeling cells and proteins in living cells, fluorescent proteins enable genetic screens to identify mutants defective in various cellular processes. In addition, fluorescent protein-based reporters (e.g., Cameleon and gCaMP3; <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4C</link>), which fluoresce in response to calcium flux, provide neuron-specific detection of calcium flux under a fluorescent microscope, and therefore allow researchers to measure electrophysiological activity <emphasis role="italic">in vivo</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib102">Kerr 2006</link><!-- PMID: 10896155-->). Furthermore, mapping of cell-cell and synaptic contacts can be accomplished by expressing complementary fragments of GFP in different cells (GRASP; <link linkend="bib53">Feinberg <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2008</link><!-- PMID: 18255029-->). Transparency also means that optogenetic tools, which alter the activity of individual neurons, are particularly effective in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib93">Husson <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2013</link><!-- PMID: 23458457-->). In all of these experiments, greater control of the animal&apos;s position and environment can be accomplished by microfluidic devices in which individual worms are mounted in custom-designed channels allowing the application of various compounds or other agents while simultaneously monitoring fluorescent readout of gene regulation or electrophysiological activity by microscopy (<link linkend="bib116">Lockery 2007</link><!-- PMID: 17762874-->; <link linkend="bib152">San-Miguel and Lu 2013</link><!-- PMID: 24065448-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 4</phrase>
</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Sharing large amounts of genetic and cellular information has been central to the success of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> research. The wealth of knowledge generated by past research is readily available to anyone via on-line resources (see <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). Much of this information, including gene expression, gene function, and references, is curated on WormBase (www.wormbase.org). Reviews on many topics of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> biology are provided by WormBook (www.wormbook.org), which includes a collection of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> methods (WormMethods) and current and past issues of the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> Newsletter (<emphasis role="italic">The Worm Breeder&apos;s Gazette</emphasis>).</para>
<para>No model organism can be used to answer every research question, and working with <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has some limitations. Not all metazoan genes are found in the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genome (<link linkend="bib150">Ruvkun and Hobert 1998</link><!-- PMID: 9851920-->). For example, Hedgehog (Hh) signaling is important in vertebrates for the patterning of various organs during development, but <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> lacks many of the genes in the regulatory cascade (<link linkend="bib26">B&uuml;rglin and Kuwabara 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050469-->). Although some <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> cells can be studied <emphasis role="italic">in vitro</emphasis> [<emphasis role="italic">e.g.,</emphasis> embryonic glial cells, larval muscle, and neuronal cells (<link linkend="bib194">Zhang <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2011</link><!-- PMID: 21559335-->; <link linkend="bib167">Stout and Parpura 2012</link><!-- PMID: 22144307-->)], no <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> cell culture lines exist. The small size of the animal and its cells also provides a challenge since experimental manipulation in individual tissues of an organism that is less than a millimeter long is difficult. Electrophysiology of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neurons and muscle is possible, but demanding (<link linkend="bib143">Raizen and Avery 1994</link><!-- PMID: 8155316-->; <link linkend="bib117">Lockery and Goodman 1998</link><!-- PMID: 19322241--> <link linkend="bib38">Cook <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050442-->; <link linkend="bib148">Richmond 2006</link>)<!-- PMID: 18050434-->and indirect measurements of neuronal activity, such as calcium imaging are often used instead (<link linkend="bib103">Kerr 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050440-->). Finally, biochemical approaches in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> have lagged behind the genetic approaches, but the development of an axenic culture medium for <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> (<emphasis role="italic">e.g.,</emphasis> <link linkend="bib145">Rao <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2005</link>)<!-- PMID: 15767563-->has meant that biochemical studies can be done on animals under defined conditions.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> tissues</title>
<para>One attractive feature of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> is that despite its simplicity, it has defined tissues. The animal is often described as a series of concentric tubes (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3C</link>). The outer layer of cells, the epidermis (traditionally called the hypodermis) encloses a pseudocoelomic fluid-filled cavity housing the main organ systems. Just inside the epidermis are the bands of muscle, which control movement of the organism, as well as the ventral and dorsal nerve cords that innervate the muscles. Inside the neuro-muscular region are the digestive, excretory, and reproductive systems. In addition, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has six cells in the pseudocoelomic cavity, called coelomocytes, which act as scavengers in the body cavity (<link linkend="bib69">Grant and Sato, 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050485-->). These cells behave similarly to vertebrate macrophages (although they have a fixed position within the animal), are highly active in endocytosis, and are thought to sort through and clear material in the pseudocoelomic cavity of the animal. More extensive descriptions of these systems with beautiful electron micrographs of the various cell types can be found in WormAtlas (www.wormatlas.org). Here, we will cover some of the basic aspects of the anatomy, particularly with respect to how the organ systems are advancing the understanding of cell and developmental biology.</para>
<sect2 id="sec5.1">
<title>Epidermis: a model for extracellular matrix production, wound healing, and cell fusion</title>
<para>The outer epithelial layer, the epidermis, of the embryo undergoes a series of cell fusions to make large multinucleate, or syncytial, epidermal cells. These cells secrete the cuticle, a protective layer of specialized extracellular matrix (ECM) consisting primarily of collagen, lipids, and glycoproteins (<link linkend="bib34">Chisholm and Hardin 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050408-->; <link linkend="bib136">Page and Johnstone 2007</link><!-- PMID: 18050497-->). The cuticle determines the shape of the body and, through connection from the epidermis to muscle, provides anchoring points for muscle contraction (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5A</link>). The cuticle also serves as a model for ECM formation and function with molecules and pathways involved in cuticle biogenesis conserved in vertebrates (<link linkend="bib136">Page and Johnstone 2007</link><!-- PMID: 18050497-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 5</phrase>
</textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Mutations in several genes needed for cuticle formation produce visible phenotypes (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>). Mutations in collagen genes can result in animals that move in a corkscrew fashion [the Roller (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00005018;class=Gene" role="_blank">Rol</ulink>) phenotype] or that have normal width but reduced length [the Dumpy (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000583;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink>) phenotype]. Other mutations affect the struts formed between layers of the adult cuticle, resulting in fluid-filled blisters [the Blister (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000025;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Bli</ulink>) phenotype]. Still other mutations make the animals longer than normal [the Long (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000022;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Lon</ulink>) phenotype]. At the end of each larval stage (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>), <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> sheds its cuticle and secretes a new one to accommodate the growing organism. Genes involved in cuticle formation are regulated so that the cuticle is reestablished after each molt.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig6" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 6</phrase>
</textobject> &fig6legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Studying the epidermis has led to insights in early cell movements, wound healing, cell-cell fusions, and the establishment of epithelial layers in developing embryos (<link linkend="bib34">Chisholm and Hardin 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050408-->; <link linkend="bib139">Podbilewicz 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050486-->). As the &ldquo;skin&rdquo; of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans,</emphasis> the epidermis is a model for the innate immune response to pathogens and for repair after a physical wound such as a needle puncture. The wounded epidermis upregulates both Ca<superscript>++</superscript> signaling to direct actin polymerization for repair and innate immune signaling pathways to help promote survival after injury (<link linkend="bib190">Xu <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2012</link><!-- PMID: 24058838-->). The cell-cell fusion events leading to the multinucleate epidermis and genes important for this process have been studied (<link linkend="bib139">Podbilewicz 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050486-->). This work has supported the idea that repression of fusion in some cells may be just as important for proper development as activation of cell fusion in other cells (<link linkend="bib139">Podbilewicz 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050486-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5.2">
<title>Muscles&mdash;controlling animal movement</title>
<para>Just interior and connected to the epidermis are four quadrants (95 cells) of body-wall muscles that run along the length of the body (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). The regular contraction and relaxation of the muscle cells leads to the &ldquo;elegant&rdquo; sinusoidal movement of the animal. These somatic muscles are striated (although, unusually, they are obliquely striated) and mononucleate (muscle cells do not fuse as they do in vertebrates) with multiple sarcomeres per cell (<link linkend="bib131">Moerman and Fire 1997</link>). The innervation of these muscles is also unusual in that the muscle cells send extensions (&ldquo;muscle arms&rdquo;) to the ventral and dorsal cord to receive <emphasis role="italic">en passant</emphasis> synapses from the motor neurons instead of the more usual case of receiving axonal projections from motor neurons (<link linkend="bib188">White <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1986</link><!-- PMID: 22462104-->; <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5D</link>).</para>
<para>Genetic studies of muscle led to the first cloning and sequencing of a myosin gene (<emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006789;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis>; <link linkend="bib120">MacLeod <emphasis role="italic">et al</emphasis>. 1981</link><!-- PMID: 6264304-->), and this finding provided major insights into the structure of all myosins. <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006789;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis> and many other <emphasis role="italic">unc</emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000643;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">uncoordinated</ulink>) genes encoding proteins needed for muscle activity produce a &ldquo;floppy paralytic&rdquo; phenotype (<link linkend="bib86">Hodgkin 1983</link><!-- PMID: 17246100-->). The study of the assembly of sarcomeres into functional muscles and, in particular, the proteins mediating attachment to the plasma membrane has revealed many molecules in common with vertebrate focal adhesion complexes (<link linkend="bib132">Moerman and Williams 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050483-->). Genetic screens designed to understand molecules involved in muscle contraction have also led to insights regarding muscle-wasting diseases such as Duchenne&apos;s Muscular Dystrophy (<link linkend="bib33">Chamberlain and Benian 2000</link>)<!-- PMID: 11084353-->and cardiomyopathies (<link linkend="bib17">Benian and Epstein 2011</link><!-- PMID: 21998299-->). In addition to the body-wall muscle, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has muscles that control eating (pharyngeal muscles), egg-laying (vulval and uterine muscles and the contractile gonad sheath), mating (male-specific tail muscles), and defecation (enteric muscles).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5.3">
<title>The digestive system&mdash;a model for organogenesis and pathogenesis</title>
<para>Food (bacteria) enters the anterior of the animals and passes through the pharynx, a two-lobed neuromuscular pump that grinds the food before it is passed on to the intestine for digestion (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5C</link>; <link linkend="bib7">Avery and You 2012</link><!-- PMID: 22628186-->). The pumping behavior of the animals depends on the availability and the quality of the food; for example, animals pump more when hungry and less when full (<link linkend="bib8">Avery and Shtonda 2003</link><!-- PMID: 12796460-->). Studying pharyngeal development has been a model for organogenesis, including how epithelial morphogenesis and cell-fate specification occur during development (<link linkend="bib121">Mango 2007</link><!-- PMID: 18050503-->). For example, the transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15998;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHA-4</ulink> plays a major regulatory role in the organ identity of the pharynx (<link linkend="bib122">Mango <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1994</link><!-- PMID: 7607089-->). Animals defective in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15998;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHA-4</ulink> function do not contain a pharynx and embryos that overexpress <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15998;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHA-4</ulink> have more pharyngeal cells (<link linkend="bib121">Mango 2007</link><!-- PMID: 18050503-->). The vertebrate FoxA transcription factors are homologous to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15998;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHA-4</ulink> and are involved in gut development in many species (<link linkend="bib28">Carlsson and Mahlapuu 2002</link><!-- PMID: 12297093-->).</para>
<para>The <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> intestine is attached to the posterior pharynx and consists of 20 large, polyploid epithelial cells arranged in pairs that form a tube running the length of the animal. Intestinal development has been studied in detail (<link linkend="bib124">McGhee 2007</link><!-- PMID: 18050495-->). Presumably to handle the increasing demands of the growing animal, the intestinal cells undergo one round of nuclear division during the first larval stage and subsequent rounds of DNA replication, but not nuclear division, in the later larval stages (<link linkend="bib78">Hedgecock and White 1985</link><!-- PMID: 2578115-->). <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has served as a model to study infection and response to infection by several different bacterial pathogens, microsporidia, and viruses that colonize the digestive system (<link linkend="bib43">Darby 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050390-->; <link linkend="bib10">Balla and Troemel 2013</link><!-- PMID: 23617769-->; <link linkend="bib45">Diogo and Bratanich 2014</link><!-- PMID: 25000902-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5.4">
<title>The nervous system&mdash;small yet complex</title>
<para><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has become an important model for the study of neurobiological questions. Researchers have identified genes and mechanisms needed for neuronal generation and specification, cell death, precursor migration, synapse formation, chemosensory and mechanosensory transduction, neuronal degeneration, neurite regeneration, and glial function (<link linkend="bib48">Driscoll and Chalfie 1992</link><!-- PMID: 1374952-->; <link linkend="bib160">Silhankova and Korswagen 2007</link><!-- PMID: 17644372-->; <link linkend="bib74">Hammarlund and Jin 2014</link><!-- PMID: 24794753-->; <link linkend="bib158">Shaham, 2015</link><!-- PMID: 25573712-->). Researchers also have investigated a variety of behaviors, both simple and complex, including chemotaxis, thermotaxis, several responses to touch, male-specific mating rituals, social feeding, and both associative and non-associative learning (<link linkend="bib13">Bargmann 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050433-->; <link linkend="bib76">Hart 2006</link>; <link linkend="bib14">Barr and Garcia 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050467-->; <link linkend="bib4">Ardiel and Rankin 2010</link><!-- PMID: 20335372-->; <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4E</link>). <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> also experiences periods of restful inactivity that are similar to aspects of mammalian sleep (<link linkend="bib144">Raizen <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2008</link><!-- PMID: 18185515-->).</para>
<para>The nervous system of the adult hermaphrodite has 302 neurons (<link linkend="bib168">Sulston and Horvitz 1977</link><!-- PMID: 838129-->; <link linkend="bib188">White <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1986</link><!-- PMID: 22462104-->); that of the adult male has 383 neurons (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>; WormAtlas.org). The majority of neuronal cell bodies are arranged in a few ganglia in the head, in the ventral cord, and in the tail (the specialized male tail has the majority of the extra neurons). Most of the neurons have a simple structure with one or two neurites (or processes) exiting from the cell body, but a few cells, such as the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006828#01--10" role="_blank">FLP</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PVD;class=Cell" role="_blank">PVD</ulink> mechanosensory neurons, have elaborately branched neurites (<link linkend="bib47">Dong <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2013</link><!-- PMID: 24120131-->). Except for sensory dendrites, which are often easy to identify, most neurites cannot be distinguished as axons or dendrites because they both give and receive synapses (although they are often referred to as &ldquo;axons&rdquo;). The neurites form synapses to each other in four major areas: the nerve ring (which encircles the pharynx), the ventral nerve cord, the dorsal nerve cord, and the neuropil of the tail. In addition to neurons, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has several glia-like support cells, which are primarily associated with sensory neurons, but are not as numerous as in vertebrates (Oikonomou and Shaham 2010<!-- PMID: 21732423-->).</para>
<para>Nerve conduction in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> appears to be primarily passive. No sodium-dependent action potentials have been detected in neurons (<link linkend="bib68">Goodman <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1998</link>)<!-- PMID: 9581767-->and the genome has no genes for voltage-gated sodium channels (<link linkend="bib11">Bargmann 1998</link><!-- PMID: 9851919-->). The absence of action potentials may be due to the very high membrane resistance. Indeed, many neurons are essentially isopotential; changes in voltage are experienced virtually instantaneously by the entire cell (<link linkend="bib68">Goodman <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1998</link><!-- PMID: 9581767-->), so action potentials may not be necessary (<link linkend="bib117">Lockery and Goodman 2009</link><!-- PMID: 19322241-->). Neurons express a wide variety of ion channels (<link linkend="bib85">Hobert 2013</link><!-- PMID: 24081909-->), including an unexpectedly large number of genes encoding potassium channels (<link linkend="bib151">Salkoff <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050399-->).</para>
<para><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neurons make more than 7000 chemical synapses and gap junction connections (<link linkend="bib188">White <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1986</link><!-- PMID: 22462104-->). Unlike in vertebrate nervous systems, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neurons do not send terminal branches with boutons to make synapses. Most of the connections are made <emphasis role="italic">en passant</emphasis> (side by side as neurites pass each other), although many bilaterally symmetrical neurons join their tips together with gap junctions at the midline and some motor neurons similarly join with homologues end to end. Nematodes are unusual in that motor neurons do not send processes that synapse onto muscle; instead muscles send cellular projections to motor neurons to receive synapses. Chemical synapses are identified in electron micrographs by presynaptic darkening and synaptic vesicles; postsynaptic specializations are not obvious (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4D</link>). <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> uses many of the most common neurotransmitters, including acetylcholine, glutamate, &gamma;-amino butyric acid (GABA), dopamine, and serotonin and has several receptors for their detection (<link linkend="bib85">Hobert 2013</link><!-- PMID: 24081909-->). Gap junctions are detected in electron micrographs as parallel membranes in the closely apposed neurons. As with other invertebrates, gap junctions are formed from innexins (<link linkend="bib165">Starich <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2001</link><!-- PMID: 12064609-->). In addition to the chemical synaptic and gap junction connections, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neurons are modulated by numerous neuroendocrine signals (<link linkend="bib115">Li and Kim, 2008</link><!-- PMID: 18819171-->). From the perspective of cellular and molecular detail, most of the problems of neurobiology can be studied in the worm.</para>
<para>In <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, some individual neurons perform functions that would be performed by multiple neurons in vertebrates. For example, individual olfactory neurons express multiple G protein-coupled odorant receptors (<link linkend="bib178">Troemel <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1995</link><!-- PMID: 7585938-->; <link linkend="bib185">Wes and Bargmann 2001</link><!-- PMID: 11287957-->), rather than a single receptor as in vertebrates; each of the two mirror image bilateral ASE chemosensory cells respond to several different ions (<link linkend="bib84">Hobert 2010</link><!-- PMID: 20891032-->); and the connectivity of the touch receptor neurons suggests that their stimulation initiates several different activities (<link linkend="bib31">Chalfie <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1985</link><!-- PMID: 3981252-->). Thus, functions of multiple vertebrate sensory neurons are compressed into a single neuron in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. This multi-functionality (or &ldquo;polymodality&rdquo;) may be an evolutionary consequence of the small number of neurons in the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> nervous system. Alternatively, multi-functionality may reflect a general feature of nervous systems that was revealed by the ability to do detailed single-cell analyses with this animal.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5.5">
<title>Reproductive tissue&mdash;sex-specific anatomy</title>
<para>The <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> sexes display several obvious anatomical differences in the somatic gonad, secondary sexual structures, and body size (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>. <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>, A and B). The somatic gonad is located in the center of the body alongside the intestine. In hermaphrodites the gonad consists of two mirror-image U-shaped tubes; in males the gonad consists of a single U-shaped lobe (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). Both gonads house the germline where the oocytes and sperm develop (<link linkend="bib92">Hubbard and Greenstein 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050415-->). The somatic gonad and the germline develop together during larval stages until animals reach maturity at the young adult stage. A powerful advantage for studies of the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> germline is that one can observe all stages of meiosis at once as the germline is a visible gradient of development (<link linkend="bib92">Hubbard and Greenstein 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050415-->; <link linkend="bib106">Kimble and Crittenden 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050413-->; <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5B</link>). Studying the germline has been a model for meiosis, gamete development, fertilization, stem cell biology, and even tumor formation (<link linkend="bib106">Kimble and Crittenden 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050413-->).</para>
<para>Secondary sexual mating structures are the vulva in hermaphrodites and the fan-shaped tail in males (<link linkend="bib51">Emmons 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050419-->; <link linkend="bib83">Herman 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050480-->). The vulva develops in the center of the epidermis on the ventral side of the hermaphrodite and is the conduit for sperm entry from the male and egg laying from the uterus (<link linkend="bib166">Sternberg 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050418-->). Studying vulval morphogenesis has provided insights into signaling by the Notch, EGF, and Wnt pathways that coordinate the spatiotemporal development of the organ. Defects in these pathways can lead to animals with no vulva [the egg-laying defective (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000640;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Egl</ulink>) phenotype] or with many vulval-like protrusions [the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000700;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">multivulva</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000700;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Muv</ulink>) phenotype; <link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>]. In many cases these animals cannot lay eggs (or mate), and their progeny develop internally, hatch within the hermaphrodite, and create the &ldquo;bag-of-worms&rdquo; phenotype whereby the larvae consume the mother (a process called endotokia matricidia). This phenotype, which also occurs when wild-type adult hermaphrodites are starved, has been used to identify numerous egg-laying defective mutants. For example, details of Ras GTPase/Map Kinase signaling have been elucidated through the identification of mutants in enhancer/suppressor screens of vulval phenotypes (<link linkend="bib173">Sundaram 2013</link><!-- PMID: 23908058-->).</para>
<para>Adult males are thinner than hermaphrodites (due to their smaller gonad and the absence of developing embryos), and their tails are flattened into a fan of cuticular material with 18 projections of neurons and associated support cells called rays (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3B</link>). As with vulval development, the development of male tail structures and their associated muscles involves the coordinated action of multiple signaling pathways (<link linkend="bib51">Emmons 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050419-->). Interestingly, the same signaling pathways are used in both males and hermaphrodites in the development of reproductive tissues (<emphasis role="italic">e.g.,</emphasis> Wnt signaling), yet these pathways produce very different sex-specific organs and structures (<link linkend="bib51">Emmons 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050419-->).</para>
<para>The outward morphology of males and hermaphrodites is determined by a regulatory cascade that controls the transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28130;class=Protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib193">Zarkower 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050479-->). The activity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28130;class=Protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> depends on the X to autosome (or X:A) ratio. In males, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28130;class=Protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> is inactive and leads to male fate and the production of sperm. In hermaphrodites, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28130;class=Protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> is active and leads to a female somatic fate and the formation of female gametes. <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> also has a dosage compensation system that down-regulates expression of genes on the X-chromosome in hermaphrodites to equalize X-linked expression between the sexes. A sex-specific dosage compensation complex, analogous to the chromatin condensin complex used in mitosis and meiosis, decorates the X chromosomes in hermaphrodites and down-regulates X-linked genes by 50% to equal the gene expression from the single X chromosome in males (<link linkend="bib128">Meyer 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050416-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>The <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genome</title>
<para><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> was the first multicellular eukaryotic organism to have its genome sequenced (<emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> Sequencing Consortium, 1998<!-- PMID: 9851916-->). As sequence information from additional <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species as well as more distantly-related nematodes has become available in the past decade, the information from <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has provided the basis for rich comparative genomics studies (<link linkend="bib35">Coghlan 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050393-->). The entire <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genome is 100 Mb (<emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> Sequencing Consortium, 1998)<!-- PMID: 9851916-->and has 20,444 protein-coding genes (WormBase release WS245, Oct. 2014). Both <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> sexes contain five autosomal chromosomes named linkage group (LG ) I, II, III, IV, and V and the X chromosome. Individual genes of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> are arranged in conventional eukaryotic fashion with 5&rsquo; untranslated regions, open reading frames (ORFs) containing exons and introns, and 3&rsquo; untranslated regions. Compared to vertebrate genes, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genes are relatively small with the average gene size of 3 kb due primarily to the presence of very small introns (<link linkend="bib164">Spieth and Lawson 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18023127-->; <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genes also have many normal-sized introns). The chromosomes do not contain traditional centromeres; during mitosis the microtubule spindle attaches to more than one position along the chromosome (these attachments are said to be holocentric or polycentric). In fact, a specific sequence does not seem to be required for attachment since extrachromosomal DNA-containing transgenes can be inherited throughout many cell divisions.</para>
<para>The <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genome has two unusual aspects: most protein-coding mRNAs are <emphasis role="italic">trans</emphasis>-spliced and some genes are organized in operons (<link linkend="bib20">Blumenthal 2005</link><!-- PMID: 23175478-->). <emphasis role="italic">Trans</emphasis>-splicing is the addition of one of two 22-nucleotide leader sequences (SL1 and SL2) at the 5&rsquo; end of mRNA. The leader sequence is believed to aid in translational initiation and, because SL1/2 sequences are known, can be used experimentally to identify the sequence at the 5&rsquo; end of mRNAs. Some <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> mRNAs are formed from multigenic transcripts with the first mRNA spliced to SL1 and subsequent mRNAs to SL2. The genes that code for these transcripts are closely spaced together in tandem and are transcribed under the control of a single promoter. These transcripts are similar to those produced by bacterial operons and code for gene products that are co-expressed (<link linkend="bib20">Blumenthal 2005</link><!-- PMID: 23175478-->). They differ, however, in that the processed transcripts in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> generate multiple mRNAs. Past experiments have indicated that DNA is not methylated in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans,</emphasis> but recent, higher resolution studies have suggested that some methylation does occur (<link linkend="bib90">Hu <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2015</link><!-- PMID: 25299492-->). Aspects of gene regulation such as transcription, translation, chromatin remodeling, and post-transcriptional modifications (ubiquitination, phosphorylation, histone methylation, glycosylation) have all been studied using the genetic tools of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title><emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis</emphasis> ecology and evolution</title>
<para>In the wild, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> is primarily restricted to temperate regions. In contrast, related species such as <emphasis role="italic">C. briggsae</emphasis>, are considered &ldquo;cosmopolitan&rdquo; since they are found in many habitats (<link linkend="bib109">Kiontke and Sudhaus 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050394-->). Although often mischaracterized as a soil nematode<emphasis role="italic">,</emphasis> larval and adult <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> have been routinely recovered from organic-rich garden soils, compost, and rotting fruit and plant stems, and only rarely from &ldquo;wild&rdquo; soil (<link linkend="bib18">Blaxter and Denver 2012</link><!-- PMID: 22731915-->; <link linkend="bib55">F&eacute;lix and Duveau 2012</link><!-- PMID: 22731941-->). Compost-like locations are likely to be attractive to the animals because they are abundant in the bacterial food the animals need. Outside of rotting fruits and stems, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> are usually found as dauer larvae, the dispersal form of the animal. Dauer larvae are unusual in that they engage in &ldquo;nictating&rdquo; behavior, wherein they stand on their tails and wave their heads in the air (<link linkend="bib111">Lee <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2011</link><!-- PMID: 22081161-->). This activity is thought to aid in attachment of the dauer larva to other invertebrate couriers, such as isopods, so the nematode can be dispersed from a depleted food source to a new food source (<link linkend="bib39">Croll and Matthews, 1977</link>). Recent work on nematode ecology has included studies on wild population structures and competition between <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species (<link linkend="bib55">F&eacute;lix and Duveau 2012</link>)<!-- PMID: 22731941-->and the effect of the richness of the bacterial biomass on nematode growth (<link linkend="bib42">Darby and Herman, 2014</link><!-- PMID: 24453006-->). In addition, <link linkend="bib146">Rechavi <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> (2014)</link><!-- PMID: 25018105-->recently demonstrated that starvation in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> leads to an upregulation of small RNAs that target nutrition genes and are inherited by multiple generations (&ldquo;transgenerational inheritance&rdquo;) providing a mechanism for memory of past environmental conditions.</para>
<para><emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and other nematodes belong to the phylum Nematoda, which is part of a larger group of the clade Ecdysozoa (<link linkend="figure7">Figure 7A</link>; <link linkend="bib22">Bourlat <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2008</link><!-- PMID: 18692145-->). This clade contains organisms that shed a cuticle by molting (or ecdysis) (<link linkend="bib22">Bourlat <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2008</link><!-- PMID: 18692145-->). Therefore, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> are more related to <emphasis role="italic">Drosophila</emphasis> and other insects than to mollusks, earthworms, or humans. The <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis</emphasis> genus is included in the order Rhabditida, itself part of the larger subclass Chromadoria (<link linkend="bib44">De Ley 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050465-->). While all known <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species are free-living, the Rhabditidae include animal and plant parasites, as well as free-living species that exist in a variety of terrestrial and aquatic ecosystems (<link linkend="bib108">Kiontke and Fitch 2005</link><!-- PMID: 19643102-->). As the ecology of <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis</emphasis> is increasingly better understood, more species have been identified (<link linkend="figure7">Figure 7B</link>; <link linkend="bib57">F&eacute;lix <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2014</link><!-- PMID: 24727800-->). <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has served as a rich starting place for comparative evolutionary studies among species. For example, developmental biologists use related nematode species to explore the changes in regulatory pathways and organogenesis that occur during evolution (<link linkend="bib162">Sommer 2005</link>)<!-- PMID: 18050392-->and the frequent independent evolution of hermaphroditism (<link linkend="figure7">Figure 7B</link>; <link linkend="bib9">Baldi <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2009</link><!-- PMID: 19965511-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure7" xreflabel="Figure 7">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig7" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 7</phrase>
</textobject> &fig7legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The evolutionary relationship between <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> and parasitic nematode species has prompted research questions with direct human health relevance. Nematode parasites of humans cause major health problems, especially in less-developed nations. These parasites include hookworm and other soil-transmitted helminths that cause malnutrition and obstructive bowel disease, filarial nematodes such as <emphasis role="italic">Onchocerca volvulus</emphasis>, which causes river blindness, and <emphasis role="italic">Brugia malayi</emphasis>, which causes lymphatic filariasis (elephantiasis; <link linkend="bib19">Blaxter 1998</link><!-- PMID: 9851921-->). Plant parasitic nematodes cause significant crop damage (billions of dollars each year; <link linkend="bib98">Kandoth and Mitchum 2013</link>)<!-- PMID: 23890967-->and animal parasites devastate domesticated animals (including heartworm in dogs and cats; <link linkend="bib123">McCall <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2008</link><!-- PMID: 18486691-->). <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has played a critical role in elucidating the mode of action of anthelmintic drugs (<link linkend="bib89">Holden-Dye and Walker 2014</link><!-- PMID: 25517625-->). <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> may also prove useful in identifying new strategies to reduce or alleviate the action of parasitic nematodes, particularly since the emergence of resistance to current drugs (<link linkend="bib89">Holden-Dye and Walker 2014</link><!-- PMID: 25517625-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>Brief history of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> research and key discoveries</title>
<para>In Brenner&apos;s original vision, detailed elucidation of the development and anatomy of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> would serve as the foundation for the subsequent analysis of mutants. Both of these efforts were completed primarily at the LMB. The transparency of the animal allowed John Sulston, Robert Horvitz, Judith Kimble, David Hirsh, and Einhard Schierenberg to describe every cell division starting with the single-celled zygote and ending with the adult male and hermaphrodite (<link linkend="bib168">Sulston and Horvitz 1977</link><!-- PMID: 838129-->; <link linkend="bib104">Kimble and Hirsh 1979</link><!-- PMID: 478167-->; <link linkend="bib171">Sulston <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1980</link><!-- PMID: 7409314-->; <link linkend="bib172">1983</link><!-- PMID: 6684600-->). These efforts produced the first and only entire cell lineage of any multicellular organism. During this same time, John White, Sydney Brenner, Donna Albertson, Eileen Southgate, Sam Ward, and Nichol Thomson described the anatomy and connectivity of all 302 neurons of the adult hermaphrodite (<link linkend="bib183">Ward <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1975</link><!-- PMID: 1112927-->; <link linkend="bib2">Albertson and Thomson 1976</link><!-- PMID: 8805-->; <link linkend="bib187">White <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1976</link><!-- PMID: 8806-->; <link linkend="bib188">1986</link><!-- PMID: 22462104-->). These projects set a standard for completeness in the understanding of the animal that has been a hallmark of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> research. Such completeness was also seen in the sequencing of the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genome (<emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> Genome Consortium, 1998<!-- PMID: 9851916-->), the description of the wiring diagram of the adult male (<link linkend="bib94">Jarrell <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2012</link><!-- PMID: 22837521-->), and development of genome-wide feeding RNAi experiments (<link linkend="bib62">Fraser <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2000</link><!-- PMID: 11099033-->; <link linkend="bib97">Kamath <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2001</link><!-- PMID: 11178279-->). Sydney Brenner, Robert Horvitz, and John Sulston were awarded the 2002 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine in part for the significance of the lineage project as a platform for discovery of genes that orchestrated developmental decisions.</para>
<para>Since work on <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genetics began in earnest during the 1970s, this animal has proven fruitful for making general discoveries about cell and developmental biology (<link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>). These findings have helped us understand molecular genetic mechanisms in all animals. Evolution has maintained thousands of conserved genes that play similar, or in some cases nearly identical, functions in nematodes and other animals including humans (<link linkend="bib29">Carroll <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2004</link>). For example, the vertebrate apoptosis regulator Bcl-2 can functionally substitute for its <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000423;class=Gene" role="_blank">ced-9</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib82">Hengartner and Horvitz 1994</link><!-- PMID: 7907274-->). Thus, discoveries with direct relevance to understanding all animals were made possible by what initially appeared to be an ambitious and esoteric undertaking to define in detail the structure and genetics of an apparently simple animal.</para>
<table id="table2" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title>TABLE 2 Selected discoveries in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> research</title>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<thead>
<row valign="bottom" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Year</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Discovery</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">References</emphasis></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1974</entry>
<entry align="center">Identification of mutations that affect animal behavior</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib23">Brenner 1974</link><!-- PMID: 4366476-->; <link linkend="bib49">Dusenberry <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1975</link><!-- PMID: 1132687-->; <link linkend="bib76">Hart 2006</link></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1975</entry>
<entry align="center">First description of mutations that affect thermotaxis and mechanotransduction</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib77">Hedgecock and Russell 1975</link><!-- PMID: 1060088-->; <link linkend="bib168">Sulston <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1975</link><!-- PMID: 240872-->; <link linkend="bib30">Chalfie and Sulston 1981</link><!-- PMID: 7227647-->; <link linkend="bib133">Mori and Ohshima 1995</link>,<!-- PMID: 7630402--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1977</entry>
<entry align="center">First cloning and sequencing of a myosin gene</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib119">Macleod <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1977</link><!-- PMID: 909083--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1977</entry>
<entry align="center">Genetic pathways for sex determination and dosage compensation described</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib88">Hodgkin and Brenner 1977</link><!-- PMID: 560330-->; <link linkend="bib128">Meyer 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050416-->; <link linkend="bib193">Zarkower 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050479--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1981</entry>
<entry align="center">Identification of mutations affecting touch sensitivity</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib168">Sulston <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1975</link><!-- PMID: 240872-->; <link linkend="bib30">Chalfie and Sulston 1981</link><!-- PMID: 7227647--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1981</entry>
<entry align="center">First germline stem cell niche identified</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib105">Kimble and White 1981</link><!-- PMID: 7202837-->; <link linkend="bib106">Kimble and Crittenden 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050413--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1983</entry>
<entry align="center">Notch signaling, presenilins, ternary complex, and lateral inhibition roles in development described</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib72">Greenwald <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1983</link><!-- PMID: 6616618-->; <link linkend="bib114">Levitan and Greenwald 1995</link><!-- PMID: 7566091-->; <link linkend="bib138">Petcherski and Kimble 2000</link><!-- PMID: 10830967-->; <link linkend="bib70">Greenwald and Kovall 2012</link><!-- PMID: 23355521--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1983</entry>
<entry align="center">First complete metazoan cell lineage</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib168">Sulston and Horvitz 1977</link><!-- PMID: 838129-->; <link linkend="bib104">Kimble and Hirsh 1979</link><!-- PMID: 478167-->; <link linkend="bib172">Sulston <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1983</link><!-- PMID: 6684600--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1983</entry>
<entry align="center">Discovery of apoptosis (cell death) genes</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib79">Hedgecock <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1983</link><!-- PMID: 6857247-->; <link linkend="bib50">Ellis and Horvitz 1986</link><!-- PMID: 3955651-->; <link linkend="bib191">Yuan and Horvitz 1992</link><!-- PMID: 1286611-->; <link linkend="bib192">Yuan <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1993</link><!-- PMID: 8242740-->; <link linkend="bib37">Conradt and Xue 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18061982--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1984</entry>
<entry align="center">Identification of heterochronic genes</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib3">Ambros and Horvitz 1984</link><!-- PMID: 6494891-->; <link linkend="bib161">Slack and Ruvkun 1997</link><!-- PMID: 9442909--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1986</entry>
<entry align="center">First complete wiring diagram of a nervous system</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib188">White <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1986</link><!-- PMID: 22462104-->; <link linkend="bib94">Jarrell <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2012</link><!-- PMID: 22837521-->; <link linkend="bib186">White 2013</link><!-- PMID: 23801597--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1987</entry>
<entry align="center">Discovery of the first axon guidance genes</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib80">Hedgecock <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1987</link>, <link linkend="bib81">1990</link><!-- PMID: 3308403--><!-- PMID: 2310575-->; <link linkend="bib41">Culotti 1994</link><!-- PMID: 7950328--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1987</entry>
<entry align="center">Identification of role of Notch signaling in embryonic blastomeres</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib141">Priess <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1987</link><!-- PMID: 3677169-->; <link linkend="bib140">Priess 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050407--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1988</entry>
<entry align="center">Discovery of <emphasis role="italic">par</emphasis> genes, whose products affect the asymmetric distribution of cellular components in embryos</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib99">Kemphues <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1988</link><!-- PMID: 3345562-->; <link linkend="bib67">G&ouml;nczy and Rose 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050411--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1988</entry>
<entry align="center">Identification of the first LIM and POU homeodomain transcription factors</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib184">Way and Chalfie 1988</link><!-- PMID: 2898300-->; <link linkend="bib58">Finney <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1988</link><!-- PMID: 2903797-->; <link linkend="bib85">Hobert 2013</link><!-- PMID: 24081909--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1990</entry>
<entry align="center">First description of a role for RAS signaling function in metazoan development</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib16">Beitel <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1990</link><!-- PMID: 2123303-->; <link linkend="bib75">Han and Sternberg 1990</link><!-- PMID: 2257629-->; <link linkend="bib166">Sternberg 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050418-->; <link linkend="bib173">Sundaram 2013</link><!-- PMID: 23908058--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1993</entry>
<entry align="center">Demonstration of a role for insulin pathway genes in regulating lifespan</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib63">Friedman and Johnson 1988</link><!-- PMID: 8608934-->; <link linkend="bib101">Kenyon <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1993</link><!-- PMID: 8247153-->; <link linkend="bib107">Kimura <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1997</link><!-- PMID: 9252323-->; <link linkend="bib36">Collins <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2007</link><!-- PMID: 18381800--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1993</entry>
<entry align="center">Identification of genes for conserved synaptic functions</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib65">Gengyo-Ando <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1993</link><!-- PMID: 8398155-->; <link linkend="bib147">Richmond <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1999</link><!-- PMID: 10526333-->; <link linkend="bib148">Richmond 2007</link><!-- PMID: 18050398--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1993</entry>
<entry align="center">First microRNA (<emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002993;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-4</ulink></emphasis>) and its mRNA target <emphasis role="italic">(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003003;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-14</ulink>)</emphasis> described</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib112">Lee <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1993</link><!-- PMID: 8252621-->; <link linkend="bib189">Wightman <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1993</link> <link linkend="bib179">Vella and Slack 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050425--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1993</entry>
<entry align="center">Identification of nonsense-mediated decay genes</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib142">Pulak and Anderson 1993</link><!-- PMID: 8104846-->; <link linkend="bib87">Hodgkin 2005b</link><!-- PMID: 18023120--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1994</entry>
<entry align="center">Introduction of GFP as a biological marker</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib32">Chalfie <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1994</link><!-- PMID: 8303295-->; <link linkend="bib21">Boulin <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050449--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1994</entry>
<entry align="center">First demonstration of specific olfactory receptor/ligand pair</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib157">Sengupta <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1994</link><!-- PMID: 8001144-->; <link linkend="bib13">Bargmann 2006</link><!-- PMID: 18050433--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1998</entry>
<entry align="center">First metazoan genome sequenced</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib27"><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> Sequencing Consortium 1998</link><!-- PMID: 9851916-->; <link linkend="bib155">Schwarz 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18023117--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">1998</entry>
<entry align="center">Discovery of RNA interference (RNAi)</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib59">Fire <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1998</link><!-- PMID: 9486653--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">2000</entry>
<entry align="center">Conservation and ubiquity of miRNAs</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib137">Pasquinelli <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2000</link><!-- PMID: 11081512--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">2000</entry>
<entry align="center">Development of genome-wide RNAi screening/first full genome-wide profiling of gene function</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib62">Fraser <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2000</link><!-- PMID: 11099033-->; <link linkend="bib97">Kamath <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2001</link><!-- PMID: 11178279--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">2000</entry>
<entry align="center">Transgenerational inheritance and its mediation by piRNA</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib73">Grishok <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2000</link><!-- PMID: 10741970-->; <link linkend="bib5">Ashe <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2012</link><!-- PMID: 22738725--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">2002</entry>
<entry align="center">First cytoplasmic polyA polymerase (<emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001596;class=Gene" role="_blank">gld-2</ulink></emphasis>) discovered</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib181">Wang <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2002</link><!-- PMID: 12239571-->; <link linkend="bib106">Kimble and Crittenden 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050413--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">2005</entry>
<entry align="center">First full-genome RNAi profiling of early embryogenesis</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib163">S&ouml;nnichsen <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2005</link><!-- PMID: 15791247--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">2005</entry>
<entry align="center">First use of channelrhodopsin optogenetics in an intact animal</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib134">Nagel <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 2005</link><!-- PMID: 16360690--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center">2011</entry>
<entry align="center">Discovery of first nematode viruses</entry>
<entry align="center"><link linkend="bib56">F&eacute;lix <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis>, 2011</link><!-- PMID: 21283608--></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>Genetic screens in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> have yielded a number of first discoveries of genes and pathways that play important roles in all animals. These discoveries include key genes regulating apoptosis (programmed cell death) (<link linkend="bib79">Hedgecock <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1983</link><!-- PMID: 6857247-->; <link linkend="bib50">Ellis and Horvitz 1986</link><!-- PMID: 3955651-->), the Ras and Notch signaling pathways (<link linkend="bib140">Priess 2005</link><!-- PMID: 18050407-->; <link linkend="bib70">Greenwald and Kovall 2013</link><!-- PMID: 23355521-->; <link linkend="bib173">Sundaram 2013</link><!-- PMID: 23908058-->), synaptic function (<link linkend="bib65">Gengyo-Ando <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1993</link><!-- PMID: 8398155-->; <link linkend="bib147">Richmond <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1999</link><!-- PMID: 10526333-->), axon pathfinding (<link linkend="bib76">Hedgecock <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1987</link><!-- PMID: 3308403-->; <link linkend="bib81">1990</link><!-- PMID: 2310575-->), longevity (<link linkend="bib101">Kenyon <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1993</link><!-- PMID: 8247153-->; <link linkend="bib107">Kimura <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1997</link><!-- PMID: 9252323-->), and developmental timing (the heterochronic genes) (<link linkend="bib3">Ambros and Horvitz 1984</link><!-- PMID: 6494891-->). The study of the heterochronic genes yielded the first small regulatory RNA, the microRNA (miRNA) product of the <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002993;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-4</ulink></emphasis> gene (<link linkend="bib112">Lee <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1993</link><!-- PMID: 8252621-->). Robert Horvitz&apos;s 2002 Nobel Prize was awarded in part to recognize the broad significance of the genetic mechanisms of apoptosis, and Gary Ruvkun and Victor Ambros shared the 2008 Albert Lasker Award for Basic Medical Research in recognition of the general importance of miRNA.</para>
<para><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> researchers also made important technical discoveries that were subsequently adapted and applied to other biological systems. For example, early gene-cloning efforts helped advance techniques for defining and assembling overlapping (contiguous) clones from animal genomes, which led to <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> being the first metazoan to have its entire genome sequenced in 1998 (<emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> Genome Consortium, 1998<!-- PMID: 9851916-->). Some of these strategies were also employed in early human genome sequencing efforts. Another discovery that led to a novel technique with broad biological impact was gene silencing by RNA interference (RNAi) (<link linkend="bib59">Fire <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1998</link><!-- PMID: 9486653-->). This powerful technique allows researchers working with many organisms to silence the expression of any gene and earned Andrew Fire and Craig Mello the 2006 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine (<link linkend="bib60">Fire 2007</link><!-- PMID: 17722137-->; <link linkend="bib125">Mello 2007</link><!-- PMID: 17712806-->). Finally, the development of green fluorescent protein (GFP) as a biological marker (<link linkend="bib32">Chalfie <emphasis role="italic">et al</emphasis>. 1994</link>)<!-- PMID: 8303295-->for which Marty Chalfie shared the 2008 Nobel Prize in Chemistry grew directly from his interest in characterizing gene expression in live (and transparent) <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. Now GFP and other fluorescent proteins are widely used biological tools.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec9">
<title>The <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> community</title>
<para>Having mentioned all the biological reasons that <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> provides outstanding opportunities to study biological questions and all the achievements that past studies have accomplished, we would be remiss if we did not mention one other reason why the field has flourished: the community of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> researchers. Our field has had a long tradition of openness and sharing of reagents and ideas. This openness was first encouraged by the publication of the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> newsletter, <emphasis role="italic">The Worm Breeder&apos;s Gazette</emphasis>. The <emphasis role="italic">Gazette</emphasis> was started by Bob Edgar at the University of California, Santa Cruz so <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> researchers could tell each other about their research. Often work was described in the <emphasis role="italic">Gazette</emphasis> many months before it was officially published. For example, the first description of GFP as a biological marker (in the October, 1993 issue of the <emphasis role="italic">Gazette</emphasis>) preceded the &ldquo;official&rdquo; publication by 5 months (<link linkend="bib32">Chalfie <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1994</link><!-- PMID: 8303295-->). The <emphasis role="italic">Gazette</emphasis>, now entirely online, is published as part of WormBook and is an excellent resource for new methods and helpful hints to aid <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> research.</para>
<para>The second person to greatly support and promote a community spirit among <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> researchers was John Sulston. When John began determining the physical map of the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genome with Alan Coulson, one of his goals was to promote sharing. He did this by not having any independent research of his own (taking away even a hint that he might be a competitor) and by providing a service whereby any researcher could get large amounts of DNA on either side of a cloned fragment or in the region of a mapped gene. As a result, researchers did not hoard their DNA before publication and investigators benefited by having clones of entire genes. The mapping project was able to link the physical (DNA) and genetic (recombination) maps. Consequently, several collaborations were initiated because scientists shared their data before publication (<emphasis role="italic">e.g.,</emphasis> <link linkend="bib153">Savage <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1989</link><!-- PMID: 2744465-->; <link linkend="bib129">Miller <emphasis role="italic">et al.</emphasis> 1992</link><!-- PMID: 1347150-->). As the mapping project turned to the sequencing of the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genome, John made sure that the openness continued; results of the sequencing project were made available daily. This same approach was used when John and Alan along with Bob Waterston and many others turned to sequencing the human genome.</para>
<para>A field with many thousands of researchers cannot be as closely associated as in the early days when virtually all researchers knew one another because they were Sydney Brenner&apos;s F1s and F2 progeny. Nonetheless, the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> field continues to share resources and information. The many free online resources (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>), the <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis</emphasis> Genetics Center, and the many large, community projects (<emphasis role="italic">e.g.,</emphasis> ModEncode Project, National Bioresource Project for the Experimental Animal <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> Gene Knockout Consortium) show that the sharing spirit continues. This spirit and the general enthusiasm of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> researchers are also evident at the biennial <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> and the many alternate-year special topics and local meetings. <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has also proven a useful system for undergraduate and even high school education. The field continues to grow and to share.</para>
<para>Looking to the future, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> will continue to be an important source of scientific discoveries. Many of the reasons for past successes will aid future research, especially the ability to look at individual cells within the context of the entire animal. Soon genome editing should generate loss-of-function alleles and transcriptionally and translationally-tagged reporters for every gene in the genome allowing structure/function studies of all the genes and their encoded products. In addition, analysis of the ever-increasing collection of regulatory RNAs certainly will add to our understanding of the development and adaptability of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. Continued use of optogenetics on larger and larger sets of neurons and the analysis of the functional expression of neurotransmitters, neuropeptides, and their receptors and of gap junction proteins is likely to produce the first integrated view of the working of a complete nervous system. Investigations using <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> promise to generate insights into new areas, such as host-pathogen interactions, synthetic biology, and ecology. Finally, we are confident that new and unexpected discoveries made in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, as they have done so often in the past, will change our views of how organisms develop, live, and age. We invite you to join us to be part of this exciting future.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec10">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>We would like to thank the following individuals for helpful discussions and manuscript improvements: Oliver Hobert, Jonathan Hodgkin, Beth De Stasio, Eric Haag, Andy Golden, and members of the WormBook Editorial Board. We also thank Christopher Crocker and David Hall for the original illustration files that were modified in <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>. Research in M.C.&rsquo;s laboratory is supported by National Institutes of Health (NIH) grant GM30997, in B.W.&rsquo;s laboratory by NIH grant R15GM107799, and in A.K.C.'s laboratory by past grants from the National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research at NIH.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec11">
<title>Literature cited</title>
<para/>
&celegansintro_ref;
</sect1>
</article>