<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'transposonsfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'transposonsfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'transposonsfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'transposonsfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'transposonsfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'transposonsfig3leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY transposons_Refs SYSTEM 'transposonsrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="transposons_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Transposons in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
            <footnote>
                <para>Edited by Jonathan Hodgkin and Philip Anderson. Last revised April 5, 2005. Published January 18, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Bessereau, J.-L. Transposons in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (January 18, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.70.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 Jean-Louis Bessereau. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
            </footnote>
        </title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 4/5/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory> 
-->
        <author>
            <firstname>Jean-Louis</firstname>
            <surname>Bessereau<remark>
                    <footnote>
                        <para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:jlbesse@biologie.ens.fr">jlbesse@biologie.ens.fr</ulink></para>
                    </footnote>
                </remark>
            </surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>ENS, Biologie Cellulaire de la Synapse, Paris, F-75005 France; Inserm, U497, Paris, F-75005 France</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Transposons are discrete segments of DNA capable of moving through the genome of their
            host via an RNA intermediate in the case of class I retrotransposon or via a
            "cut-and-paste" mechanism for class II DNA transposons. Since transposons take advantage
            of their host's cellular machinery to proliferate in the genome and enter new hosts,
            transposable elements can be viewed as parasitic or "selfish DNA". However, transposons
            may have been beneficial for their hosts as genome evolution drivers, thus providing an
            example of molecular mutualism. Interactions between transposon and</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C.
            elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">research were undoubtedly mutualistic, leading to the advent of
            needed genomic tools to drive</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">research while providing
            insights into the transposition field. Tc1, the first</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis>
            <emphasis role="bold">transposon to be identified, turned out to be the founding member of a widespread family
            of mobile elements: the Tc1/</emphasis><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">mariner</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">superfamily. The investigation
            into transposition regulation in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">has uncovered an
            unforeseen link between transposition, genome surveillance and RNA interference.
            Conversely, transposons were utilized soon after their identification to inactivate and
            clone genes, providing some of the first molecular identities of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C.
            elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">genes. Recent results suggest that transposons might provide a means
            to engineer site-directed mutations into the</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">genome.
            This article describes the different transposons present in the</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C.
            elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">genome with a specific emphasis on the ones that proved to be mobile
            under laboratory conditions. Mechanisms and control of transposition are discussed
            briefly. Some tools based on the use of transposons for</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis>
            <emphasis role="bold">research are presented at the end of this review.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
        <sect1>
        <title>
            <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> transposons, the catalog</title>
        <para>Analysis of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome sequence indicates that
            approximately 12 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
            genome is derived from transposable elements (<link linkend="bib17"><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Sequencing Consortium, 1998<!--; PMID 9851916--></link>; <link linkend="bib76">Sijen and Plasterk, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14628056-->; <link linkend="bib77">Stein et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14624247-->). However, most of these
            sequences are fossil remnants that are no longer mobile but can be used by molecular archeologists to trace back the interactions between parasitic "selfish DNA" (<link linkend="bib62">Orgel and Crick, 1980</link>) and a host genome (for review see <link linkend="bib8">Brookfield, 2005</link>; <link linkend="bib40">Kazazian, 2004</link>). In this section, I will mostly
            describe elements that can transpose under laboratory conditions (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). Other elements will be mentioned only briefly.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig1" align="center" width="6.5in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> Transposable elements figure 1</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
        <sect2>
            <title>The Tc1 and Tc3 transposons</title>
            <para>Tc1 and Tc3 are the most active and best characterized transposons in <emphasis>C.
                elegans</emphasis>. The article of Anderson, Emmons and Moerman (1992) describes how
                circulating information between laboratories conducting simultaneous molecular and
                genetics approaches lead to the identification of the first transposable element in
                    <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, Tc1. Tc1 was isolated as a repeated sequence
                responsible for polymorphism among different strains (<link linkend="bib25">Emmons et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6297788-->; <link linkend="bib50">Liao et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6304721-->; <link linkend="bib70">Rosenzweig et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6306578-->).
                Analysis of spontaneous and reversible mutations of the myosin heavy-chain
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-54" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis> demonstrated the mobile nature of Tc1 (<link linkend="bib22">Eide and Anderson, 1985</link><!--; PMID 2984668-->; <link linkend="bib23">Eide and Anderson, 1988</link><!--; PMID 2832734-->). This feature
                was used to clone another muscle gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-22" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink></emphasis> by transposon
                tagging (<link linkend="bib56">Moerman et al., 1986</link><!--; PMID 3010313-->; <link linkend="bib57">Moerman and Waterston, 1984</link><!--; PMID 6096205-->). The subsequent characterization of additional spontaneous <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-22" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink></emphasis> mutations
                lead to the identification of Tc3 (<link linkend="bib13">Collins et al., 1989</link><!--; PMID 2537252-->).</para>
            <para>Tc1 is 1,610 bp long and contains two 54-bp terminal inverted repeats (TIRs; <link linkend="bib70">Rosenzweig et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6306578-->). Tc3 is an element of 2,335 bp with 462 bp
                TIRs. The genome of the Bristol N2 strain contains 31 and 22 copies of Tc1 and Tc3,
                respectively (<link linkend="bib27">Fischer et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12750326-->). These numbers are strain
                dependent. In some strain isolates such as Bergerac, Tc1 transposition is active in
                the germ line and each haploid genome contains up to 300-500 Tc1 copies (<link linkend="bib21">Egilmez et al., 1995</link><!--; PMID 7769614-->; <link linkend="bib25">Emmons et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6297788-->; <link linkend="bib50">Liao et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6304721-->).</para>
            <para>Tc1 and Tc3 are part of a superfamily of transposable elements which is named
                after its two best-studied members: Tc1 and the related transposon
                <emphasis>mariner</emphasis> which was identified in 1986 in <emphasis>Drosophila
                mauritiana</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib38">Jacobson et al., 1986</link><!--; PMID 3022302-->).
                Tc1/<emphasis>mariner</emphasis> elements are probably the most widespread DNA
                transposons in nature and can be found in fungi, plants, ciliates and animals
                including ecdysozoans and vertebrates (for review see <link linkend="bib65">Plasterk et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10431195-->). These transposons are about 1,300-2,400 bp in length, are flanked at
                either end by TIR and contain a single open reading frame that encodes a transposase
                enzyme. Tc1/<emphasis>mariner</emphasis> transposases all contain a triad of acidic
                residues (DDE or DDD) with a characteristic spacing which is shared by a superfamily
                of endonucleases (review in <link linkend="bib36">Haren et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10547692-->, see below). Primary
                sequence conservation of the Tc1/<emphasis>mariner</emphasis> transposases is
                relatively low (about 15 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> identity
                among the superfamily) but phylogenetic analysis suggests that all
                Tc1/<emphasis>mariner</emphasis> were derived from a common ancestor and might all
                transpose through similar mechanisms.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Other active transposons</title>
            <para>The Tc2 element was initially identified as a polymorphism marker (<link linkend="bib48">Levitt and Emmons, 1989</link><!--; PMID 2541437-->). It is 2,074 bp in length and has perfect terminal
                inverted repeats of 24 bp (<link linkend="bib74">Ruvolo et al., 1992</link><!--; PMID 1312336-->). There are 4
                full-length Tc2 copies in the N2 genome, each flanked by a TA dinucleotide at either
                end. In addition, up to 300 copies of remnant Tc2 elements have been detected in the
                genome (<link linkend="bib20">Duret et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11102365-->). Although not tested experimentally, gene
                prediction algorithms suggest that Tc2 encodes a 477 aa protein containing a DNA
                binding domain and a catalytic domain related to the DDE endonuclease superfamily.
                Transposition of Tc2 has been documented in the offspring of interstrain crosses
                between Bristol N2 and Bergerac BO or in a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mut-2" role="_blank">mut-2</ulink></emphasis> background
                (<link linkend="bib29">Francis et al., 1995</link><!--; PMID 7713419-->; <link linkend="bib48">Levitt and Emmons, 1989</link><!--; PMID 2541437-->).</para>
            <para>The first Tc4 element was identified as a mutagenic insertion in the gene
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-86" role="_blank">unc-86</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib96">Yuan et al., 1991</link><!--; PMID 1849651-->). It is a fold-back
                element of 1.6 kb which contains almost perfect terminal inverted repeats of 774 bp
                with a 57-bp unique internal sequence. No open reading frame can be detected within
                Tc4. Five such Tc4 copies are present in N2 Bristol. A variant class of Tc4 (Tc4v, 5
                copies in the N2 genome) contains a 2,343 bp sequence which replaces 477 bp in one
                of the inverted repeats (<link linkend="bib49">Li and Shaw, 1993</link><!--; PMID 8382791-->). A transcript from Tc4v
                has been detected. It may encode a 537-aa protein which resembles transposases of
                the DDE superfamily. Tc4v might provide in <emphasis>trans</emphasis> the transposase required to
                mobilize all Tc4 elements. These elements duplicate a 3-bp target sequence TNA upon
                integration and are mobile in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mut-2" role="_blank">mut-2</ulink> </emphasis> (<link linkend="bib96">Yuan et al., 1991</link><!--; PMID 1849651-->) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mut-7" role="_blank">mut-7</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib42">Ketting et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10535732-->)
                <emphasis>mutator</emphasis> (<emphasis>mut</emphasis>) backgrounds.</para>
            <para>The Tc5 element is present in four copies per haploid genome (<link linkend="bib15">Collins and Anderson, 1994</link><!--; PMID 8088523-->). It is 3,171 bp long and has 491 bp long terminal
                inverted repeats. Tc5 and Tc4v share common features. Tc5 encodes a putative 532
                amino acid transposase which is overall 33 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> identical to the Tc4v transposase, Tc4 and
                Tc5 TIRs share a few short nucleotide sequences, and integration of Tc5 causes
                duplication of the same TNA trinucleotide sequence. Tc5 elements are mobile only in
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mut-2" role="_blank">mut-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib15">Collins and Anderson, 1994</link><!--; PMID 8088523-->) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mut-7" role="_blank">mut-7</ulink></emphasis>
                (<link linkend="bib42">Ketting et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10535732-->) backgrounds.</para>
            <para>Tc7 is a 921 bp element that uses the Tc1A transposase for transposition
                (<link linkend="bib67">Rezsohazy et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9321656-->). It is made up of two 345 bp inverted repeats
                separated by a unique sequence that does not contain an ORF. 36 of the 38 outer bp
                of Tc7 are identical to the ones of Tc1. Forced expression of Tc1A in somatic cells
                causes transposition of Tc7. Furthermore, Tc7 is mobile in the germ line in the same
                backgrounds as Tc1 such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mut-6" role="_blank">mut-6</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mut-7" role="_blank">mut-7</ulink></emphasis>
                lines.</para>
            <para>CemaT1 elements were identified in a genome search as a clade of transposons
                intermediate between <emphasis>mariner</emphasis> and Tc1 (<link linkend="bib12">Claudianos et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12446802-->). They are 1,281 bp long and are flanked by two perfect 26 bp inverted
                repeats. 12 copies are present per haploid genome, of which 8 contain a single ORF
                encoding a putative 336 amino acid transposase. These elements can be excised in
                somatic cells and might possibly transpose in the germ line of TR403 strains
                (<link linkend="bib10">Brownlie and Whyard, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15302406-->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Transposons with no detected activity:</title>
            <para>The genome of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> contains several class II
                transposons that are not mobile under laboratory conditions. Tc3-CeIIa and CeIIb
                are closely related to Tc3 (<link linkend="bib83">Tu and Shao, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11814685-->), Tc6 is a fold-back
                element (<link linkend="bib18">Dreyfus and Emmons, 1991</link><!--; PMID 1674369-->; <link linkend="bib19">Dreyfus and Gelfand, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10449100-->), Tc8 is related to the plant Tourist transposon (<link linkend="bib47">Le et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11454757-->), Tc9 and Tc10 are related to Tc4(v) (<link linkend="bib27">Fischer et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12750326-->),
                and the <emphasis>mariner</emphasis>-like element <emphasis>mle-1</emphasis> is more
                closely related to the fly <emphasis>mariner</emphasis> elements than to the
                    <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Tc1 (<link linkend="bib69">Robertson and Lampe, 1995</link><!--; PMID 7476131-->;
                <link linkend="bib75">Sedensky et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 8202377-->). In addition, up to 2 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
                genome is made up from MITEs (miniature inverted-repeat transposable elements).
                MITEs are small non-autonomous elements that derive from transposons and are
                identified based on the presence of target site duplications and terminal inverted
                repeats (<link linkend="bib60">Oosumi et al., 1995</link><!--; PMID 7568037-->; <link linkend="bib61">Oosumi et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8660424-->;
                <link linkend="bib78">Surzycki and Belknap, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10618403-->).</para>
            <para>The genome of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> also contains class I
                retrotransposons. These elements are subclassified into Long Terminal Repeat (LTR)
                retrotransposons that resemble retroviruses but usually lack the gene encoding the
                envelop protein and non-LTR retrotransposons. 124 sequences derived from
                <emphasis>Cer</emphasis> LTR retrotransposons, including 20 full-length elements,
                have been identified in the genome sequence of N2 (<link linkend="bib6">Bowen and McDonald, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10523521-->; <link linkend="bib7">Britten, 1995</link><!--; PMID 7530364-->; <link linkend="bib28">Frame et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11223261-->; <link linkend="bib32">Ganko et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11731497-->). They can be grouped in 19 families related either to the
                <emphasis>gypsy</emphasis> or <emphasis>Bel</emphasis> clades of retrotransposons. These LTR retrotransposons constitute 0.4
                    <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of the <emphasis>C.
                elegans</emphasis> genome (<link linkend="bib31">Ganko et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12885961-->). A thousand sequences
                derived from non-LTR retrotransposons can be detected in the genome and grouped into
                the 4 families: <emphasis>Rte</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib95">Youngman et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8603714-->),
                <emphasis>NeSL</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib53">Malik and Eickbush, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10628980-->),
                <emphasis>Sam</emphasis> and <emphasis>Frodo</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib54">Marin et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 12572603-->). These elements only constitute 0.2 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
                genome (<link linkend="bib97">Zagrobelny et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15087124-->) suggesting that retrotransposons
                have been altogether strongly counterselected in this compact genome as compared to
                other species such as <emphasis>Homo sapiens</emphasis> in which more than 40
                    <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of the genome is composed of
                retroelement sequences. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome contains full
                length LTR and non-LTR elements but no retrotransposition events have been
                documented so far under laboratory conditions.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Mechanisms of Tc1 and Tc3 transposition</title>
        <para>Tc1/<emphasis>mariner</emphasis> transposons move via a "cut-and-paste" mechanism:
            transposase binds the TIRs, catalyses excision and subsequent reinsertion into target
            DNA in a TA dinucleotide and leaves behind a double-strand DNA break which is repaired
            by the cellular machinery.</para>
        <para>The Tc1A transposase is the only factor required in trans to mediate Tc1
            transposition: forced expression of Tc1A in Bristol N2 enhances somatic transposition of
            Tc1 (<link linkend="bib91">Vos et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8391505-->) and recombinant transposase purified from <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis>
            is capable of performing the entire transposition reaction <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis>
            (<link linkend="bib89">Vos et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8598301-->). Similar evidence has been obtained for the Tc3A
            transposase (<link linkend="bib84">van Luenen et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8389698-->; <link linkend="bib85">van Luenen et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7954797-->). The Tc1A and Tc3A transposases are 343 and 329 acid long, respectively. They
            contain a bipartite N-terminal DNA-binding domain similar to the paired domains found in
            some transcription factors (<link linkend="bib86">van Pouderoyen et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9312061-->; <link linkend="bib92">Watkins et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15304566-->). This domain binds in a sequence-specific manner to bases located
            at the terminal part of the inverted repeats (position 7 to 26 in Tc1; <link linkend="bib16">Colloms et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7838706-->; <link linkend="bib90">Vos and Plasterk, 1994</link><!--; PMID 7813449-->; <link linkend="bib91">Vos et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8391505-->). A non-specific DNA-binding domain located in more C-terminal regions of the
            transposase might interact with the first four bases of the TIR and the flanking TA
            dinucleotide, thus bringing the catalytic domain of the transposase in close proximity
            to the cleavage site.</para>
        <para>Tc1A and Tc3A share a common catalytic triad of acidic residues with transposases and
            integrases and also with more distant enzymes that promote phosphoryltransfer reactions
            such as RNaseH (for review, see <link linkend="bib36">Haren et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10547692-->). In these proteins
            the D,DX<emphasis role="underline">35</emphasis>E motif (two aspartates and a glutamate 35 residues away) was shown to be part
            of a catalytic pocket in which the acidic residues coordinate one or two magnesium or
            manganese ions that play a key role during transesterification reactions. Mutation of
            any of the DDE residues in Tc1A or Tc3A inactivate the transposase activity (<link linkend="bib85">van Luenen
            et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7954797-->; <link linkend="bib90">Vos and Plasterk, 1994</link><!--; PMID 7813449-->). Terminal inverted
            repeats are necessary and sufficient <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> and <emphasis>in
            vivo</emphasis> for transposition as long as transposase is provided in
            <emphasis>trans</emphasis>. Within the TIRs, the first four bases of the transposon and
            the transposase binding sites located immediately downstream are strictly required for
            excision (<link linkend="bib85">van Luenen et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7954797-->; <link linkend="bib90">Vos and Plasterk, 1994</link><!--; PMID 7813449-->).
            However, an element only containing the 26 terminal nucleotides of Tc1 is mobilized
                <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> ten times less efficiently than an element with full
            length TIRs (<link linkend="bib89">Vos et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8598301-->), suggesting that the transposase binding
            sites contained in this terminal fragment are not sufficient for fully efficient
            transposition. First, additional internal sequence might be required in
            <emphasis>cis</emphasis>. Second, the distance between the two TIRs might be important
            since insertion of foreign DNA into Tc1 causes an exponential decrease of transposition
            frequency (<link linkend="bib26">Fischer et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10517322-->). A similar phenomenon has been described
            in related transposons such as <emphasis>Sleeping Beauty</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib37">Izsvak et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10964563-->), <emphasis>Himar1</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib46">Lampe et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9584095-->) and
            <emphasis>Mos1</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib51">Lohe and Hartl, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11861558-->) but its molecular basis
            is not known.</para>
        <para>Transposon excision results from a pair of double-strand breaks at the ends of the
            inverted repeats (<xref linkend="figure2"/>). Coordination of cleavage at the ends of a
            transposon is presumably mediated by the formation of a "synaptic complex" in which the
            two transposon ends on the same molecule are brought together via transposase-mediated
            oligomerization. In Tc1 and Tc3, the 5' end is cleaved two bases from the end of the
            transposon and the 3' cut occurs at the junction of the transposon with the flanking
            DNA, resulting in a two-base pair 3'-hydroxyl overhang at each termini. Following
            excision, the transposon then integrates 5' of a thymidine nucleotide at a TA target
            sequence using the free 3' hydroxyl as a nucleophile. Repair of the resulting
            single-strand gaps causes a duplication of the TA dinucleotide at each transposon end.
            In vitro experiments demonstrated that the transposase was sufficient to catalyze
            excision and insertion reactions (<link linkend="bib45">Lampe et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8895590-->; <link linkend="bib82">Tosi and Beverley, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10637331-->; <link linkend="bib89">Vos et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8598301-->). However,
            Tc1/<emphasis>mariner</emphasis> transposases can interact with cellular factors such as
            the DNA-bending protein HMGB1 which might affect the efficiency of transposition
                <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib98">Zayed et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12711676-->).</para>
    <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata entityref="fig2" align="center" width="3.5in"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
            <phrase> Transposon excision figure 2</phrase>
        </textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Transposon insertion target</title>
        <para>Tc1, Tc3 and Tc7 always integrate into the TA sequence and Tc4 and Tc5 integrate into
            TNA sites. Since intron sequences are AT-rich, this may explain why such elements have a
            higher probability of inserting into introns rather than into coding sequences (<link linkend="bib55">Martin et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12242258-->). However, all TA dinucleotides do not represent equivalent
            targets. First, the difference between insertion "hot spots" and "cold spots" depends on
            the target sequence since <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> transposition using naked DNA
            and purified Tc1A transposase mostly recapitulates Tc1 insertion preferences (<link linkend="bib41">Ketting et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9321655-->; <link linkend="bib89">Vos et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8598301-->). The comparison of Tc1 and Tc3
            insertion sites reveals a weak consensus limited to 4 nucleotides on each side
            suggesting that the transposase interacts directly with the TA dinucleotide and less
            specifically with surrounding bases. Second, there are regional differences in insertion
            preferences. For example, the gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-22" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink></emphasis> is hit about a 100 times
            more frequently than <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-54" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis> although its coding sequence is only
            3.5 times larger (<link linkend="bib22">Eide and Anderson, 1985</link><!--; PMID 2984668-->; <link linkend="bib57">Moerman and Waterston, 1984</link><!--; PMID 6096205-->). Part of these differences might arise from the fact that transposons such
            as Tc1 have a preference for local reinsertion into the same chromosome from which they
            were excised (<link linkend="bib27">Fischer et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12750326-->). However, <emphasis>Mos1</emphasis>,
            a <emphasis>drosophila</emphasis> transposon from the Tc1/<emphasis>mariner</emphasis>
            family was recently mobilized in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> from an
            extrachromosomal array (<link linkend="bib5">Bessereau et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11544527-->). Analysis of random
            insertions indicates the presence of a 4 kb hot-spot at the right end of chromosome I
            which cannot be explained by local transposition (<link linkend="bib33">Granger et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15310838-->).
            Third, transposon sequences are not evenly distributed in the genome and a correlation
            has been observed between the density of DNA transposons but not retrotransposons and
            the regions of higher chromosomal recombination rate (<link linkend="bib20">Duret et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11102365-->;
            <link linkend="bib68">Rizzon et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14668370-->). Whether these two features are mechanistically
            linked or indirectly reflect another parameter such as differences in chromatin
            structure remains to be established.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Repair of the excision site</title>
        <para>Upon excision, Tc1/<emphasis>mariner</emphasis> transposons leave behind a DNA double
            strand break. Such breaks are repaired by the cellular machinery using two general types
            of repair: non homologous end joining (NHEJ) and repair by homologous recombination (for
            a review on DSB repair, see <link linkend="bib35">Haber, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10827453-->; <xref linkend="figure3"/>).
            The decision to use one or another mechanism depends on tissue type and cell-cycle
            stage. During NHEJ, DNA ends are joined after little or no trimming. Since Tc1 and Tc3
            excision leaves behind the duplicated TA and non complementary two nucleotide 5'
            overhangs, NHEJ generates short footprints ranging from 4 base pair insertion with TA
            duplications to a few base pair deletion. Occasionally, wild type sequence can be
            regenerated at the site of excision. NHEJ is active in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
            somatic cells but is also used in the germ line (<link linkend="bib23">Eide and Anderson, 1988</link><!--; PMID 2832734-->;
            <link linkend="bib24">Emmons and Yesner, 1984</link><!--; PMID 6321037-->; <link linkend="bib25">Emmons et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6297788-->; <link linkend="bib63">Plasterk, 1991</link><!--; PMID 1646714-->; <link linkend="bib71">Ruan and Emmons, 1987</link><!--; PMID 2821484-->; <link linkend="bib85">van Luenen et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7954797-->).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig3" align="center" width="6.5in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> DNA bouble strand break repair figure 3</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>DSB repair by homologous recombination first involves the 5' to 3' resection of the
            DSB ends to produce long 3'-ended single-stranded DNA tails. Several pathways can be
            used for repair that will generate different class of final products. In some cases,
            resection exposes complementary sequences allowing single-strand annealing and
            subsequent deletion of the segments located between these sequences. Such deletions were
            noticed in revertants of an <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-22" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink></emphasis> Tc1 reversion allele (<link linkend="bib43">Kiff et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID 2829031-->). Zwaal et al. (<link linkend="bib99">Zwaal et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8395047-->) demonstrated
            that such deletions could be isolated among the progeny of most Tc1 mutants and could be
            used in a reverse genetic approach to generate deletion alleles in genes of interest.
            Alternatively, recombination can occur with the sister chromatid or the homologous
            chromosome. This latter mechanism seems preferentially used for Tc1 repair in the
            germ line. If the animal is heterozygous for the Tc1 insertion, gene conversion will
            revert the broken locus to wild-type. If the animal is homozygous for the Tc1 insertion,
            repair will regenerate a Tc1 insertion at the excision site (<link linkend="bib63">Plasterk, 1991</link><!--; PMID 1646714-->). Interestingly, analysis of Tc1 sequence polymorphisms suggest that the repair
            machinery can switch from allelic Tc1 template to Tc1 elements located elsewhere in the
            genome, resulting in chimeric Tc1 elements (<link linkend="bib27">Fischer et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12750326-->).
            Occasionally, repair can be imperfect and generate partial deletions of the transposon
            (<link linkend="bib27">Fischer et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12750326-->; <link linkend="bib52">Lohe et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10655218-->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Regulation of transposition</title>
        <para>All <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> strains contain numerous transposons prone to be
            mobilized. However, in most strains such as the reference isolate Bristol N2,
            transposition is only detected in somatic cells but is completely silenced in the
            germ line (<link linkend="bib24">Emmons and Yesner, 1984</link><!--; PMID 6321037-->). In some natural isolates such as the
            strain Bergerac BO which was isolated in Bergerac, France (<link linkend="bib59">Nigon and Dougherty, 1949</link><!--; PMID 15404785-->), Tc1 transposons are active in the germ line (<link linkend="bib21">Egilmez et al., 1995</link><!--; PMID 7769614-->; <link linkend="bib22">Eide and Anderson, 1985</link><!--; PMID 2984668-->; <link linkend="bib34">Greenwald, 1985</link><!--; PMID 3000611-->; <link linkend="bib56">Moerman et al., 1986</link><!--; PMID 3010313-->). Bergerac individuals exhibit a mutator phenotype due to
            spontaneous mutations caused by <emphasis>de novo</emphasis> Tc1 insertions. Strikingly,
            EMS-induced mutations of single loci such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mut-2" role="_blank">mut-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib14">Collins et al., 1987</link><!--; PMID 3039378-->) or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mut-7" role="_blank">mut-7</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib42">Ketting et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10535732-->;
            <link linkend="bib79">Tabara et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10535731-->) are able to globally activate the transposition of
            multiple Tc families including Tc1, Tc3, Tc4 and Tc5. Therefore, the germ line of
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is permissive for transposition but a
            defense-mechanism exists to protect the genome from heritable defects caused by
            transposon jumps.</para>
        <para>Transposition silencing in the germ line involves an RNA interference (RNAi)-related
            mechanism. This notion emerged after the realization that a set of mutants including
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rde-2" role="_blank">rde-2</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mut-8" role="_blank">mut-8</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rde-3" role="_blank">rde-3</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mut-2" role="_blank">mut-2</ulink></emphasis>,
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mut-7" role="_blank">mut-7</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis>-14</emphasis>, <emphasis>-15</emphasis> and
            <emphasis>-16</emphasis> are defective for both RNAi and germ-line silencing of
            transposition (<link linkend="bib11">Chen et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib14">Collins et al., 1987</link><!--; PMID 3039378-->; <link linkend="bib42">Ketting et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10535732-->; <link linkend="bib79">Tabara et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10535731-->; <link linkend="bib80">Tijsterman et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11809977-->; <link linkend="bib81">Tops et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15653635-->; <link linkend="bib87">Vastenhouw et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12906791-->; for a complete review, see <link linkend="bib88">Vastenhouw and Plasterk, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15219396-->). In a
            simplified model of RNAi, a double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) molecule is cleaved into 21-24
            nucleotide-long short-interfering RNAs (siRNAs) by the RNAse III-like enzyme <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DCR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DCR-1</ulink> of
            the dicer family. siRNAs are loaded into the RNA-induced silencing complex (RISC) and
            used for specific cleavage of target RNAs. dsRNAs derived from Tc1, Tc3 and Tc5 Terminal
            Inverted Repeats are indeed detected in Bristol N2 animals that might arise from the
            fold-back of transcripts encompassing entire Tc elements. siRNAs corresponding to Tc1
            and other transposons are produced in the N2 strain (<link linkend="bib1">Ambros et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12747828-->;
            <link linkend="bib76">Sijen and Plasterk, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14628056-->). These siRNAs seem to be functional in the
            germ line since a Tc1 TIR fused to gfp causes silencing of GFP expression, at least in
            part, by post-transcriptional silencing of the transgene in the germ line (<link linkend="bib76">Sijen and Plasterk, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14628056-->). Therefore, in a simple model, RNAi might repress
            transposition by causing the degradation of tranposon-derived mRNA in the germ line,
            hence preventing the expression of any Tc transposase. In other tissues,
            transposon-induced RNAi might be less efficient, hence enabling somatic excision.
            However, mutator strains exist that are not RNAi deficient. In
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mut-4" role="_blank">mut-4</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis>-5</emphasis> and <emphasis>-6</emphasis> mutant
            backgrounds, transposition of Tc1 but not of other Tcs is specifically derepressed (<link linkend="bib58">Mori et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID 2848746-->). These loci have not been identified at the molecular level
            but they have been proposed to correspond to specific Tc1 copies. For example, truncated
            Tc1 elements might produce transcripts which lack a sequence targeted by the RNAi
            surveillance system but could still produce a functional transposase. Alternatively,
            these elements might be full-length Tc1 elements inserted in genomic regions that lead
            to very efficient transcription of these copies in the germ line, hence allowing some
            transcripts to escape degradation. In addition to Tc1-specific mutators, a number of
            genes are required for global silencing of transposition but not for RNAi (<link linkend="bib42">Ketting et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10535732-->; <link linkend="bib87">Vastenhouw et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12906791-->). It is not clear at
            the moment if these genes act in a specific branch of an RNAi-dependent process or if
            they are involved in an RNAi-independent control of transposition.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Transposon-based tools for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> research</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Gene identification in forward genetic screens</title>
            <para>Insertional mutagenesis with transposons generates mutant alleles that are tagged
                by the presence of a transposon. This molecular tag can subsequently be used to
                identify the mutated gene. Mutator strains and Tc1 gene tagging was used early in
                forward genetic screens to identify mutated-genes before the genome project reagents
                were available (<link linkend="bib34">Greenwald, 1985</link><!--; PMID 3000611-->; <link linkend="bib56">Moerman et al., 1986</link><!--; PMID 3010313-->)
                (for review see <link linkend="bib2">Anderson, 1995</link><!--; PMID 8531732-->; <link linkend="bib66">Plasterk and van Luenen, 1997</link><!--; PMID-->).
                Nowadays, Tc elements can be used in combination with PCR to amplify the genomic
                sequence that flank a mutagenic insertion and identify the mutated gene without
                genetic mapping (<link linkend="bib93">Wicks et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10790327-->). However, using Tc elements as
                mutagens has some major drawbacks. First, the mobilization of Tc transposons is not
                restricted to a single class of elements in mutator strains. Second, there are
                several copies of each transposons in the genome which complicate the identification
                of the mutagenic insertion. Third, in the mutator strains that are used,
                transposition is not controlled. Some Tc insertions are poorly mutagenic either
                because they are in introns, or because they are removed from the mature mRNA by
                aberrant splicing (<link linkend="bib72">Rushforth and Anderson, 1996</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib73">Rushforth et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID-->). Spontaneous re-excision can generate mutagenic footprints that generate a
                stronger phenotype but can no longer be detected in a transposon tagging strategy.
                These limitations have been circumvented by mobilizing the Mos1 transposon in the
                germ line of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib5">Bessereau et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11544527-->). <emphasis>Mos1</emphasis> is a member of the
                Tc1/<emphasis>mariner</emphasis> family and was isolated from <emphasis>Drosophila
                mauritiana</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib38">Jacobson et al., 1986</link><!--; PMID 3022302-->). The
                <emphasis>Mos1</emphasis> element is absent from the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
                genome and controlled mobilization of <emphasis>Mos1</emphasis> is achieved by
                conditional expression of the <emphasis>Mos1</emphasis> transposase.
                <emphasis>Mos1</emphasis> mutagenesis is 10 times less efficient than chemical
                mutagens but the cloning of mutated genes is extremely fast since
                <emphasis>Mos1</emphasis> insertions represent rare tags that are easy to localize
                in the genome (<link linkend="bib30">Gally et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15457263-->; <link linkend="bib94">Williams et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15654093-->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Targeted gene inactivation</title>
            <para>Tc1 can be used to target the inactivation of a selected gene. In such approaches,
                Tc1 are mobilized randomly in a mutator background and independent lines are
                subsequently screened by PCR for the presence of a Tc1 insertion in the gene of
                interest (<link linkend="bib73">Rushforth et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID-->). Then, deletions can be generated at low
                frequency by imprecise repair of double-strand breaks caused by Tc1 re-excision. The
                line containing the Tc1 insertion in the gene to inactivate is propagated in a
                mutator background. PCR analysis of the progeny can identify animals that have lost
                that Tc1 insertion plus a variable amount of flanking DNA (<link linkend="bib99">Zwaal et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8395047-->). This strategy has been widely used initially, but more recent protocols of
                gene inactivation utilize chemical mutagens to generate random deletions in the
                    <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome (<link linkend="bib39">Jansen et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9288111-->).
                However, transposon targeted gene inactivation can still be useful when these other
                strategies fail or if a transposon has already been identified in the gene to
                inactivate (<link linkend="bib44">Korswagen et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8962114-->; <link linkend="bib55">Martin et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12242258-->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Site-directed mutagenesis</title>
            <para>Gene targeting techniques based on homologous recombination, such as those used in
                mice and yeast, are difficult in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib4">Berezikov et al.,
                2004</link><!--; PMID 14982959-->; <link linkend="bib9">Broverman et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8506273-->). Transposons might
                represent an interesting alternative to engineer specific mutations in the genome.
                In 1992, Plasterk and Groenen (<link linkend="bib64">Plasterk and Groenen, 1992</link><!--; PMID 1740110-->)
                demonstrated that a transgene containing a fragment of the
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-22" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink></emphasis> gene could be used as a template to repair a
                double-strand break caused by Tc1 excision out of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-22" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink></emphasis>
                locus in a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mut-6" role="_blank">mut-6</ulink></emphasis> background (<link linkend="bib64">Plasterk and Groenen, 1992</link><!--; PMID 1740110-->). Point mutations contained in the transgene were copied in the genome
                during the repair process. Therefore, transgene-instructed gene conversion provides
                a strategy to engineer mutations or introduce exogenous sequence in the genome.
                However, such events were rare (2.10-5 event per meiosis), thus preventing this
                technique from being widely utilized in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Recently, a
                similar strategy was tried in different mutator backgrounds to engineer deletions
                and introduce GFP in the genome (<link linkend="bib3">Barrett et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15502826-->).
                Transgene-instructed gene conversion was found to be 10 times more frequent than
                previously reported, thus providing an efficient technique to engineer custom
                alleles in a reverse genetic approach. Efforts to generate libraries containing
                transposon insertions in most <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes would expand the
                use of this method (<link linkend="bib33">Granger et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15310838-->; <link linkend="bib55">Martin et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12242258-->).</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Acknowledgments</title>
        <para>I thank V. Robert and R. Weimer for critical reading of the manuscript and M. Augustin
            for stimulating interactions. This work was funded by an AVENIR grant from the Institut
            National de la Sante et de la Recherche Mdicale, and by a European Union grant (6th
            Framework program, code NEMAGETAG).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
		<para/>
		&transposons_Refs;</sect1>
</article>