<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'phylofig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'phylofig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'phylofig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'phylofig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'phylofig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'phylofig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'phylofig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'phylofig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'phylofig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'phylofig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6A SYSTEM 'phylofig6A.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6B SYSTEM 'phylofig6B.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'phylofig6leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY phylo_Refs SYSTEM 'phylorefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="phylo_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
<title>The phylogenetic relationships of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and other rhabditids<footnote><para>Edited by Lisa R. Girard. Last revised July 27, 2005. Published August 11, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Kiontke, K. and Fitch, D.H.A. The Phylogenetic relationships of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and other rhabditids (August 11, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.11.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 Karin Kiontke and David H. A. Fitch. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
</footnote></title>

		<author>
			<othername>Karin Kiontke<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:kk52@nyu.edu">kk52@nyu.edu</ulink> or <ulink url="mailto:david.fitch@nyu.edu">david.fitch@nyu.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark>, David H. A. Fitch<remark><superscript>&#x000A7;</superscript></remark></othername>
			<affiliation>
				<address>Department of Biology, New York University, New York, NY 10003 USA</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		
<!-- ORIGINAL AUTHOR INFO BELOW
		<author>
			<firstname>Karin</firstname>
			<surname>Kiontke<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed.
	    	<ulink url="kk52@nyu.edu">kk52@nyu.edu</ulink>
						</para>
					</footnote>
				</remark>
			</surname>
			<affiliation>
				<orgname>Department of Biology, New York University</orgname>
				<address>New York, NY 10003 USA</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<firstname>David H. A.</firstname>
			<surname>Fitch<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed.
                            <ulink url="david.fitch@nyu.edu">david.fitch@nyu.edu</ulink>
						</para>
					</footnote>
				</remark>
			</surname>
			<affiliation>
				<orgname>Department of Biology, New York University</orgname>
				<address>New York, NY 10003 USA</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
-->

	</articleinfo>
	
	<abstract>
		<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
		<para><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">is a member of a group of nematodes called rhabditids,
            which encompasses a large number of ecologically and genetically diverse species. A new,
            preliminary phylogenetic analysis is presented for concatenated sequences of three
            nuclear genes for 48 rhabditid and diplogastrid species (including 10</emphasis>
                <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Caenorhabditis</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">species), as well as four species representing
            the outgroup. Although many relationships are well-resolved, more data are still needed
            to resolve some key relationships, particularly near the base of the rhabditid tree.
            There is high confidence for two major clades: (1) a clade comprising</emphasis>
                <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Mesorhabditis</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Parasitorhabditis,</emphasis></emphasis>
                <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Pelodera,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Teratorhabditis</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">plus a few other
            species; (2) a large clade (Eurhabditis) comprising most of the remaining rhabditid
                genera, including</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Caenorhabditis</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">and its sistergroup</emphasis>
                <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Protorhabditis-Prodontorhabditis-Diploscapter.</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">Eurhabditis also contains the parasitic
                strongylids, the entomopathogenic</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Heterorhabditis,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">and the
                monophyletic group</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Oscheius</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">which includes the satellite model organism</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">O. tipulae.</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">The
                relationships within</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Caenorhabditis</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">are well resolved. The
            analysis also suggests that rhabditids include diplogastrids, to which the second
                satellite model organism</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Pristionchus pacificus</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">belongs. Genetic
                disparity within</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Caenorhabditis</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">is as great as that across
            vertebrates, suggesting</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Caenorhabditis</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">lineages are quickly evolving, ancient, or both. The
            phylogenetic tree can be used to reconstruct evolutionary events within rhabditids. For
            instance, the reproductive mode changed multiple times from gonochorism to
            hermaphroditism, but only once from hermaphroditism to gonochorism. Complete retraction
                of the male tail tip, leading to a blunt, peloderan tail, evolved
            at least once. Reversions to unretracted tail tips occurred within both major rhabditid
            groups. The phylogeny also provides a guide to species which would be good candidates
            for future genome projects and comparative studies.</emphasis>
		</para>
	</abstract>
	<sect1>
		<title>Introduction<footnote><para>Terms used: taxon (plural taxa)- a group of phylogenetically related species; monophyletic- a group of species that includes all descendants of one ancestor; paraphyletic- a group of species that includes some but not all descendants of an ancestor; polyphyletic- a group of species that includes descendants of more than one ancestor; clade- a monophyletic taxon.</para></footnote></title>
		<para>
			<emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> belongs to a large group of primarily
            bacteriophagous nematodes called rhabditids (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). This taxon
            comprises a great diversity of species, including some parasites (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_quicktourdiversity/quicktourdiversity.html" role="_blank">A quick tour of nematode diversity and the backbone of nematode phylogeny</ulink>). Resolving rhabditid phylogeny is key to uncovering how
            evolutionary changes occurred in this diversification. A phylogeny for rhabditids also
            provides an important foundation for comparative biology using <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis>, "satellite" model systems <emphasis>Pristionchus
            pacificus</emphasis>, <emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis>, and other
                <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species with sequenced genomes (<emphasis>C.
                briggsae</emphasis>, <emphasis>C. remanei</emphasis>, <emphasis>C.
            japonica</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> n. sp. represented by
            strain CB5161 among others; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_evoldevnematode/evoldevnematode.html" role="_blank">Evolution of development in nematodes related to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). The selection of appropriate representative taxa for further genome
            sequencing projects also depends on an accurate phylogeny.</para>
		<para>Phylogenetic analyses using DNA sequences of small subunit ribosomal RNA (SSU rRNA)
            genes have revealed some relationships that are inconsistent, as well as some that are
            consistent, with earlier phylogenies (<link linkend="bib8">Fitch et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 7700158 -->; <link linkend="bib3">Blaxter et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9510248 -->; <link linkend="bib20">Sudhaus and Fitch, 2001</link>). Many relationships, however,
            have not been sufficiently resolved. It is therefore important to expand the data pool
            with regard to both loci and taxa.</para>
		<para>Here we report conclusions of an analysis (which will be published elsewhere) using three genes for rhabditids and
            their closest relatives. In this phylogeny, several branches are well supported. For
            example, most species belong to either of two major monophyletic groups, here called
            "Eurhabditis" and "Pleiorhabditis", both of which show high support in this analysis.
            Eurhabditis includes strongylids and <emphasis>Heterorhabditis</emphasis>, as well as
                <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and its sister taxon, the Protorhabditis group.
            There is also some evidence that diplogastrids (e.g., <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis>)
            are part of rhabditids. As we accumulate more data, we are gaining a clearer picture of
            rhabditid phylogeny. There is still much that remains mysterious, however. In
            particular, it will be important to establish who are the closest relatives of
            rhabditids, to sort out the earliest lineages of rhabditids, and to further elucidate
            the relationships among members of the Eurhabditis group. Only after this is achieved
            should the much-needed taxonomic revision be initiated. At the moment, however, it is
            still too early to attempt such a classification because a number of relationships are
            not sufficiently resolved.</para>
		<para>A well-resolved phylogeny is an essential step in inferring the evolutionary changes
            that have occurred and for discovering possible correlations between such changes. We
            provide examples of how the phylogeny so far has provided insight into the evolution of
            reproductive mode, morphological evolution in the male tail tip, the evolution of
            introns, and molecular divergence. Database and strain resources for rhabditids are
            being developed to support comparative work with rhabditids.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Rhabditid phylogeny</title>
		<sect2>
			<title>Overview of rhabditid relationships</title>
			<para>A preliminary phylogenetic hypothesis for representative rhabditid species and
                four species from the outgroup is shown in <xref linkend="figure1"/>. The analysis
                is based on DNA sequences from nearly complete small and large subunit (SSU and LSU)
                ribosomal RNA (rRNA) genes and a portion of the RNA Pol II (RNAP2) gene (KK and DF,
                unpublished; original data and details of the analysis will be published elsewhere).</para>
				
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="5.8in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase> figure 1</phrase>
				</textobject> &fig1legend; </mediaobject>
			
			<para>Two major clades of rhabditids can be distinguished, called here "Pleiorhabditis"
                and "Eurhabditis" (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). Although these two groups were
                combined in a single monophyletic group (supported by 87% bootstrap value) in an
                earlier analysis using only SSU rRNA genes (<link linkend="bib20">Sudhaus and Fitch, 2001</link>), such a clade
                does not appear in the present jackknife analysis with additional genes.
                Pleiorhabditis comprises several genera of species with a posterior vulva (e.g.,
                    <emphasis>Mesorhabditis</emphasis>, <emphasis>Teratorhabditis</emphasis>) and
                also the genus <emphasis>Pelodera</emphasis> which includes <emphasis>Pelodera</emphasis>
				<emphasis>strongyloides</emphasis>, reported to be a facultative parasite of mammals
                (<link linkend="bib23">Sudhaus and Schulte, 1988</link>; <link linkend="bib13">Jones et al., 1991</link><!-- PMID 1935236 -->). Eurhabditis includes
                almost all the other rhabditid species, including
                <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>, and thus differs from the Eurhabditis
                originally proposed by Sudhaus on the basis of a different view of relationships
                (see <link linkend="bib20">Sudhaus and Fitch, 2001</link>). Additionally, Eurhabditis includes the "Protorhabditis
                group", named after its most prominent members, which is the sister clade to
                    <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>. Eurhabditis includes a monophyletic genus
                    <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> that comprises two separate clades, one of
                leptoderan species, the <emphasis>Insectivora</emphasis> group, and another of
                    peloderan species, the <emphasis>Dolichura</emphasis>
                group, as proposed by <link linkend="bib21">Sudhaus and Hooper (1994</link>; see also <xref
						linkend="figure4"/>). One member of this latter group, <emphasis>Oscheius
                    tipulae</emphasis> (represented here by strain CEW1) is used as a satellite
                model organism for comparative studies of development (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_evoldevnematode/evoldevnematode.html" role="_blank">Evolution of development in nematodes related to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>; <link linkend="bib18">Sommer, 2000</link><!-- PMID 20566942 -->) and molecular biology (e.g. <link linkend="bib7">Evans et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 97420754 -->). The strongylid parasites of vertebrates and the
                    <emphasis>Heterorhabditis</emphasis> pathogens of insects have also clearly
                evolved from within the Eurhabditis clade (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_quicktourdiversity/quicktourdiversity.html" role="_blank">A quick tour of nematode diversity and the backbone of nematode phylogeny</ulink>).</para>

		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Relationships within <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>
			</title>

			<para>Relationships are now well-resolved among the <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>
                species which are represented by live strains (<xref linkend="figure2"/>; <link linkend="bib14">Kiontke et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15184656 -->; <link linkend="bib4">Cho et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15231741 -->). Of these species,
                    <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. remanei</emphasis> are closest
                relatives. No single species is most closely related to <emphasis>C.
                elegans</emphasis>, which is the sister species of a clade that includes
                    <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>, <emphasis>C. remanei</emphasis>, and
                    <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> n. sp. (represented here by strain CB5161).
                The closest species to these four <emphasis>Elegans</emphasis> group species is
                    <emphasis>C. japonica</emphasis>, which was chosen for a genome sequencing
                project in order to provide an outgroup comparison for the four
                <emphasis>Elegans</emphasis> group species. Another undescribed new species
                (represented here by strain PS1010), which has been used in some comparisons (e.g.
                <link linkend="bib2">Baldwin et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 97446281 -->), diverged earlier than <emphasis>C.
                japonica</emphasis>. Uncertainty still exists for some
                <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> relationships; instead of being related in the
                manner depicted in <xref linkend="figure2"/>, <emphasis>C.</emphasis> sp. PS1010 could be most closely
                related to <emphasis>C. drosophilae</emphasis> and
                <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> n. sp. (DF5070) (<link linkend="bib14">Kiontke et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15184656 -->). For more about <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> biodiversity and a
                phylogenetic hypothesis incorporating other <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>
                species, see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_ecolCaenorhabditis/ecolCaenorhabditis.html" role="_blank">Ecology of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species</ulink>
                (also <link linkend="bib22">Sudhaus and Kiontke, 1996</link>).</para>
		
			<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="2.0in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase> figure 2</phrase>
				</textobject> &fig2legend; </mediaobject>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Strongylids and diplogastrids are rhabditids</title>
			<para>Rhabditids, as a monophyletic group, include two taxa that have been previously
                classified separately. First, the strongylids are a group of vertebrate parasites
                traditionally considered outside of rhabditids. Molecular analyses have placed
                strongylids clearly within the Eurhabditis group of rhabditids and as a sister group
                of the insect pathogenic <emphasis>Heterorhabditis</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib11">Fitch and Thomas, 1997</link>; <link linkend="bib3">Blaxter et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9510248 -->; <link linkend="bib20">Sudhaus and Fitch, 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib6">De
                Ley and Blaxter, 2002</link>).</para>
			<para>A second group of species traditionally classified outside of rhabditids is the
                group designated here informally as diplogastrids (called Diplogastrina,
                Diplogastridae, or Diplogasteromorpha in formal classification systems), which
                includes the satellite model system, <emphasis>Pristionchus pacificus</emphasis>
                (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_evoldevnematode/evoldevnematode.html" role="_blank">Evolution of development in nematodes related to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). Specifically, there appears to be a relationship between diplogastrids
                and <emphasis>Rhabditoides inermis</emphasis>, a rhabditid (see also <link linkend="bib20">Sudhaus and
                Fitch, 2001</link>). According to this phylogeny, <emphasis>R. inermis</emphasis>
                is more closely related to diplogastrids than to its traditional congener, <emphasis>Rhabditoides inermiformis</emphasis>, despite their morphological similarities. (Another
                species, <emphasis>Rhabditoides regina</emphasis>, resides within Pleiorhabditis,
                thus making "<emphasis>Rhabditoides</emphasis>" polyphyletic.) Furthermore, our
                phylogeny suggests that <emphasis>Poikilolaimus</emphasis> could be in the most
                anciently diverged lineage of rhabditids, placing diplogastrids distinctly within
                rhabditids, although the jackknife support (58%) is not strong for this conclusion.
                Together, these data suggest that diplogastrids are not a clade separate from
                rhabditids, but are instead derived from within rhabditids. These data contradict a
                recent proposal based on morphology that bunonematids are the sister taxon of diplogastrids (<link linkend="bib12">F&#x000FC;rst von Lieven, 2002</link>).</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Examples of character evolution</title>
		<sect2>
			<title>Reproductive mode</title>
			<para>Using the molecular phylogeny, we have traced the evolution of gonochorism (males
                and females must cross to propagate), self-fertile hermaphroditism (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_sexgermline/sexgermline.html" role="_blank">Sex-determination in the germ line</ulink>), heterogony (alternating generations of gonochorism and hermaphroditism), and parthenogenesis (sperm, if they exist, do not contribute genetic material; <xref linkend="figure3"/>). Among the taxa represented in <xref linkend="figure3"/>, we find that gonochorism is ancestral and that hermaphroditism has arisen at least ten times independently in all the
                major rhabditid clades, with only one possible reversal back to gonochorism
                occurring within the <emphasis>Dolichura</emphasis> species group of
                    <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis>. Such massive convergence provides an excellent
                opportunity to study how significantly developmental constraints limit or channel
                evolution.</para>
				
			<para>According to the most parsimonious reconstruction, and assuming reversibility and
                equal chances of changes between character states, <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>
                and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> evolved hermaphroditism independently (<link linkend="bib14">Kiontke et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15184656 -->). If we consider that changes from gonochorism to
                hermaphroditism have occurred ten times more frequently than the reverse in
                rhabditids, it becomes even more plausible that hermaphroditism evolved
                independently in these two species. In such a case, there are two possibilities for
                evolutionary change: parallelism (in which independent changes affect the same
                mechanism) or convergence (in which the changes affect different mechanisms but
                yield similar results). In the case of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and
                    <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>, hermaphroditism appears to be convergent
                because there is a fundamental difference between the two species in the identity of
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FOG-2;class=protein" role="_blank">FOG-2</ulink>, for which no single ortholog exists in <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>, and
                developmental role of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLD-1</ulink>, which inhibits female fate in the germline of
                    <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> but promotes female fate in <emphasis>C.
                    briggsae</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib15">Nayak et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID 15630478 -->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_sexgermline/sexgermline.html" role="_blank">Sex-determination in the germ line</ulink>).</para>
			<para>We also find that heterogony evolved twice (in
                <emphasis>Heterorhabditis</emphasis> and an undescribed species represented by
                strain SB347) and parthenogenesis evolved once (within the Protorhabditis
            group).</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Morphological evolution</title>
			<para>As an example of morphological evolution, we have traced the history of changes in
                morphogenesis of the male tail tip. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, the shapes
                of the hypodermal cells in the male tail tip change dramatically as the cells fuse
                during L4 male morphogenesis and the conically pointed tail tip of the larva
                retracts to form the rounded, "peloderan" tail of the adult
                male (<link linkend="bib16">Nguyen et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10049567 -->). Tail morphogenesis does not occur in
                hermaphrodites or in females of most other rhabditid species. Although males of most
                rhabditid species do undergo tail morphogenesis, the tip of the tail does not always
                retract. In such cases, the tail tip remains pointed, as in larvae, usually sticking
                out beyond the posterior edge of the fan or bursa, if a fan exists. This tail form
                is called "leptoderan".</para>
			<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4.7in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase> figure 3</phrase>
				</textobject>&fig3legend;
			</mediaobject>
			<para>There have been at least seven independent changes in the shape of the male tail
                tip during rhabditid evolution (<xref linkend="figure4"/>). Because some branches
                are still unresolved, the directionality of most of these changes is unclear.
                However, the present phylogeny allows us to conclude that at least two changes
                occurred from peloderan to leptoderan. Some of the changes in
                male tail tips must be convergent because we know that
                peloderan tail tips can be constructed in different ways (e.g.,
                with or without fusions of the hypodermal cells), as can leptoderan tail tips
                (<link linkend="bib16">Nguyen et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10049567 -->; <link linkend="bib9">Fitch, 1997</link><!-- PMID 11975351 -->; <link linkend="bib10">Fitch, 2000</link>). Because of
                these convergences, it is clear that there is no monophyletic clade of leptoderan
                species or of peloderan species (cf. Peloderinae of <link linkend="bib1">Andr&#x000E1;ssy, 1983</link>). We have found that several other morphological characters (such as
                lack of glottoid apparatus) show similar homoplasy at gross morphological levels
                (e.g., <link linkend="bib20">Sudhaus and Fitch, 2001</link>). Thus, rhabditids provide fertile ground for
                investigating the role of developmental plasticity in evolution.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="5.2in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase> figure 4</phrase>
				</textobject> &fig4legend; </mediaobject>
			
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Intron evolution</title>
			<para>Using the well-resolved <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> phylogeny, we inferred
                the most parsimonious history of intron gains and losses in a 1,860-bp portion of
                the gene coding for the largest subunit of RNAP2 (<link linkend="bib14">Kiontke et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15184656 -->). This phylogeny of closely related species allows finer resolution of
                such events than do comparisons among distantly related model organisms, which have
                been the main staple of intron evolution fare (e.g. <link linkend="bib17">Rogozin et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12956953 -->). We find that intron evolution is extraordinarily dynamic (<xref
						linkend="figure5"/>). In this one region, the number of introns present in a
                species can range between 1 and 14. Considering only homologous intron positions at
                which a single most parsimonious reconstruction could be made ("unequivocal"
                positions) and assuming that intron gains and losses are equally likely, introns
                were lost 12 times and gained 4 times (<link linkend="bib14">Kiontke et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15184656 -->). If one
                considers the possibility that losses are more likely than gains and that it might
                be highly improbable for an intron to be regained in exactly the same spot, it is
                possible that as many as 27 losses and at most 3 gains (but at least 1 gain)
                occurred. Most of these intron losses occurred in the stem species of the
                    <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> clade, and several losses occurred later as
                the clade evolved (<xref linkend="figure5"/>). One intron in <emphasis>C.</emphasis> sp. CB5161 is unique
                among all rhabditids we have characterized so far, and is thus a clear gain (<xref
						linkend="figure5"/>). Characterization of the homologous region in other
                rhabditids suggests that intron evolution is very dynamic with periods of losses and
                gains (KK and DF, unpub.). Frequent intron loss in other
                <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> genes has also been reported (<link linkend="bib4">Cho et al., 2004</link>).
                Recent intron gains have also been documented, some of which have sequence
                similarity to other introns and could therefore have originated by reverse splicing
                (<link linkend="bib5">Coghlan and Wolfe, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15243155 -->).</para>
			<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="3.4in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase> figure 5</phrase>
				</textobject> &fig5legend; </mediaobject>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Molecular divergence</title>
			<para>Genome-level comparisons of molecular divergence show that <emphasis>C.
                elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> are a little bit less
                similar at the molecular level than are human and mouse (<link linkend="bib19">Stein et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14624247 -->). We find the same relative differences when comparing these species
                with RNAP2 and rRNA genes alone (<link linkend="bib14">Kiontke et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15184656 -->). Because many
                taxa are represented by SSU rRNA sequences, we can use this molecule to compare the
                degree of molecular divergences among other vertebrate taxa with the divergences
                among rhabditids. The divergence between the least closely related
                    <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species (<emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>
                versus <emphasis>C.</emphasis> sp. SB341) is comparable to the divergence between
                mouse and zebrafish, encompassing a broad range of vertebrate lineages (<xref linkend="figure6"/>). Furthermore, species within the Eurhabditis clade are at
                least as different at the molecular level as mouse and sea urchin, encompassing a
                broad range of deuterostome lineages. It is important to note that the Eurhabditis
                clade is but a small fraction of Nematoda. Thus, the nematodes diverged from other
                animals very anciently, rates of molecular evolution are much faster in nematodes
                than in deuterostomes, or both. Because there is no accurate method for calibrating
                a "molecular clock" for nematodes, estimates for dates of divergence will be
                extremely unreliable. Complicating this issue, there is considerable rate
                heterogeneity among different lineages for some genes (e.g., SSU rRNA; see <link linkend="bib14">Kiontke et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15184656 -->). The best measure of taxonomic difference in rhabditids
                is therefore simply the relative amount of sequence difference (as in <xref linkend="figure6" />), not some date of divergence which could be very inaccurate.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
			<mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig6A" width="3.2in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig6B" width="3.5in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject>
					<phrase> figure 6A</phrase>
				</textobject>&fig6legend;
		</mediaobject>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Resources for comparative biology using rhabditids</title>
		<para>Arguably the most important tools for comparative studies using emerging model systems
            are the organisms themselves. Genome sequences, interactome maps, cDNA libraries, and
            other such molecular data and resources are important tools for functional genomics.
            Ultimately, however, <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> understanding of gene and genome
            function - particularly with respect to mechanisms and patterns of gene expression,
            development and behavior - requires analysis in the context of the living system itself.
            Powerful comparative approaches depend on the availability of multiple, phylogenetically
            well-defined, living species with clearly defined, standardized strains that can be
            archived and shared. The <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> Genetics Center <ulink url="http://biosci.umn.edu/CGC/CGChomepage.htm" role="_blank">(CGC)</ulink> provides many stocks of wild strains that can be easily maintained cryogenically. We are
            also developing a stock collection of rhabditid species, the New York University Rhabditidae Collection (<ulink
					url="http://www.nyu.edu/projects/fitch/fresources/fresources.html" role="_blank">NYURC</ulink>) that is as
            thoroughly representative of rhabditid phylogeny as possible. The NYURC curates strains
            that are difficult to culture or archive cryogenically along with data about ecology,
            biology, morphology, etc., for all rhabditids in culture.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Acknowledgments</title>
		<para>We thank the National Science Foundation and the Human Frontier Science Program for
            supporting this work. Although many people have been important to this work, we
            especially thank Marie-Anne F&#x000E9;lix, W. Kelley Thomas and Walter Sudhaus for their important collaborations and contributions.
            We thank Byron Adams and Steve Nadler for providing excellent suggestions in their
            reviews of the manuscript.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>References</title>
		<para/>
		&phylo_Refs;</sect1>
</article>