<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'synaptfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'synaptfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'synaptfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'synaptfig2leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY synapt_Refs SYSTEM 'synaptrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>]>
<article id="synapt_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<title>Synaptogenesis<footnote>
			<para>Edited by Erik M. Jorgensen and Joshua M. Kaplan. Last revised December 9, 2005. Published December 23, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Jin, Y. Synaptogenesis (December 23, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.44.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 Yishi Jin, This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
		<!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>version 03/22/05</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised June 13, 2005.</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
-->
		<author>
			<firstname>Yishi</firstname>
			<surname>Jin<remark>
					<footnote>
						<para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:jin@biology.ucsc.edu">jin@biology.ucsc.edu</ulink></para>
					</footnote>
				</remark>
			</surname>
			<affiliation>
				<address>Department of Molecular, Cell and Development Biology, Howard Hughes Medical Institute, University of California, Santa Cruz, Santa Cruz, CA 95064, USA</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<abstract>
		<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Synaptogenesis is a process involving the formation of a neurotransmitter release site in the presynaptic neuron and a receptive field at the postsynaptic partners, and the precise alignment of pre- and post-synaptic specializations. In</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">synapses are found as</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">en passant</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">axonal swellings along the nerve processes. Genetic screens using a synaptic vesicle-associated GFP marker have identified key players in synaptic target recognition and organization of the presynaptic terminals. Importantly, the functions of most genes are evolutionarily conserved. Further studies using a combination of genetic modifier screens and reverse genetics have begun to reveal the underlying signaling pathways.</emphasis></para>
	</abstract>
	<sect1>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>Synapses are morphologically distinct subcellular junctional structures, composed of a presynaptic terminal, a postsynaptic target and the synaptic cleft aligning pre- and post-synaptic specializations (<link linkend="bib6">Cowan et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib35">Pappas and Purpura, 1972</link><!--; PMID-->). The presynaptic terminal is characterized by a cluster of synaptic vesicles surrounding the electron-dense membrane specializations; and the postsynaptic site contains densely packed ion channels and signal transduction molecules. Both the pre- and post-synaptic specializations display variable appearances depending on the organisms and neuronal types (<link linkend="bib10">De Camilli et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib51">Sorra and Harris, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11075821-->; <link linkend="bib61">Zhai and Bellen, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15381754-->).</para>
		<para>Synapse formation occurs in two general manners: <emphasis>en passant</emphasis>&#x02014;synaptic boutons are formed along the axon shaft; or <emphasis>terminaux</emphasis>&#x02014;synaptic boutons are formed at the end of axon branches. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> synapses occur <emphasis>en passant</emphasis> between neighbouring parallel nerve processes, or between nerve processes and muscle arms (<link linkend="bib57">White et al., 1986</link><!--; PMID-->). The presynaptic site is seen as a vesicle-filled varicosity containing the electron-dense presynaptic density in the membrane adjacent to the contact with the postsynaptic elements (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). On samples prepared by traditional fixation method clear and spherical synaptic vesicles (SV) are usually 35&#x02013;45 nm in diameter, and large dense-core vesicles (LDCV) range from 40&#x02013;53nm. The size of the presynaptic regions, defined by the axonal swellings and the number of SV and the size of density, varies considerably, even among the same types of synapses or among the synapses from the same neuron. The prominence of presynaptic density also varies in a way that does not necessarily correspond to the number of vesicles. The overall ultrastructural appearance of presynaptic terminals of worm synapses bears much resemblance to those of many synapses in the vertebrate central nervous system. However, the postsynaptic sites of worm synapses usually have no visible density-like structures that are commonly found in other organisms. Therefore, synaptic partners are assigned mostly based on proximity, with monad synapse having one postsynaptic partner, dyad with two, and triad with three postsynaptic partners. In the case of dyad and triad synapses, it is difficult to tell whether all partners are functional. The presence of more than one postsynaptic target also raises the possibility that synaptogenesis may depend on the simultaneous presence of two particular postsynaptic elements. The number of synapses each nerve process makes is quite variable (<link linkend="bib57">White et al., 1986</link>). Designated synaptic partners often make contact through fasciculation for a long distance, but form synapses only at specific sites. This chapter focuses on presynaptic assembly and synaptic target selection. For more information on postsynaptic assembly, see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_synapticfunction/synapticfunction.html">Synaptic function</ulink>.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Visualizing synapses in living animals</title>
		<para>A key reagent to examine synapses in vivo is the synaptobrevin GFP fusion reporter (<link linkend="bib29">Nonet, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10476681-->). Synaptobrevin (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>/T0H9.4) is a 109 amino acid, integral membrane protein of synaptic vesicles. The original <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>::GFP marker has GFP fused at the C-terminal of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>, and by topology prediction, GFP would reside inside the vesicle. Evidence for this marker as labeling synaptic vesicles are (1) colocalization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>::GFP with endogenous <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink> by wholemount immunocytochemistry; (2) <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>::GFP fluorescence is seen predominantly in cell bodies in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-104" role="_blank">unc-104</ulink></emphasis> kinesin mutant; and (3) deletion of the transmembrane domain of SNB-1(<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00394;</symbol> TM)::GFP causes GFP to be not restricted to synaptic regions. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>::GFP expressed in interneurons and HSN neurons show close apposition to postsynaptic markers (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLR-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-10;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-10</ulink>; <link linkend="bib39">Rongo et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9753322-->; <link linkend="bib48">Shen and Bargmann, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12628183-->). However it is not yet precisely known which population of synaptic vesicles the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>::GFP fluorescence observed represents. A variety of synaptic GFP reporter genes have also recently been  developed (Sieburth et al., 2005<!--, PMID: 16049479-->; <link linkend="bib58">Yeh et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID: 15829635-->; Francis et al., 2005<!-- PMID: 15944127-->).</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Genetic screens for synaptogenesis mutants</title>
		<para>The success of screening mutants for synaptogenesis defects has depended critically on several factors. First, the worm is transparent and GFP is readily observable in living animals. Second, much of the nervous system function is not required for viability or fertility, making it easy to maintain homozygous mutants. Third, expression of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>::GFP under neuron-specific promoters allows the optical resolution of single synapses; and the choice of neurons or synapses seems to be an important factor to the class of mutants isolated. Lastly, visual inspection of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>::GFP pattern following the traditional mutagenesis by far is most rewarding, although it is labor intensive.</para>
		<para>Several screens have been performed using <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>::GFP to label synaptic vesicle clusters in ASI chemosensory neurons (<emphasis>Pstr-3</emphasis>; <link linkend="bib7">Crump et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID-->), mechanosensory neurons (<emphasis>Pmec-7</emphasis>; <link linkend="bib43">Schaefer et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10839354-->), type D motor neurons (<emphasis>Punc-25</emphasis>; <link linkend="bib64">Zhen and Jin, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10517634-->) and HSN neurons (<emphasis>Punc-86</emphasis>; <link linkend="bib48">Shen and Bargmann, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12628183-->; <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>), which identified sets of overlapping genes, named <emphasis>sad</emphasis>, <emphasis>sam</emphasis>, <emphasis>syd,</emphasis> and <emphasis>syg</emphasis>, respectively. Most mutations appear to have wide effects on many or all synapses, but cause little behavior abnormalities. Moreover, the terminal synaptic phenotypes differ in a synapse-type specific manner. Importantly, although the mutations were isolated based on abnormal patterns of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>::GFP, the molecular characterizations thus far have shown that none of the genes is a component of synaptic vesicles, rather these genes define distinct subdomains within presynaptic terminals.</para>
		<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="6in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig1legend;
</mediaobject>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Presynaptic assembly</title>
		<para>Presynaptic assembly involves coordinated action of several inter-dependent events (<link linkend="bib25">Murthy and De Camilli, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14527272-->): formation of the electron-dense presynaptic density at the membrane apposition to the post-synaptic cell; clustering of the synaptic vesicles surrounding the density; and establishment of the active zone with the proper ratio of docked vesicles to presynaptic density.</para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Formation of presynaptic density</title>
			<para>Presynaptic density is in the center of a presynaptic terminal, and is often called &#x0201C;active zone&#x0201D;. Its electron-dense appearance likely reflects the presence of a protein scaffold, frequently referred as &#x0201C;the presynaptic grid&#x0201D; within which vesicles are docked (<link linkend="bib2">Akert et al., 1972</link><!--; PMID-->). The density in worm synapses is simple and small (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>), and does not appear to have elaborate sub-ultrastructural characteristics described for those in large synapses in other animals. It is assumed that the molecular components of presynaptic density include voltage-gated calcium channels&#x02013;like candidates are <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-2;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-36;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-36</ulink> (<link linkend="bib52">Tam et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10993677-->), SV fusion complex <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-64;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-64</ulink>/Syntaxin (<link linkend="bib41">Saifee et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9614171-->) and affiliated proteins that function in vesicle docking and priming such as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-10;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-10</ulink>/Rim (<link linkend="bib22">Koushika et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11559854-->) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-13;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-13</ulink>/mUNC13 (<link linkend="bib37">Patton et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9396756-->). Several mammalian presynaptic density proteins such as Bassoon and Picoloo (<link linkend="bib66">Ziv and Garner, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15100721-->) do not seem to have direct homologs in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> by the worm genome sequence annotation.</para>
		<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="6in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
			<para>Disruptions of vesicle docking, priming and fusion machinery have no obvious effect on the integrity of presynaptic density. Loss of function mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-64" role="_blank">unc-64</ulink>/</emphasis>syntaxin (<link linkend="bib41">Saifee et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9614171-->), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-13" role="_blank">unc-13</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib38">Richmond et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10526333-->), and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-18" role="_blank">unc-18</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib56">Weimer et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12973353-->) each cause a range of defects in synaptic vesicle docking and priming. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-10;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-10</ulink>/Rim (Rab3-interacting-molecule) family of proteins contain conserved Zn-finger, PDZ and C2 domains, and interact with Rab3GTP (<link linkend="bib55">Wang et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9252191-->), cAMPGEFII (<link linkend="bib34">Ozaki et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11056535-->), Munc13 (<link linkend="bib45">Schoch et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11797009-->) and others (<link linkend="bib33">Ohtsuka et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12163476-->; <link linkend="bib54">Wang et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12391317-->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-10" role="_blank">unc-10</ulink></emphasis> mutants, presynaptic density and vesicle docking are normal, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-13;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-13</ulink> localization is normal (<link linkend="bib22">Koushika et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11559854-->). There are two cAMPGEFII (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pxf-1" role="_blank">pxf-1</ulink></emphasis>/T14G10.2 and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pxf-2" role="_blank">pxf-2</ulink>/</emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T20G5.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">T20G5.5</ulink>), but whether they have a role in synapses is not known.</para>
			<para>Liprins are conserved proteins containing coiled-coil and SAM domains (<link linkend="bib47">Serra-Pages et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9624153-->). They were originally identified through binding to the intracellular domain of LAR receptor tyrosine phosphatase, and have now been shown to bind Rim and CAST/ERC (for CAZ-associated structural protein/ELKs-Rab6-interacting protein-CAST; <link linkend="bib21">Ko et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12923177-->; <link linkend="bib45">Schoch et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11797009-->). Liprins include two subfamilies, liprin-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> and liprin-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>, of which only liprins-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> bind LAR-RPTP (<link linkend="bib47">Serra-Pages et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9624153-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syd-2" role="_blank">syd-2</ulink></emphasis> encodes the worm liprin-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> (<link linkend="bib64">Zhen and Jin, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10517634-->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syd-2" role="_blank">syd-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants, presynaptic densities are altered and appear less electron-dense than normal. The localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-10;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-10</ulink>/Rim is less discrete in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syd-2" role="_blank">syd-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants than in wild type (<link linkend="bib26">Ackley et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID: 16107639-->). Antibody studies show that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SYD-2</ulink> is localized at synapses (<link linkend="bib64">Zhen and Jin, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10517634-->); and immuno-EM puts <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SYD-2</ulink> in the very center of presynaptic density (<link linkend="bib58">Yeh et al., 2005</link><!--, PMID: 15829635-->). The localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SYD-2</ulink> does not depend on the presence of synaptic vesicles (<link linkend="bib64">Zhen and Jin, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10517634-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elks-1" role="_blank">elks-1</ulink></emphasis>, a worm homolog of CAST/ERC, is localized at synapses; mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elks-1" role="_blank">elks-1</ulink></emphasis> do not cause detectable synaptic defects, and ELKS localization is normal in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syd-2" role="_blank">syd-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-10" role="_blank">unc-10</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib8">Deken et al., 2005</link><!--, PMID: 15976086-->). These data indicate that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SYD-2</ulink>/Liprin-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> is one important organizer of presynaptic density. In vertebrate synapses several isoforms of liprin-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> are associated with both presynaptic and postsynaptic densities (<link linkend="bib59">Wyszynski et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11931740-->). No evidence for a postsynaptic association of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SYD-2</ulink> has been reported, although <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SYD-2</ulink> is expressed in muscle cells (<link linkend="bib64">Zhen and Jin, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10517634-->).</para>
			<para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> LAR-RPTP, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ptp-3" role="_blank">ptp-3</ulink></emphasis>, has several isoforms (<link linkend="bib16">Harrington et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11959824-->). The long isoform PTP-3A most resembles the vertebrate LAR. Antibodies for common region of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PTP-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PTP-3</ulink> detects staining in the nervous system; isoform-specific GFP tagged transgenes suggest that PTP-3A is likely the predominant form in synapse (<link linkend="bib26">Ackley et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID: 16107639-->). The synaptic localization of PTP-3 and SYD-2 shows subtle dependency. Mutations disrupting <emphasis>ptp-3A</emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ptp-3" role="_blank">ptp-3</ulink></emphasis> show synaptic pattern defects similar to, but weaker than, <emphasis>syd-2(lf).</emphasis> Interestingly, a mutation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nid-1" role="_blank">nid-1</ulink></emphasis>, nidogen, shows similar defects (<link linkend="bib1">Ackley et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12736328-->). In mammalian cultured cells, LAR can bind Nidogen-laminin (<link linkend="bib32">O&apos;Grady et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9647658-->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nid-1" role="_blank">nid-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants, the synaptic localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PTP-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PTP-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SYD-2</ulink> are both altered. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SYD-2</ulink> localization is also abnormal in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ptp-3" role="_blank">ptp-3</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib26">Ackley et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID: 16107639-->). These analyses reveal a functional link between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SYD-2</ulink>, LAR and Nidogen, hinting at the possibility that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SYD-2</ulink> recruits other density components to facilitate its assembly, and that such presynaptic organizing activity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SYD-2</ulink> may be modulated through LAR-Nidogen interaction, which, together with laminin, secure the synaptic assembly.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Vesicle clustering</title>
			<para>At synapses, there are multiple forms of vesicles (<link linkend="bib3">Bodian, 1972</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib25">Murthy and De Camilli, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14527272-->; <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). Biosynthetic precursor vesicles containing synaptic proteins are generated at the cell body and transported to the terminals through MT based motor proteins. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-104;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-104</ulink> motor was the founding member of the KIF1A kinesins that transport synaptic vesicle precursors (<link linkend="bib13">Hall and Hedgecock, 1991</link><!--; PMID 1710172-->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-104" role="_blank">unc-104</ulink></emphasis> mutant animals, very few mature synaptic vesicles are detected at synapses; whereas small, clear vesicles that resemble synaptic vesicles are retained in the cell bodies. This mutant has been used as a standard genetic background for testing whether proteins are associated with SV. The conventional kinesin-1 is a tetramer composed of heavy chain and light chain, corresponding to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-116;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-116</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KLC-2;class=protein" role="_blank">KLC-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib36">Patel et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8105472-->; <link linkend="bib42">Sakamoto et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15563606-->; <link linkend="bib50">Signor et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 9950681-->). Mutations in both seem to affect the traffic of SV-like components (<link linkend="bib5">Byrd et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11738026-->; <link linkend="bib42">Sakamoto et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15563606-->). EM analysis on <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-116" role="_blank">unc-116</ulink></emphasis> reveals rather broad and diverse defects in cellular organelle distribution (D. Hall, personal communication), suggesting that kinesin-1 has broad activity in vesicle traffic.</para>
			<para>The presence of coated endocytic vesicles at presynaptic membranes indicate that most of the vesicles can be assembled locally from components that either are recycled or are previously transported from the cell soma (<link linkend="bib25">Murthy and De Camilli, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14527272-->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> proteins that function in SV endocytosis such as <emphasis>unc-26</emphasis>/synaptojanin (<link linkend="bib17">Harris et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10931870-->), <emphasis>unc-57</emphasis>/endophilin (<link linkend="bib46">Schuske et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14622579-->) and <emphasis>unc-11</emphasis>/AP180 (<link linkend="bib30">Nonet et al., 1999</link>;<!--PMID 10397769--> see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_synapticfunction/synapticfunction.html">Synaptic function</ulink>) are identified based on behavior defects and are mostly identified through aldicarb resistance screens (<link linkend="bib28">Nguyen et al., 1995</link><!--; PMID 7498734-->). As expected, these mutants exhibit a severe depletion of SV at synapses. The direct link between the anterograde transported SV precursors and local-recycled SV is not yet known.</para>
			<para>In various EM fixation filamentous fibers are seen in synapses (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>; <link linkend="bib18">Hedgecock and Hall, 1991</link><!--; PMID-->; R. Weimer and J-L. Bessereau, personal communication). MT runs very close to, but not within, the synapses. No intermediate filament is identified. Actin is presumed to be concentrated primarily around the active zone and vesicle clusters, and studies in other organisms show that actin likely prevents SV dispersion or to recapture endocytic SV (<link linkend="bib11">Goda and Davis, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14556707-->). No direct studies on the role of actins in worm synapses are reported. Spectrins are actin bundling proteins. There are two spectrin genes, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-70" role="_blank">unc-70</ulink>/<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-spectrin</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spc-1" role="_blank">spc-1</ulink>/<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-spectrin</emphasis>. The existing mutation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spc-1" role="_blank">spc-1</ulink></emphasis> causes embryonic lethal (<link linkend="bib31">Norman and Moerman, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11994313-->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-70" role="_blank">unc-70</ulink>(lf)</emphasis> mutants the number and localization of vesicles are normal, indicating that spectrins are not essential for preserving the vesicle clustering domain (<link linkend="bib15">Hammarlund et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10811832-->). Synapsins are a family of actin-associated phosphoproteins that are required for maintaining the vesicle reserve pool in vertebrate synapses (<link linkend="bib12">Greengard et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7848718-->). Worm has a synapsin homolog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=snn-1" role="_blank">snn-1</ulink>/Y38C1BA.2</emphasis> whose function is not known.</para>
			<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sad-1" role="_blank">sad-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants were identified through <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>::GFP screens for ASI and type D motor neurons (<link linkend="bib7">Crump et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11182085-->). Ultrastructural analysis shows that synaptic vesicles distribute more broadly than wild type animals, but presynaptic densities are normal. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SAD-1</ulink> defines a novel conserved family of protein Ser/Thr kinases, with the kinase domain closely related to that of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> and MARK (MAP/microtubule affinity regulating kinase) family (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SAD-1</ulink> localization intermingles with SV cluster, but does not depend on synaptic vesicles. Overexpression of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SAD-1</ulink> can induce clustering of synatic vesicle markers or vesicle precursors at non-synaptic regions. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SAD-1</ulink> may play a role in organizing synaptic cytoskeleton to pattern vesicle accumulation. In addition, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SAD-1</ulink> also regulates neuronal polarity as the polarity of the DD neurons is altered in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sad-1" role="_blank">sad-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib7">Crump et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11182085-->). Studies of mouse <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SAD-1</ulink> homologs reveal a similar role in neuronal polarity (<link linkend="bib20">Kishi et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15705853-->).</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Periactive zone</title>
			<para>At most synapse, there is an abrupt transition in SV density at the edge of the clusters. The identification of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rpm-1" role="_blank">rpm-1</ulink></emphasis> defines a new subsynaptic domain called &#x0201C;Periactive zone&#x0201D;, which is further away from the active zone and devoid of synaptic vesicles and could have a role in separating synaptic domains from non-synaptic cytoplasm. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rpm-1" role="_blank">rpm-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants exhibit diverse abnormalities in synaptic morphology. Mechanosensory neurons frequently fail to cluster synaptic vesicles in the proper synaptic sites, and often over-extend axons (<link linkend="bib43">Schaefer et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10839354-->). Chemosensory neurons have disorganized vesicle clusters (<link linkend="bib7">Crump et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11182085-->). In motor neurons, EM analysis shows multiple defects including severe reduction of vesicle numbers per synapse, presence of several presynaptic densities within one synaptic terminal and alteration in the ratio of SV to density (<link linkend="bib27">Nakata et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib63">Zhen et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10839353-->).</para>
			<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RPM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">RPM-1</ulink> is a large conserved protein with homologs known as Highwire in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>, Esrom in Zebrafish, Phr1 in mouse and Pam in human. These proteins are all implicated in synapse formation (<link linkend="bib4">Burgess et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14729956-->; <link linkend="bib9">D&apos;Souza et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15590740-->; <link linkend="bib53">Wan et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10839352-->). They have several predicted functional modules, one of which is a Ring finger domain that is a signature of the ubiquitin E3 ligase. An F-box domain containing protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FSN-1;class=protein" role="_blank">FSN-1</ulink> has been identified as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RPM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">RPM-1</ulink> binding partner provides, supporting <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RPM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">RPM-1</ulink> as an E3 ubiquitin-ligase domain (<link linkend="bib23">Liao et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15208641-->). A genetic suppressor screen of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rpm-1" role="_blank">rpm-1</ulink></emphasis> identified three map kinases, the Dual-Leucine-zipper-bearing MAPKKK <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DLK-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DLK-1</ulink>, the MAPKK <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MKK-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MKK-4</ulink>, and the p38-like MAP kinase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PMK-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PMK-3</ulink> (<link linkend="bib27">Nakata et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15707898-->). Inactivation of these three kinases suppresses <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rpm-1" role="_blank">rpm-1</ulink></emphasis> loss of function phenotypes, whereas elevated expression or constitutive activation of these kinases causes synaptic defects resembling <emphasis>rpm-1(lf)</emphasis>. This MAP kinase pathway functions presynaptically. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DLK-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DLK-1</ulink> is localized to the periactive zone. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DLK-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DLK-1</ulink> protein levels are elevated in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rpm-1" role="_blank">rpm-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RPM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">RPM-1</ulink> can bind to, and stimulate ubiquitination of, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DLK-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DLK-1</ulink> in cultured cells. These data thus reveal an in vivo function for a previously uncharacterized p38 MAP kinase mediated signaling cascade in presynaptic development, and further suggest that activity of this MAP kinase cascade is negatively controlled by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RPM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">RPM-1</ulink> through regulation of protein stability. The subsynaptic localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DLK-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DLK-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RPM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">RPM-1</ulink> implies that this regulation by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RPM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">RPM-1</ulink> may generate/maintain a &#x0201C;boundary&#x0201D; between cellular transporting domain and synaptic domain. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FSN-1;class=protein" role="_blank">FSN-1</ulink> shows physical and genetic interactions with an ALK-like receptor tyrosine kinase (<link linkend="bib23">Liao et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15208641-->). It is yet to be investigated the functional connections between this ALK kinase and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DLK-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DLK-1</ulink> pathway.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Synaptic target recognition</title>
		<para>Synaptic assembly can be induced in vitro by multiple factors.  Therefore, selecting synaptic partners is a crucial step in neural circuit formation (<link linkend="bib44">Scheiffele et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10892652-->; <link linkend="bib60">Yamagata et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14519398-->). Because target selection often occurs at the late stage of axon navigation, the mechanistic understanding of target recognition is complicated by the pleiotropic effect of genes that function in both axon guidance and target selection. One excellent system to examine this question is in the HSN neurons. HSN axons extend through half of the body, but form synapses specifically on two motor neurons, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=VC4;class=Cell" role="_blank">VC4</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=VC5;class=Cell" role="_blank">VC5</ulink>, at the mid-body near the vulva (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). Using a P<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-86" role="_blank">unc-86</ulink></emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>::YFP marker to label synaptic site of HSNs, it is shown that the vulval epithelium acts as a guidepost to instruct the HSN synapses (<link linkend="bib48">Shen and Bargmann, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12628183-->). A screen for mutants displaying ectopic <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>::GFP in HSN neurons yielded two immunoglobulin superfamily genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syg-1" role="_blank">syg-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syg-2" role="_blank">syg-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib48">Shen and Bargmann, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12628183-->; <link linkend="bib49">Shen et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15035988-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SYG-1</ulink> is similar to the vertebrate NEPH1 and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> IrrecC and Kirre/DUF, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYG-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SYG-2</ulink> is similar to vertebrate Nephrin and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> Sticks and Stones (SNS) and Hibris (HIB). When expressed in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> S2 cells, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SYG-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYG-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SYG-2</ulink> proteins bind each other. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syg-1" role="_blank">syg-1</ulink></emphasis> functions cell autonomously in HSNs. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syg-2" role="_blank">syg-2</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in vulval epithelial cells. Functional <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SYG-1</ulink>::GFP is localized to HSN synapses in wild type animals, but not in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syg-2" role="_blank">syg-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants. These results demonstrate that the vulval epithelial functions as guidepost cells to instruct growth cone movements and that SYG-2 acts as a ligand for SYG-1 to initiate synapse formation.  Not much is known about the molecules linking target recognition and assembly of synaptic components. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SYD-1</ulink> protein contains PDZ, C2 and rhoGAP-like domains, and is localized at the presynaptic active zone. In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syd-1" role="_blank">syd-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants different types of neurons show different phenotypes. In D type neurons, synaptic proteins are mislocalized and presynaptic terminals are formed in dendritic compartments in addition to their normal localizations (<link linkend="bib14">Hallam et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12379863-->). In HSN neurons, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>::GFP failed to accumulate at HSN synapses, rather retained in cell bodies. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syd-1" role="_blank">syd-1</ulink></emphasis> may be involved in linking synaptic vesicular traffic and local cytoskeleton remodeling to membrane target recognition.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Synaptic ECM</title>
		<para>Many rudimentary aspects of synaptic assembly can happen independent of each other. Synapse formation depends on the recruitment of cell adhesion molecules (CAMs), which likely stabilize the cytoarchitecture in pre- and post- synaptic sites. In worm synapses, the endostatin-containing type XVIII collagen <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CLE-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CLE-1</ulink> and Nidogen <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NID-1;class=protein" role="_blank">NID-1</ulink> display restricted localization pattern around synapses (<link linkend="bib1">Ackley et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12736328-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cle-1" role="_blank">cle-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants show enlarged <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>::GFP cluster, accompanied with reduced number of NMJ. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nid-1" role="_blank">nid-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants have diffused <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SNB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SNB-1</ulink>::GFP cluster. The function of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NID-1;class=protein" role="_blank">NID-1</ulink> involves LAR RPTP, which interacts with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SYD-2</ulink>/Liprin to pattern presynaptic assembly (<link linkend="bib26">Ackley et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID: 16107639-->). An laminin alpha subunit, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LAM-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LAM-3</ulink>, is expressed in nervous system (<link linkend="bib19">Huang et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783803-->). However, most of the mutations in laminins (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=epi-1" role="_blank">epi-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lam-3" role="_blank">lam-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lam-1" role="_blank">lam-1</ulink></emphasis>) cause early embryonic lethality (<link linkend="bib19">Huang et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783803-->; <link linkend="bib65">Zhu et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10727078-->), precluding direct analysis of the role of laminins in synapse formation.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Activity-dependence of synapse development</title>
		<para>In vertebrate nervous system, synaptic activity plays a crucial role in shaping synaptic patterns. Not much is explored to address whether and how much activity plays a role in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. The cholinergic SAB neurons innervate head muscles, and show synapse sprouting and alterations in mutants with reduced cholinergic synaptic transmission. A source for this activity-dependence seems to involve a retrograde signal (<link linkend="bib62">Zhao and Nonet, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10683178-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-122;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-122</ulink> is a conserved transmembrane protein containing collagen repeats and a cysteine-rich olfactomedin domain, and is localized to postsynaptic muscle arms (<link linkend="bib24">Loria et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14999070-->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-122" role="_blank">unc-122</ulink></emphasis> mutants NMJ development is morphological normal, the GABAergic <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink> neuron displays axon sprouting due to impairment in synaptic transmission. It remains to be determined whether such axon and synapse spouting phenomena bear the same nature as those in other nervous system.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Perspectives</title>
		<para>The identification of mutants from the primary visual screen using synaptic GFP reporter genes opens up the venue for further identification of synaptic components through genetic modifier screens and molecular binding partners studies. A major puzzle is how SV clustering and density formation is coordinated. In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-104" role="_blank">unc-104</ulink></emphasis> animals, few synapses are detected with normal density (<link linkend="bib13">Hall and Hedgecock, 1991</link><!--; PMID 1710172-->). Yet, most of the density proteins are localized largely normal by light microscope analysis (<link linkend="bib14">Hallam et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12379863-->; <link linkend="bib22">Koushika et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11559854-->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syg-1" role="_blank">syg-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syg-2" role="_blank">syg-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants, although HSN synapses are formed at incorrect locations, the ectopic synapses have similar, but small, configuration (<link linkend="bib49">Shen et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15035988-->). Thus, SV clustering and density formation involve feedback mechanisms to which we know little about them. Understanding such mechanisms requires direct observation of synapse formation in real time. Necessary methodology that allows detection of synapse formation under low light and long period would greatly facilitate the studies of the dynamics of synaptic assembly. Ultrastructural analysis of synapses in young larvae would also be very informative.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Acknowledgement</title>
		<para>Special thanks to M. Nonet, R. Weimer, J-L. Bessereau, D. Hall, for communicating unpublished results. I appreciate discussions and support from A. Chisholm and members of my laboratory.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>References</title>
		<para/>
		&synapt_Refs;
	</sect1>
</article>
