<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'embvarfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'embvarfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'embvarfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'embvarfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'embvarfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'embvarfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'embvarfig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'embvarfig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'embvarfig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'embvarfig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'embvarfig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'embvarfig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig7 SYSTEM 'embvarfig7.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig7legend SYSTEM 'embvarfig7leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig8 SYSTEM 'embvarfig8.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig8legend SYSTEM 'embvarfig8leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig9 SYSTEM 'embvarfig9.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig9legend SYSTEM 'embvarfig9leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY embvar_Refs SYSTEM 'embvarrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="embvar_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Embryological variation during nematode development<footnote>
                <para>Edited by James M. Priess and Geraldine Seydoux. Last revised April 28, 2005. Published January 02, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Schierenberg, E. Embryological variation during nematode development (January 02, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.55.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 Einhard Schierenberg. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
            </footnote>
       </title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 4/28/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory> 
-->
        <author>
            <firstname>Einhard</firstname>
            <surname>Schierenberg<remark>
                    <footnote>
                        <para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:e.schierenberg@uni-koeln.de">e.schierenberg@uni-koeln.de</ulink></para>
                    </footnote>
                </remark>
            </surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Zoological Institute, University of Cologne, D-50923 K&#x000F6;ln, Germany</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Early cell lineages and arrangement of blastomeres in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">are similar to the
            pattern found in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Ascaris</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">and other studied nematodes leading to the assumption that
            embryonic development shows little variation within the phylum Nematoda. However,
            analysis of a larger variety of species from various branches of the phylogenetic tree
            demonstrate that prominent variations in crucial steps of early embryogenesis exist
            among representatives of this taxon. So far, most of these variations have only been
            studied on a descriptive level and thus essentially nothing is known about their
            molecular or genetic basis. Nevertheless, it is obvious that the limited morphological
            diversity of the freshly hatched juvenile and the uniformity of the basic body plan
            contrast with the many modifications in the way a worm is generated from the egg cell.
            This chapter focuses on the initial phase between egg activation and gastrulation and
            deals with the following aspects: reproduction and diploidy, polarity, cleavage and
            germ line, cell lineages; cell cycles and maternal contribution, cell-cell communication
            and cell specification, gastrulation.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
    <sect1 id="sec1">
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>Embryogenesis of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has been studied in detail (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html" role="_blank">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>).
            As the early cell lineages and arrangement of blastomeres (<link linkend="bib32">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!--;
            PMID 6684600-->) were found to be similar to the classic model <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib5">Boveri, 1899</link>) and
            other studied representatives of the phylum (<link linkend="bib30">Skiba and Schierenberg, 1992</link><!--: PMID 1601187-->),
            the implicit assumption has been that the pattern of embryonic development is very
            similar among nematodes. However, as we know now, this conception is inaccurate. More
            recent analysis of a larger variety of species (see below) and older data from Russian
            researchers, which only became available with the English translation of Malakhov's
            (1994) book on nematodes, demonstrate that prominent variations in crucial steps of
            early embryogenesis exist (<link linkend="bib12">Goldstein, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11604120-->). So far, most of these
            variations have only been studied on a descriptive level and thus essentially nothing is
            known about their molecular or genetic basis. Nevertheless, it is obvious that the
            limited morphological diversity of the freshly hatched juvenile (e.g., structure of
            mouth, pharynx, and tail) and the uniformity of the basic body plan contrast with the
            many modifications in the way a worm is generated from the egg cell. Often species-or
            even group-specific structural peculiarities like large body size, gonadal structure or
            appendages develop only during the postembryonic phase. As the vast majority of
            variations have been discovered during early embryogenesis, this chapter focuses on the
            initial phase between egg activation and gastrulation. The assumed phylogenetic position
            of all taxa mentioned in the text can be deduced from <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>. For
            easier reference the assignment of species to a specific clade according to <link linkend="bib3">Blaxter et
            al. (1998)</link> is given in parantheses.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure1">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig1" width="5.5in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 1</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec2">
        <title>Reproduction and diploidy</title>
        <para>Nematodes show various modes of reproduction (<link linkend="bib18">Laugsch and Schierenberg, 2004</link><!--:
            PMID 15470638-->) including parthenogenesis which is frequently found in some taxa like
            <emphasis>Cephalobidae</emphasis> or <emphasis>Plectida</emphasis> (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). In comparison to the situation in
            bisexual or hermaphroditic species, parthenogenesis requires a number of modifications
            during oogenesis or embryogenesis including the preservation or restoration of diploidy
            in the absence of sperm. The finding that haploid <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos arrest during the
            second half of embryogenesis (<link linkend="bib26">Schierenberg and Wood, 1985</link><!--: PMID 3972159-->) indicates that a
            diploid status is crucial for normal development. How diploidy is achieved in embryos of
            three parthenogenetic species, <emphasis>Diploscapter coronatus</emphasis>, <emphasis>Acrobeloides nanus</emphasis> and <emphasis>Plectus</emphasis>
            sp. (lab designation ES 601) can be deduced from the pattern of meiotic divisions
            accompanying the formation of polar bodies (PBs). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (clade V) two PBs are
            generated as a result of two consecutive meiotic divisions (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2a</link>).
            In <emphasis>D. coronatus</emphasis>, a close relative of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>), also
            two PBs are present (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2b</link>), however, these result from a mitotic
            division of the first PB. In <emphasis>A. nanus</emphasis> (clade IV) usually only one large PB is formed
                (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2c</link>). Thus, in these two species the diploid status is
            evidently reached via a truncated meiosis. In contrast, in <emphasis>Plectus</emphasis> sp.(PCM group) two
            PBs are formed (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2d</link>) in a regular two-step meiosis. Preliminary
            data suggest that here an extra DNA replication cycle is inserted before first cleavage
            to restore diploidy.</para>
        <para>Thus, variant solutions appear to exist for the same developmental challenge, i.e.
            establishment of diploidy. Together with the scattered phylogenetic distribution of
            parthenogenetic species these findings support the view that parthenogenetic
            reproduction has been acquired independently in different branches of the nematode phylum.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure2">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.5in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 2</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec3">
        <title>Polarity</title>
        <para>It has been shown in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> that the sperm has another important function for
            embryogenesis besides contributing its DNA and centrosome. Its entrance into the egg
            induces the primary polarity, i.e. defines the posterior pole (<link linkend="bib13">Goldstein and Hird, 1996</link><!--:
            PMID 8625834-->) whereby the primary spatial cue derives from microtubules emanating from
            the sperm asters (<link linkend="bib35">Wallenfang and Seydoux, 2000</link><!--: PMID 11081513-->, see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_controloocytematuration/controloocytematuration.html" role="_blank">Control of oocyte meiotic maturation and fertilization</ulink>). As
            oocytes of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are usually fertilized at the pole that enters the spermatheca
            first, cleaving embryos in the uterus point (with few exceptions) with their posterior
            pole towards the vulva (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3a</link>).</para>
        <para>Despite the absence of sperm, parthenogenetic nematodes express an anterior-posterior
            (a-p) polarity similar to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> in that with their first cleavage they generate a
            larger somatic cell <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> and a smaller germ line cell P<subscript>1</subscript>.</para>
        <para>In <emphasis>A. nanus</emphasis> (clade IV) embryos point (with few exceptions) with their anterior pole
            toward the vulva (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3b</link>). Thus, here some external cue other than
            sperm seems to induce the direction of egg polarity. A similar conclusion has been drawn
            by <link linkend="bib14">Goldstein et al. (1998</link><!--: PMID 9443914-->) for a bisexual <emphasis>Acrobeloides</emphasis> species where the
            position of the sperm bears no consistent relationship to embryonic polarity. Their data
            suggest that in the suborder <emphasis>Cephalobinae</emphasis>, independent of the mode of reproduction, a
            different mechanism has evolved to establish embryonic polarity. As in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> the
            meiotic spindle can induce polarity under certain circumstances (<link linkend="bib35">Wallenfang and Seydoux,
            2000</link><!--: PMID 11081513-->) it may play a role in the establishment of the &#x0201C;reversed&#x0201D; polarity
            in <emphasis>A. nanus</emphasis> embryos. In <emphasis>D. coronatus</emphasis> (clade V), half of the embryos point with their
            anterior pole toward the vulva and half with their posterior pole (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3c, d</link>). Hence, fixation of the a-p orientation in the egg cell seems
            to occur in a random fashion independent of an external signal. Thus, there are
            obviously different ways among nematodes for embryonic polarity to be established prior
            to first cleavage.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure3">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4.5in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 3</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec4">
        <title>Cleavage and germ line</title>
        <para>In members of clades III-V plus the &#x0201C;PCM&#x0201D; group (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>), the first
            cleavage goes along with a separation into a larger soma (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink>) and a smaller germ line
            cell (P<subscript>1</subscript>). This process of soma/germ line separation continues during the following
            divisions finally resulting in the establishment of a small number of somatic founder
            cells and the primordial germ cell (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_specgermline/specgermline.html" role="_blank">Specification of the germ line</ulink>). This type of cleavage has been named
            &#x0201C;strong expression of the germ line&#x0201D; (<link linkend="bib27">Schierenberg and Lahl, 2004</link>).</para>
        <para> Representatives of clade I were found to behave differently (<link linkend="bib19">Malakhov, 1994</link>; Lahl and
            Schierenberg, unpublished). In <emphasis>Trichuris muris</emphasis> the first division is extremely
            asymmetric but the following ones are more or less equal (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4a,b</link>)
            while in Prionchulus clear asymmetric cleavages can only be detected at a later stage
                (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4c, d</link>). This cleavage behavior, which may be characteristic
            for clade I, has been named &#x0201C;weak expression of the germ line&#x0201D; (<link linkend="bib27">Schierenberg and Lahl, 2004</link>).</para>
        <para>Even more dramatic deviations from the standard pattern are found in clade II. In the
            handful of species studied so far (<link linkend="bib19">Malakhov, 1994</link>; <link linkend="bib33">Voronov, 1999</link>; Schierenberg, 2004) no
            early asymmetric cleavages and thus no a-p polarity has been detected at all (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5a, b</link>). It remains to be determined whether in these species, which
            are all dioecious, a hidden early germ line exists or whether germ cells are generated
            via a different mechanism. At least the sperm does not have the same polarizing function
            in these species as it does in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure4">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig4" width="5in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 4</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>The germ line in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> contains cytoplasmic granules which play an important role
            for the preservation of germ line identity (<link linkend="bib31">Strome et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID 7835156-->; <link linkend="bib29">Seydoux and
            Schedl, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11131515-->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_specgermline/specgermline.html" role="_blank">Specification of the germ line</ulink>). Antibodies directed against
            these so-called P granules were found to also detect cellular structures in early
            embryos of other nematode species of clade IV and V. However, their localization can
            differ from the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> pattern (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>; <link linkend="bib30">Skiba and Schierenberg, 1992</link><!--: PMID 1601187-->; <link linkend="bib14">Goldstein et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9443914-->). In those cases where
            intranuclear components are detected in all cells (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5c</link>), the <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> antibodies seem to cross-react with structures unrelated to germ line.</para>
        <para>A classical example for developmental variations among the nematodes is constituted by
            the case of &#x0201C;chromatin diminution&#x0201D; in <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis> (clade III), where nearly all blastomeres
            lose a large fraction of their chromatin. Those few cells that do not were identified as
            germ line cells (<link linkend="bib1">Boveri, 1887</link>) giving support for the earlier postulated &#x0201C;continuity of
            the germplasm&#x0201D; (<link linkend="bib36">Weismann, 1885</link>). This unusual mode of making cells different from each
            other is not found in any of the other nematodes mentioned in this chapter but has
            apparently developed independently in a small number of unrelated species from different
            animal phyla. Its underlying mechanism and significance are only partly understood
                (<link linkend="bib21">M&#x000FC;ller and Tobler, 2000</link><!--:
            PMID 107315621-->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_quicktourdiversity/quicktourdiversity.html" role="_blank">A quick tour of nematode diversity and the backbone of nematode phylogeny</ulink>).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure5">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig5" width="1.8in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 5</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec5">
        <title>Cell lineages</title>
        <para>The impressively detailed studies on cellular development in the <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis> (clade III)
            embryo more than a hundred years ago (<link linkend="bib20">Muller, 1903</link>) strongly suggested the existence of
            invariant cell lineages. The complete description of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryogenesis on a
            cell-by-cell basis (<link linkend="bib32">Sulston et al., 1983</link>) revealed that it is very similar to <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis>
            and gave proof that the old assumption was correct.</para>
        <para>More recent analysis of nematodes embryogenesis in different clades uncovered that the
            order of early cleavages can vary considerably among species, particularly with respect
            to the germ line and can be correlated to the developmental tempo (<link linkend="bib30">Skiba and
            Schierenberg, 1992</link><!--: PMID 1601187-->). While, for instance in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> the primordial germ
            cell P<subscript>4</subscript> is formed when 16 <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cells have been already generated, in some <emphasis>Acrobeloides</emphasis>
            species, which develop several times slower, all embryonic germ line divisions are
            executed before any of the somatic cells divide (<link linkend="bib23">Schierenberg, 1997</link>). Based on
            experiments where after artificially delayed divisions a reduced number of asymmetric
            germ line divisions took place, it was postulated that the preservation of germ line
            identity requires the timely separation from the soma (<link linkend="bib28">Schlicht and Schierenberg, 1991</link>).</para>
        <para>To fully appreciate how variable embryogenesis can be among nematodes, lineages have
            to be followed completely and terminal differentiation must be monitored. Besides <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib32">Sulston et al. (1983</link><!--: PMID 6684600-->), this has only been done in a close
            relative, <emphasis>Pellioditis marina</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib15">Houthoofd et al, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12781682-->). It was found that
            lineage homology between the two species is very high (about 95%) but fate homology
            considerably lower (about 75%). The authors suggested that the differences in the fate
            distribution pattern are due to different compromises between minimizing the number of
            specification events and minimizing the need for time-consuming cell migrations.</para>
        <para>In members of clade II, due to the absence of a visible germ line (see <link linkend="sec4">section 4</link>)
            initially no cell lineages can be defined. All blastomeres look alike and occupy
            variable positions relative to each other. In <emphasis>Enoplus brevis</emphasis> at the 8-cell stage, one
            blastomere divides with some delay. This is the founder cell for the intestine
            generating the only cell lineage that has been identified so far. Other blastomeres
            appear to adopt variable fates at a later stage (see <link linkend="sec7">section 7</link>).</para>
        <para>In contrast to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and most of the other studied nematodes, in members of
            clades I and II the gut founder cell has been described to come from the anterior
            blastomere of the 2-cell stage (<link linkend="bib19">Malakhov, 1994</link>; for a variable origin or an origin not
            related to the a-p axis in <emphasis>Enoplida</emphasis>, see <link linkend="bib34">Voronov and Panchin; 1998</link><!--: PMID 9738496-->;
            <link linkend="bib33">Voronov, 1999</link>).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec6">
        <title>Cell cycles and maternal contribution</title>
        <para>The duration of early embryonic cell cycles differs dramatically among nematodes.
            While in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> they are as short as 10 minutes, in the marine <emphasis>E. brevis</emphasis> (clade II) they
            require 6 to 7 hours. The analysis of maternal-effect mutants demonstrates that in <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> early embryogenesis depends heavily on gene products already synthesized during
            oogenesis (<link linkend="bib6">Bowerman, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9475998-->). Drug-induced inhibition of transcription
            revealed that the rapid cleavages including proper soma/germ line separation continue
            beyond the 100-cell stage under these conditions (<link linkend="bib10">Edgar et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID 7512022-->).
            However, this does not apply for nematodes in general. In <emphasis>A. nanus</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib37">Wiegner and
            Schierenberg, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9851839-->) but also in other Rhabditis species, without
            transcription cleavage ceases after a few divisions. In addition, cell cycle durations
            change over time. While for instance in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> the tempo of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cell cycles becomes
            slower, in <emphasis>A. nanus</emphasis> they become faster, and in <emphasis>Rhabditis dolichura</emphasis> they first become
            slower and then faster (<link linkend="bib18">Laugsch and Schierenberg, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15470638-->). These variations
            can be explained with different availability of maternal and zygotic gene products
                (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure6">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig6" width="3.1in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 6</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig6legend;</mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec7">
        <title>Cell-cell communication and cell specification</title>
        <para>Cell-specification in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> involves two mechanisms. First, early blastomeres are
            assigned different fates by unequally segregated maternal factors. Second, cell-cell
            interactions can modulate or completely alter the original developmental program of a
            cell (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html" role="_blank">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>).
            Only few data are available on experimental analysis of cell specification in other
            nematode embryos. In <emphasis>E. brevis</emphasis>, where no germ line and only one somatic lineage have been
            detected (see <link linkend="sec4">sections 4</link> and <link linkend="sec5">5</link>), development of partial embryos and cell marking
            experiments (<link linkend="bib34">Voronov and Panchin, 1997</link><!--: PMID 9738496-->) indicate that as a rule blastomeres
            are not specified early and embryos possess a considerable regulative potential.</para>
        <para>Also a nematode much more closely related to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> shows an unexpected degree of
            developmental plasticity. In <emphasis>A. nanus</emphasis> (clade IV) early blastomeres appear to compete
            for a primary fate (<link linkend="bib38">Wiegner and Schierenberg, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10525346-->). After ablation of
            early blastomeres, the embryos can still develop into a juvenile because the remaining
            blastomeres switch their fates in a hierarchical manner (<link linkend="figure7">Figure 7</link>). In
            the same species the spatial arrangement of posterior blastomeres varies considerably
            among individuals, prompting experiments wherein the role of the germ line as the source
            of inductions was investigated. They revealed that an induction of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> by the germ line
            cell P<subscript>2</subscript>, as found in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html" role="_blank">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>),
            is not required for proper specification of the gut precursor cell <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink>. Here early
            somatic blastomeres are pluripotent and inhibiting interactions among them appear to
            ensure different cell fate assignments (<link linkend="figure8">Figure 8</link>; <link linkend="bib37">Wiegner and
            Schierenberg, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9851839-->).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure7" xreflabel="Figure7">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig7" width="4.7in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 7</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig7legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>A somewhat comparable situation seems to exist in <emphasis>D. coronatus</emphasis> (clade V). Here all
            early blastomeres are aligned along the a-p axis because a rotation of the
            nuclear-centrosome complex takes place, not only in cells of the germ line like in <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib16">Hyman and White, 1987</link><!--: PMID 3680373-->) but also in the anterior somatic blastomere
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink>. An induction of the germ line P<subscript>2</subscript> making <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> different from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABa;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABa</ulink> as found in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
            (<link linkend="bib7">Bowerman et al., 1992</link><!--PMID 1295733-->) does apparently not take place in this species,
            as cell arrangements are variable and P<subscript>2</subscript> never touches <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> (Lahl and Schierenberg, unpublished).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure8" xreflabel="Figure8">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig8" width="3in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 8</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig8legend;</mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec8">
        <title>Gastrulation</title>
        <para>Gastrulation as seen in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> leads to a triblastic embryo with only a
            rudimentary blastocoel present. It can be subdivided into two distinct phases, (i)
            ingression of the two gut precursors (E cells) starting at the 26-cell stage (<link linkend="figure9">Figure 9a</link>) and (ii) immigration of a larger number of mesodermal progenitors
            derived from different lineages at a much higher cell stage (<link linkend="bib32">Sulston et al., 1983</link>). Here only variations of the first step, the generation of a
            gut primordium, will be considered. This process appears to be similar in members of
            clades I, III, IV and V (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>), even in <emphasis>Enoplida</emphasis> (<link linkend="figure9">Figure 9c, d</link>) with
            their unusual cleavage pattern (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4j-l</link>). However, in <emphasis>Plectida</emphasis>
            (&#x0201C;PCM group&#x0201D;) gastrulation starts as early as the 8-cell stage and it is always the gut
            founder cell itself that immigrates (<link linkend="figure9">Figure 9b</link>; <link linkend="bib17">
Lahl et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12590349-->). Other
            members of the &#x0201C;PCM group&#x0201D; (Chromadorida, Monhysterida) show the same phenomenon
            (<link linkend="bib19">Malakhov, 1994</link>; <link linkend="bib27">Schierenberg and Lahl, 2004</link>; E.S., unpublished).</para>
        <para>The most unexpected variant, however, is seen in <emphasis>Tobrilus diversipapillatus</emphasis>, a member
            of the <emphasis>Triplonchida</emphasis> (clade II). Here, in contrast to all other nematodes studied so far,
            a large blastocoel is formed and cells migrate into this cavity after the 64-cell stage
            (<link linkend="bib25">Schierenberg, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15592936-->; <link linkend="figure9">Figure 9e, f</link>). Thus, this species
            follows the "classical" type widely distributed in the animal kingdom which is
            considered a plesiomorphic character (<link linkend="bib2">Arendt, 2004</link>). Structural and molecular analyses
            suggest that clade II may represent the most ancient branch of nematodes (<link linkend="bib19">Malakhov,
            1994</link>; <link linkend="bib1">Aleshin et al., 1998</link>). The developmental findings demonstrate that within the
            nematode phylum not only a switch from one cleavage type to another (see <link linkend="sec4">section 4</link>) has
            taken place but also from one type of gastrulation to another. So far no obvious
            correlations have been found between the type of gastrulation and other developmental
            parameters like embryo size, cell numbers or developmental tempo (<link linkend="bib25">Schierenberg, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15592936-->).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure9" xreflabel="Figure9">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig9" width="4in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 9</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig9legend;</mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec9">
        <title>Concluding remarks</title>
        <para>The data summarized in this chapter document that embryogenesis in nematodes is more
            variable than the final product, the hatching juvenile, would predict. While
            unexpectedly large genetic differences exist even between closely related nematode
            species (<link linkend="bib11">Fitch et al., 1997</link>), their special body plan apparently prevented a
            corresponding degree of morphological diversification as found in other phyla like
            arthropods or vertebrates. The wealth of early developmental variations appears
            paradoxical in a way, as these do not have any obvious impact on structure or
            performance of the resulting worms. Why then are there different ways to reach
            essentially the same goal? Two explanations appear possible. It could either be a result
            of neutral evolution, i.e. variations are due to system-inherent plasticity without any
            adaptive value. Alternatively, the different ways may reflect alternative developmental
            strategies to increase fitness, for instance by making production faster or cheaper
            (<link linkend="bib24">Schierenberg, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11536296-->).</para>
        <para>It is not immediately clear why early embryogenesis should be more variable than later
            phases. One argument has been that development is modular and integration of the
            emerging modules increases over time, putting fewer constraints on early development
            (<link linkend="bib22">Raff, 1996</link>). This seems reasonable for organisms where cells are specified relatively
            late, like vertebrates and may-be very slow developing nematodes like Enoplids. However,
            in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> type of development, essential decisions requiring intercellular
            communication have been shifted to a very early phase. Thus, it can be questioned
            whether this argument is valid for fast developing nematodes.</para>
        <para>In order to correlate ontogeny and phylogeny, embryonic variations may be useful
            heuristically as phylogenetic markers in addition to morphology and molecules because
            (i) they are potentially independent of these parameters and (ii) they constitute events
            rather than structures and therefore represent a different quality of information
            (<link linkend="bib24">Schierenberg, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11536296-->). By looking at processes like axis specification
            (<link linkend="bib14">Goldstein et al.; 1998</link><!--: PMID 9443914-->), cleavage pattern, arrangement of blastomeres
            (<link linkend="bib9">Dolinski et al., 2001</link>), germ line behavior and gastrulation (<link linkend="bib27">Schierenberg and Lahl,
            2004</link>; <link linkend="bib25">Schierenberg, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15592936-->), attempts have been made to trace the evolution
            of embryonic diversity in nematodes.</para>
        <para>By extending comparative studies to a larger number of species and by identifying
            relevant genes, we should learn more about the intrinsic prerequisites for the
            implementation of embryonic novelty. It will be even more ambitious to try to understand
            to what extent the Darwinian rules of variation and selection apply to developmental
            processes and how the interplay between internal genetic provision and external
            conditions determines the chance for a deviation from an original embryonic pattern to
            arise and to succeed.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec10">
        <title>Acknowledgements</title>
        <para>Much of the work performed in my laboratory was supported by the Deutsche
            Forschungsgemeinschaft, partly through SFB 572.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec11">
        <title>References</title>
		<para/>
		&embvar_Refs;</sect1>
</article>