<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'nemaisolatfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'nemaisolatfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'nemaisolatfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'nemaisolatfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'nemaisolatfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'nemaisolatfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'nemaisolatfig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'nemaisolatfig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'nemaisolatfig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'nemaisolatfig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY nemaisolat_Refs SYSTEM 'nemaisolatrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="nemaisolat_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title>Isolation of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and related nematodes<footnote>
			<para>Edited by Ralf J. Sommer. WormMethods editor, Victor Ambros. Last revised May 10, 2006. Published July 17, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Barri&#x000E8;re, A. and F&#x000E9;lix, M.-A. Isolation of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and related nematodes (July 17, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.115.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 Antoine Barri&#x000E8;re and Marie-Anne F&#x000E9;lix. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
		<author>
			<othername>Antoine Barri&#x000E8;re and Marie-Anne F&#x000E9;lix<remark>
				<footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:felix@ijm.jussieu.fr">felix@ijm.jussieu.fr</ulink></para></footnote>
				</remark></othername>
				<affiliation><address>Institut Jacques Monod, CNRS - Universities of Paris, 75251 Paris cedex 05, France</address></affiliation>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
	<para>The easiest and most efficient way to recover <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and some other nematodes from soil or any other substrate is to place the sample onto a standard <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> culture plate (see <link linkend="sec2">section 2</link>). Alternative methods used by nematologists to recover soil nematodes (see <link linkend="sec3">sections 3</link> and <link linkend="sec4">4</link>) are in our hands more difficult to implement and only yield a fraction of the individuals in the sample. More detailed information on different sampling methods can be found in <link linkend="bib12">Hooper (1986)</link> or <link linkend="bib6">De Ley and Mundo-Ocampo (2004)</link>. The most difficult part is then to recognize your species of interest out of the zoo of species that comes with a typical soil or compost sample (see <link linkend="sec5">section 5</link>). We summarize the organization and timing of an isolation experiment (see <link linkend="sec6">section 6</link>). Finally, culture (see <link linkend="sec7">section 7</link>) and freezing (see <link linkend="sec8">section 8</link>) conditions are briefly reviewed. Bear in mind that this chapter is strongly biased towards the isolation of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> and close relatives.</para>
</sect1>
<?newpage?>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Isolation on an agar culture plate</title>
<para>The easiest way to recover nematodes from soil is simply to place the substrate around the bacterial lawn of a standard <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> culture dish (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html">Maintenance of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). Bacteria-feeding nematodes such as <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are attracted and crawl out of the sample towards the bacterial lawn (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). For fast-moving species like <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, this occurs within minutes to hours.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="6in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<itemizedlist mark="dash">
<listitem><para>Spread about 1&#x02013;2 grams of soil around the <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> OP50 lawn of a standard NGM Petri dish, and moisten with about 1 ml M9 solution (3 g KH<subscript>2</subscript>PO<subscript>4</subscript>, 6 g Na<subscript>2</subscript>HPO<subscript>4</subscript>, 5 g NaCl, 1 ml 1 M MgSO<subscript>4</subscript>, H<subscript>2</subscript>O to 1 liter. Sterilize by autoclaving.) or water.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Pick individual worms that have crawled out to a new plate (in obligate male-female species, worms of both sexes or a mated female are required). Worms are ideally picked within a few hours after the sample has been placed on the plate. Later on, growing bacteria and fungi species that have been introduced with the sample may prevent worms from accessing the OP50 lawn (to avoid such growth, the sample can be moistened with 0.01% thimerosal in M9).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Using this method, all developmental stages can be recovered from soil and compost samples in a quantitative manner (except for the embryonic stages, which can only be retrieved after hatching). The number of individuals in the original sample can be measured in this way (<link linkend="bib4">Barri&#x000E8;re and F&#x000E9;lix, 2005</link><!--; PMID 16005289-->). Some nematode species, including <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis>, will eventually form dauers that present a characteristic waving behavior: they &#x02018;stand&#x02019; on their tail on any substrate with a narrow tip (the substrate or the molds that grow out of it) and move their body, putatively as a way to be carried away by an invertebrate. One can thus a posteriori check that every <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> individual has been picked by the absence of waving dauer larvae after 6&#x02013;10 days.</para>
<para>Many nematode species are associated with invertebrates (molluscs, arthropods, etc.) during the dauer stage (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_ecolCaenorhabditis/ecolCaenorhabditis.html">Ecology of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species</ulink>; <link linkend="bib13">Kiontke, 1997</link>). They can be recovered by sacrifying the carriers, placing them on NGM plates and waiting for the worms to move to the OP50 lawn or collect them directly from the decaying invertebrate host.</para>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has been isolated from compost heaps (decaying leaves or vegetal matter), garden soil and carrier invertebrates (<link linkend="bib4">Barri&#x000E8;re and F&#x000E9;lix, 2005</link><!--; PMID 16005289-->; <link linkend="bib5">Cutter, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16272415-->; <link linkend="bib10">Haber et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15371529-->; <link linkend="bib15">Sivasundar and Hey, 2005</link><!--; PMID 16139217-->). Recently, we also found large populations of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species in fruits decaying under their tree (figs, apples, etc.).</para>
</sect1>
<?newpage?>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Baermann funnel</title>
<para>This is the classical method to recover all species of nematodes, particularly those not attracted by <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis>. Many modifications and improvements are possible, and here we show only a single basic design.</para>
<itemizedlist mark="dash">
<listitem><para>Fit a rubber tube onto the stem of a funnel (diameter ca. 50 mm). Close the tube with a clamp (a simple paperclip can be used instead) and fill the rubber tubing with M9 solution up to the neck of the funnel (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Line the funnel cone with a piece of sieve (standard cleaning tissue, muslin, mosquito mesh&#x02026;), then fill with soil material and fold to enclose the sample. Add M9 solution or water until the sample is submerged.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Active nematodes crawl through the sieve and sediment at the end of the tubing. Recover them by opening the clamp (after a few hours until several days).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="2.5in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>A problem with the Baermann funnel technique, especially when isolating worms from bacteria-rich samples, is the poor oxygenation of the sample that results in nematode mortality.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Centrifugal flotation</title>
<para>Terrestrial nematodes have a specific gravity of 1.08 and can be recovered by flotation on a solution with a specific gravity of 1.15 (<link linkend="bib12">Hooper, 1986</link>). This method is best used with soil samples, whereas decaying leaves or compost material yield too much detritus.</para>
<para>Several solutions can be used:</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Sucrose</emphasis> - inexpensive, but sticky and has a strong osmotic effect that harms the worms (1.71 mol/L for a density of 1.15).</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">MgSO<subscript>4</subscript></emphasis> - less sticky than sucrose, but also has a strong osmotic effect (1.38 mol/L).</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Ludox</emphasis> - colloidal silica: expensive, but weak osmotic effect; samples can therefore be extracted several times, in contrast to extraction with the other solutions. Ludox comes in two forms: Ludox HS40, toxic, that may be used for fixed samples, and Ludox AS, non-toxic, that is best used to recover live material. A 50% solution in water has a specific gravity of 1.15.</para>
<itemizedlist mark="dash">
<listitem><para>If your sample contains a lot of debris, rinse it first over a 1 mm mesh to remove the bulkiest fragments (this will however remove some of the nematodes).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Soak the sample in water and centrifuge at 1,800 g to obtain a compact pellet, and eliminate the supernatant.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Resuspend the pellet in 20 ml of the chosen solution of density 1.15 and centrifuge at 1,800 g for 1 minute. Add 2 to 5 ml of water or M9 buffer on top and centrifuge again for 5-15 minutes. Nematodes will accumulate at the interface between the two solutions.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Pipet the worms at the interface (some can be seen with the naked eye) using a cut 1 ml pipette tip.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Rinse them in M9, centrifuge, and pipet the pellet onto a standard NGM culture plate.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Identifying <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> and other species</title>
<para>The worms can be identified by morphological criteria either as they come out of the substrate, or on their progeny after they were brought in culture (see <link linkend="sec6">section 6</link>). Except for a few plant parasitic nematodes (which are very long nematodes with a stylet in the mouth that helps them invading their hosts) and fungal feeders like aphelenchids, most nematodes from soil or compost samples belong to one of four families: Rhabditidae (including <emphasis>Caenorhabditis, Oscheius, Mesorhabditis</emphasis>, etc.), Diplogastridae (<emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis>), Panagrolaimidae (<emphasis>Panagrolaimus</emphasis>) and Cephalobidae (<emphasis>Cephalobus</emphasis>). A first diagnosis can be performed using a compound microscope, based on mouth morphology (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). There is, to date, no easy-to-use identification key for soil nematodes. The best way to identify the genus or the species is to compare with published drawings. For a detailed guide of soil nematodes, see <link linkend="bib1">Andrassy (1983</link>, or <link linkend="bib2">1984</link>, in German); for the Rhabditidae, see <link linkend="bib16">Sudhaus and Fitch (2001)</link>; for the <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species, see <link linkend="bib17">Sudhaus and Kiontke (1996)</link>. Note that soil nematode diversity is huge and that most species are still undescribed. We detail below how to identify <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and closely related <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="5.5in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<sect2 id="sec5_1">
<title>Morphology</title>
<para>Here are some tips to identify <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> under the dissecting microscope: <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> hermaphrodites/females move relatively fast and elegantly, have a pointy tail, which folds back on itself when the worm is moving backwards. Most characteristically, the gut has a homogeneous light brown color under transmitted illumination and displays few large cell nuclei (which appear white). By contrast, most other nematodes have a greyer and darker gut, often with an antero-posterior asymmetry in pigment intensity, and with a large number of small or barely visible cell nuclei (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>). The <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> vulva is located towards the middle of the animal along the antero-posterior axis. With proper illumination, it is possible to see the second pharyngeal bulb (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="5in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 4</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="5in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 5</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
<para>In rich soil or in a compost sample, <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> animals are mostly found in the dauer stage, which makes them difficult to recognize by the above criteria. By experience, the longest dauers of compost samples are often <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>, whereas the smaller ones are of the <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> genus. If one waits for a week for the culture to bloom, <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> may appear in the form of waving dauers (some other species also adopt this behavior, but not <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis>).</para>
<para>When the worms are mounted and observed under a compound microscope, additional traits that characterize <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> are its mouth shape (Rhabditidae; <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>) and the wide cytoplasmic rachis (see Figure 1 in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transformationmicroinjection/transformationmicroinjection.html" role="_blank">Transformation and microinjection</ulink>) in the center of the two-armed (didelphic) hermaphrodite/female gonad. <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> species can be best recognized by their long rectum (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>).</para>
</sect2>
<?newpage?>
<sect2 id="sec5_2">
<title>Species-specific RNAi</title>
<para>Most <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> isolates are sensitive to RNAi by feeding. <link linkend="bib15">Sivasundar and Hey (2005<!--; PMID 16139217-->)</link> developed a screen based on this feature: worms extracted from a soil sample are transferred onto a plate seeded with bacteria expressing dsRNA against <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-22" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink></emphasis>/twitchin (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_introreversegenetics/introreversegenetics.html">Reverse genetics</ulink>). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> individuals can be recognized within a few days by their twitching behavior, while other nematode species will be unaffected, because most are probably insensitive to RNAi by feeding, and moreover, the degree of gene similarity is too low for the inactivation of the orthologous gene to occur. There is however a caveat, as some natural strains of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> may be resistant to RNAi by feeding (<link linkend="bib15">Sivasundar and Hey, 2005<!--; PMID 16139217--></link>).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5_3">
<title>Molecular identification</title>
<para>Sequencing of the 18S ribosomal RNA (small subunit) gene with nematode-specific primers (<link linkend="bib8">Floyd et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11972769-->; <link linkend="bib10">Haber et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15371529-->) and blasting it against databases is another way to identify a species, or at least the group to which it belongs. Possible primers are:
<orderedlist numeration="lowerroman">
<listitem><para>SSU18A (5<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol>-AAAGATTAAGCCATGCATG-3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol>)</para>
<para>and SSU26R (5<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol>-CATTCTTGGCAAATGCTTTCG-3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol>),</para>
<para>which amplify a 1 kb fragment of 18S rDNA in rhabditid nematodes (<link linkend="bib5">Floyd et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11972769-->), or</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>RHAB1350F (5<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol>-TACAATGGAAGGCAGCAGGC-3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol>)</para>
<para>and RHAB1868R (5<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol>-CCTCTGACTTTCGTTCTTGATTAA-3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol>),</para>
<para>which amplify a fragment of about 500 bp (<link linkend="bib10">Haber et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15371529-->).</para></listitem>
</orderedlist></para>
<para>In order to discriminate between closely related <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species (especially the hermaphroditic species <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>), one can perform a PCR using species-specific oligonucleotides (<link linkend="bib4">Barri&#x000E8;re and F&#x000E9;lix, 2005</link><!--; PMID 16005289-->). For example, the following species-specific PCR primers in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> gene amplify different fragment sizes in <emphasis>C. elegans, C. briggsae</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. remanei</emphasis>. PCR can be performed using all 6 primers in the same reaction (annealing T&#x000B0; of 60&#x000B0;C).</para>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>: CCGCTTGGATTCTATGGATTG and CTCTCCTTGCTCCGGGATTG, product: 208 bp.</para>
<para><emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>: GAACCTGCGAGTGCATGTAC and CCGTCTGCAAACGAACGGGC, product: 302 bp.</para>
<para><emphasis>C. remanei</emphasis>: CAACGGAGGTATCTGCTCAG and CCGCCGTCAAATTTGCATTC, product: 391 bp.</para>
<para>Different <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> species of the <emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> group can be distinguished using a PCR-RFLP test (<link linkend="bib7">F&#x000E9;lix et al., 2001</link>).</para>
<para>Different <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis> species are distinguished by sequencing of 18S RNA (<link linkend="bib11">Herrmann et al., 2006</link>).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5_4">
<title>Crosses</title>
<para>Species identity can be confirmed by crossing several virgin (L4 stage) females or hermaphrodites (all progeny of a single individual) with males of identified laboratory strains (about 5 animals of each sex are placed onto a culture plate). In hermaphroditic species, successful crosses can be scored by the occurrence of a high proportion of male progeny; in female-male species, the presence of (fertile) progeny is a sufficient indicator. Crosses between some closely related species (such as <emphasis>C. remanei</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>; <link linkend="bib3">Baird, 2002</link><!--; PMID 12136036-->) may yield a few (sterile) F1 progeny, but most of the eggs that are laid in these crosses never hatch. No progeny of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> with any other species has been reported so far. Strains of many species can be obtained either from the CGC (<ulink url="http://biosci.umn.edu/CGC/Strains/strains.htm">http://biosci.umn.edu/CGC/Strains/strains.htm</ulink>), the NYU Rhabditidae collection (<ulink url="http://www.nyu.edu/projects/fitch/WSRN/">http://www.nyu.edu/projects/ fitch/WSRN/</ulink>) or our collection (<ulink url="http://www2.ijm.jussieu.fr/worms/">http://www2.ijm.jussieu.fr/worms/</ulink>).</para>
<para>A refined method is to use males of laboratory strains that express dominant markers (e.g., GFP). In this case, cross-progeny are identified by the presence of the marker.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Typical time course and organization of an isolation experiment</title>
<para>The organization and timecourse of a nematode isolation experiment depend on its goal:</para>
<orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">If the goal is to isolate a specific species</emphasis>, it may be best recognized once in the adult stage and may be easier to spot after one generation on the plate. Some species are resistant to harsh conditions and can be isolated by plating the sample several weeks/months after its collection. <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> can be recovered after up to 10 days of sample collection, yet most likely with a much reduced efficiency compared to fresh samples.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">If the goal is to obtain an accurate representation of genetic diversity of a natural population</emphasis>, one needs to isolate the individuals that were present at the time of sampling, that is within a single generation (obviously, the time between sample isolation and plating must be reduced to the minimum).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">If the goal is to study wild worms and directly determine their number, sex, stage, associated bacteria, etc.</emphasis>, the worms need to be isolated within minutes to a few hours after sample collection.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
<sect2 id="sec6_1">
<title>Succession of appearance of the different nematode species on the plate</title>
<para>As mentioned above, <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> are easily spotted as dauers on the first day of plating, or as L4s/young adults on the second day. Individuals of <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis> species are best recognized after two days by their characteristic &#x02018;Dumpy&#x02019; appearance and the strong longitudinal ridges on the adult cuticle. Slow moving species that only become apparent after several days are cephalobs (these are also the major group of nematodes found in samples from dry soil) and <emphasis>Bunonema</emphasis> (tiny worms with a left-right asymmetric cuticle). Finally, when the plate is mostly depleted of bacteria and full of nematodes (6&#x02013;10 days), dauers appear again, some of which adopt a waving behavior and may belong to the <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> genus.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6_2">
<title>Security procedures</title>
<para>Be aware that some nematodes that can be found in soil samples such as <emphasis>Halicephalobus</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib14">Shadduck et al., 1979</link><!--; PMID 495570-->) or <emphasis>Pelodera</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib9">Ginsburg et al., 1984</link><!--; PMID 6542207-->; <link linkend="bib18">Tanaka et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15577765-->) have been described to be potentially harmful to humans. However, the major danger you may encounter is to contaminate your lab with wild mites, either nematophagous ones, swallowing worms like spaghettis, or bacterivorous ones, competing with nematodes and messing up cultures by transferring eggs and larvaes between plates. Good practice is keeping your sampling plates apart from your culture plates, and wrapping them with tight Parafilm. Mites can be killed by heating plates/incubators to 50&#x02013;60&#x000B0;C for a few hours; alternatively, dichlorobenzene moth balls have been reported to kill mites but not nematodes (K. Kiontke, personal communication).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">	
<title>Culture conditions</title>
<para>Some species of the Rhabditidae, Diplogastridae, Panagrolaimidae and Cephalobidae families can be grown on standard NGM plates seeded with OP50 (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html">Maintenance of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>); however, NGM is too rich for some other species, which prefer water plates (1% agar in water + 5 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003BC;</symbol>g/ml cholesterol).</para>
<para>Some species of other families require special culturing media or conditions (P. DeLey, personal communication). <emphasis>Bunonema</emphasis>, <emphasis>Tylocephalus</emphasis> and <emphasis>Plectus</emphasis> can be best cultured on soil plates (1% agar + 1% soil + 5 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003BC;</symbol>g/ml cholesterol), and <emphasis>Teratocephalus</emphasis> on water plates (1% agar in water + 5 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003BC;</symbol>g/ml cholesterol). Add ca. 2 ml of M9 solution to the <emphasis>Plectus</emphasis> and <emphasis>Teratocephalus</emphasis> cultures (they like to swim). Keep cultures at 15&#x02013;20&#x000B0;C, except for <emphasis>Bunonema</emphasis>, which grows best at 25&#x000B0;C.</para>
<para>Male-female species may be subject to inbreeding depression after a few generations of culturing in the lab. This is best avoided by taking a large number of worms (&gt;10) at each transfer and/or culturing them on larger (90 mm diameter) culture plates.</para>
</sect1>
<?newpage?>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>Freezing conditions</title>
<para>Many species can be frozen using the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> freezing protocol (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html">Maintenance of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). However, several species do not survive freezing using this method.</para>
<para>For species of the <emphasis>Mesorhabditis, Teratorhabditis, Pelodera, Poikilolaimus, Oscheius</emphasis> (Insectivora group) and <emphasis>Panagrolaimus</emphasis> genera, we have had more success using the <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis> protocol (using tap water in the freezing solution and PBS instead of M9 to resuspend the worms; R. Sommer, personal communication; or adding 1 mM CaCl<subscript>2</subscript> in the freezing solution, Andr&#x000E9; Pires da Silva, personal communication).</para>
<para>Finally, species of the Cephalobidae family are particularly drought-resistant and can be frozen by directly placing large chunks of a half-dried culture plate (slightly before it turns into an agar &#x02018;chip&#x02019;) into a tube at <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02212;</symbol>80&#x000B0;C; for &#x02018;revival&#x02019;, H<subscript>2</subscript>O or M9 solution is added to the tube for a few hours and the tube contents are then transferred to a new culture plate.</para>
<para><emphasis>We thank Asher Cutter, Karin Kiontke and two anonymous reviewers for helpful comments.</emphasis></para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec9">
<title>References</title>
&nemaisolat_Refs;
<para/>
</sect1>
</article>