<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY anthelminticdrugs.2_ref SYSTEM 'anthelminticdrugs.2_ref.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="anthelminticdrugs.2">
<articleinfo>
<title>Anthelmintic drugs and nematicides: studies in <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis><footnote><para>Edited by Peter J. Roy. Last revised January 3, 2014. Published December 16, 2014. This chapter should be cited as: Holden-Dye L. and Walker R.J. Anthelmintic drugs and nematicides: studies in <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> (December 22, 2014), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.143.2, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2014 Lindy Holden-Dye and Robert J. Walker. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para></footnote></title>
<author><othername>Lindy Holden-Dye<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:lmhd@soton.ac.uk">lmhd@soton.ac.uk</ulink></para></footnote></remark> and Robert J. Walker</othername>
<affiliation><orgname>Southampton Neuroscience Group (SoNG), Centre for Biological Sciences, University of Southampton, Southampton SO17 1BJ, UK.</orgname></affiliation></author></articleinfo>
<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Parasitic nematodes infect many species of animals throughout the phyla, including humans. Moreover, nematodes that parasitise plants are a global problem for agriculture. As such, these nematodes place a major burden on human health, on livestock production, on the welfare of companion animals and on crop production. In the 21<superscript>st</superscript> century there are two major challenges posed by the wide-spread prevalence of parasitic nematodes. First, many anthelmintic drugs are losing their effectiveness because nematode strains with resistance are emerging. Second, serious concerns regarding the environmental impact of the nematicides used for crop protection have prompted legislation to remove them from use, leaving agriculture at increased risk from nematode pests. There is clearly a need for a concerted effort to address these challenges. Over the last few decades the free-living nematode <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> has provided the opportunity to use molecular genetic techniques for mode of action studies for anthelmintics and nematicides. These approaches continue to be of considerable value. Less fruitful so far, but nonetheless potentially very useful, has been the direct use of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> for anthelmintic and nematicide discovery programmes. Here we provide an introduction to the use of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as a &lsquo;model&rsquo; parasitic nematode, briefly review the study of nematode control using <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and highlight approaches that have been of particular value with a view to facilitating wider-use of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as a platform for anthelmintic and nematicide discovery and development.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction to anthelmintics and nematicides</title>
<para>Anthelmintic is the term used to describe a drug used to treat infections of animals with parasitic worms. This includes both flat worms, e.g., flukes (trematodes) and tapeworms (cestodes) as well as round worms (nematodes). The parasites are of huge importance for human tropical medicine and for veterinary medicine. The World Health Organization estimates that 2 billion people harbour parasitic worm infections (<ulink url="http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs366/en/">http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs366/en/</ulink>) causing increased morbidity and mortality, while parasitic worms that infect livestock are an important animal welfare issue and place a major economic burden on food production. Domestic pets are also susceptible to parasitic worm infection and it is of note that the companion animal market is a key economic consideration for animal health companies undertaking drug discovery programmes.</para>
<para>The majority of anthelmintics and nematicides are limited in their action between trematodes, cestodes, and nematodes, for example, praziquantel, a drug used in the treatment of most humans infected with trematodes or cestodes and thought to act by disrupting calcium homeostasis (<link linkend="bib56">Greenberg, 2005</link>)<!--: PMID 16569296-->, has no activity against nematodes (see <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). Only benzimidazoles have cross-phyla activity and even then are more active against nematodes than against cestodes or trematodes.</para>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1. Key drugs registered for the treatment of parasitic worms in humans.</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<tbody>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Schistosomiasis (blood fluke)</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Intestinal round worms</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">Oxamnaquine</entry>
<entry align="left">Piperazine</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">Praziquantel</entry>
<entry align="left">Benzimidazoles</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry/>
<entry align="left">Morantel</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry/>
<entry align="left">Pyrantel</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Cestodiasis (tape worm)</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">Levamisole</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">Albendazole</entry>
<entry align="left">Avermectins and milbemycins</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">Niclosamide</entry>
<entry align="left">Tribendimidine</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">Benzimidazoles</entry>
<entry/>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">Praziquantel</entry>
<entry/>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Fasciolasis (liver fluke)</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Filariasis (tissue round worms)</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">Triclabendazole</entry>
<entry align="left">Diethylcarbamazine</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry/>
<entry align="left">Albendazole</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry/>
<entry align="left">Ivermectin</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>Despite the prevalence of parasitic worms, anthelmintic drug discovery is the poor relation of the pharmaceutical industry. The simple reason is that the nations that suffer most from these tropical diseases have little money to invest in drug discovery or therapy. It comes as no surprise therefore that the drugs available for human treatment were first developed as veterinary medicines. There is thus a pitifully small repertoire of chemotherapeutic agents available for treatment (see <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). In some respects, this situation has been exacerbated by the remarkable success of ivermectin over the last thirty years (<link linkend="bib45">Geary, 2005</link>)<!--: PMID 16126457-->, which has decreased motivation for anthelmintic drug discovery programmes (<link linkend="bib48">Geary et al., 1999</link>)<!--: PMID 10456419-->. This prompts concern, as anthelmintic resistance has been widely reported in livestock and it may also only be a matter of time before this phenomenon also occurs widely in parasites of humans (<link linkend="bib149">Osei-Atweneboana et al., 2011</link><!-- : PMID 22545160-->; <link linkend="bib25">Churcher et al., 2009</link><!-- : PMID 19805362-->; <link linkend="bib150">Osei-Atweneboana et al., 2007</link>)<!--: PMID 17574093-->.</para>
<para>Also of importance are species of nematode that infect plants. These plant parasitic nematodes cause major crop losses and are a threat to food security. Chemicals termed nematicides are used to protect crops from infestation. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has been used to provide insight into mechanisms for controlling these nematodes (<link linkend="bib27">Costa et al., 2009</link>)<!--: PMID 19367833-->, albeit in a rather limited fashion to date. This review will also discuss the study of the action of the organophosphate and carbamate nematicides in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Is <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> a model &lsquo;parasite&rsquo;?</title>
<para>Parasitic nematodes are very difficult to work with, requiring passage through their host for maintenance of their parasitic life-cycle. This greatly complicates quantitative experiments in their natural habitat. Methods for conducting forward and reverse genetics are also at best primitive. Thus <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has routinely been exploited as a more &lsquo;user-friendly&rsquo; model system that is also highly tractable to molecular genetic techniques. However, the life-style of the free-living worm <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is very different to that of the parasites, and therefore parasitologists have given careful thought to its relevance (<link linkend="bib68">Holden-Dye and Walker, 2012</link>; <link linkend="bib49">Geary and Thompson, 2001</link>)<!--: PMID 11707307-->. In terms of overall &lsquo;body plan&rsquo; there is no doubt that all the species in the phylum Nematoda exhibit similarity despite their very different habitats. More detailed consideration has been given to a comparison of the genetics, for example, the arrangement of the genome, synteny, and homology between specific genes (<link linkend="bib136">Mitreva et al., 2005</link>)<!--: PMID 16099532-->. Overall, there would seem to be considerable molecular diversity between the different species in the phylum. It is probably safe to conclude that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is no more dissimilar to parasitic nematodes than each individual species of parasite is to another. Using <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> permits the application of powerful molecular genetic approaches and it has been extensively, and successfully, exploited as a model system to define molecular components of signalling pathways that underpin nematode physiology.</para>
<para>Indeed, it could be argued that the most relevant consideration for using <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as a model to study anthelmintics and nematicides is the comparative physiology and pharmacology of the Nematoda. Most anthelmintics target the neuromusculature and therefore similarities here become of particular importance. The wiring diagram for the neuromuscular system is similar between <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and the parasitic nematode <emphasis>Ascaris suum</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib3">Angstadt et al., 1989</link>)<!--: PMID 2754041-->, as are the major neurotransmitters: acetylcholine in the excitatory motorneurons (<link linkend="bib86">Johnson and Stretton, 1985</link>)<!--: PMID 4020429-->, GABA in the inhibitory motorneurons (<link linkend="bib87">Johnson and Stretton, 1987</link>)<!--: PMID 3543249-->, and glutamate providing input onto the motorneurons (<link linkend="bib32">Davis, 1998</link>)<!--: PMID 9614330-->. A striking feature of the pharmacology of the nematode nervous system is the abundance of neuropeptides. The majority, conceivably all, of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> neurons express neuropeptides along with their classical neurotransmitters (for review see <link linkend="bib123">Li and Kim, 2010</link><!-- : PMID 21189676-->; <link linkend="bib122">Li, 2005</link>)<!--: PMID 16569285-->. Many of these peptides have potent effects in parasitic nematodes, specifically on musculature which regulates vital nematode processes including feeding, locomotion, and egg-laying (<link linkend="bib19">Brownlee et al., 2000</link>)<!--: PMID 10751940-->. Further evidence for an important functional role for peptidergic signalling has been provided by analysis of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> mutants. In these studies mutants for the enzymes involved in the processing of neuropeptides, the proconvertase <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001172;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-3</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib98">Kass et al., 2001</link>)<!--: PMID 11717360--> and carboxypeptidase <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001189;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-21</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib81">Jacob and Kaplan, 2003</link>)<!--: PMID 12657671-->, have been shown to be severely depleted in neuropeptide content (<link linkend="bib80">Husson et al., 2006</link>)<!--: PMID 16945111--> and to have phenotypes consistent with the idea that neuropeptides have modulatory roles within the neural networks that direct a range of important worm behaviours.</para>
<para>Neuropeptides are present throughout the animal phyla and also subserve pivotal roles in the nervous systems of the mammalian hosts of parasitic nematodes. However, neuropeptides, unlike the small molecule &lsquo;classical&rsquo; transmitters, (e.g., acetylcholine), have diverged considerably in structure during evolution and this presents the promise that drugs targeting peptidergic signalling in nematodes may have low mammalian toxicity. There has thus been considerable interest in the prospect of developing peptidomimetics as a novel approach for nematode control. A comparative analysis of the neuropeptide content for a range of nematodes has been comprehensively reviewed (<link linkend="bib127">Marks and Maule, 2010</link><!-- : PMID 21189674-->; <link linkend="bib62">McVeigh et al., 2005</link>)<!--: PMID 16076468--> and may become an important consideration if this strategy is to be pursued. Progress has been made towards pairing the neuropeptide ligands with their cognate receptors in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib42">Frooninckx et al., 2012</link>)<!--: PMID 23267347--> and this may point to new molecular targets for nematode control.</para>
<para>A comparative analysis of the physiology and pharmacology of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> with plant parasitic nematodes is more difficult as there is very little information available for these species in this regard. However, compared with most animal parasitic nematodes, plant parasitic nematodes are more amenable to maintenance in the laboratory. A recent review summarises the current knowledge concerning the plant parasitic nematodes and broadly speaking in terms of neurotransmitters there would appear to be good conservation with <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib72">Holden-Dye and Walker, 2011</link>)<!--: PMID 21538093--> although the pharmacology of the respective neurotransmitter receptors has yet to be explored.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Approaches for the study of anthelmintics and nematicides in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
<para>There is a large body of literature describing the study of bioactive compounds in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and the proposal to use it for the study of anthelmintics precedes the publication of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome sequence by nearly 20 years. <link linkend="bib156">Rand and Johnson (1995)</link><!--: PMID 8531725--> coined the term &lsquo;genetic pharmacology&rsquo; to describe this approach. These studies generally hinge on the ability of a drug to elicit a significant, ideally quantifiable, change in the worm&apos;s growth, development, metabolism, and/or behaviour. Pharmacokinetic considerations include the method and duration of drug exposure. For the vast majority of experiments the anthelmintics are applied to intact <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. There are thus two ways in which the drug can gain access to target tissues, namely by ingestion or by diffusion across the cuticle. In this regard it should be noted that for many drugs the cuticle presents a significant permeability barrier. Thus the lipophilicity of drugs has a strong bearing on the concentration that is achieved in target tissues following external application. It is not uncommon for polar drugs to be applied at a concentration 1000 fold higher than their predicted affinity for the target. It may be possible to ameliorate this problem to some extent by employing animals that have a compromised cuticle (<link linkend="bib55">Gravato-Nobre et al., 2005</link>)<!--: PMID 16079230-->. A number of possible strategies for overcoming <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> xenobiotic resistance and enhancing its value in identifying new anthelmintics have been reviewed recently by <link linkend="bib21">Burns and Roy (2012)</link>.</para>
<para>Once the effect of a particular drug on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has been defined, two different strategies may be adopted to investigate the molecular basis for its biological activity. The first follows a hypothesis-led approach in which strains with mutations in genes of known function are tested for altered sensitivity to the drug. The alternate strategy is to conduct a forward genetic screen. This is a powerful and objective approach that provides novel insight into the signalling pathways that mediate anthelmintic action. Often the impact of these studies extends beyond the interests of parasitologists and into the broader context of cellular and molecular neuroscience. This is because the vast majority of anthelmintics exert their effects in the neuromuscular system and key transduction molecules in the nervous system are highly conserved across the phyla from worm to human. Thus anthelmintic resistance screens can promote the discovery and characterisation of genes that have important roles in neurotransmission. An excellent example of the utility of this approach is provided by genetic screens employing the organophosphate cholinesterase inhibitors, in particular aldicarb which provides an excellent example of &lsquo;genetic pharmacology&rsquo; and the interested reader is directed to <link linkend="bib144">Nguyen et al. (1995)</link><!--: PMID 7498734-->, <link linkend="bib134">Miller et al. (1996)</link><!--: PMID 8901627-->, and <link linkend="bib175">Sieburth et al. (2005)</link><!--: PMID 16049479-->.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Classes of anthelmintic drugs and nematicides</title>
<para>Anthelmintics and nematicides are separated into classes on the basis of similar chemical structure and mode of action. There are only a few main classes and each is briefly discussed in turn below. For the most part, information on the physiological and pharmacological actions of these compounds has been obtained from studies on the large parasitic nematode <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis>. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, on the other hand, has been valuable in defining molecular targets and downstream signalling cascades.</para>
<sect2 id="sec4-1">
<title>Piperazine</title>
<para>Piperazine was first used as an anthelmintic in the 1950s and it is still the active constituent of over the counter remedies for thread worm infection in children. Its mode of action has primarily been studied in <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> where it acts as a weak GABA-mimetic and causes a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000349;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">flaccid</ulink>, reversible paralysis of body wall muscle. Single channel recordings provide evidence that it is a low efficacy, partial agonist at GABA-gated chloride channels (<link linkend="bib129">Martin, 1985</link>)<!--: PMID 2579701-->. Recently the action of piperazine has been investigated in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> by comparing its action on wild type and mutants for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006784;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-49</ulink></emphasis>, a gene which encodes <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> GABA<subscript>A</subscript>-like receptor subunits expressed at the body wall neuromuscular junction (<link linkend="bib135">Miltsch et al., 2013</link>)<!--: PMID 23707730-->. Although very high concentrations were required (50-100 mM), piperazine had a similar inhibitory action on both wild type and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006784;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-49</ulink></emphasis> mutant animals. In a development assay for <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> piperazine also had the same inhibitory effect on both wild type and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006784;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-49</ulink></emphasis> mutants. It is possible that piperazine does not interact with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28086;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-49</ulink> but may possibly interact with other putative GABA-gated chloride channel receptors identified in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome, for example, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33900;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGC-37</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36534;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGC-38</ulink>, and GAB-1.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-2">
<title>Benzimidazoles: thiabendazole and albendazole</title>
<para>The first of this class, thiabendazole, was discovered in 1961 and subsequently a number of further benzamidazoles were introduced as broad spectrum anthelmintics. There is an extensive literature on these compounds reporting a number of different biochemical effects. Nonetheless, it is clear that their anthelmintic efficacy is due to their ability to compromise the cytoskeleton through a selective interaction with &beta;-tubulin (<link linkend="bib13">Borgers and de Nollin, 1975</link><!-- : PMID 1117352-->; for review see <link linkend="bib110">Lacey, 1990</link>)<!--: PMID 15463312-->. The effects of benzimidazoles on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, which include impaired locomotion and reproduction, and a detrimental effect on oocytes, are consistent with disruption of processes requiring integral microtubules. The sensitivity of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to benzimidazoles is mediated by a single gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000248;class=Gene" role="_blank">ben-1</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes &beta;-tubulin (<link linkend="bib36">Driscoll et al., 1989</link>)<!--: PMID 2592410-->. This has provided a platform to investigate the molecular basis of benzimidazole resistance in parasitic nematodes. It has been noted that benzimidazole resistance in <emphasis>Haemonchus contortus</emphasis> seems to be associated with the presence of specific alleles for &beta;-tubulin in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000011;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">drug resistant</ulink> isolates (<link linkend="bib108">Kwa et al., 1994</link>)<!--: PMID 7911975-->. Whether or not a specific &beta;-tubulin isoform could confer resistance to the drug was tested by experiments that showed that the sensitivity of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000248;class=Gene" role="_blank">ben-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants to benzimidazole can be rescued by expressing a <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> allele of &beta;-tubulin from benzimidazole susceptible isolates, but cannot be rescued by the allele present in the resistant isolates (<link linkend="bib109">Kwa et al., 1995</link>)<!--: PMID 7877171-->. This unequivocally demonstrated that a single amino acid substitution, Y for F, in &beta;-tubulin, can confer anthelmintic resistance. This is the first elegant example of a &lsquo;model hopping&rsquo; approach in which the genetic tractability of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is directly exploited to define gene function for a parasitic worm. The relationship between &beta;-tubulin genes in <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is explored in greater detail in <link linkend="bib169">Saunders et al. (2013)</link><!--: PMID 23416426-->.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-3">
<title>Imidazothiazole: levamisole, and tetrahydropyrimidines: pyrantel and morantel</title>
<para>These compounds have a broad-spectrum anthelmintic efficacy against nematodes but have no action against cestodes or trematodes. Tetramisole is a racemic mixture of L and D isomers, while levamisole is the pure L-isomer. Pyrantel and morantel are structurally related to each other but different in structure from levamisole and are also effective anthelmintics.</para>
<para>Over 40 years ago it was shown that tetramisole (<link linkend="bib1">Aceves et al., 1970</link>)<!--: PMID 5445688--> and pyrantel (<link linkend="bib7">Aubry et al., 1970</link>)<!--: PMID 5417856--> both act as nicotinic receptor agonists and elicit spastic muscle paralysis due to prolonged activation of the excitatory nicotinic acetylcholine receptors (nAChRs) on body wall muscle of nematodes. Voltage-clamp studies using <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> body wall muscle cells have shown that morantel, pyrantel, and levamisole mimic the actions of acetylcholine, with the following order of potency: morantel=pyrantel&gt;levamisole&gt;acetylcholine (<link linkend="bib63">Harrow and Gration, 1985</link>). The reversal potential for all the compounds was around +10 mV, indicating they all activate the same ion channels. These authors also found evidence that pyrantel and acetylcholine compete for the same receptor. Their precise mode of action has been carefully studied at the single-channel level on the body wall muscle preparation of <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> (for review see <link linkend="bib132">Martin et al., 2005</link>)<!--: PMID 16569294-->. Pharmacological analysis has provided evidence for subtypes of nACh receptor (<link linkend="bib153">Qian et al., 2006</link>)<!--: PMID 17056760-->, an N-type (preferentially activated by nicotine), a B-type (preferentially activated by bephenium), and an L-type (preferentially activated by levamisole and associated with levamisole resistance).</para>
<para>Levamisole, and related compounds, also cause spastic paralysis and egg-laying in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Thus <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has provided an experimental platform to further investigate the molecular pharmacology of imidazothiazoles and tetrahydropyrimidines on nAChRs and some of this work will now be reviewed.</para>
<para>Forward genetic screens using levamisole have been extremely productive. Initially tetramisole was used (<link linkend="bib16">Brenner, 1974</link>)<!--: PMID 4366476--> but later this was replaced by levamisole (<link linkend="bib119">Lewis et al., 1980a</link>)<!--: PMID 7203008-->. These screens have provided a resource of mutants that have been used over the last two to three decades to assign functions to genes expressed at the neuromuscular junction. Some of these are nAChR subunits but others interestingly are not and serve to either regulate nicotinic receptors or muscle function. A list of these genes is given in <link linkend="table2">Table 2</link> together with their likely functions.</para>
<table id="table2" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 2. A summary of gene function for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000421;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">levamisole resistant</ulink> mutants.</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<thead>
<row valign="bottom" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Gene</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Function</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Reference</emphasis></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006774;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-38</ulink></emphasis><superscript>1</superscript></entry>
<entry align="left">&alpha;-like nAChR subunit</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib39">Fleming et al., 1997</link><!-- : PMID 92217820--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006765;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-29</ulink></emphasis><superscript>1</superscript></entry>
<entry align="left">non &alpha;-like nACh R subunit</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib39">Fleming et al., 1997</link><!-- : PMID 92217820--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002974;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-1</ulink></emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></entry>
<entry align="left">non &alpha;-like AChR subunit</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib39">Fleming et al., 1997</link><!-- : PMID 92217820--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006797;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-63</ulink></emphasis><superscript>1</superscript></entry>
<entry align="left">&alpha;-like nAChR subunit</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib29">Culetto et al., 2004</link><!-- : PMID 15280391--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002975;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-8</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002975;class=Gene" role="_blank">acr-13</ulink>)</emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></entry>
<entry align="left">&alpha;-like nAChR subunit</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib183">Towers et al., 2005</link><!-- : PMID 15773900--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006759;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink></emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></entry>
<entry align="left">twitchin</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib139">Moerman et al., 1988</link><!-- : PMID 2833427--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006785;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-50</ulink></emphasis><superscript>1</superscript></entry>
<entry align="left">regulation of subtype specific nAChR trafficking to cell surface</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib14">Boulin et al., 2008</link><!-- : PMID 19020092--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006801;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-68</ulink></emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></entry>
<entry align="left">ryanodine receptor</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib133">Maryon et al., 1996</link><!-- : PMID 8769414--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002976;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-9</ulink></emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></entry>
<entry align="left">secreted protein required for clustering of L-nAChRs</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib29">Culetto et al., 2004</link><!-- : PMID 15280391--> <link linkend="bib50">Gendrel et al., 2009</link><!-- : PMID 19794415--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002978;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-11</ulink></emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></entry>
<entry align="left">tropomyosin</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib90">Kagawa et al., 1995</link><!-- : PMID 7666414--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002977;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-10</ulink></emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></entry>
<entry align="left">transmembrane protein required for aggregation of nAChRs</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib43">Gally et al., 2004</link><!-- : PMID 15457263--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004363;class=Gene" role="_blank">ric-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">chaperone for receptor maturation</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib61">Halevi et al., 2002</link><!-- : PMID 11867529--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00043050;class=Gene" role="_blank">oig-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">stabilization and localization of L-nAChRs</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib157">Rapti et al., 2011</link><!-- : PMID 21252855--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012128;class=Gene" role="_blank">nra-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">putative Ca-dependent phospholipid copine binding protein</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib53">Gottschalk et al., 2005</link><!-- : PMID 15990870--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006527;class=Gene" role="_blank">tax-6</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">regulation of nAChR sensitivity to nicotine</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib53">Gottschalk et al., 2005</link><!-- : PMID 15990870--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001184;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-15</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">required for optimal nAChR levels</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib53">Gottschalk et al., 2005</link><!-- : PMID 15990870--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004928;class=Gene" role="_blank">soc-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">required for optimal nAChR levels</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib53">Gottschalk et al., 2005</link><!-- : PMID 15990870--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006599;class=Gene" role="_blank">tpa-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">role in nicotine adaptation of nAChRs</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib187">Waggoner et al., 2000</link><!-- : PMID 11102488--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016803;class=Gene" role="_blank">bath-42</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">maintenance of optimal <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27448;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-3</ulink> levels</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib174">Shteingauz, et al., 2009</link><!-- : PMID 19223395--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006806;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-74</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">required for trafficking nAChR subunits to surface and their correct folding</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib14">Boulin et al., 2008</link><!-- : PMID 19020092--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00017299;class=Gene" role="_blank">molo-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">auxillary transmembrane subunit enhances channel gating, no effect on unitary conductance</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib15">Boulin et al., 2012</link><!-- : PMID 22922783--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00011488;class=Gene" role="_blank">nra-2</ulink>/4</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">control of nAChR subunit composition or ratio of subunits</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib2">Almedom et al., 2009</link><!-- : PMID 19609303--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis>miR-1</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">muscle-specific microRNA, regulation of expression level of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE13451;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-29</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30706;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-63</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib176">Simon et al., 2008</link><!-- : PMID 18510933--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col3">Isolated and identified as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000421;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">levamisole resistant</ulink> by <superscript>1</superscript><link linkend="bib16">Brenner (1974)</link><!--: PMID 4366476-->, <superscript>2</superscript><link linkend="bib119">Lewis et al. (1980a)</link><!--: PMID 7203008-->.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>Levamisole is more potent than acetylcholine at contracting cut preparations of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, inducing contraction at low &micro;M concentration (<link linkend="bib165">Ruiz-Lancheros et al., 2011</link><!-- : PMID 21195075-->; <link linkend="bib120">Lewis et al., 1980b</link>)<!--: PMID 7402460-->. In intact animals, the EC<subscript>50</subscript> for levamisole-induced paralysis is 9 &micro;M (<link linkend="bib154">Qian et al., 2008</link>)<!--: PMID 18519804-->. The work of <link linkend="bib39">Fleming et al. (1997)</link><!--: PMID 92217820--> provided evidence for the role of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24908;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-38</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE13451;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-29</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24888;class=Protein" role="_blank">LEV-1</ulink> as subunits of the nAChR of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Until this work, eleven genes had been identified that conferred levamisole resistance (<link linkend="bib121">Lewis et al., 1987</link><!-- : PMID 3668616-->; <link linkend="bib120">Lewis et al., 1980b</link><!-- : PMID 7402460-->; <link linkend="bib16">Brenner, 1974</link>)<!--: PMID 4366476-->. Extreme resistance to levamisole was shown by the following mutants: <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002974;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006765;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-29</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006774;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-38</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006797;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-63</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006806;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-74</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006785;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-50</ulink></emphasis>; partial resistance was seen in mutants to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002975;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-8</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002976;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-9</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002977;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-10</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006759;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006751;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-11</ulink></emphasis> (the latter two classified as twitchers). Whole-cell voltage-clamp experiments using <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ventral body wall muscle cells revealed evidence for two nAChRs, a levamisole-sensitive receptor requiring both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006774;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-38</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006765;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-29</ulink></emphasis> genes for activity, and a receptor activated by both nicotine and acetylcholine present in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006774;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-38</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006765;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-29</ulink></emphasis> mutants that underwent rapid desensitization (<link linkend="bib159">Richmond and Jorgensen, 1999</link>)<!--: PMID 10461217-->. They concluded that the N- (nicotinic sensitive) and L- (levamisole sensitive) AChRs contributed about equally to the acetylcholine current of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> body wall muscle. These results clearly demonstrate that levamisole has a direct excitatory effect on body wall muscle, which represents at least one of the sites for the anthelmintic action of levamisole. Subsequent work in which AChR subunits were expressed in <emphasis>Xenopus laevis</emphasis> oocytes demonstrated that five subunits were required for a functional receptor: <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002974;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002975;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-8</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006765;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-29</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006774;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-38</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006797;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-63</ulink></emphasis>, together with three ancillary factors: <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004363;class=Gene" role="_blank">ric-3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006785;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-50</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006806;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-74</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib14">Boulin et al., 2008</link>)<!--: PMID 19020092-->. This receptor combination responded to both acetylcholine and levamisole, but not to nicotine, which acted as an antagonist. The removal of any of the subunits greatly reduced the responses to both compounds. Interestingly, when these authors expressed <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000055;class=Gene" role="_blank">acr-16</ulink></emphasis> together with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004363;class=Gene" role="_blank">ric-3</ulink></emphasis> in <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes they obtained large currents to acetylcholine and nicotine but levamisole failed to induce a current. A number of ancillary factors have been shown to play a role in the assembly and functioning of L-nAChRs (<link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>). One of these, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29258;class=Protein" role="_blank">MOLO-1</ulink>, physically interacts with the L-nAChR to increase gating and so is a true auxiliary transmembrane subunit (<link linkend="bib15">Boulin et al., 2012</link>)<!--: PMID 22922783-->. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29258;class=Protein" role="_blank">MOLO-1</ulink> interacts with L-nAChRs at an early stage in the secretory pathway and co-localizes with the receptor at the neuromuscular junction. However, it does not interact with N-nAChRs. Another factor, miR-1, regulates both the sensitivity of muscle cells to acetylcholine through the expression level of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE13451;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-29</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30706;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-63</ulink>, and the amount of acetylcholine released from presynaptic neurons via a retrograde messenger, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25156;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEF-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib176">Simon et al., 2008</link>)<!--: PMID 18510933-->.</para>
<para>Embryonic cells grown from a primary culture developed into L1 <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> muscle cells and these were used for single channel recordings from nAChRs (<link linkend="bib158">Rayes et al., 2007</link>)<!--: PMID 17314321-->. These nAChRs were levamisole sensitive and showed a single population of channels with a conductance of 39 pS which was five times more sensitive to levamisole than to acetylcholine. The presence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24908;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-38</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30706;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-63</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE13451;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-29</ulink> subunits was essential for channel activity. Interestingly, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002974;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants had a channel conductance of 26 pS, with prolonged open duration but were less sensitive to levamisole. This shows that L-nAChRs can still function in L1 muscle cells in the absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24888;class=Protein" role="_blank">LEV-1</ulink>. Using this preparation, single channel currents could also be activated by pyrantel and morantel. The relative potencies of the agonists tested were morantel=pyrantel&gt;levamisole&gt;acetylcholine, the same order of potency as found by <link linkend="bib63">Harrow and Gration (1985)</link> using <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> body wall muscle and voltage-clamp recordings. In a later paper (<link linkend="bib66">Hernando et al., 2012</link>)<!--: PMID 22734069--> it was shown that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34160;class=Protein" role="_blank">LEV-8</ulink> is not essential for functional L-nAChRs, though <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002975;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-8</ulink></emphasis> mutants showed kinetic changes in the channel properties and were less sensitive to levamisole. These authors also showed that while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36679;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACR-8</ulink> is not required for wild-type L-nAChRs, it can replace <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34160;class=Protein" role="_blank">LEV-8</ulink> in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002975;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-8</ulink></emphasis> mutants. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002975;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-8</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000047;class=Gene" role="_blank">acr-8</ulink></emphasis> double mutant is strongly resistant to levamisole. Since no gene corresponding to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002975;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-8</ulink></emphasis> has been found in several trichostrongylid species it is possible that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000047;class=Gene" role="_blank">acr-8</ulink></emphasis> replaces <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002975;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-8</ulink></emphasis> in these parasitic nematodes (<link linkend="bib143">Neveu et al., 2010</link>)<!--: PMID 20531256-->. <link linkend="bib154">Qian et al. (2008)</link><!--: PMID 18519804--> have also made single channel recordings from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> body wall muscle. In these experiments they used <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002977;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-10</ulink></emphasis> mutants in which aggregation of nAChRs is absent, allowing recordings from single channels. The mean conductance for these channels was around 30 pS when activated by either levamisole or acetylcholine. These levamisole-activated channels were insensitive to nicotine. These authors found that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002975;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-8</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002977;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-10</ulink></emphasis> double mutants expressed fewer channels, which also had a smaller mean conductance of 26.9 pS. These authors review the value of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> levamisole receptor as a model for parasitic nematodes and note that while <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has levamisole-activated channels ranging from 26-36 pS, those in <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> range from 18-53 pS (<link linkend="bib153">Qian et al., 2006</link><!-- : PMID 17056760-->; <link linkend="bib116">Levandoski et al., 2005</link>)<!--: PMID 15950977-->. The reader is referred to an in-depth review relating levamisole research using <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to research using parasitic nematodes by <link linkend="bib131">Martin et al. (2012b)</link><!--: PMID 22607692-->. Another review compares the nAChRs of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> with those of parasitic nematodes <link linkend="bib69">(Holden-Dye et al., 2013)</link><!--: PMID 23500392-->.</para>
<para>Levamisole does not activate N-nAChRs in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> though it does act as an antagonist at these receptors <link linkend="bib8">(Ballivet et al., 1996)</link><!--: PMID 8627624-->. Dihydro-&beta;-erythroidine also distinguishes between L- and N-nAChRs, acting as an antagonist at N-nAChRs but has a very weak blocking effect at L-nAChRs (<link linkend="bib159">Richmond and Jorgensen, 1999</link>)<!--: PMID 10461217-->. In contrast to the L-nAChR, the N-nAChR is a homomer composed of five <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE09639;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACR-16</ulink> subunits and probably accounts for all non-levamisole-sensitive nicotinic synaptic events at the neuromuscular junction (<link linkend="bib182">Touroutine et al., 2005</link>)<!--: PMID 15917232-->. There is evidence that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03753;class=Protein" role="_blank">CWN-2</ulink> (a Wnt ligand), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/protein/LIN-17" role="_blank">LIN-17</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39126;class=Protein" role="_blank">CAM-1</ulink> (Ror receptor tyrosine kinase) are all involved in controlling the translocation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE09639;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACR-16</ulink> receptors (<link linkend="bib85">Jensen et al., 2012</link><!-- : PMID 22464329-->; <link linkend="bib41">Francis et al., 2005</link>)<!--: PMID 15944127-->. A neuronal acetylcholine receptor has also been identified in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and has the following composition: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24908;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-38</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30706;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-63</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07380;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACR-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07380;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACR-2</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29334;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACR-12</ulink> (<link linkend="bib89">Jospin et al., 2009</link>)<!--: PMID 20027209-->. When expressed in <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes this receptor is almost completely insensitive to levamisole and only weakly activated by nicotine, but the effect of acetylcholine is clearly blocked by mecamylamine. For expression in oocytes, it was necessary to co-inject <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006785;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-50</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006806;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-74</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004363;class=Gene" role="_blank">ric-3</ulink>,</emphasis> in addition to the five cholinergic subunits<emphasis>.</emphasis></para>
<para>In summary, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has provided a useful platform to investigate the molecular pharmacology of these classes of compounds and in turn these anthelmintics continue to provide important pharmacological tools to dissect subtypes and the stoichiometry of native nematode nicotinic receptors.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-4">
<title>Spiroindoles: paraherquamide and derquantel (2-deoxyparaherquamide/PNU 141962)</title>
<para>Paraherquamide A and marcfortine A are both members of the oxindole alkaloid family, originally isolated from <emphasis>Penicillium paraherquei</emphasis> and <emphasis>P. roqueforti</emphasis>, respectively (<link linkend="bib205">Zinser et al., 2002</link>)<!--: PMID 12213111-->. Their chemistry, efficacy, and mode of action have been reviewed (<link linkend="bib114">Lee et al., 2002</link>)<!--: PMID 12052190-->. A specific, high affinity binding site for paraherquamide has been identified in a membrane preparation isolated from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, with an apparent Kd of 263 nM (<link linkend="bib170">Schaeffer et al., 1992</link>)<!--: PMID 1540222-->. Paraherquamide and its derivative, 2-deoxy-paraherquamide (derquantel), induce <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000349;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">flaccid</ulink> paralysis in parasitic nematodes <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis>. Pharmacological analysis of the effects of these drugs on acetylcholine-stimulated body wall muscle contractions in <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> muscle strips <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> has shown that they act as typical competitive antagonists, shifting the concentration-response curves to the right in a parallel fashion (<link linkend="bib160">Robertson et al., 2002</link>)<!--: PMID 12183640-->. These drugs have no apparent direct effect on <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> body wall muscle tension or membrane potential (<link linkend="bib114">Lee et al., 2002</link>)<!--: PMID 12052190-->. Paraherquamide also blocks the actions of other nicotinic agonists, but not equipotently (<link linkend="bib160">Robertson et al., 2002</link><!-- : PMID 12183640-->; <link linkend="bib205">Zinser et al., 2002</link>)<!--: PMID 1221311-->. Interestingly, this antagonist seems to distinguish nicotinic receptor subtypes on the muscle, and has a greater affinity for the receptors mediating the response to levamisole and pyrantel than the receptors that mediate the response to nicotine. Patch-clamp recording from <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> body wall muscle has found at least three subtypes of nAChRs based on conductance, namely, N, L, and B, with conductances of 22/24 pS, 33/35 pS, and 45 pS, respectively (<link linkend="bib153">Qian et al., 2006</link>)<!--: PMID 17056760-->. Confirming previous studies, paraherquamide failed to antagonize the N (nicotine-sensitive) subtype, the L (levamisole-sensitive) subtype was antagonized by paraherquamide, and the B (bephenium-sensitive) subtype was antagonized more by 2-deoxyparaherquamide than by paraherquamide. Using a cut preparation of <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> 2-deoxyparaherquamide has been shown to paralyse <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and to antagonize the actions of bephenium in preference to pyrantel and, to a lesser extent, levamisole on this preparation; that is, bephenium&gt;pyrantel&gt;levamisole, suggesting a preference for B subtype nAChRs (<link linkend="bib165">Ruiz-Lancheros et al., 2011</link>)<!--: PMID 21195075-->. 2-Deoxyparaherquamide only antagonized 10 &micro;M nicotine and so it was difficult to compare sensitivity of nicotine to 2-deoxyparaherquamide in relation to the other nicotinic agonists. Deoxyparaherquamide appeared to be more potent as an antagonist compared to mecamylamine. These authors raised the possibility that the cuticle of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> may be less permeable than the cuticles of parasitic nematodes, which might influence the value of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as a primary screen for anthelmintics.</para>
<para>Importantly, the mode of action of this class of anthelmintics differs from the more established drugs that interfere with cholinergic transmission (e.g., levamisole) in that they act as competitive antagonists rather than cholinomimetics. The use of paraherquamide in forward genetic screens has not yet been reported but could potentially generate interesting new mutants. As it is a competitive inhibitor of the body wall nACh receptor, it would be predicted that mutations that increase transmitter release should confer resistance. Thus a forward genetic screen might reveal further negative regulators of neurotransmitter release. For a review that covers the discovery, mode of action, and use of 2-deoxyparaherquamide in combination with abamectin as the anthelmintic, Startect, see <link linkend="bib196">Woods et al. (2012)</link>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-5">
<title>Macrocyclic lactones; avermectins and milbemycins; ivermectin and moxidectin</title>
<para>Ivermectin was introduced as an anthelmintic in the 1980s by Merck. It is a semi-synthetic derivative of avermectin which is a large macrocyclic lactone fermentation product of the micro-organism <emphasis>Streptomyces avermitilis</emphasis>. It is remarkably potent (~1 nM) and persistent in its effect, and its discovery enthused other companies to invest in the development of ivermectin analogues which include moxidectin, milbemycin oxime, doramectin, selamectin, abamectin, and eprinomectin. Here <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> played a role, as it was employed in a screen for further macrocyclic lactones with ivermectin-like activity (<link linkend="bib60">Haber et al., 1991</link>)<!--: PMID 1719935-->.</para>
<para>Ivermectin elicits a potent and persistent paralysis of nematode pharyngeal (<link linkend="bib151">Pemberton et al., 2001</link><!-- : PMID 11306685-->; <link linkend="bib18">Brownlee et al., 1997</link>)<!--: PMID 9368907--> and body wall musculature (<link linkend="bib97">Kass et al., 1982</link><!-- : PMID 7128715-->; <link linkend="bib96">Kass et al., 1980</link>)<!--: PMID 6255481-->. It has been shown to interact with a range of ligand-gated ion channels including &agr;7 nACh receptors (<link linkend="bib106">Krause et al., 1998</link>)<!--: PMID 9463487-->, acetylcholine-gated chloride channels (<link linkend="bib12">Bokisch and Walker, 1986</link>)<!--: PMID 2873943-->, GABA-gated chloride channels (<link linkend="bib70">Holden-Dye and Walker, 1990</link><!-- : PMID 2175874-->; <link linkend="bib161">Robertson, 1989</link>)<!--: PMID 2478243-->, histamine-gated chloride channels (<link linkend="bib204">Zheng et al., 2002</link>)<!--: PMID 11714703-->, glycine receptors (<link linkend="bib173">Shan et al., 2001</link>)<!--: PMID 11278873-->, and P2X4 receptors (<link linkend="bib102">Khakh et al., 1999</link>)<!--: PMID 10460235-->. However, it is its high affinity for nematode glutamate-gated chloride channels (GluCl) that correlates with its potent anthelmintic activity. This was defined by the team at Merck that succeeded in expression cloning GluCl&agr; and GluCl&beta; ion channel subunits from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib30">Cully et al., 1994</link>)<!--: PMID 7935817-->. Both subunits were expressed either singly or together in <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes. GluCl&agr; responds to micromolar ivermectin but not to glutamate, while GluCl&beta; responds to glutamate but not ivermectin. Co-expression of GluCl&agr; and GluCl&beta; yields a channel which responds to glutamate and is positively allosterically modulated by nanomolar ivermectin. Subsequently a small family of nematode genes encoding GluCl channels has been identified (for review see <link linkend="bib200">Yates et al., 2003</link>)<!--: PMID 13678634-->. The nomenclature is confusing as the same genes have been discovered by both homology screening approaches and from forward genetic screens for ivermectin resistance genes. Essentially there are four <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes encoding GluCl&agr; subunits, two of which are alternately spliced yielding the GluCl channels: GluCl&agr;1 encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001591;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-1</ulink></emphasis>, GluCl&agr;2A and B encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000233;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis>, GluCl&agr;3A and B encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000232;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink></emphasis>, and GluCl&agr;4 encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001593;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-3</ulink></emphasis>, (<link linkend="table3">Table 3</link>). There is just one GluCl&beta; subunit encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001592;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-2</ulink>,</emphasis> and a further gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001594;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-4</ulink></emphasis>, which is divergent from the genes encoding &agr; and &beta; subunits. Although the pharmacology of channels assembled from these GluCl subunits has been defined in heterologous expression systems, the important question of the subunit stoichiometry and pharmacology of the native channels is much more poorly defined. Further studies on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are providing a better understanding of this by delineating the expression pattern for GluCl subunits in the nervous system. For example, the pharyngeal muscle expresses <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000233;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001592;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib33">Dent et al., 1997</link><!-- : PMID 9312045-->; <link linkend="bib113">Laughton et al., 1997</link>)<!--: PMID 9192499-->. Thus it might be expected that GluCl&agr;2 and GluCl&beta; subunits co-assemble to form a native ivermectin-sensitive channel. Whether or not other subunits contribute to the functional receptor is not yet clear. However, the pharyngeal muscle of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000233;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> mutants does not respond to ivermectin (<link linkend="bib151">Pemberton et al., 2001</link><!-- : PMID 11306685-->; <link linkend="bib33">Dent et al., 1997</link>)<!--: PMID 9312045-->, clearly indicating an involvement of GluCl&agr;2. An important point to note in terms of the site of anthelmintic action of ivermectin is that although the pharynxes of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000233;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> mutants are not inhibited by ivermectin, populations of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000233;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> mutants exposed to ivermectin are still <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000644;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">paralyzed</ulink>. Thus GluCl channels in the pharynx are not required for the paralytic effect. This may also be true for parasitic nematodes. For example, ivermectin has anthelmintic activity against <emphasis>Ascaridia galli</emphasis> and yet the pharynx of this species is not inhibited by the drug (<link linkend="bib71">Holden-Dye and Walker, 2006</link>)<!--: PMID 16442540-->.</para>
<table id="table3" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 3. A summary of glutamate-gated chloride receptor subunits and their expression in <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis></emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<thead>
<row valign="bottom" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Subunit</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Gene</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Expression</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Reference</emphasis></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">GluCl&alpha;1</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001591;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">intestine, pharyngeal and body wall muscle, head neurons</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib34">Dent et al., 2000</link><!-- : PMID 10716995--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">GluCL&alpha;2A,B</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000233;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">pharyngeal muscle (pm4 and 5), head neurons, including <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RMED;class=Cell" role="_blank">RMED</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RMEV;class=Cell" role="_blank">RMEV</ulink>, RMGs, weak stain in sublateral nerve cords and some mechanosensory neurons.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib33">Dent et al., 1997</link><!-- : PMID 9312045--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">GluCL&alpha;3A,B</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000232;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">neurons in ring ganglion, ventral cord, and some mechanosensory neurons.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib34">Dent et al., 2000</link><!-- : PMID 10716995--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">GluCl&alpha;4</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001593;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">AIY interneuron</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib191">Wenick and Hobert, 2004</link><!-- : PMID 15177025--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">GluCl&beta;</entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001592;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">pharyngeal muscle pm4</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib113">Laughton et al., 1997</link><!-- : PMID 9192499--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry/>
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001594;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">intestine, anal depressor muscle, head mesodermal cell, nerve ring, head and tail neurons</entry>
<entry align="left">M. Pellegrino and J. Dent, personal communication</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>In order to obtain a better understanding of the role of GluCl channels in mediating the paralytic actions of ivermectin it is probably most informative to consider their role in the motornervous system. Currently most information is available for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000232;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000233;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis>. These genes are expressed in the motor nervous system of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib34">Dent et al., 2000</link><!-- : PMID 10716995-->; <link linkend="bib33">Dent et al., 1997</link>)<!--: PMID 9312045--> and there is immunostaining for GluCl&agr;3A and B in motorneurons of the parasitic nematode <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib152">Portillo et al., 2003</link>)<!--: PMID 12794744-->. One role of these GluCl channels in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> involves regulation of the duration of forward movement, a well established glutamatergic-regulated behaviour (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_ionotropicglutatmaterecep/ionotropicglutatmaterecep.html">Ionotropic glutamate receptors: genetics, behavior and electrophysiology</ulink>). This function may be conserved between <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> as <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> GluCl&agr;3 subunits expressed in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000232;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink></emphasis> mutants restore the wild-type pattern of movement (<link linkend="bib26">Cook et al., 2006</link>)<!--: PMID 16527366-->. It is most likely that the paralytic action of ivermectin derives from its potent activation of GluCl in the motor nervous system of nematodes. However, the precise role of individual GluCl channels in mediating the effects of ivermectin on these circuits is yet to be established. The mechanism of resistance to ivermectin has also been studied in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. High level resistance is a complex phenomenon which requires mutations in at least three genes: <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001591;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000232;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000233;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis>. Further genes, regulating membrane permeability (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003883;class=Gene" role="_blank">osm-1</ulink></emphasis>) and gap junctions (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006747;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-7</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006749;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-9</ulink></emphasis>), are also involved (<link linkend="bib34">Dent et al., 2000</link>)<!--: PMID 10716995-->. Defining the role of GluCl mutations in conferring ivermectin resistance to parasitic nematodes in the field is a less tractable and more controversial problem (<link linkend="bib195">Wolstenholme et al., 2004</link>)<!--: PMID 15363440-->.</para>
<para>Ivermectin has been found to interact with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32092;class=Protein" role="_blank">AVR-14</ulink> subunits located in the muscle layer of the excretory-secretory apparatus of <emphasis>Brugia malayi</emphasis> microfilariae (<link linkend="bib111">Moreno et al., 2010</link>)<!--: PMID 21041637-->. <emphasis>In vitro</emphasis> treatment of the microfilariae with ivermectin reduced the proteins released by the excretory-secretory apparatus. It is proposed that <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> the lack of these proteins no longer allows the microfilariae to overcome the host&apos;s immune system and so they are rapidly eliminated from the host.</para>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has been used to study ivermectin resistance, which may involve changes in P-glycoprotein (members of the ABC transporter superfamily, for review see <link linkend="bib4">Ardelli, 2013</link>)<!--: PMID 23474412--> activity. Increased expression of <emphasis>pgp</emphasis> genes resulted in increased resistance to ivermectin (<link linkend="bib83">James and Davey, 2009</link>)<!--: PMID 18708066-->, while loss-of-function of individual P-glycoproteins resulted in enhanced susceptibility to ivermectin (<link linkend="bib5">Ardelli and Prichard, 2013</link><!-- : PMID 23062691-->; <link linkend="bib84">Janssen et al., 2013</link>)<!--: PMID 23518455-->. In their study, <link linkend="bib83">James and Davey (2009)</link><!--: PMID 18708066--> exposed <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to increasing concentrations of ivermectin. Increased resistance was associated with increased expression of multidrug-resistance protein and P-glycoprotein genes. Strains that showed resistance to ivermectin also showed resistance to moxidectin, levamisole, and pyrantel, but not to albendazole. Inactivation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003995;class=Gene" role="_blank">pgp-1</ulink>, -5, -6, -12,</emphasis> and <emphasis>-13</emphasis> all produced enhanced sensitivity to ivermectin (<link linkend="bib5">Ardelli and Prichard, 2013</link>)<!--: PMID 23062691-->. These genes are primarily expressed in the intestine, pharynx and amphids. <link linkend="bib5">Ardelli and Prichard (2013)</link><!--: PMID 23062691--> suggest there are multiple avenues for the action of ivermectin.</para>
<para>In an attempt to identify differences between the mode of action of ivermectin and moxidectin, <link linkend="bib6">Ardelli et al. (2009)</link><!--: PMID 19631471--> have investigated their actions on pharyngeal pumping, development, and locomotion in wild type and glutamate-gated chloride channel mutants in <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis> The results are summarized in <link linkend="table4">Table 4</link>, from which it can be seen there are differences between the two anthelmintics. While the activity of both anthelmintics is lost in the absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32092;class=Protein" role="_blank">AVR-14</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25076;class=Protein" role="_blank">AVR-15</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24896;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLC-1</ulink>, it is notable that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001592;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants showed increased motility when 2.5 nM moxidectin was applied during the first 90 minutes, an effect not observed with ivermectin. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001592;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-2</ulink></emphasis> mutant&apos;s pharyngeal pumping was equally sensitive to both ivermectin and moxidectin whereas in the wild type moxidectin was &gt;10 times less active compared to ivermectin. In general, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001594;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-4</ulink></emphasis> mutants were more sensitive to both anthelmintics.</para>
<table id="table4" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 4. Differential actions of ivermectin and moxidectin on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis>. A comparison of the concentrations (in nM) of ivermectin and moxidectin required to arrest larval development, motility, and pharyngeal pumping in wild-type and glutamate-gated chloride channel mutants (after <link linkend="bib6">Ardelli et al. 2009</link>)<!--: PMID 19631471-->.</title>
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5"/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6"/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7"/>
<thead>
<row valign="bottom" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Strain</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left" namest="col2" nameend="col3"><emphasis role="bold">Larval development</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left" namest="col4" nameend="col5"><emphasis role="bold">Motility</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left" namest="col6" nameend="col7"><emphasis role="bold">Pharyngeal pumping</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="bottom" rowsep="1">
<entry/>
<entry align="left">ivermectin</entry>
<entry align="left">moxidectin</entry>
<entry align="left">ivermectin</entry>
<entry align="left">moxidectin</entry>
<entry align="left">ivermectin</entry>
<entry align="left">moxidectin</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">Wild type</entry>
<entry align="left">0.61</entry>
<entry align="left">39.0</entry>
<entry align="left">19.5</entry>
<entry align="left">39.0</entry>
<entry align="left">4.9</entry>
<entry align="left">78</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000232;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink>:avr-15:glc-1</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">&gt;5000</entry>
<entry align="left">&gt;5000</entry>
<entry align="left">&gt;5000</entry>
<entry align="left">&gt;5000</entry>
<entry align="left">&gt;5000</entry>
<entry align="left">&gt;5000</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001592;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">39.0</entry>
<entry align="left">2500</entry>
<entry align="left">170</entry>
<entry align="left">310</entry>
<entry align="left">9.8</entry>
<entry align="left">9.8</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001593;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">19.5</entry>
<entry align="left">5000</entry>
<entry align="left">9.8</entry>
<entry align="left">19.5</entry>
<entry align="left">4.9</entry>
<entry align="left">19.5</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001594;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left">2.4</entry>
<entry align="left">19.5</entry>
<entry align="left">2.4</entry>
<entry align="left">4.9</entry>
<entry align="left">2.4</entry>
<entry align="left">9.8</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>Information concerning the binding of ivermectin and its activation mechanism has advanced with the publication of the crystal structure of ivermectin bound to the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homomeric pentamer &agr;GluClR (<link linkend="bib126">Lynagh and Lynch, 2012</link><!-- : PMID 22586367-->; <link linkend="bib67">Hibbs and Gouaux, 2011</link>)<!--: PMID 21572436-->. Ivermectin binds at the transmembrane domain interface of two adjacent subunits, wedged between M3 from the principal subunit (M3(+)) and M1 from the complementary subunit (M1(-)). Thus ivermectin re-arranges the transmembrane domain helical organization in order to open the channel. This structural change induced by ivermectin to open the channel pore is different from that induced by glutamate (<link linkend="bib126">Lynagh and Lynch, 2012</link>)<!--: PMID 22586367-->. Studies such as these on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are providing a deeper insight into the mode of action of this important class of anthelmintic.</para>
<para>One of the macrocyclic lactones, abamectin, has also been found to be useful as a nematicide and is marketed as a seed treatment (Avicta) to protect plants from invasion from plant parasitic nematodes. Presumably, extrapolating from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, abamectin exerts its action through plant parasitic nematode glutamate-gated chloride channels but this has not yet been studied.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-6">
<title>Cyclooctadepsipeptides: emodepside and PF1022A</title>
<para>The cyclooctadepsipeptide molecule, emodepside, is a semi-synthetic derivative of PF1022A, a fermentation product obtained from the fungus, <emphasis>Mycelia sterilia</emphasis>, of <emphasis>Camelia japonica</emphasis>. Its discovery and anthelmintic activity is described in <link linkend="bib62">Harder and von Samson-Himmelstjerna (2002)</link><!--: PMID 12107468--> and has been reviewed recently (<link linkend="bib107">Krucken et al., 2012</link>)<!--: PMID 22858281-->. It is effective against isolates of parasites that are resistant to benzimidazole, levamisole, and ivermectin indicating, importantly, that it has a novel mode of action. The molecule has pore-forming properties in planar lipids, however, this does not appear to be important in conferring its anthelmintic potency as an optical isomer of emodepside, with similar pore forming properties, does not have anthelmintic action. Thus it would appear that it may act through stereospecific binding to a receptor. Studies in <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> have highlighted muscle paralysis and point to a calcium- and potassium-dependent mechanism of action (<link linkend="bib192">Willson et al., 2003</link>)<!--: PMID 12613766-->. A candidate receptor for the cyclodepsipeptides has been cloned from an <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> cDNA library by immunoscreening with an antibody to PF1022 A. This receptor, designated HC110R, has been expressed in HEK293 cells and shown to gate calcium flux in a PF1022 A-dependent manner (<link linkend="bib166">Saeger et al., 2001</link>)<!--: PMID 11344131-->. It has homology to mammalian latrophilins, a class of G protein-coupled receptors which bind the neurotoxin, latrotoxin. Latrotoxin paralyses mammals by triggering neurotransmitter release, and thus the identification of latrophilin as an emodepside receptor raised the intriguing possibility that emodepside may cause paralysis of nematodes by stimulating excessive neurotransmitter release at neuromuscular sites.</para>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is very susceptible to the effects of emodepside at nanomolar concentrations (<link linkend="bib20">Bull et al., 2007</link>)<!--: PMID 17157854-->. The effects include slowed development, inhibition of pharyngeal pumping, decreased locomotion (forward movement is most affected at low concentrations), and inhibition of egg-laying leading to &lsquo;bagging&rsquo; in adult hermaphrodites. Thus <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has provided an excellent model in which to define the molecular target, or targets, through which emodepside exerts its pleiotropic actions and indeed, to test whether latrophilins are involved.</para>
<para>There are two genes encoding candidate latrophilins in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002251;class=Gene" role="_blank">lat-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002252;class=Gene" role="_blank">lat-2</ulink></emphasis>. The role of these latrophilins in mediating the inhibitory effects of emodepside on feeding and locomotion has been investigated using RNAi and gene knockouts (<link linkend="bib20">Bull et al., 2007</link><!-- : PMID 17157854-->; <link linkend="bib59">Guest et al., 2007</link><!-- : PMID 7583712-->; <link linkend="bib193">Willson et al., 2004</link>)<!--: PMID 15296755-->. The pharyngeal system of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002251;class=Gene" role="_blank">lat-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants shows a reduced sensitivity to emodepside but their locomotor activity is inhibited in a similar fashion to wild-type animals (<link linkend="bib59">Guest et al., 2007</link>)<!--: PMID 7583712-->. Emodepside does not exert its inhibitory effect on locomotion through the other latrophilin, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36968;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAT-2</ulink>, as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002252;class=Gene" role="_blank">lat-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants respond just like wild-type animals. Nor is there redundancy of function between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02945;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAT-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36968;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAT-2</ulink> in terms of the effect of emodepside on locomotion, as the double mutant <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002252;class=Gene" role="_blank">lat-2</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002251;class=Gene" role="_blank">lat-1</ulink></emphasis> responds to emodepside in a similar fashion to the single mutant, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002251;class=Gene" role="_blank">lat-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib59">Guest et al., 2007</link>)<!--: PMID 7583712-->. Clearly, emodepside has latrophilin-independent actions.</para>
<para>Forward genetic screens have provided further insight into the mechanism through which emodepside exerts its inhibitory action on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> muscle (<link linkend="bib59">Guest et al., 2007</link>)<!--: PMID 7583712-->. A chemical mutagenesis screen of twenty thousand genomes for mutants that could move and propagate on micromolar emodepside recovered nine alleles of a single gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004830;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis>. Strains carrying functional null alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004830;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> are highly resistant to the inhibitory effects of emodepside on locomotion and feeding. Furthermore, strains carrying gain-of-function alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004830;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> behave in a similar manner to emodepside-treated animals but are not themselves emodepside hypersensitive. These data strongly support the contention that emodepside activates a SLO-1-dependent pathway to bring about neuromuscular inhibition.</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> is a calcium-activated potassium channel (<link linkend="bib188">Wang et al., 2001</link>)<!--: PMID 11738032--> homologous to the mammalian BK channels. Thus the discovery of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> as an important effector for emodepside resonates with earlier work on <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis> muscle which showed a calcium and potassium-dependent hyperpolarisation (<link linkend="bib192">Willson et al., 2003</link>)<!--: PMID 12613766-->. This channel is highly conserved throughout the animal phyla and plays a pivotal role in regulating neuronal and muscle cell excitability (for review, <link linkend="bib168">Salkoff et al., 2006</link>)<!--: PMID 17115074-->. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> it is widely expressed in the nervous system and body wall muscle, but not in pharyngeal muscle. By expressing a wild-type copy of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004830;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> in specific subsets of cells in a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004830;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> null background it has been shown that emodepside can inhibit locomotor activity when <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> is present in neurons or body wall muscle (<link linkend="bib59">Guest et al., 2007</link>)<!--: PMID 7583712-->.</para>
<para>Since BK channels occur widely in animals, including host species for nematodes, the effect of emodepside on <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> where the native <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> channels had been replaced by a mammalian orthologue, the human KCNMA1 channel, was investigated (<link linkend="bib28">Crisford et al., 2011</link>)<!--: PMID 21415309-->. <emphasis>C. elegans <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004830;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants display certain behavioural deficits and these were restored when <emphasis>kcnma1</emphasis> was expressed in these mutants, indicating that KCNMA1 channels can function in <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis> Animals expressing <emphasis>kcnma1</emphasis> in place of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004830;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> were 10 to 100 times less responsive to emodepside. Interestingly, body bends of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> expressing <emphasis>kcnma1</emphasis> were reduced in the presence of both NS 1619 and rottlerin (mallotoxin), both agonists of mammalian BK channels (<link linkend="bib202">Zakharov et al., 2005</link><!-- : PMID 15998639-->; <link linkend="bib147">Olesen et al., 1994</link>)<!--: PMID 8137869-->, but neither compound had any effect on wild-type <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis> <link linkend="bib28">Crisford et al. (2011)</link><!--: PMID 21415309--> also investigated the effect of emodepside on <emphasis>C. elegans <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004830;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants where <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004830;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> was ectopically expressed in pharyngeal muscle. Normally <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004830;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> is not expressed in pharyngeal muscle at detectable levels but is selectively expressed in pharyngeal neurons (<link linkend="bib22">Chiang et al., 2006</link><!-- : PMID 16651552-->; <link linkend="bib188">Wang et al., 2001</link>)<!--: PMID 11738032-->. Further experiments showed that when wild-type <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004830;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> was selectively expressed in the pharyngeal muscle of <emphasis>C. elegans <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004830;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants emodepside inhibited pharyngeal pumping, providing further evidence for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> being a major target for emodepside in <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis> The interaction between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> channel genes from <emphasis>Ancylostoma caninum</emphasis> and <emphasis>Cooperia oncophora</emphasis> and emodepside expressed in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has also been investigated (<link linkend="bib190">Welz et al., 2011</link>)<!--: PMID 21490955-->. When <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004830;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> from <emphasis>A. caninum</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. oncophora</emphasis> were expressed in <emphasis>C. elegans <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004830;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants, their sensitivity to emodepside was restored, providing evidence that emodepside can act on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> channels from parasitic nematodes and for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as an excellent model for such expression studies. In addition, these authors showed that penitrem A, an inhibitor of BK channels (<link linkend="bib103">Knaus et al., 1994</link>)<!--: PMID 7514038-->, blocked the effect of emodepside in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, providing further evidence for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> channels as the site of emodepside&apos;s action in nematodes. Assuming the main target for emodepside is <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink>, the question arises as to whether emodepside activates or inhibits <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> actions. Preliminary data would suggest that emodepside facilitates activation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> channels heterologously expressed in HEK293 cells (<link linkend="bib68">Holden-Dye et al., 2012</link>)<!--: PMID 22539031-->. A recent review summarises research on emodepside and the value of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> in elucidating its mode of action (<link linkend="bib107">Krucken et al., 2012</link>)<!--: PMID 22858281-->.</para>
<para>The discovery of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> as a mediator of the inhibitory effects of emodepside on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is an important development in this field, which in the light of ivermectin resistance has an urgent need for such breakthroughs. In the broader context, there is an emerging body of evidence indicating that BK channels such as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> may play a pivotal role in conferring sensitivity to neuroactive drugs, including ethanol and local anaesthetics (<link linkend="bib35">Dillon et al., 2013</link><!-- : PMID 23882127-->; <link linkend="bib64">Hawasli et al., 2004</link><!-- : PMID 15514057-->; <link linkend="bib31">Davies et al., 2003</link>)<!--: PMID 14675531-->, and in regulating the pattern of activity of neural networks (<link linkend="bib168">Salkoff et al., 2006</link>)<!--: PMID 17115074-->. Thus, an additional and valuable facet of these studies is that emodepside provides a new tool to dissect the functional role of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> in neural networks using the power of molecular genetics in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Recent reviews summarise the evidence for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> as the major target site for emodepside in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and parasitic nematodes (<link linkend="bib68">Holden-Dye at al., 2012</link><!-- : PMID 22539031-->; <link linkend="bib130">Martin et al., 2012a</link>)<!--: PMID 21910990-->. Current evidence would suggest that emodepside acts on both latrophilin receptors and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> channels in the pharyngeal system to inhibit pumping but only on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> channels in body wall muscle to inhibit locomotion.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-7">
<title>Thiazolide: nitazoxanide</title>
<para>Nitazoxanide, a pyruvate:ferredoxin oxidoreductase inhibitor, acts against a broad spectrum of protozoa and helminths that occur in the intestinal tract. The enzyme it targets is required to maintain electron transfer during anaerobic respiration. It is currently used for the treatment of protozoal infections (and is therefore not listed in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). The site of action of this compound has not been established in nematodes although anaerobic electron transport enzymes may be a potential target (<link linkend="bib51">Gilles and Hoffman, 2002</link>)<!--: PMID 11854075-->. The effect of nitazoxanide has been examined on growth and development of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib40">Fonseca-Salamanca et al., 2003</link>)<!--: PMID 14574563-->. After seven days culture nitazoxanide (100 &mu;M) only reduced population growth by 33%. In contrast mebendazole (5 &mu;M) and albendazole (1 &mu;M) reduced growth by over 90%. Nitazoxanide (100 &mu;M) had no effect on either embryonation or hatching in <emphasis>Heligmosomoides polygyrus.</emphasis> Therefore the efficacy of this compound is relatively low compared to other anthelmintic agents. Nitazoxanide also failed to show much activity against <emphasis>Trichuris muris</emphasis> or <emphasis>Ancylostoma ceylanicum in vivo</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib184">Tritten et al., 2012</link>)<!--: PMID 24533270-->. Nitazoxanide has been found to inhibit ATP synthesis in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib65">Hemphill et al., 2006</link>)<!--: PMID 16634717-->.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-8">
<title>Amino-acetonitrile derivatives: monepantel</title>
<para>During investigations for new anthelmintics acting through novel sites, the amino-acetonitrile derivatives (AADs) were identified using a larval development assay against a benzimidazole-resistant isolate of <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib37">Ducray et al., 2008</link>)<!--: PMID 18400497-->. These authors noted that while N-acyl amino-acetonitriles had been used against insects, fungi and bacteria, they had not previously been tested against nematodes. Subsequent research showed the AADs were active against a range of nematodes, including various stages of <emphasis>Cooperia oncophora, Trichostrongylus colubriformis, Ostertagia ostertagi, Nematodirus spathiger, Teladorsagia circumcincta,</emphasis> and <emphasis>Chabertia ovina</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib91">Kaminsky et al., 2008a</link>)<!--: PMID 18337814-->. After testing a number of AADs for their anthelmintic activity, including their efficacy and tolerability in sheep and cattle, AAD-1566 was selected for in depth study in sheep and given the name, monepantel (<link linkend="bib92">Kaminsky et al., 2008b</link><!-- : PMID 18594861-->; <link linkend="bib93">Kaminsky and Rufener, 2012</link>). The AADs were effective against nematodes that had shown resistance to levamisole, ivermectin and/or albendazole (<link linkend="bib93">Kaminsky et al., 2008a</link>)<!--: PMID 18337814-->. Monepantel is also more effective as an anthelmintic compared to derquantel in combination with abamectin when sheep were treated with a multi-resistant <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> isolate (<link linkend="bib167">Sager et al., 2012</link>)<!--: PMID 22576857-->.</para>
<para>A forward genetic screen for amino-acetonitrile resistance, using <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> mutants, identified two possible genes, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000056;class=Gene" role="_blank">acr-17</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000062;class=Gene" role="_blank">acr-23</ulink></emphasis>, both members of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06083;class=Protein" role="_blank">DEG-3</ulink> group of nicotinic receptor subunits in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib91">Kaminsky et al., 2008a</link>)<!--: PMID 18337814-->. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36939;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACR-23</ulink>, and not <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE10922;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACR-17</ulink>, was identified as the main contributor to the AAD response of hypercontraction of body wall muscle and paralysis, that is, acting as an acetylcholine agonist. Interestingly, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06083;class=Protein" role="_blank">DEG-3</ulink> group of nicotinic subunits is not present in mammals (<link linkend="bib140">Mongan et al., 2002</link>)<!--: PMID 11967372--> consistent with the observation that monepantel is well tolerated by the host. Further screens in <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> were conducted to identify the molecular target in the parasitic nematodes. Three <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> lines were identified that were resistant to AADs, all of which carried mutations in a gene encoding the nicotinic ACh receptor subunit, <emphasis>Hco-des-2H</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib91">Kaminsky et al., 2008a</link>)<!--: PMID 18337814-->. However, a <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> mutant lacking the homologous receptor subunit, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47329;class=Protein" role="_blank">DES-2</ulink>, was not resistant to AADs. Two of these <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> lines also carried mutations in <emphasis>Hco-acr-23H,</emphasis> which is now called <emphasis>Hco-mptl-1</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib164">Rufener et al., 2009</link>)<!--: PMID 19360096-->. This raises the question as to the role of these subunits in mediating the anthelmintic action of monepantel. The pharmacology of the subunits, <emphasis>Hco-deg-3</emphasis> and <emphasis>Hco-des-2</emphasis>, was investigated in more detail through expression in <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes, and interestingly a heteromer of these subunits was found to be more sensitive to choline than to acetylcholine (<link linkend="bib162">Rufener et al., 2010a</link>)<!--: PMID 20679419-->. Monepantel and monepantel sulfone, the major metabolite of monepantel in sheep (<link linkend="bib95">Karadzovska et al., 2009</link>)<!--: PMID 19614841--> both enhanced the choline-induced currents, thus indicating that they act as positive allosteric modulators of these channels. <link linkend="bib162">Rufener et al. (2010a)</link><!--: PMID 20679419--> were unable to express <emphasis>Hco-mptl-1</emphasis> in <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes, perhaps because the HcoMPTL-1 receptor requires a specific chaperone and/or additional AChR subunits for functionality; therefore, direct evidence that this subunit is sensitive to monepantel is lacking. Nonetheless, there is further evidence for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36939;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACR-23</ulink>/MPTL-1 subunit as the primary target for monepantel as when this subunit is absent in a nematode, for example, <emphasis>Pristionchus pacificus</emphasis> or <emphasis>Strongyloides ratti,</emphasis> these species are relatively insensitive to monepantel (&gt;100 times less sensitive compared to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>) (<link linkend="bib163">Rufener et al., 2010b</link>)<!--: PMID 20838602-->. The monepantel story from its discovery to mode of action has been summarized recently (<link linkend="bib93">Kaminsky and Rufener, 2012</link>) and a comparison of the properties of monepantel, emodepside and derquantel has also recently been published (<link linkend="bib38">Epe and Kaminsky, 2013</link>)<!--: PMID 23376212-->.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-9">
<title>Aminophenylamidines: amidantel and tribendimidine</title>
<para>Over 30 years ago amidantel (Bayd 8815) was introduced as a new anthelmintic against hookworms, <emphasis>A. caninum</emphasis> and <emphasis>Unicinaria stencephala</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib181">Thomas, 1979</link>)<!--: PMID 295548-->. Amidantel and its derivatives, including tribendimidine, were later synthesized in China and studied for biological activity (<link linkend="bib198">Xiao et al., 2013</link><!-- : PMID 23352956-->; <link linkend="bib197">Xiao et al., 2005</link>)<!--: PMID 15777691-->. Tribendimidine was particularly active against <emphasis>Ascaris lumbricoides</emphasis> and <emphasis>Necator americanus</emphasis>. In an attempt to identify the site of action of tribendimidine a forward genetic screen for tribendimidine resistant mutants was undertaken using <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib77">Hu et al., 2009</link>)<!--: PMID 19668355-->. Wild-type <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> were <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000644;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">paralyzed</ulink> when exposed to 220 &micro;M tribendimidine and closer inspection indicated degeneration of their internal structure. The development of L1 larvae in this concentration was also delayed. In their screen, <link linkend="bib77">Hu et al. (2009)</link><!--: PMID 19668355--> identified ten resistant animals that they divided into four groups, <emphasis>trb-1, trb-2, trb-3,</emphasis> and <emphasis>trb-4</emphasis>. These mutants had normal brood sizes in the presence of tribendimidine while wild-type <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> had <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000154;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">reduced brood size</ulink>. <link linkend="bib77">Hu et al. (2009)</link><!--: PMID 19668355--> found that tribendimidine mutants were also resistant to levamisole and pyrantel, indicating that tribendimidine resistant <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> were also resistant to L-subtype nAChR agonists suggesting a common target for tribendimine and levamisole, the L-nAChR. Moreover, they found that <emphasis>trb-1</emphasis> to <emphasis>-4</emphasis> correlated to genes already identified for levamisole resistance: <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006797;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-63</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002975;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-8</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006785;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-50</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006759;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink></emphasis>, respectively. In addition, it was shown that tribendimidine resistance occurred in eleven further levamisole-resistant mutants. The action of tribendimidine in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> mutants lacking components of the L-nAChR has been investigated (<link linkend="bib135">Miltsch et al., 2013</link>)<!--: PMID 23707730--> where <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006774;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-38</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006797;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-63</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002974;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-1</ulink>,</emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002975;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-8</ulink></emphasis> mutants had greatly reduced sensitivity to the anthelmintic, demonstrating the importance of all these subunits for tribendimidine action. Thus using <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> it has been shown that tribendimidine and levamisole act at the same receptor and so nematodes resistant to levamisole would also be predicted to be resistant to tribendimidine. Levamisole is listed as an anthelmintic for use in humans (<ulink url="http://www.who.int/medicines/publications/essentialmedicines/18th_EML_Final_web_8Jul13.pdf">WHO Model List of Essential Medicines, 2013</ulink>) but is rarely used in practice due to its low therapeutic index.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-10">
<title>Crystal (Cry) proteins from <emphasis>Bacillus thuringiensis</emphasis>: Cry5B, Cry21A</title>
<para>Cry proteins are pore-forming proteins made by the Gram-positive bacterium, <emphasis>Bacillus thuringiensis</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib74">Hu and Aroian, 2012a</link><!-- : PMID 22562659-->; <link linkend="bib75">Hu and Aroian, 2012b</link>). Though first used as insecticides, these compounds have since been shown to have anthelmintic properties, including against <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib105">Kotze et al., 2005</link><!-- : PMID 15964574-->; <link linkend="bib189">Wei et al., 2003</link>)<!--: PMID 12598644-->. When Cry5B is fed to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> there is damage to its intestine, a fall in brood size from around 250 to 5, and death (<link linkend="bib128">Marroquin et al., 2000</link>)<!--: PMID 10924467-->. These authors developed a genetic screen for recovery of mutants resistant to Cry5B. The mutants were called <emphasis>bre</emphasis> mutants, <emphasis role="bold">B</emphasis>acillus-toxin <emphasis role="bold">re</emphasis>sistant, and five genes were identified, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000266;class=Gene" role="_blank">bre-1</ulink>, -2, -3 -4</emphasis> and <emphasis>-5</emphasis>. The intestine of all five mutants was unaffected by Cry5B while the <emphasis>bre</emphasis> mutants were strongly resistant to Cry5B-induced death. The effect of Cry5B on brood size was also greatly reduced in these mutants. The same group in a later paper cloned <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000266;class=Gene" role="_blank">bre-1</ulink></emphasis> and characterized its phenotype (<link linkend="bib9">Barrows et al., 2007</link>)<!--: PMID 17135259-->. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000266;class=Gene" role="_blank">bre-1</ulink></emphasis> encodes an enzyme with homology to GDP-mannose 4,6-dehydratase which is involved in the synthesis of GDP-fucose. Injection of GDP-fucose into intestinal cells of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> rescues the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000266;class=Gene" role="_blank">bre-1</ulink></emphasis> phenotype. These mutants also show defects in the production of polar glycolipids which act as receptors for Cry5B (<link linkend="bib58">Griffiths et al., 2005</link>)<!--: PMID 15705852-->. These carbohydrates contain the arthroseries core which is present in nematodes but absent in vertebrates (<link linkend="bib75">Hu and Aroian, 2012b</link>). Cry protein monomers bind to intestinal cell receptors, oligomerize, and enter the plasma membrane to form pores. These holes in the membrane disrupt cell integrity, ionic balance, and membrane potentials, resulting in death or severe disruption of cell activity. So far, all nematodes tested, whether they are free-living, animal, or plant parasites, are sensitive to Cry5B. In an interesting study it has been shown that combination therapy of Cry5B and nAChR agonists may have potential as the combination exhibits synergistic properties (<link linkend="bib76">Hu et al., 2010</link>)<!--: PMID 20231450-->. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> the p38 mitogen activated protein kinase (MAPK) pathway protects against Cry5B (<link linkend="bib94">Kao et al., 2011</link>)<!--: PMID 21408619-->. A similar situation has been found in hookworms, for example, <emphasis>A. ceylanicum</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib74">Hu et al., 2012a</link>)<!--: PMID 22562659-->, demonstrating that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is likely to be a good model for the study of these toxins in nematodes.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-11">
<title>Organophosphate and carbamate anticholinesterases: dichlorvos, haloxon, trichlorphon and aldicarb</title>
<para>Anticholinesterases block the enzymes that break down the neurotransmitter acetylcholine. Thus adminstration of the compounds leads to elevation of synaptic levels of acetycholine at the neuromuscular junction in nematodes and results in spastic paralysis. However, these compounds are highly toxic to all organisms that use acetylcholine as a neurotransmitter, including humans, and this severely limits their use. They have been used as nematicides against plant parasitic nematodes, but their toxicity is now prompting their withdrawal from use, even as chemical control agents for crop protection, because of serious environmental concerns. Here we will briefly discuss investigation of these compounds in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and highlight possible areas for future improvements.</para>
<para>Organophosphates and carbamates, acting through phosphorylation and carbamylation of the enzyme active site, respectively, have been the main cholinesterase inhibitors used as anthelmintics (<link linkend="bib172">Selkirk et al., 2005</link>)<!--: PMID 16569291-->. In general organophosphates are not selective to nematode cholinesterases and so have a low therapeutic index and have largely been replaced by anthelmintics less toxic to the host. However, in recent studies on pyridinic compounds as potential anthelmintics, one compound, diethyl 2,2&rsquo;-[(3-nitropyridine-2,6-diyl) bissulfanediyl] diacetate, which was effective as an anticholinesterase anthelmintic, was non-toxic in rats at a dose of 2000 mg/kg (<link linkend="bib185">Valli et al., 2011</link>)<!--: PMID 21728957-->. Therefore, pyridinic compounds together with pyrazinics, may provide future safer cholinesterase inhibitors with high therapeutic indices.</para>
<para>Cholinesterases occur widely in animals, including nematodes, and have been studied in detail in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Eighteen aldicarb- and trichlorphon-resistant genes have been characterized in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib144">Nguyen et al., 1995</link>)<!--: PMID 7498734-->. These include <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000481;class=Gene" role="_blank">cha-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004362;class=Gene" role="_blank">ric-1</ulink>, -3, -4, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004921;class=Gene" role="_blank">snt-1</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004921;class=Gene" role="_blank">ric-2</ulink>)</emphasis> and ten <emphasis>unc</emphasis> mutants. Subsequently, four distinct acetylcholinesterase genes, <emphasis>viz, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000035;class=Gene" role="_blank">ace-1</ulink></emphasis> (class A), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000036;class=Gene" role="_blank">ace-2</ulink></emphasis> (class B), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000037;class=Gene" role="_blank">ace-3</ulink></emphasis> (class C), and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000038;class=Gene" role="_blank">ace-4</ulink></emphasis> have been identified in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib54">Grauso et al., 1998</link>)<!--: PMID 9539167-->. Expression patterns of these genes have been investigated by <link linkend="bib24">Combes et al. (2003)</link><!--: PMID 12911746-->. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000035;class=Gene" role="_blank">ace-1</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in all body wall muscle and vulval muscle cells, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000036;class=Gene" role="_blank">ace-2</ulink></emphasis> in neurons (including amphid neuron AWC), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000037;class=Gene" role="_blank">ace-3</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000038;class=Gene" role="_blank">ace-4</ulink></emphasis> operon in pharyngeal muscle cells, pm3, pm4, pm5, and pm7, a few head and ganglion neurons and in CANs. Interestingly, pm5 pharyngeal muscle cells express <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000035;class=Gene" role="_blank">ace-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000036;class=Gene" role="_blank">ace-2</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000037;class=Gene" role="_blank">ace-3</ulink></emphasis> but otherwise these genes have their own expression patterns, indicating lack of redundancy.</para>
<para>Several papers have investigated the effect of organophosphates on gene expression in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib117">Lewis et al., 2013</link><!-- : PMID 23631360-->; <link linkend="bib186">Vinuela et al., 2010</link><!-- : PMID 20808445-->; <link linkend="bib82">Jadhav and Rajini, 2009</link><!-- : PMID 19202558-->; <link linkend="bib118">Lewis et al., 2009</link>)<!--: PMID 19402892-->. Using sublethal concentrations of dichlorvos, 5&ndash;80 &micro;M, and four hours exposure, <link linkend="bib82">Jadhav and Rajini (2009)</link><!--: PMID 19202558--> found that pharyngeal pumping and acetylcholinesterase activity were inhibited. The LD<subscript>50</subscript> for dichlorvos decreased as exposure time was increased from 4 to 36 h. When exposed to 5&ndash;80 &micro;M dichlorvos for between 4 and 3 h, induction of the heat shock protein, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002020;class=Gene" role="_blank">hsp-16</ulink></emphasis>, increased both with concentration and time, with a maximum after 24 h and then induction declined. The induction of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002020;class=Gene" role="_blank">hsp-16</ulink></emphasis> was confined to the pharynx. These studies showed that sub-lethal concentrations of an organophosphate can affect feeding, acetylcholinesterase activity, and expression of a stress gene. Induction of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002020;class=Gene" role="_blank">hsp-16</ulink></emphasis> in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has been used as a monitor of environmental stress (<link linkend="bib180">Stringham and Candido, 1994</link>). In their study, <link linkend="bib186">Vinuela et al. (2010)</link><!--: PMID 20808445--> exposed <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> eggs for a total of 72 h to chlorpyrifos (0.5 mg/L, approx. 1.4 &micro;M) or diazinon (1.0 mg/L, approx. 3.3 &micro;M) or a mixture of the two organophosphates. They found that 551 genes were regulated by chlorpyrifos, 245 by diazinon, with 126 regulated by either compound. 233 genes were regulated by the mixture, including 89 genes which were not regulated by the compounds alone. It is interesting that though the structures of the two organophosphates are similar, many of the genes they induced are different. These genes are involved in a number of pathways associated with detoxification (involving both phases I and II of xenobiotic metabolism), stress, innate immunity, and transport and metabolism of lipids. <link linkend="bib186">Vinuela et al. (2010)</link><!--: PMID 20808445--> noted that while the effects on gene expression of the mixture of the two organophosphates showed differences from the effects of the single compounds, the pathways affected were similar, involving <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000912;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001250;class=Gene" role="_blank">elt-2</ulink>, snk1/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004055;class=Gene" role="_blank">pmk-1</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004862;class=Gene" role="_blank">sma-9</ulink></emphasis>. In their first paper <link linkend="bib118">Lewis et al. (2009)</link><!--: PMID 19402892--> exposed L4 stage <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to the organophosphates dichlorvos (3&ndash;50 mg/L, approx. 13.5&ndash;226 &micro;M) or fenamiphos (10&ndash;200 mg/L, approx. 33&ndash;660 &micro;M) or to the antimalarial mefloquine (26&ndash;1300 &micro;M) (as a control) for 8 h. The expression of 87 genes was affected by exposure to the organophosphates but not to mefloquine while the abundance of 34 proteins also changed. Many of these genes and proteins were expressed in muscle and neuronal tissue and play a role in lipid metabolism, cell adhesion, apoptosis and detoxification. As in the study of <link linkend="bib186">Vinuela et al. (2010)</link><!--: PMID 20808445-->, some of the genes whose expression was altered were selective for one or the other organophosphate. In the second paper, <link linkend="bib117">Lewis et al. (2013)</link><!--: PMID 23631360--> initially investigated the effect of a range of concentrations (0.12&ndash;15.0 &micro;M) of dichlorvos on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> behaviour. 0.6 &micro;M and 15.0 &micro;M were selected for the gene expression study, and L3/L4 animals exposed for 2 or 8 h or continuously during the experiment. A large number of the genes expressed following exposure to dichlorvos were transcriptionally regulated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> which is associated with the control of metabolism, aging, innate immunity and stress responses in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Dichlorvos activated similar genes to those activated by bacterial infections in <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> which are involved in innate immunity. Dichlorvos also upregulated genes required for myogenesis, and for axon regeneration (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001008;class=Gene" role="_blank">dlk-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004057;class=Gene" role="_blank">pmk-3</ulink></emphasis>) and guidance. Genes associated with immune response and energy metabolism were upregulated within 2 h. <link linkend="bib117">Lewis et al. (2013)</link><!--: PMID 23631360--> also looked for genes involved in recovery from dichlorvos and identified <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00011839;class=Gene" role="_blank">T19C4.5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002018;class=Gene" role="_blank">hsp-16.41</ulink>,</emphasis> which were expressed following removal of dichlorvos. Seven key genes were identified that were upregulated by dichlorvos; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006779;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-43</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006575;class=Gene" role="_blank">tir-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004758;class=Gene" role="_blank">sek-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001461;class=Gene" role="_blank">flp-18</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004858;class=Gene" role="_blank">sma-4</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004860;class=Gene" role="_blank">sma-6</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002090;class=Gene" role="_blank">ins-7</ulink></emphasis>. They concluded that the main mechanisms for dichlorvos effects are the inhibition of acetylcholinesterase and depletion of energy reserves, possibly due to mitochondrial dysfunction. However, it is clear from these studies that, in addition to manipulating acetylcholine levels, organophosphates can act on a range of physiological processes in <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> and by analogy also in parasitic nematodes,.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-12">
<title>Flavonoids: apigenin</title>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has been used to screen flavonoids for anthelmintic activity. In a study involving 13 flavones, apigenin was found to inhibit larval growth (<link linkend="bib201">Yoon et al., 2006</link>)<!--: PMID 16903079-->. When the first generation developed in the presence of apigenin there was a slight reduction in body size but larval development in the F1 generation was severely impaired in the presence of the flavone. The mechanism associated with this inhibition of larval growth in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> was investigated by <link linkend="bib99">Kawasaki et al. (2010)</link><!--: PMID 20647014--> and found to be associated with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> activation. These authors proposed that apigenin acts as a stressor to either stimulate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> activity directly or inhibit <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46852;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink>/insulin signalling, which reduces the inhibitory effect of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46852;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink> on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink>. In either case <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44821;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> is activated which leads to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000059;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">larval arrest</ulink>. Flavone (2-phenyl chromone) has been shown to induce embryonic and larval lethality in both <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and a plant parasitic nematode, the pinewood nematode, <emphasis>Bursaphelenchus xylophilus</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib115">Lee et al., 2008</link>)<!--: PMID 18596412-->.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-13">
<title>Fluoroalkenyls: fluensulfone</title>
<para>Fluensulfone (5-chloro-2-(3,4,4-trifluorobut-3-enylsulfonyl)-1,3-thiazole) is a member of the fluoroalkenyl thioether group and has proven potential as a new nematicide to control plant parasitic nematode infections (<link linkend="bib146">Oka et al., 2012</link><!-- : PMID 21842527-->; <link linkend="bib145">Oka et al., 2009</link>)<!--: PMID 19488996-->. For example, application of fluensulfone through both soil drenching and foliar spray has been shown to significantly reduce root infection and penetration by plant parasitic nematodes, <emphasis>Meloidogyne javanica</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib145">Oka et al., 2009</link>)<!--: PMID 19488996--> and <emphasis>M. incognita</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib146">Oka et al., 2012</link>)<!--: PMID 21842527-->. Fluensulfone has marked effects on the development and behaviour of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and the profile of its effects is different from the other main classes of anthelmintic and nematicides including levamisole, ivermectin, and the organophosphates, suggesting a distinct mode of action (<link linkend="bib101">Kearn et al., 2014</link>)<!--: PMID 24581383-->.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-14">
<title>Spiroindolines: SYN351, SYN876</title>
<para>Spiroindolines have both insecticidal and anthelmintic activity, with SYN351 being the lead compound for studies using <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib178">Sluder et al., 2012</link>)<!--: PMID 22563457-->. SYN351 induces an <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000643;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">uncoordinated</ulink> &ldquo;loopy&rdquo;, coiling locomotion in <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> and also inhibits pharyngeal pumping frequency. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000481;class=Gene" role="_blank">cha-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants, which have a defect in their ability to synthesise acetylcholine, are hypersensitive in the presence of the spiroindoline SYN876 while sublethal doses of SYN876 suppress the effect of the cholinesterase inhibitor, aldicarb. These experiments suggest that spiroindolines exert their effects on nematode behaviour by effectively reducing the levels of available acetylcholine at the synapse. A chemical mutagenesis screen employing <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> generated mutants which were resistant to spiroindolines. These resistant strains harboured mutations in the gene encoding the vesicular acetylcholine transporter (VAChT), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006756;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-17</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib178">Sluder et al., 2012</link>)<!--: PMID 22563457-->, providing evidence that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17307;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-17</ulink> might be the target for the compound. Further studies, in which the vesicular acetylcholine transporter from <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> was expressed in PC12 cells, demonstrated a spiroindoline binding site that could be displaced by the classical acetylcholine vesicular transport inhibitor vesamicol. Taken together these data are consistent with the proposal that mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006756;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-17</ulink></emphasis> confer <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> resistance to spiroindolines. Therefore spiroindolines are a group of compounds which appear to target a novel site for anthelmintic action, namely the vesicular acetylcholine transporter (<link linkend="bib178">Sluder et al., 2012</link>)<!--: PMID 22563457-->.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>The future</title>
<para>A particular challenge for companies engaged in anthelmintic and nematicide research, not experienced to the same extent by the pharmaceutical industry, is that cost-effectiveness is a prime concern. Moreover, there are additional constraints in terms of the levels of host toxicity that can be tolerated. For example, in tropical medicine, anthelmintics must be used in mass chemotherapy programmes in regions where clinical support is sparse, and therefore drugs need to be very well tolerated in humans of all ages. In treatment of livestock, persistence of chemicals in tissues becomes an issue for meat production, while the use of nematicides for crop protection has to take into careful consideration stability, leaching from the soil, and environmental toxicity, especially effects on non-target organisms.</para>
<para>As can be seen from the discussion above, only a relatively small repertoire of drugs and chemicals are currently available to address these needs. Notably, ivermectin has been hugely successful both in veterinary and tropical medicine, and its use in Africa has transformed the lives of populations previously devastated by the tropical disease onchocerciasis (river blindness). However, in the last five years resistance to ivermectin has been emerging (<link linkend="bib149">Osei-Atweneboana et al., 2011</link>)<!--: PMID 21468315--> and it is highly likely that successors will soon be needed for this extremely important anthelmintic.</para>
<para>There has been recent progress in drug and chemical development for the control of parasitic nematodes. Since 2007 three new anthelmintics have been used in the formulation of commercially available treatments; emodepside (Profender<superscript>&reg;</superscript> spot-on for cats and tablets for dogs, Procox<superscript>&reg;</superscript> for puppies), monepantel (Zolvix<superscript>&reg;</superscript> for sheep), and derquantel (Starect<superscript>&reg;</superscript> for sheep). Whether or not these anthelmintic drugs can be used in formulations to address further parasitic nematode infections of livestock and humans, or indeed whether they have efficacy or provide new leads to address the problem of plant parasitic nematodes, remains to be seen. The introduction of these anthelmintics and their current limited use has recently been concisely discussed by <link linkend="bib38">Epe and Kaminsky (2013)</link><!--: PMID 23376212-->. Emodepside has efficacy against filarial nematodes and compounds of this class may prove to be of use in the future for the treatment of filariasis (<link linkend="bib148">Olliaro et al., 2011</link><!-- : PMID 21695247-->; <link linkend="bib203">Zahner et al., 2001</link>)<!--: PMID 11595239-->. There are also further possibilities in the pipeline. For example, closantel (a salicylanilide) has potential to treat onchocerciasis (<link linkend="bib52">Gloeckner et al., 2010</link>)<!--: PMID 20142509-->. Closantel is an inhibitor of filarial chitinase which results in inhibition of moulting in infective L3 larvae of <emphasis>Onchocerca volvulus</emphasis>. However, this stage of the parasite is only briefly present in the host, and in addition closantel acts as a protonophore and is an uncoupler of oxidative phosphorylation (<link linkend="bib177">Skuce and Fairweather, 1990</link>)<!--: PMID 2315284-->, both of which may limit this compound&apos;s usefulness. Nonetheless a number of closantel analogues have also been synthesized and tested for activity on <emphasis>O. volvulus</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib44">Garner et al., 2011</link>)<!--: PMID 21534605-->.</para>
<para>As we have noted in this review, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has played a major role in defining the mode of action for anthelmintics and nematicides and can also contribute to understanding mechanisms of resistance, especially through the adoption of a &lsquo;model-hopping&rsquo; approach whereby the functionality of parasite genes is assessed by using <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as an expression system. The utility of this approach will be facilitated by progress in the sequencing and characterisation of parasite genomes. Noteworthy in this regard is the recent publication of a draft genome of MHCO3(ISE).N1, an inbred <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> strain that is susceptible to all the major anthelmintics, and its comparison to the genome of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib111">Laing et al., 2013</link>)<!--: PMID 21041637-->. The pentameric ligand-gated ion channels of <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> are very similar to those of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, suggesting the value of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as a model for the Strongylid nematode nervous system. However, there are important gene differences in relation to glutamate, acetylcholine, and amine signalling. <link linkend="bib111">Laing et al. (2013)</link><!--: PMID 21041637--> was followed by a second paper on the genome and developmental transcriptome of <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib171">Schwarz et al., 2013</link>)<!--: PMID 23985341-->.</para>
<para>An interesting extension of the model hopping approach is in the development of vaccines against parasitic nematodes, in which <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> can be used for the expression of vaccine antigens (<link linkend="bib104">Knox, 2012</link>; <link linkend="bib142">Murray et al., 2007</link>)<!--: PMID 17451718-->.</para>
<para>Of likely importance for the future is the use of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as a model system for drug discovery. It is to be hoped that this will provide new anthelmintics that have novel modes of action and thus circumvent the problem of anthelmintic resistance. The combination of RNAi and high throughput techniques for analysis of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> stimulated interest in drug discovery using chemical genetic screens (<link linkend="bib10">Behm et al., 2005</link><!-- : PMID 15734653-->; <link linkend="bib88">Jones et al., 2005</link>)<!--: PMID 15803195-->. Advances in the application of microfluidic- and droplet-based approaches to the study of <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> and the incorporation of optogenetics, has extended this capability; a variety of &lsquo;chips&rsquo; have been designed that facilitate imaging, behavioural analysis, and electrophysiology (<link linkend="bib78">Hu et al., 2013</link><!-- : PMID 23717588-->; <link linkend="bib100">Kearn et al., 2013</link><!-- : PMID 23242591-->; <link linkend="bib124">Liu et al., 2013</link><!-- : PMID 23254956-->; <link linkend="bib125">Lockery et al., 2012</link><!-- : PMID 22588281-->; <link linkend="bib199">Xu and Kim, 2011</link><!-- : PMID 21969037-->; <link linkend="bib179">Stirman et al., 2010</link><!-- : PMID 20538016-->; <link linkend="bib11">Ben-Yakar et al., 2009</link><!-- : PMID 19896831-->; <link linkend="bib79">Hulme et al., 2008</link><!-- : PMID 18587316-->; <link linkend="bib23">Chronis et al., 2007</link>)<!--: PMID 17704783-->. The molecular targets for the drugs that come out of these screens or from other pipe-lines can be defined using the powerful approach of forward genetics in <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> and may uncover new effectors for anthelmintic action.</para>
<para>More targeted approaches to anthelmintic drug discovery are also ongoing. These are providing fundamental information on nematode neurobiology with the aim of identifying signalling molecules that have pivotal roles in neural circuits that underpin vital behaviours. In this context the nematode nervous system still has target sites, such as ion channels and receptors, which have not yet been exploited and can form the basis for novel anthelmintics (<link linkend="bib194">Wolstenholme, 2011</link>)<!--: PMID 24533259-->. It will be interesting to see whether or not the ambition to target peptidergic signalling pathways translates into a marketable drug (<link linkend="bib47">Geary and Maule, 2010</link><!-- : PMID 21189670-->; <link linkend="bib57">Greenwood et al., 2005</link>)<!--: PMID 16569288-->, although the industry is actively investigating the characterization of FLP receptors from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib112">Larsen et al., 2013</link>)<!--: PMID 24533288-->. However, to date there has been little success (<link linkend="bib46">Geary, 2012</link>; <link linkend="bib137">McVeigh et al., 2012</link>)<!--: PMID 24533265-->. There are also numerous enzymes involved in signalling and metabolic pathways that might provide novel sites for anthelmintic action, together with nematode amine receptors (<link linkend="bib155">Rana and Misra-Bhattacharya, 2013</link><!-- : PMID 23529336-->; <link linkend="bib46">Geary, 2012</link>).</para>
<para>In conclusion, as discussed here and further emphasized elsewhere (<link linkend="bib38">Epe and Kaminsky, 2013</link><!-- : PMID 23376212-->; <link linkend="bib148">Olliaro et al., 2011</link>)<!--: PMID 21695247-->, there is an urgent need to develop novel anthelmintics in view of the increasing threat to live-stock and humans from anthelmintic-resistant strains of parasites. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has proved to be an extremely useful model organism for mode of action studies, however, the opportunity it presents for drug discovery has arguably been under-utilised (see &lsquo;<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/articles/volume-19-number-4/bridging-the-divide-abstract-a-tripartite-association-steinernema-nematodes-xenorhabdus-bacteria-and-insects/">Bridging the Divide</ulink>&rsquo;; Worm Breeder&apos;s Gazette Volume 19, Number 4). An additional concern is the threat to crops from plant parasitic nematodes, as currently available nematicides are progressively withdrawn from use due to their environmental impact. For the future, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> research should be further applied to these important challenges for human and veterinary medicine and for food security.</para>
<para>Acknowledgments: We are grateful to two anonymous reviewers for helpful comments which improved this manuscript.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>References</title>
<para/>
&anthelminticdrugs.2_ref;
</sect1>
</article>