<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 12. Functions of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49403;class=Protein" role="_blank">DYS-1</ulink> and associated proteins in muscle</title>
<para>Part of a muscle cell is shown with one dense body anchored to the distal sarcolemma. Actin containing filaments are anchored to the dense body and interact with myosin containing thick filaments. Cellular organelles such as the nucleus, mitochondria, and endoplasmic reticulum with ribosomes are localized in the deeper part of the muscle cell. A muscle arm corresponding to the postsynaptic elements of the neuromuscular junction in the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> muscle is represented in close contact with a motoneuron. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49403;class=Protein" role="_blank">DYS-1</ulink> and the associated Dystrophin Glycoprotein Complex (DGC, represented in red) fulfill different functions in muscle. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49403;class=Protein" role="_blank">DYS-1</ulink> is involved in maintaining dense body and sarcolemma integrtity. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49403;class=Protein" role="_blank">DYS-1</ulink> localizes under the entire sarcolemma of striated body wall muscle and in muscle arms. Through the interaction of its C-terminal end with the dense body protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31397;class=Protein" role="_blank">DEB-1</ulink> (vinculin; blue), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49403;class=Protein" role="_blank">DYS-1</ulink> links the DGC to the dense body. The LIM-domain protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46698;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZYX-1</ulink>, which interacts with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31397;class=Protein" role="_blank">DEB-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46675;class=Protein" role="_blank">ATN-1</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30500;class=Protein" role="_blank">DYC-1</ulink> may be involved in signaling from the dense body to the nucleus, thus linking <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49403;class=Protein" role="_blank">DYS-1</ulink> and DGC function to dense body signaling. The interaction of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41901;class=Protein" role="_blank">ISLO-1</ulink> with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE09809;class=Protein" role="_blank">STN-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> connects the K<superscript>+</superscript> channel, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink>, to the DGC. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> localizes close to the L-type Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> channel <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49477;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-19</ulink>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47467;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> mediated potassium efflux is thought to negatively regulate the calcium-mediated activation of muscle, thus involving <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49403;class=Protein" role="_blank">DYS-1</ulink> and DGC in the control of calcium homeostasis. At the neuromuscular junction acetylcholine (Ach) binding to its receptor (AchR) lead to muscle excitation. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49403;class=Protein" role="_blank">DYS-1</ulink> and the DGC are involved in cholinergic transmission by controlling <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07569;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACE-1</ulink>/2 acetylcholine esterase (AchE) activity and Acetylcholine (Ach) uptake through the acetylcholine/choline transporter <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39951;class=Protein" role="_blank">SNF-6</ulink>, which interacts with STN-1.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>
