<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 4. Networks of interacting proteins found at integrin adhesion sites in body wall muscle of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>.</title>
<para>Yellow denotes proteins that are localized to both M-lines and dense bodies; red denotes proteins that are localized only to M-lines; green denotes proteins localized only to dense bodies; white (or clear) denotes proteins that are found around or between dense bodies, and in some cases, also to M-lines; blue indicates proteins that are localized to the A-band. In parentheses are the names of the human orthologs or homologs. Most of the interactions were first identified by Y2H screens or assays, and then confirmed by in vitro binding using purified recombinant proteins, localized by antibodies and/or GFP fusions, and genetic analysis. Black lines indicate confirmed interactions; dotted lines indicated interactions only suggested by Y2H results. At M-lines, these interactions create a physical linkage from the muscle cell membrane (via integrins) to MHC A in thick filaments. At dense bodies, beginning also with integrins, there is a similar linkage of multiple proteins, presumably to actin in thin filaments, via <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31397;class=Protein" role="_blank">DEB-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46675;class=Protein" role="_blank">ATN-1</ulink>. A few of the interactions (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE48036;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEL-26</ulink> to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30771;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIM-8</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31857;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-95</ulink> to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30771;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIM-8</ulink>; CeTalin (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29914;class=Protein" role="_blank">TLN-1</ulink>) to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46956;class=Protein" role="_blank">UIG-1</ulink>; CeTalin to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31397;class=Protein" role="_blank">DEB-1</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31397;class=Protein" role="_blank">DEB-1</ulink> to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46675;class=Protein" role="_blank">ATN-1</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46956;class=Protein" role="_blank">UIG-1</ulink> to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36722;class=Protein" role="_blank">TTN-1</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05443;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-112</ulink> to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27706;class=Protein" role="_blank">DIM-1</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46956;class=Protein" role="_blank">UIG-1</ulink> to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27706;class=Protein" role="_blank">DIM-1</ulink>) are unpublished (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson505">H. Qadota</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson427">D.G. Moerman</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson56">G.M. Benian</ulink>, unpublished data).</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>
