<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 1. The body wall muscle of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>.</title>
<para>(A) Transmission electron microscopy (EM) of a cross-section of a body wall muscle cell showing two full sarcomeres. An arrow points to a dense body and an arrowhead points to an M-line. The largest black dots are cross sections of thick filaments in the A-bands; the smallest dots are cross sections of thin filaments in the I-bands (surrounding the dense bodies). Note that all the dense bodies and the M-lines are anchored to the muscle cell membrane, which sits on top of a basement membrane, a thin hypodermis, and thick cuticle. A diagonal line indicates how the EM view is related to the drawing in (B). Scale bar, 1 &mu;m. (B) The small drawing on the right shows a cross-section through an adult worm emphasizing that the body wall muscle consists of four quadrants. Each quadrant consists of interlocking pairs of mononuclear spindle-shaped cells (23 or 24 per quadrant). In the enlargement, note that the myofilament lattice is limited to one side of the cell rather than filling the entire cross-sectional area as in a vertebrate striated muscle cell. Several planes of section are depicted, one of which emphasizes the muscle&apos;s striated organization with typical A-bands containing thick filaments organized around M-lines, and overlapping thin filaments probably attached to Z-disk-like structures called dense bodies. The sarcomere, which is defined as the repeating distance from one dense body to the next dense body is approximately 12 &mu;m in adult muscle. Note that the plane of section parallel to the page is the plane viewed when an animal crawls on agar or is placed on a slide and examined by light microscopy (note the lines to the polarized light view in (D) and immunostaining views in (E). (C) A drawing of a typical sarcomere in vertebrate striated muscle. The sarcomere, which is defined as the repeating distance from one Z-line to the next Z-line is typically 2.2-2.5 &mu;m. (D) Polarized light microscopy on a live nematode of portions of two muscle quadrants, each containing interlocking pairs of spindle shaped cells. The parallel white lines are A-bands, which alternate with parallel dark lines that are I-bands. Scale bar, 10 &mu;m. (E) Immunofluorescent localizations of several sarcomeric proteins in adult muscle, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34936;class=Protein" role="_blank">MYO-3</ulink> (myosin heavy chain A, MHC A) localized to the middle of the A-bands; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46675;class=Protein" role="_blank">ATN-1</ulink> (&alpha;-actinin) localized to dense bodies; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30426;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-89</ulink> (obscurin) localized to M-lines; and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18268;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAT-6</ulink> (actopaxin) localized to both M-lines and dense bodies. Scale bar, 10 &mu;m.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>
