<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 7. Recently reported methods to assess the locomotion and force generated by <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>.</title>
<para>(A) Measurement of maximum bending amplitude (A/L) as a worm moves backwards. (A1) Frame from a video showing a deep bend of an adult during a reversal. (A2) Binary image of the frame from (A1). (A3) Outline of the animal and the corresponding midline spline used to determine the length of the animal. (A4) Measurement of the amplitude of the bend was made by measuring the longest perpendicular length, A, from a line connecting the head to the tail into the midline spline, of coutour length L. The ratio of this value, A, to the contour length, L, was calculated (A/L). (A4) Time course of A/L values. Shortly before t = 0, the worm was tapped gently on the head to induce backwards movement. The grey region indicates the time the animal is in a reversal. Reproduced from <link linkend="bib173">Nahabedian et al. (2012)</link><!--:PMID 22126736--> with permission. (B) The use of an atomic force microscope (AFM) to measure force generated by a single nematode. (B1) Schematic of how the experiment is setup. (B2) Representative force curves generated by four <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> strains. Animals were exposed to a deforming force (push), and their force-generating activities were measured (worm mechanical activity) until the retraction of the cantilever (pull). The inset shows the force production averages and error bars with standard deviations of 15-25 animals from each strain. Reproduced with permission from <link linkend="bib230">Varkuti et al. 2012</link><!--:PMID 22343723-->. (C) Measurement of the force generated by single nematodes by measuring deflection of flexible micropillars. (C1) Drawing of an animal as it deflects an array of micropillars made from polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS). (C2) Experimental setup comprising the PDMS device on a microscope stage with a camera connected to a computer for recording worm videos. (C3) Schematic of the deflected pillar for <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> force measurement model. Reproduced with permission from <link linkend="bib101">Johari et al. (2013)</link><!--:PMID 23511608-->. (D) Use of optogenetics to measure the kinetics of muscle contraction and relaxation. (D1) Experimental setup that combines microfluidics, optogenetics and image processing. (D2) The microfluidic device has 16 parallel microchannels for simultaneous illumination and analysis of multiple animals trapped by pneumatically-controlled microvalves (red). (D3) Microscopic and segmented images of a wild-type worm trapped in a microchannel with (bottom) and without (top) the illumination of blue light. (D4) Temporal change in the body size of wild type animals that was calculated from the segmented images and normalized by average value in the first 5 seconds (s). The light was on for 15 s beginning at the 5 s time point. Data represent mean +/- standard error of the mean, n = 88. Reproduced with permission from <link linkend="bib100">Hwang et al. (2016)</link><!--:PMID 26822332-->.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>
