<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 2. An automated system for the correlation of electrical potentials and muscle movement in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> pharynx</title>
<para>Intracellular recordings from the terminal bulb were made in the manner described. The muscle was simultaneously imaged using a black and white CCD. The CCD supplied a standard PAL, interlaced video signal from which the vertical sync was extracted using a simple circuit developed in-house. The extraction circuit was placed in-line between the video camera and a PC-based frame grabber. It consisted of an LM1881 chip, used to read vertical sync data and pass it to a monostable oscillator (a 555 chip) set to generate one TTL pulse (Tag) for every two fields in the video feed. In an interlaced video signal, two fields corresponds to one full frame of video. Therefore, every frame in the video sequence had an associated tag which was then passed to the Digidata acquisition system to be recorded simultaneously with the electrophysiological events. A single command switch simultaneously controlled the video feed to the frame grabber and also the output of the tag signal to ensure that the first and last recorded video frames corresponded to the first and final tags in the sequence sent to the data acquisition system. Each video frame was automatically analysed using a simple image/signal correlation algorithm. The degree of muscle movement between video frames was calculated and matched back to the timing tags in the electrophysiological recordings. Briefly, a region of interest ROI was defined manually and then signal intensity for each pixel in the ROI was automatically calculated. The mean square difference (MSD) of ROIs in adjacent frames was calculated and used as a measure of muscle movement. As the timing tags were based on the vertical sync signal of the PAL video feed MSD calculations were 40 ms apart. The figure shows output from the full recording setup. A. Each frame of the video (iii) signal can be directly associated with a TTL timing tag (ii) recorded simultaneously with the electrophysiological recording of membrane potential (i). The lumen of the terminal bulb can be seen to gradually open and close in each successive frame during the action potential. One action potential corresponds to one motor cycle in the terminal bulb. B. In this recording each full action potential (i) is reflected in the MSD trace (ii). The mean latency of peak muscle contraction to peak action potential amplitude in this experiment was approximately 150 ms primarily reflecting the latency associated with excitation-contraction coupling in the pharyngeal muscle. Only six action potentials are shown in the trace, which spans 4.5 seconds. However, the number of action potentials that can be recorded with corresponding video and then processed, is limited only by the hard disk capacity and processing power of the PC used.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>