<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 5. Asymmetric cell division regulated by the Wnt/&beta;-catenin asymmetry pathway.</title>
<para>Asymmetric <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> division in the 4-cell embryo. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MOM-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">MOM-2</ulink> (Wnt) polarizes the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> cell, which divides into the anterior <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink> blastomere, a mesoderm precursor, and the posterior E blastomere, which produces the endoderm (a). DIC images of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> and its granddaughters (daughters of the E blastomere, which express <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=end-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">end-3</ulink></emphasis>::gfp [26, 55]), are shown in (b). (B) SGP (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4</ulink>) and T cell divisions during post-embryonic development. (a) Positions of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4</ulink> and T cells in the L1 larva. The position of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LIN-44;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-44</ulink> (Wnt)-expressing cells is indicated in red. (b) Asymmetric <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4</ulink> and T cell divisions in wild-type animals. The distal daughters of the SGPs generate DTCs, which guide elongation of the gonad, whereas the proximal daughters produce the anchor cell (AC), which induces formation of the vulva. The anterior daughter of the T cell produces hypodermal cells, and the posterior daughter generates neural cells. (c) Symmetric divisions in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=wrm-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">wrm-1</ulink></emphasis> (&beta;-catenin) mutants. The gonad fails to elongate because of the loss of DTCs (the Sys phenotype). The posterior T cell daughters adopt a hypodermal fate instead of the neuronal fate (the Psa phenotype). Anterior is toward the left, and ventral is toward the bottom. Reprinted with permission from (<link linkend="bib78">Mizumoto and Sawa, 2007</link><!--PMID 17919911-->).</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>