<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Movie 1. An animated model of asymmetric cell division (see html version of this chapter to view animation).</title>
<para>Wnts binds to Fz on the posterior side of cells and induce the accumulation of Fz and DSHs on the posterior cortex. Probably in response to the localization of DSHs, the WRM-1-LIT-1 complex localizes to the anterior cortex and recruits <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=APR-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">APR-1</ulink>. At telophase of the division, the cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=APR-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">APR-1</ulink> stabilizes the astral microtubules to create asymmetry in their numbers. The WRM-1-LIT-1 complex can be imported into both daughter nuclei, but its nuclear export is accelerated from the anterior nucleus by the astral microtubules, possibly through its kinesin-dependent transport along the microtubules toward the cell cortex. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SYS-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYS-1</ulink> is destabilized in the anterior daughter cell and accumulates in the posterior nucleus. In the posterior nucleus, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=POP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> binds either to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SYS-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYS-1</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WRM-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">WRM-1</ulink>. When it binds to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WRM-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">WRM-1</ulink>, it is phosphorylated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LIT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIT-1</ulink>, which induces its release from the WRM-1-LIT-1 complex and export out of the nucleus through the function of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PAR-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-5</ulink> (not shown in the movie), which binds to phosphorylated <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=POP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink>. POP-1 that binds to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SYS-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYS-1</ulink> cannot bind to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WRM-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">WRM-1</ulink> and stays in the nucleus.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>