<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY karyotype_refs SYSTEM 'karyotyperefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="Karyotype_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <!-- PDF stylesheet changes 
        <xsl:attribute-set name="normal.para.spacing">
              <xsl:attribute name="space-before.optimum">0.8em</xsl:attribute>
              <xsl:attribute name="space-before.minimum">0.8em</xsl:attribute>
              <xsl:attribute name="space-before.maximum">1em</xsl:attribute>
              <xsl:attribute name="text-indent">24pt</xsl:attribute> 
      </xsl:attribute-set> -->
		<title>Karyotype, ploidy, and gene dosage<footnote><para>Edited by Philip Anderson. Last revised July 18, 2005. Published June 25, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Hodgkin, J., Karyotype, ploidy and gene dosage (June 25, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.3.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 Jonathan Hodgkin. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
</footnote></title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 4/13/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory> 
-->
		<author>
			<firstname>Jonathan</firstname>
			<surname>Hodgkin<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:jah@bioch.ox.ac.uk">jah@bioch.ox.ac.uk</ulink></para></footnote></remark></surname>
			<affiliation>
				<address>Genetics Unit, Department of Biochemistry, University of Oxford, Oxford OX1 3QU, UK</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<abstract>
		<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">The normal karyotype of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Caenorhabditis
            elegans,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">with its five pairs of autosomes and single pair of X chromosomes,
            is described. General features of chromosomes and global differences between different
            chromosomal regions are discussed. Abnormal karyotypes, including duplications,
            deficiencies, inversions, translocations and chromosome fusions are reviewed. The
            effects of varying ploidy and of varying gene dosage are summarized. Dosage-sensitive
            genes seem to be rare in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">and the
            organism is able to tolerate substantial levels of aneuploidy. However, autosomal
            hemizygosity for more than about 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of the
            total genome may be incompatible with viability.</emphasis></para>
	</abstract>
	<sect1>
		<title>Normal karyotype</title>
		<para>In the earliest genetic investigations of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <link linkend="bib25">Nigon (1949a)</link> showed that hermaphrodites and males both had five pairs of autosomes, but differed in the presence of two X chromosomes in hermaphrodites (<emphasis>2A;2X</emphasis>) as opposed to one X chromosome in males (<emphasis>2A;1X</emphasis>). Cytologically, all chromosomes appear as short rods at mitosis or meiosis, with no obvious substructure.</para>
		<para>The six chromosomes are roughly equal in size, both in terms of DNA content [ranging from 12.8 Mb (Linkage Group III, abbreviated LGIII) to 20.8 Mb (LGV)] and in terms of recombinational length, at about 50 centimorgans each. The 50 cM genetic map length reflects the fact that each chromosome usually experiences one and only one crossover at meiosis (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_meiosis/meiosis.html" role="_blank">Meiosis</ulink>).</para>
		<para>The mitochondrial genome is a small circular molecule of 13.8 kb, and is discussed at greater length elsewhere (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_mitogenetics/mitogenetics.html" role="_blank">Mitochondrial genetics</ulink>).</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Overview of chromosome organization</title>
		<para>Each of the five linkage groups corresponding to the five autosomes has a discernible
            organization, with a central region or cluster, containing a higher density of genes,
            flanked by arms with fewer genes. These clusters were apparent in the first genetic map
            of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, worked out by Brenner (<link linkend="bib5">Brenner,1974</link><!-- PMID 4366476 -->).
            With the availability of genomic information, it became clear that part of the
            clustering results from long-range variation in recombination rate, with a metric (ratio
            of physical distance to genetic distance) of 100 - 500 kb/cM on the arms, as compared to
            1500 kb/cM in the cluster regions (<link linkend="bib4">Barnes et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 8536965 -->). Various general
            sequence features also distinguish the arm regions from the clusters: the arm regions
            have, overall, a slightly lower gene density (5.12 kb per gene as compared to 4.56 kb
            per gene in the clusters) and a different distribution of repeat sequences (<link linkend="bib6"><emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> Sequencing Consortium, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9851916 -->). Initial annotations also
            indicated that the cluster regions contain relatively more conserved and essential genes
            than do the arms (<link linkend="bib6"><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Sequencing Consortium, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9851916 -->; <link linkend="bib15">Hutter et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10669422 -->). Large-scale functional analyses of the
            genome by RNAi have confirmed and extended these regional distinctions (<link linkend="bib17">Kamath et al. 2003</link><!-- PMID 12529635 -->; <link linkend="bib21">Miller et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15268860 -->).</para>
		<para>The X chromosome exhibits much less dramatic variation in recombination across its
            length, so that there is no obvious gene cluster in the X linkage map, and it also has a
            significantly lower gene density (6.54 kb per gene) (<link linkend="bib6"><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Sequencing Consortium, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9851916 -->). The X chromosome is also unusual from a
            functional point of view, in that essential genes are significantly under-represented on
            this chromosome as compared to the autosomes (<link linkend="bib28">Piano et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 11137018 -->; <link linkend="bib29">Piano et al. 2002</link><!-- PMID 12445391 -->; <link linkend="bib30">Reinke et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 11030340 -->; <link linkend="bib18">Kelly et al. 2002</link><!-- PMID 11807039 -->).</para>
		<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> chromosomes, like those of nematodes in general, do not
            have a single centromere. At mitosis, spindle microtubules attach at multiple points
            along the chromosome (<link linkend="bib2">Albertson and Thomson, 1982</link><!-- PMID7172865 -->). It is not clear
            whether there are preferred points on the chromosomes for spindle attachment; if so,
            these chromosomes should be regarded as polycentric rather than holocentric.
            Heterologous DNA, introduced as a transgenic array, seems to be handled fairly
            adequately by the mitotic machinery (<link linkend="bib34">Stinchcomb et al., 1985</link><!-- PMID 3837845 -->), which suggests that there are no special sequence requirements for spindle attachment (see
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_celldivision/celldivision.html" role="_blank">Cell division</ulink>).</para>
		<para>At meiosis, there is a necessary requirement for a single attachment site on each
            chromosome to allow resolution and segregation of recombined chromatids. It appears that
            either end of each chromosome can be used for this purpose (<link linkend="bib3">Albertson and Thomson, 1993</link><!-- PMID 8143084 -->). With respect to the initial pairing of chromosomes at meiosis, the ends do differ: there appears to be a preferred pairing site close to one end of each chromosome (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_meiosis/meiosis.html" role="_blank">Meiosis</ulink>; right end of LGI and LGV; left end of LGII, LGIII, LGIV, LGX).</para>
		<para>The absence of a defined centromere means that the genetic maps for each chromosome
            were plotted around arbitrarily chosen zero points, in the approximate middle of each
            chromosome. Genes to the left of this point were given negative coordinates, and are
            drawn on the upper arm in vertical display; genes to the right were given positive
            coordinates, and are drawn on the lower arm in vertical display. With the advent of
            complete sequence information, it has become possible to correlate these genetic map
            coordinates with absolute sequence coordinates.</para>
		<para>The telomeres of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> conform to the usual eukaryotic
            pattern of a long series of hexanucleotide repeats, with a repeat sequence TTAGGC
            similar to the vertebrate repeat TTAGGG (<link linkend="bib36">Wicky et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8799140 -->). In contrast to some organisms, however, there are no obviously specialized sub-telomeric regions.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Abnormal karyotype</title>
		<para> Many alterations to the normal karyotype have been generated and examined. In
            addition to changes in whole chromosome number, discussed in the following section, a
            variety of sub-chromosomal alterations are possible, including duplications,
            deficiencies, inversions, and translocations.</para>
		<para>A special class of translocations is those involving the fusion of whole chromosomes.
            The first of these to be reported was <emphasis>mnT12</emphasis>, a fusion between the left end of LGIV and the right end of the X chromosome (<link linkend="bib33">Sigurdson et al., 1984</link><!-- PMID 6500256 -->). A stable and fairly healthy hermaphrodite line having only five pairs of chromosomes could be generated using <emphasis>mnT12</emphasis>. Males of constitution <emphasis>IV/mnT12/0</emphasis> are fertile, and can be regarded as having a neo-X
            (mnT12) neo-Y (LGIV) constitution.</para>
		<para>Similar chromosomal fusions can now be readily generated by growing mutants with
            telomere maintenance defects (<link linkend="bib1">Ahmed and Hodgkin, 2000</link><!-- PMID 10646593 -->). After many
            generations, these mutants experience telomere erosion, which leads to promiscuous
            chromosome fusion. The resulting fusion chromosomes are propagated reasonably stably,
            because the holocentric nature of nematode chromosomes is permissive for such
            structures. A variety of different fusions have been generated so far, and it is not
            clear if there is any limit to the possible combinations that can be generated, or to
            the associated variant karyotypes. A fusion of three chromosomes has been used to
            examine control of crossover distribution (<link linkend="bib9">Hillers and Villeneuve, 2003</link><!-- PMID 13678597 -->).</para>
		<para>An attached-X chromosome (two X chromosomes fused at their left ends, symbolized <emphasis>X^X</emphasis>)
            has also been obtained in a different kind of experiment; this can be propagated but
            tends to break down, reverting to a normal XX constitution (<link linkend="bib13">Hodgkin and Albertson, 1995</link><!-- PMID 8647390 -->). In comparison, attached X (and attached autosome) chromosomes that have
            been generated for <emphasis>Drosophila melanogaster</emphasis> are relatively stable.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Tetraploids, triploids and haploids</title>
		<para>Nigon was also able to establish and examine tetraploid lines of the species, although
            these were subsequently lost (<link linkend="bib26">Nigon 1949b</link>, <link linkend="bib23">1951a</link>, <link linkend="bib24">1951b</link>). He found two types of
            tetraploid hermaphrodite, both larger in size than normal diploids; the two types
            differed in progeny production, one producing <symbol
					role="symbolfont">&#x003C;</symbol>1<symbol
					role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> males and the other more than 40<symbol
					role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> males. He concluded that these were of
            constitution 4A;4X and 4A;3X respectively, and that the males were of karyotype 4A;2X.
            Madl and Herman confirmed and extended these conclusions (<link linkend="bib19">Madl and Herman, 1979</link><!-- PMID 295035 -->). They reported that 4A;4X hermaphrodites were of lower fertility than diploids
            (average tetraploid brood 84 eggs as compared to about 300 for diploids). Tetraploid egg
            viability was lower, with 87<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of eggs
            hatching compared to <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003E;</symbol>99<symbol
					role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> for diploids.</para>
		<para>Triploids were also generated and examined by these authors, by mating diploid males
            and tetraploid hermaphrodites and vice versa. 3A;3X animals were found to be
            hermaphrodite and 3A;2X animals were male. The 3A;3X hermaphrodites exhibited high
            levels of embryonic inviability in their broods, with only 15<symbol
					role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of eggs hatching, which presumably results from
            the production of many aneuploid progeny.</para>
		<para>The implications of these observations on the effect of X chromosome dosage and
            autosomal dosage on sexual phenotype are discussed more extensively in the chapters on
            Sex determination.</para>
		<para>Haploids of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, generated by extrusion of the maternal
            pronucleus after fertilization, are unable to complete embryogenesis although they
            produce several hundred cells. (<link linkend="bib31">Schierenberg and Wood, 1985</link><!-- PMID 3972159 -->). It was
            suggested that a female pronucleus might be necessary for successful embryogenesis,
            despite the fact that no imprinting appears to occur in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>,
            as discussed below. Chromosomal balance should be identical between a normal diploid
            (<emphasis>2A;2X</emphasis>) and a haploid (<emphasis>1A;1X</emphasis>). Another
            possible explanation for haploid inviability is that excess dosage compensation occurs,
            resulting in insufficient X chromosome expression and therefore lethality. A third
            possibility is that the nuclear volume of a haploid <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> cell
            is simply too small to sustain normal gene regulation and expression. Nuclear volume
            seems to be largely determined by DNA content, and the 50 megabase DNA content of a
            haploid <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> nucleus would be smaller than any known animal genome.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Aneuploids</title>
		<para>In principle, there are six possible trisomies and six possible monosomies for the
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> diploid genome, of which one, monosomy X or XO,
            occurs naturally in the form of the male sex. XO individuals are entirely viable as a
            consequence of the X chromosome dosage compensation system (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_dosagecomp/dosagecomp.html" role="_blank">X-chromosome dosage compensation</ulink>), which equalizes gene expression between the XX sex (normally hermaphrodite)
            and the XO sex (normally male). Trisomy X is also viable but abnormal:
            <emphasis>2A;3X</emphasis> individuals, otherwise known as triplo-X animals, are
            hermaphrodites with a dumpy body morphology, slower growth rate and lower fertility than
            normal <emphasis>2A;2X</emphasis> hermaphrodites (<link linkend="bib14">Hodgkin et al., 1979</link>). Since they are
            abnormal, it seems that the dosage compensation mechanism is not proportionately more
            active in a triplo-X animal than in a diplo-X animal. Triplo-X animals with partial
            defects in dosage compensation, such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dpy-21" role="_blank">dpy-21</ulink></emphasis> mutants (which are
            viable but dumpy as diplo-X individuals) are inviable (<link linkend="bib10">Hodgkin, 1983</link>). Individuals of
            karyotype <emphasis>2A;4X</emphasis> appear to be inviable, as inferred from the
            proportion of dead eggs produced in the progeny of <emphasis>2A;3X</emphasis>
            hermaphrodites. In all these cases, the inviabilities presumably result from cumulative
            over-expression of sex-linked genes. It is unlikely that any single gene on the X
            chromosome contributes a major part of the lethality, because screens for suppressors of
            the lethality due to defective dosage compensation have not yielded any candidates.
            Reduction in X chromosome dose has also been examined: individuals of karyotype
            <emphasis>3A;1X</emphasis> are viable males, but they are noticeably abnormal and
            unhealthy, suggesting that any further reduction would be lethal (<link linkend="bib12">Hodgkin, 1987</link><!-- PMID 3503722 -->).</para>
		<para>Among autosomal aneuploids, one trisomy (for LGIV) is known to be viable. Trisomy IV
            was generated by means of the IV-X fusion chromosome, <emphasis>mnT12</emphasis>, and
            also by using a meiotic mutant, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=him-6" role="_blank">him-6</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib33">Sigurdson et al., 1984</link><!-- PMID 6500256 -->). The triplo-IV animals have surprisingly normal appearance and viability,
            although they produce 50<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> fewer progeny
            than normal hermaphrodites. The inviability of most of the other possible aneuploids was
            initially suggested by the very high level of embryonic lethality observed in some
            meiotic mutants, which have general defects in recombination and chromosome
            nondisjunction. Lethality is most probably due to extensive nondisjunction resulting in
            many nullisomic and disomic gametes and hence to aneuploid progeny. Consistent with this
            interpretation, males of such meiotic mutants sire many inviable progeny, when crossed
            with normal hermaphrodites (<link linkend="bib14">Hodgkin et al., 1979</link>).</para>
		<para>The general meiotic mutant <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=him-6" role="_blank">him-6</ulink></emphasis> was explicitly tested for the
            production of nullisomic and disomic gametes for each chromosome in turn (<link linkend="bib8">Haack and
            Hodgkin, 1991</link><!-- PMID 1896016 -->). The results showed that all of these possible abnormal
            gamete types were being generated, at roughly equal frequencies. These experiments also
            tested for gross chromosomal imprinting effects, which appear to be absent, because it
            was possible to recover normal diploids that had received a pair of autosomes only from
            the maternal parent or only from the paternal parent.</para>
		<para>The inviability of all autosomal monosomies can be inferred independently from the
            failure to recover them in any of the many screens for genetic deficiencies that have
            been carried out. Such screens have concentrated on specific regions on each chromosome,
            and as a result large partial deficiencies have been recovered for each of the five
            autosomes (these are discussed further below), but no cases of monosomy have been seen.
            The fact that large deficiencies are usually conspicuously unhealthy suggests that there
            is a limit to how much haploidy can be tolerated in the genome, and that a deficiency as
            large as a whole chromosome would be well above this limit. It follows that there is no
            general mechanism for autosomal dosage compensation.</para>
		<para>Autosomal trisomies have not been recovered from screens for duplications, although
            trisomy for LGIV might have been obtained, and the large duplication
            <emphasis>mnDp37</emphasis> appears to duplicate almost all of LGIII (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). Some of the other autosomal trisomies (for LGI, LGII and LGV) may possibly be viable, but no explicit crosses designed to generate them have yet been reported.</para>

<table id="table1" frame="all">
	<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1. Large free duplications.</emphasis> The table lists some of the larger free
            duplications that have been obtained so far, together with their approximate extent as
            inferred from genetic data, and minimum size in Mb, based on the physical distance
            between loci known to be duplicated. Exact endpoints are not known for most
            duplications. Some of the duplications may however contain internal gaps, and therefore
            be somewhat smaller than indicated.</title>
                <tgroup cols="4">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="0.5*" align="center"/>
                    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="0.5*" align="center"/>
                    <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="0.7*" align="center"/>
                    <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="0.8*" align="center"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Duplication name</entry>
                        <entry>Location</entry>
                        <entry>Approximate extent (centimorgans)</entry>
                        <entry>Minimum size (megabases)</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis>sDp2</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>I, L</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>21.4</entry> 
                        <entry>7.2</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis>sDp1</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>I, R</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>31.7</entry>
                        <entry>10.6</entry>
                        </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis>mnDp34</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>II, R</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>21.3</entry>
                        <entry>3.8</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis>sDp3</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>III, L</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>23.0</entry>
                        <entry>6.6</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis>mnDp37</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>III</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>40.3</entry>
                        <entry>11.6</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis>eDp6</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>III, R</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>15.7</entry>
                        <entry>2.8</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis>mDp4</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>IV, L</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>31.7</entry>
                        <entry>9.1</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis>yDp1</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>IV, R+V, L</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>26.0</entry>
                        <entry>7.0</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis>yDp13</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>X, L</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>15.7</entry>
                        <entry>2.4</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis>mnDp3</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>X, R</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>14.9</entry>
                        <entry>4.3</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
</table>
	</sect1>
<?newpage?>
	<sect1>
		<title>Chromosomal duplications</title>
		<para>The holocentric nature of nematode chromosomes means that chromosomal fragments can be
            propagated readily through mitosis, as long as they retain a sufficient amount of
            centric material to capture spindle microtubules. As a result, chromosomal fragments
            have been generated and preserved for many parts of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
            genome, as free duplications. Some of the larger free duplications are listed in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>. Additional duplications have also been recovered as stable translocations to other chromosomes.</para>
		<para>The limits to generation of free chromosomal duplications are not known,
            but very small free duplications have never been reported.
            Extrachromosomal transgenic arrays which behave much like free duplications can be
            generated after microinjection; these arrays appear always to carry at least 40 copies
            of the injected sequences, probably adding up to a megabase or more in total length
            (<link linkend="bib34">Stinchcomb et al., 1985</link><!-- PMID 3837845 -->). Smaller arrays and small chromosomal fragments
            may therefore not be successfully handled by the mitotic machinery.</para>
		<para>More than 80<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> the <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> genome has been duplicated by one means or another, implying that a
                50<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> increase in gene dosage for any of
            the genes concerned has no seriously deleterious effect. Two large regions, on the left
            arm of LGII and the right arm of LGV, are not represented in the set of duplications,
            probably because no serious attempts have yet been made to generate duplications for
            these regions.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Chromosomal deficiencies</title>
		<para>Numerous chromosomal deficiencies have been generated in the course of many different
            investigations, such that more than 75<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of
            the genome is now covered by at least one deficiency. These deficiencies provide
            extremely useful tools for analysis of mutations, for manipulation of gene dosage and
            for mapping. The majority of deficiencies appear to be continuous, with breakpoints that
            can be exactly defined on both genetic and molecular maps. However, it should be noted
            that some deficiencies, like some duplications, appear to have more complex structures,
            with discontinuities or rearrangements within the overall span apparently deleted.</para>
		<para>A few large segments of the genetic map are currently lacking in any deficiencies,
            notably on the right arm of LGII (17 centimorgans) and the left arm of LGIV (26
            centimorgans). These absences may simply result from a lack of any systematic screens
            for deficiencies in the relevant segments, rather than from failure to recover them.
            However, in some small regions of the genome, deficiencies appear to be difficult or
            impossible to generate, presumably because one or more haplo-insufficient loci
            (discussed below) are present in the intervals concerned. A conspicuous example is
            provided by a region on LG II, genetic map interval 0.79 to 0.81. Numerous deficiencies
            extend leftward or rightward from this interval, but none crosses it (<link linkend="bib33">Sigurdson et al., 1984</link><!-- PMID 6500256 -->). One or more genes in this gap are likely to be
            haplo-insufficient, so that a deletion would have dominant lethal effects. The only gene
            in the gap that has been studied in any detail is <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=zyg-9" role="_blank">zyg-9</ulink></emphasis>, which
            encodes a conserved spindle component, but mutations in this gene show no dominant
            effects (<link linkend="bib20">Matthews et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9606208 -->), so <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=zyg-9" role="_blank">zyg-9</ulink></emphasis> does not
            appear to be needed in more than one copy. Some other possible haplo-insufficient
            regions can be tentatively identified on other chromosomes, but their existence is hard
            to prove, and the whole genome may contain fewer than ten.</para>
		<para>The large-scale structure of chromosomes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> probably
            also contributes to the size and distribution of known deficiencies. As discussed above,
            the five autosomes all have a structure with a central cluster region, with slightly
            higher gene density, reduced recombination, and more conserved and essential genes, as
            compared to the flanking arm regions. <link linkend="table2">Table 2</link> lists some of the largest deficiencies
            that have been obtained so far, together with estimates of their genetic length in
            centimorgans and minimum physical extent in Mb. All the largest deficiencies affect
            mainly arm regions, and none removes an entire cluster or more than about 4 Mb. Most or
            all of these deficiencies exhibit significantly reduced viability and fertility, as
            heterozygotes (<emphasis>Df/+</emphasis>). These deleterious effects probably result from the cumulative effect of reducing gene dosage. Consequently, it is expected that deficiencies larger
            than those generated so far would be dominantly lethal, although all of the genes
            affected may be individually haplo-sufficient. This effect will be greater for the
            cluster regions, because of the higher density of essential and non-redundant genes. One
            can predict that any deficiency, or combination of deficiencies, that removes more than
            about 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of the total gene content of
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, will be dominantly lethal. Tests of this prediction
            by combining smaller deficiencies on different chromosomes are feasible, but have not
            yet been carried out.</para>
<?newpage?>
            <table id="table2" frame="all">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 2. Large deficiencies.</emphasis> The table lists a set of large deficiencies, two for each chromosome. Approximate genetic extents have been inferred from genetic data. Physical sizes are estimated from the distance between the last sequence-positioned genes that are known to be deleted, at either end of each deficiency. Therefore, these sizes may be underestimates. Exact endpoints are known for few deficiencies. Also, some deficiencies may be discontinuous, and therefore remove less of the genome than their predicted length suggests.</title>
<tgroup cols="4">
		<colspec colname="c1" colwidth="0.5*" align="center"/>
		<colspec colname="c2" colwidth="0.5*" align="center"/>
		<colspec colname="c3" colwidth="0.7*" align="center"/>
		<colspec colname="c4" colwidth="0.8*" align="center"/>
<thead>
	<row>
		<entry>Deficiency name</entry>
		<entry>Location</entry>
		<entry>Approximate extent (centimorgans)</entry>
		<entry>Minimum size (megabases)</entry>
	</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
	<row>
		<entry><emphasis>hDf10</emphasis></entry>
		<entry><emphasis>I, L</emphasis></entry>
		<entry>6.5</entry>
		<entry>1.8</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
		<entry><emphasis>dxDf2</emphasis></entry>
		<entry><emphasis>I, R</emphasis></entry>
		<entry>15.0</entry>
		<entry>3.1</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
		<entry><emphasis>ccDf11</emphasis></entry>
		<entry><emphasis>II, L</emphasis></entry>
		<entry>14.1</entry>
		<entry>4.6</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
		<entry><emphasis>mnDf89</emphasis></entry>
		<entry><emphasis>II, RC</emphasis></entry>
		<entry>3.7</entry>
		<entry>2.5</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
		<entry><emphasis>nDf11</emphasis></entry>
		<entry><emphasis>III, LC</emphasis></entry>
		<entry>5.1</entry>
		<entry>1.1</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
		<entry><emphasis>eDf2</emphasis></entry>
		<entry><emphasis>III, R</emphasis></entry>
		<entry>15.9</entry>
		<entry>2.9</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
		<entry><emphasis>mDf9</emphasis></entry>
		<entry><emphasis>IV, LC</emphasis></entry>
		<entry>2.6</entry>
		<entry>1.1</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
		<entry><emphasis>nDf27</emphasis></entry>
		<entry><emphasis>IV, C</emphasis></entry>
		<entry>5.3</entry>
		<entry>2.1</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
		<entry><emphasis>sDf45</emphasis></entry>
		<entry><emphasis>V, L</emphasis></entry>
		<entry>11.5</entry>
		<entry>3.7</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
		<entry><emphasis>ozDf1</emphasis></entry>
		<entry><emphasis>V, R</emphasis></entry>
		<entry>12.0</entry>
		<entry>3.0</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
		<entry><emphasis>syDf1</emphasis></entry>
		<entry><emphasis>X, L</emphasis></entry>
		<entry>4.6</entry>
		<entry>2.0</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
		<entry><emphasis>mnDf1</emphasis></entry>
		<entry><emphasis>X, R</emphasis></entry>
		<entry>8.0</entry>
		<entry>3.4</entry>
	</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Dosage sensitive genes</title>
		<para>Most genes display no obvious phenotype when their dosage is reduced by 50<symbol
					role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>, in hemizygotes, or increased by 50<symbol
					role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>, in duplication-bearing animals. In general, it
            is likely that such alterations in dosage do have a small impact on viability, which is
            cumulatively deleterious in large deficiency heterozygotes, but the reduction in
            viability is not easily perceptible at the level of a single gene. Moreover,
            considerations from metabolic control theory indicate that genes encoding enzymes in
            metabolic pathways are expected in general to be insensitive to variations in dose
            (<link linkend="bib16">Kacser and Burns, 1981</link><!-- PMID 7297851 -->).</para>
		<para>As noted above, the absence of hemizygously viable deficiencies for certain parts of
            the genome suggests that they may contain haplo-lethal genes, but no specific case of
            haplo-lethality has yet been demonstrated. A few genes do appear to be conspicuously
            haplo-insufficient, such that hemizygotes exhibit a recognizable phenotype. Most of
            these seem to be genes encoding structural proteins or regulatory molecules. An example
            of the former is the collagen gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dpy-13" role="_blank">dpy-13</ulink></emphasis> (von Mende et al., 1988<!-- PMID 2846184 -->). Examples of the latter are provided by the sex determination genes
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-2" role="_blank">tra-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib35">Trent et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 11813735 -->) and
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-3" role="_blank">fem-3</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib11">Hodgkin, 1986</link><!-- PMID 3770465 -->). The expression of both of
            these genes is partly regulated by translational control, in order to achieve proper
            development of the hermaphrodite germ line (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_sexgermline/sexgermline.html" role="_blank">Sex-determination in the germ line</ulink>) so it may be that transcription levels for these genes are necessarily limiting, in order to facilitate
            the translational modulation. The paucity of haplo-insufficient genes in <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> is also evident from a general screen for dominant mutations in this
            organism (<link linkend="bib27">Park and Horvitz, 1986</link><!-- PMID 3744028 -->), which yielded many gain-of-function
            mutations but only one candidate for a gene with a dominant null phenotype, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-108" role="_blank">unc-108</ulink></emphasis>.</para>
		<para>Haplo-insufficiency is rare when genes are considered alone and on a wildtype
            background, but it can become much more frequent on a sensitized background. Effects of
            this type are described and discussed further in the Chapters on <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_complementation/complementation.html" role="_blank">Complementation</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_geneticenhancers/geneticenhancers.html" role="_blank">Genetic enhancers</ulink>.</para>
<para>No examples of triplo-lethal genes have yet been reported in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. However, further increases in the dosage of many individual genes
            can be deleterious. Such increases are routinely achieved in the generation of multicopy
            extrachromosomal transgene arrays, which may have 50 or more copies of an individual
            gene. There has been no systematic study of copy number and corresponding expression
            levels for these arrays, and it is unlikely that these arrays express gene products as
            efficiently as the normal chromosomal copies do, but several-fold over-expression seems
            probable. Creation of multi-copy arrays is difficult or impossible for some cosmid
            transgenes, probably as a result of such over-expression lethality. A few specific cases
            have been demonstrated, where multicopy transgene arrays of a particular gene have been
            impossible to generate, but integrated single-copy transgenes have proved viable and
            functional. One example is <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rom-1" role="_blank">rom-1</ulink></emphasis>, encoding the rhomboid protease (<link linkend="bib7">Dutt et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15455032 -->); another is the collagen gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dpy-17" role="_blank">dpy-17</ulink></emphasis> (Jacopo Novelli and J. H., unpublished observations).</para>
		<para>Genes encoding proteins that are needed in stoichiometric amounts, as part of a
            multi-protein complex, might be expected to show strong dosage effects, but these genes often exhibit a specific auto-regulatory mechanism, which ensures that
            protein levels do not go too high or too low. An example is provided by some of the
            ribosomal proteins, such as RPL-12, which appears able to inhibit productive splicing of
            its own pre-mRNA, as a negative feedback control (<link linkend="bib22">Mitrovich and Anderson, 2000</link><!-- PMID 10970881 -->).</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>References</title>
        <para/>
        &karyotype_refs;
        </sect1>
</article>