<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'Cbrigmethfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'Cbrigmethfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'Cbrigmethfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'Cbrigmethfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY Cbrigmeth_Refs SYSTEM "Cbrigmethrefs.xml">
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="Cbrigmeth_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
<title><emphasis>Caenorhabditis briggsae</emphasis> methods<footnote>
			<para>Edited by Ralf J. Sommer. WormMethods editor Victor Ambros. Last revised November 6, 2006. Published December 18, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Baird, S.E. and Chamberlin, H.M. <emphasis>Caenorhabditis briggsae</emphasis> methods (December 18, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.128.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 Scott E. Baird and Helen M. Chamberlin. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
		<author>
			<firstname>Scott E.</firstname>
			<surname>Baird<remark><superscript>&#x000A7;</superscript></remark></surname>
			<affiliation>
				<address>Department of Biological Sciences, Wright State University, Dayton, OH 45435-0001 USA</address>
			</affiliation>
</author>
<author>
	<firstname>Helen M.</firstname>
	<surname>Chamberlin<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:scott.baird@wright.edu">scott.baird@wright.edu</ulink> or <ulink url="mailto:chamberlin.27@osu.edu">chamberlin.27@osu.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></surname>
<affiliation><address>Department of Molecular Genetics, The Ohio State University, Columbus, OH 43210-1292 USA</address>
</affiliation>
</author>
</articleinfo>
<?newpage?>
<sect1>
<title>The <emphasis>Caenorhabditis briggsae</emphasis> model system</title>
<para><emphasis>Caenorhabditis briggsae</emphasis> is being developed in parallel to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as a model system, primarily for the study of evolution. Like <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> is a protandrous hermaphrodite (<link linkend="bib24">Nigon and Dougherty, 1949</link>) and like <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, its genome has been sequenced (<link linkend="bib26">Stein et al., 2003</link>). From this point, these two model systems diverge. The development, behavior, and physiology of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have been characterized through tens of thousands of genetic and molecular studies. Genetic and molecular characterizations of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> are relatively few. Experimental resources in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> include a high density recombination map that is well integrated with the genome sequence. The <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> recombination map has yet to be published and attempts to integrate it with the genome sequence are in their infancy. Despite these deficiencies, <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> is attractive for several reasons. First as a parallel system, it can be used to test the generality of results obtained in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Second, it appears that the structure of the <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> world-wide population is qualitatively different from that of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and that <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> may be more amenable to studies of gene flow, genome evolution, and speciation (<link linkend="bib7">Cutter et al., 2006</link>; Baird and Hampton, unpubl. results). Finally, <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. remanei</emphasis> are sister species with <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as an outgroup, making the <emphasis>C. briggsae&#x2013;C. remanei</emphasis> species better for some aspects of comparative genomics (<link linkend="bib20">Kiontke et al., 2004</link>; <link linkend="bib6">Cho et al., 2004</link>; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_phylogrhabditids/phylorhab.html" role="_blank">The phylogenetic relationships of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and other rhabditids</ulink>).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Natural history and population biology</title>
<sect2>
<title>Natural history</title>
<para>Most <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species form phoretic and/or necromenic associations with other soil invertebrates (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_ecolCaenorhabditis/ecolCaenorhabditis.html" role="_blank">Ecology of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species</ulink>). In phoretic associations, hosts are used for transport between microenvironments. In necromenic associations, nematodes resume development and reproduce in the bacterial bloom that occurs following the host death. A variety of snails have been identified as hosts for <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> dauer larvae (S. Baird, unpubl. obs.). <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> dauers also have been obtained from soil and compost (<link linkend="bib7">Cutter et al., 2006</link>). As dauers can persist for several months without feeding, generation times in wild populations are not known and may vary widely between and within populations.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Biogeography and population biology</title>
<para><emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> is a cosmopolitan species, having been obtained from collections in Asia, North America, and Europe (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1A</link>; <link linkend="bib7">Cutter et al., 2006</link>). Phylogentic reconstructions of strains derived from these collections strongly support the division of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> into distinct tropical and temperate clades (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1B</link>; <link linkend="bib11">Graustein et al., 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib7">Cutter et al., 2006</link>; Baird and Hampton, unpubl. results). This clade structure should be considered when designing experiments, as tropical and temperate strains exhibit morphological and developmental differences. Consequently, different experimental results sometimes are obtained for tropical and temparate strains (<link linkend="bib1">Baird, 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib2">2002</link>; <link linkend="bib9">Dellatre and F&#x000E9;lix, 2001</link>). Few collections have been made in the Southern hemisphere. However, <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> strains have been obtained from Kenya and South Africa (E. Dolgin, personal communication).</para>
<para>The division of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> into tropical and temperate clades probably results from a recent expansion of the <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> range into temperate latitudes. Nucleotide diversity within the temperate clade is very low and the coalescence time for this clade has been estimated to be 700 years (<link linkend="bib7">Cutter et al., 2006</link>). This estimate was based on an effective population size (N<subscript>e</subscript>) for the temaperate clade of 1,000 and a 60 day generation time (assuming that in wild populations, <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> individuals spend most of their time as dauers).</para>
		<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="6.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Genetics</title>
<sect2>
<title>Genetic nomenclature</title>
<para>Nomenclatural rules for <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>, which currently are in flux, reflect the conflicting goals of providing unique durable gene names for mutationally identified genes while at the same time allowing for the identification of orthologs to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes. The history of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> nomenclature rules and detailed nomenclatural suggestions can be found at the <ulink url="http://wormlab.caltech.edu/briggsae/nomenclature/message28-20031016.html" role="_blank"><emphasis>Caenorhabditis briggsae</emphasis> Research Page</ulink>. One feature of this system is that <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> gene names may change as orthology is determined. For example, the <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> <emphasis>mip-1</emphasis> gene was identified based on mutations that cause mutant animals to twitch uncontrollably. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, this phenotype results commonly from mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-22;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink></emphasis>. Hence, <emphasis>mip-1</emphasis> may be the <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> ortholog of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-22;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink></emphasis>. If this orthology is confirmed, <emphasis>mip-1</emphasis> will be renamed <emphasis>Cb-unc-22</emphasis>. Confusion caused by changes in <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> gene names is expected to be minimal as gene name histories will be archived in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/" role="_blank">WormBase</ulink>.</para>
<para>Alleles, strains, polymorphisms, rearrangements, transgenes, and other variants will be given unique identifiers following <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> nomenclatural conventions (<link linkend="bib14">Horvitz et al., 1979</link>; <ulink url="http://biosci.umn.edu/CGC/Nomenclature/nomenguid.htm" role="_blank">CGC</ulink>). These identifiers will include a lab strain or allele designation followed by a unique strain or allele number for that lab. For example, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bd101;class=Variation" role="_blank">bd101</ulink></emphasis> is a <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> mutation that is present in several strains including <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PB101;class=Strain" role="_blank">PB101</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PB107;class=Strain" role="_blank">PB107</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PB108;class=Strain" role="_blank">PB108</ulink>. These names will be unique and durable.</para>
<?newpage?>
<para>Finally, it should be noted that a different convention is used by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/" role="_blank">WormBase</ulink> to name predicted <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> genes. In this convention, each gene prediction gets a CBG (<emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> gene) prefix followed by a unique five digit identifier, e.g., CBG00123. Gene predictions in WormBase are continually refined as algorithms are improved. Therefore, predicted CBG gene names also may change over time.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Single nucleotide polymorphisms</title>
<para>The genome sequence of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> is that of the tropical strain, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AF16;class=Strain" role="_blank">AF16</ulink> (<link linkend="bib26">Stein et al., 2003</link>). To facilitate genetic studies, 13,000 randomly selected clones derived from a temperate strain, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HK104;class=Strain" role="_blank">HK104</ulink>, also have been sequenced. From these sequences over 26,000 single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) have been identified giving a SNP density of greater than 0.2% (Hillier, Miller, Chinwalla, Fulton, Kolboldt, and Waterston, personal communication).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Recombination maps</title>
<para>Two recombination maps have been constructed for <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>. One is a <ulink url="http://snp.wustl.edu/snp-research/c-briggsae/" role="_blank">SNP-based map</ulink> that was constructed based on the segregation of SNP alleles in recombinant inbred lines (RIL) (Hillier, Miller, Chinwalla, Fulton, Kolboldt, and Waterston, personal communication). These RIL were derived from a cross between <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> strains <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AF16;class=Strain" role="_blank">AF16</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HK104;class=Strain" role="_blank">HK104</ulink> (<link linkend="bib3">Baird et al., 2005</link>). Each RIL was initiated with a single L4 F2 hermaphrodite and inbred through a single hermaphrodite per generation to F11. The current draft SNP map (v3.3) includes segregation data for 290 SNPs in 93 RIL. RIL genotypes for each SNP were determined using a fluorescent polarization-terminal dye incorporation (FP-TDI) assay (<link linkend="bib15">Hsu et al., 2001</link>). This assay does not require any post-reaction product purification and has been adapted for the high-throughput genotyping of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> RIL. The other is a <ulink url="http://wormlab.caltech.edu/briggsae/" role="_blank">mutation-based map</ulink> that was constructed based on the segregation of visible phenotypes in F2 progeny (B. Gupta, P. Sternberg, and D. Baillie, personal communication). Both maps identified six linkage groups. Integration of the SNP- and mutation-based maps is in progress (R. Miller and B. Gupta, personal communication). Nearly all <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> induced mutations were derived from strain <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AF16;class=Strain" role="_blank">AF16</ulink>. Therefore, map integration will be accomplished by mapping mutant alleles relative to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HK104;class=Strain" role="_blank">HK104</ulink> SNPs. This will entail the genotyping of individual mutant F2s for multiple SNPs. To facilitate this, template DNA from F2 single-worm lysates will be amplified by whole genome amplification (<link linkend="bib8">Dean et al., 2001</link>). Preliminary experiments have demonstrated the whole genome amplification provides template sufficient for several thousand genotyping reactions (S. Baird, unpubl results; B. Gupta and R. Miller, personal communication).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Bulk segregant analysis</title>
<para>In <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>, as in other organisms, most SNPs do not affect restriction endonuclease recognition sites. Therefore it is difficult and/or expensive to distinguish between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AF16;class=Strain" role="_blank">AF16</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HK104;class=Strain" role="_blank">HK104</ulink> SNP alleles with using commonly available lab equipment. One way around this, at least for linkage determination, is bulk segregant analysis. In <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> a bulk segregant assay is initiated by crossing an AF16-derived mutant strain to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HK104;class=Strain" role="_blank">HK104</ulink>. Pools of 10&#x2013;25 mutant F2 progeny then are collected and lysed following a scaled-up (25 &#x003BC;l) <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_SNPsintrotwopointmap/SNPsintrotwopointmap.html" role="_blank">single-worm protocol</ulink>. Primers for these reactions are designed to amplify short (200&#x02013;500 bp) products that contain a polymorphic nucleotide at least 50 nucleotides from either end. Amplification products are sequenced and polymorphisms are detected as ambiguities in the sequence traces. For unlinked loci, both alleles, i.e. an ambiguity, will be apparent in the sequence trace. For linked loci, only the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AF16;class=Strain" role="_blank">AF16</ulink> allele will be present. In control reactions, a strong allelic bias was observed from lysates made from a 9:1 ratio of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HK104;class=Strain" role="_blank">HK104</ulink> to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AF16;class=Strain" role="_blank">AF16</ulink> hermaphrodites (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). In F2 progeny, a 9:1 ratio would be expected for loci located 10 mu from the selected mutation. Thus, two-fold redundant coverage of the <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> genome can be achieved with as few as four SNPs per chromosome. This approach has been used successfully to identify loci involved in fitness loss in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AF16;class=Strain" role="_blank">AF16</ulink>::HK104 F2 hybrids (Hampton and Baird, unpubl. results).</para>
		<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Reverse genetic methods</title>
<sect2>
<title>Identification of <emphasis>C. elegans&#x2013;C. briggsae</emphasis> orthologs</title>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> share a similar number of protein-coding genes (just under 20,000), with an estimate of 12,200 orthologous genes. Another 6,500 genes in <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> have one or more <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog, leaving about 800 genes as <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>-specific (<link linkend="bib26">Stein et al., 2003</link>). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>&#x2013;<emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> orthologs are annotated in Wormbase (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/" role="_blank">http://www.wormbase.org/</ulink>) according to the criteria of <link linkend="bib26">Stein et al. (2003)</link>. Each ortholog was identified either as the reciprocal top BLASTP match when queried against the genome of the other species, or was identified as a homolog (but not the reciprocal best match) with conserved synteny (gene order) with respect to other genes on the chromosome.</para>
<para>Although ortholog predictions by Stein et al. are fairly robust, false positives can result if best matches are not orthologous due to gene loss or divergence, or gene amplification events. Reciprocally, false negatives can result in the cases of rapid gene evolution or from errors in genome annotation. Consequently, researchers interested in a specific gene or set of genes will want to perform additional analysis to confirm orthology. Commonly, this can be achieved by phylogenetic reconstruction using all sequences of homologs available from different <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species, as well as an outgroup species. Homologs can be identified using BLAST to identify conserved domains as well as other genes (or translated gene products) that contain the domains. The relationship among the genes/proteins can be determined using a neighbor joining program with confidence assessed by bootstrapping methods (e.g., PHYLIP). True orthologs should exhibit fewer sequence differences and thus join, or cluster, with each other (e.g., <link linkend="bib17">Jovelin and Phillips, 2005</link>; <link linkend="bib23">Nayak et al., 2005</link>; <link linkend="bib29">Thomas, 2006</link>).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Transgenesis and heterologous gene expression</title>
<para>Introduction of transgenes into <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> allows for mutant rescue experiments, reporter transgene assays, and heterologous gene expression, both for ectopic expression studies, and inter-specific functional assays (e.g., <link linkend="bib28">Streit et al., 1999</link>; <link linkend="bib30">Wang and Chamberlin, 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib31">Wang and Chamberlin, 2004</link>). High copy number extrachromosomal transgenes can be introduced into <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> by microinjection of DNA into the hermaphrodite germline (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transformationmicroinjection/transformationmicroinjection.html" role="_blank">Transformation and microinjection</ulink>) following protocols developed for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib22">Mello et al., 1991</link>). Transformation markers from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> that are effective in <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> include <emphasis>ce-rol-6(d)</emphasis>, <emphasis>ce-myo-2::gfp</emphasis>, <emphasis>ce-myo-3::gfp</emphasis>, <emphasis>ce-hsp-16-48::gfp</emphasis>, and <emphasis>ce-sur-5::gfp</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib28">Streit et al., 1999</link>; <link linkend="bib30">Wang and Chamberlin, 2002</link>) M.-A. Felix, personal communication). Extrachromosomal arrays can be integrated (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transformationmicroinjection/transformationmicroinjection.html" role="_blank">Transformation and microinjection</ulink>) into the chromosome using 3000&#x2013;4000 rad <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B3;</symbol>-irradiation and following <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> protocols (<link linkend="bib16">Inoue et al., 2002</link>).</para>
<para><emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> exhibits differences from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> with respect to the efficacy of transgene formation, and they exhibit greater transgene silencing and mosaicism. In general, similar DNA mixtures and injection conditions result in 3-10 fold fewer stable transgenes in <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> than in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, with reduced efficiency at both F1 and F2 generations (M.-A. Felix, personal communication). Although some of these differences may reflect the use of heterologous [usually <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib21">Li et al., 2006</link>)] DNA in transformation experiments, these results suggest that producing transgenes in <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> will benefit from further optimization of protocols.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>RNA-mediated interference</title>
<para>As in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, double stranded RNA-mediated gene interference (RNAi; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_introreversegenetics/introreversegenetics.html" role="_blank">Reverse genetics</ulink>) can provide a relatively easy method to assess the function of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> genes <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> (e.g., <link linkend="bib12">Haag et al., 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib25">Rudel and Kimble, 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib27">Stothard et al., 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib28">Streit et al., 1999</link>). For this method, introduction of double-stranded RNA corresponding to a gene of interest results in the specific degradation of the corresponding mRNA, allowing phenotypic analysis of animals depleted for the gene. However, in contrast to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, an effective RNAi response is generally obtained in <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> only when double stranded RNA is introduced directly into animals, such as by microinjection. <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> is resistant to RNAi introduced by soaking or bacterial feeding methods (M. K. Montgomery, personal communication; C. Hunter, personal communication). This resistance reflects a difference between <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> animals in availability of RNAi uptake and spreading mechanisms that allow RNAi transport into the animal and across epithelial boundaries. Consequently, RNAi can frequently be less effective in <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> than <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, and negative results or differences in RNAi phenotypes between the species must be interpreted with caution. Recent work has shown that the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sid-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">sid-2</ulink></emphasis> gene required for environmental uptake of RNA by <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is altered and not functional in <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>. Consequently, introduction of <emphasis>ce-sid-2</emphasis> as part of a transgene enhances RNAi uptake in <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>, and confers sensitivity to RNAi by feeding onto this species (W. M. Winston, M. Sutherlin, A. J. Wright, E. Feinberg, and C. Hunter, unpublished results). We anticipate that these transgenic animals or other genetically modified or mutant <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> strains will allow for enhanced RNAi response and a greater range of methods to introduce RNAi.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Targeted deletion screens</title>
<para>Although functional studies using RNAi are efficient, the gold standard in genetic analysis is chromosomal mutations. Strategies developed to isolate deletion alleles (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_introreversegenetics/introreversegenetics.htm" role="_Blank">Reverse genetics</ulink>) in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes have been applied effectively to <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib10">Edgley et al., 2002</link>), although the frequency of allele recovery may be somewhat lower than in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. <link linkend="bib13">Hill et al. (2006)</link> report a single deletion allele each of <emphasis>Cb-fem-2</emphasis> and <emphasis>Cb-fem-3</emphasis> recovered from a library of 1.1 million EMS mutagenized gametes.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title><emphasis>Mos</emphasis> mutagenesis</title>
<para>The Drosophila transposon <emphasis>Mos1</emphasis> has been shown to mobilize and cause heritable mutations in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, providing a method for rapid tagging and recovery of mutant genes (<link linkend="bib32">Williams et al., 2005</link>). Following a modified protocol (below), M.-A. Felix and her group have shown that <emphasis>Mos1</emphasis> mutagenesis can be applied to <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> as well. Although the SNP-based polymorphism map (v3.3) combined with genomic sequence will provide the tools for positional cloning of genes in <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>, transposon tagging may allow a more efficient strategy for gene cloning in some cases.</para>
<para>In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <emphasis>Mos1</emphasis> mutagenesis is achieved using two transgenes: an extrachromosomal array that expresses the transposase under control of a heat-shock promoter, and a second transgene that includes the transposon (<link linkend="bib4">Bessereau et al., 2001</link>). Expression of the transposase is induced in parental (P0) hermaphrodites, and then offspring are screened in the F1 or F2 for mutant phenotypes. Following outcross of the mutant allele, the tagged gene can be isolated using PCR. A detailed protocol for <emphasis>Mos1</emphasis> mutagenesis is available (<link linkend="bib5">Bessereau et al., 2006</link>).</para>
<para>In <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>, <emphasis>Mos1</emphasis> mutagenesis can be achieved following the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> protocol, substituting transgenes <emphasis>mfEx18</emphasis> (transposase) and <emphasis>mfEx24</emphasis> (transposon) (M.A. Felix, personal communication). Heat-shock conditions are also modified to allow for the greater heat-tolerance of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> animals. Mos1 germline insertions and mutant alleles have been obtained using the following heat-shock treatment of P0 young adults:
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>37&#x000B0; C for one hour, 20&#x000B0; C for one hour, 37&#x000B0; for one hour, and 15&#x000B0; overnight.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>37&#x000B0; C for 2.5 hours, 20&#x000B0; C for 35 minutes, 37&#x000B0; for one hour, and 25&#x000B0; overnight.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist></para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Online resources for <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> genetics and genomics</title>
<para>As the development of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> as a model system is in its infancy, information on its genetics and genomics is changing rapidly. The most valuable resources for staying up to date are a set of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> web sites that are the repository of considerable published and unpublished data.</para>
<sect2>
<title>The <emphasis>Caenorhabditis briggsae</emphasis> Research Page</title>
<subtitle><ulink url="wormlab.caltech.edu/briggsae" role="_blank">wormlab.caltech.edu/briggsae</ulink></subtitle>
<para>This is the best site for <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> experimental genetics. Of primary importance are archival lists of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> mutations, linkage data, and recombination maps based on visible mutations. This site also has links to a variety of other resources including a list of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> labs.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>The <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> SNP map</title>
<subtitle><ulink url="snp.wustl.edu/snp-research/c-briggsae" role="_blank">snp.wustl.edu/snp-research/c-briggsae</ulink></subtitle>
<para>In addition to the SNP map, this site is a download site for <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> sequence data, including strain-specific nucleotide polymorphisms.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>WormBase</title>
<subtitle><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/" role="_blank">www.wormbase.org</ulink></subtitle>
<para><emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> genomics data have been incorporated into WormBase. Features include <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> gene preditions, the identification of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>-<emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> orthologs and syntenic alignments of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>The WashU <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> Genome server</title>
<subtitle><ulink url="http://genome.wustl.edu/genome.cgi?GENOME=Caenorhabditis%20briggsae" role="_blank">http://genome.wustl.edu/genome.cgi?GENOME=Caenorhabditis%20briggsae</ulink></subtitle>
<para>The <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> genome server offers sequence data downloads and a link to <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>-specific BLAST server.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>The <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> Genetics Center</title>
<subtitle><ulink url="biosci.umn.edu/CGC/CGChomepage.htm" role="_blank">biosci.umn.edu/CGC/CGChomepage.htm</ulink></subtitle>
<para>The CGC is a repository of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> wild isolates and mutant strains.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>References</title>
		&Cbrigmeth_Refs;
		<para/>
	</sect1>
</article>