<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'IntroGermlinefig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'Introgermlinefig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
	<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
		 ]>
		 <article id="IntroGermline_ArticleID">
         <articleinfo>
		         <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
                 <title>Introduction to the germ line<footnote><para>Edited by Judith Kimble and Susan Strome. Last revised April 09, 2005. Published September 1, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Hubbard, E.J.A., and Greenstein, D. Introduction to the germ line (September 1, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.18.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 E. Jane Albert Hubbard and David Greenstein. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
</footnote></title>

<!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 4/9/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory> 
-->
		<author>
        <firstname>E. Jane Albert</firstname>
		<surname>Hubbard<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:jane.hubbard@nyu.edu">jane.hubbard@nyu.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></surname>
            <affiliation>
            <address>Department of Biology, New York University, New York, NY 10003 USA</address>
            </affiliation>
            </author>
            <author>
            <firstname>David</firstname>
            <surname>Greenstein</surname>
            <affiliation>
            <address>Department of Cell &amp; Developmental Biology, Vanderbilt University School of Medicine, Nashville, TN 37232-2175 USA</address></affiliation></author>
            </articleinfo>
<sect1>
    <title>An unbroken chain: the germ line</title>
		<para>In sexually reproducing organisms, cells of the germ line form gametes and establish a physical link, an unbroken chain, from generation to generation. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> germline development can be conceptually divided into three phases: specification, growth, and maintenance. Early in embryogenesis, germ cells are specified as distinct from somatic cells. During postembryonic larval stages, the germ line proliferates and undergoes meiotic development. During the remainder of reproductive life the mature germ line continues proliferation and meiotic development, and produces gametes. Chapters in the Germ line section focus on specific molecular/developmental aspects of these events. Here, we briefly introduce these chapters in the context of the temporal progression of germline development in hermaphrodites (<xref linkend="figure1" />).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig1" width="6.5in" align="center"/>
                   </imageobject><textobject><phrase>WormBook Introduction to the germ line figure 1</phrase></textobject>
            &fig1legend;
        </mediaobject>
		</sect1>
        <sect1>
		<title>Embryogenesis and early L1: germline specification</title>
		<para>During early embryogenesis, germline potential is segregated to the P blastomeres, culminating in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P4;class=Cell" role="_blank">P4</ulink>, the germline founder cell that gives rise to all of the germ cells and does not contribute to the soma. Specialized ribonucleoprotein particles, called P granules, are maternally provided and segregated to the P blastomeres. Though P granules are not sufficient for specifying the germ cell fate, germline development is severely impaired in the absence of their constituent proteins (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_specgermline/specgermline.html" role="_blank">Specification of the germ line</ulink>).</para> 
        <para>The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PIE-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> protein plays a critical role in specifying germline fate. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PIE-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> promotes germline fate in part by repressing transcriptional elongation. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PIE-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> also interacts directly with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">MEP-1</ulink>, a component of the nucleosome remodeling and deacetylase (NuRD) complex that is required in somatic cells to avoid acquisition of germline fate. The role of chromatin remodeling in the germ line has been further established by characterization of maternal-effect sterile (<emphasis>mes</emphasis>) genes and modifications of specific histone residues (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_specgermline/specgermline.html" role="_blank">Specification of the germ line</ulink>;  <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germline/germlinechromatin.html" role="_blank">Germline chromatin</ulink>).</para>
         </sect1>
        <sect1>
        <title>L1-L3: germline proliferation, survival and differentiation</title>
            <para>At hatching, the gonad comprises the primordial germ cells (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z2;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z3;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z3</ulink>) flanked by the somatic gonad precursors (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4</ulink>) and their surrounding basement membrane. These four cells remain mitotically quiescent until the mid-L1. <emphasis>nanos</emphasis>-related genes have been implicated in the localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z2;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z3;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z3</ulink> to the gonad, maintenance of quiescence, and germline survival. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z2;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z3;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z3</ulink> also require nutritional and cell-cell signals to proliferate. Changes in chromatin modification that precede proliferation occur in response to nutritionally favorable conditions. Maternal <emphasis>mes</emphasis> genes are required for subsequent larval germline survival (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlinechromatin/germlinechromatin.html" role="_blank">Germline chromatin</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlineprolifcontrol/germlineprolifcontrol.html" role="_blank">Germline proliferation and its control</ulink>).</para>
            <para>The somatic gonad develops in concert with the germ line. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4</ulink> proliferate to 12 cells by the end of the L1:  two distal tip cells (DTCs) that are critical for proliferation of the germ line, and 10 proximal cells that undergo a rearrangement in the late L2 to form the hermaphrodite somatic gonad primordium, which is distinct from the male somatic gonadal primordium. During formation of the somatic gonad, the germ cells are relegated to anterior and posterior populations. By the early L3, the anatomical stage is set for rapid extension of the gonadal arms, matched by robust proliferation of the germ line in response to signals from the DTCs and the developing sheath. Germline sex determination and meiotic prophase also begin in this stage (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_sexdetermination/sexgermline.html" role="_blank">Sex-determination in the germ line</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlineprolifcontrol/germlineprolifcontrol.html" role="_blank">Germline proliferation and its control</ulink>).</para>
            </sect1>
            <sect1>
            <title>Late larval and adult stages: germline proliferation and gametogenesis</title>
            <para>An approximately four-fold amplification in total germ cell numbers occurs during the L4 and young adult stages. Germ cell proliferation occurs in the distal mitotic zone, a region that has been likened to a niche. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLP-1</ulink> signaling in the germ line negatively regulates meiotic entry in response to a signal from the DTC throughout larval and adult stages. The regulation of meiotic entry is complex, but involves <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLD-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GLD-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FBF-1;class=protein" role="_blank">FBF-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NOS-3;class=protein" role="_blank">NOS-3</ulink>, all of which are involved in post-transcriptional gene regulation (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlineprolifcontrol/germlineprolifcontrol.html" role="_blank">Germline proliferation and its control</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RNAregulationgermline/RNAregulationgermline.html" role="_blank">RNA regulation in the germ line</ulink>). Germline proliferation, meiotic entry, and germline sex determination go hand in hand and several key genes function in multiple processes (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_sexgermline/sexgermline.html" role="_blank">Sex-determination in the germ line</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlineprolifcontrol/germlineprolifcontrol.html" role="_blank">Germline proliferation and its control</ulink>).</para>
            <para>Once germ cells have entered the meiotic pathway, germ cell chromosomes undergo homologous recombination and synaptonemal complex (SC) formation. Chromosome pairing and alteration of nuclear organization begin in the transition zone (<xref linkend="figure1"/>) and meiotic recombination is largely completed by pachytene. As cells exit pachytene, asymmetric disassembly of the SC patterns the meiotic chromosomes for bipolar orientation on the meiotic spindle and the stepwise loss of sister chromatid cohesion during successive meiotic divisions (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_meiosis/meiosis.html" role="_blank">Meiosis</ulink>). Progression through pachytene to diplotene requires the mitogen-activated protein kinase signaling pathway in the germ line (see <ulink  url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_controloocytematuration/controloocytematuration.html" role="_blank">Control of oocyte meiotic maturation and fertilization</ulink>). As meiotic chromosomes progress from diplotene to diakinesis, they become highly condensed, forming the six discrete oocyte bivalents.</para>
            <para>Germline sex-specific differences in histone modifications occur as germ cells traverse meiotic prophase. Differences in histone modifications are most dramatic between autosomes and the X chromosome. Genome-wide transcription studies, genetics, and studies on chromatin modification have converged to suggest links between germline function, transcriptional control, and chromatin structure. Germline-enriched genes are under-represented on the X chromosome. Consistent with this observation, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MES-2;class=protein" role="_blank">MES-2</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=Mes-3;class=protein" role="_blank">-3</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=Mes-6;class=protein" role="_blank">-6</ulink> protein complex acts as a histone methyltranferase that preferentially methylates the X chromosome, thereby likely conferring a repressive chromatin structure (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlinegenomics/germlinegenomics.html" role="_blank">Germline genomics</ulink>;  <ulink  url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlinechromatin/germlinechromatin.html" role="_blank">Germline chromatin</ulink>).</para>
            <para>Gametogenesis spans the late L4 and adult stages: spermatogenesis occurs during the L4 stage and oogenesis during the adult stage. As in other species, spermatogenesis produces a motile gamete. However, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> spermatozoa move by a unique crawling mechanism, utilizing the major sperm protein as the chief cytoskeletal element instead of actin. Genes involved in spermatogenesis-specific controls on translation, meiosis, morphogenesis, cytoskeletal rearrangements, and signal transduction have been identified (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_spermatogenesis/spermatogenesis.html" role="_blank">Spermatogenesis</ulink>). Oogenesis entails a tremendous increase in cytoplasmic volume and ultimately produces a maternally provisioned cell that can support early embryogenesis. Apoptosis is a common feature of oogenesis in diverse metazoan phyla. During oogenesis in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, many female germ cells undergo the apoptotic program in the loop region of the gonad (<xref linkend="figure1"/>) and are engulfed by the gonadal sheath cells (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_controloocytematuration/controloocytematuration.html" role="_blank">Control of oocyte meiotic maturation and fertilization</ulink>;  <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlinesurvivalcelldeath/germlinesurvivalcelldeath.html" role="_blank">Germline survival and cell death</ulink>). The utility of culling the oogenic germ line in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> by apoptosis is unclear, but it may facilitate the rapid loading of the remaining oocytes with maternal factors to support embryogenesis.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
        <title>Closing the circle: fertilization</title>
        <para>The oocytes of most animal species arrest during meiotic prophase, and complete meiosis in response to intercellular signaling in a process called meiotic maturation. Oocyte meiotic maturation is defined by the transition between diakinesis and metaphase of meiosis I and is accompanied by nuclear envelope breakdown, rearrangement of the cortical cytoskeleton, and meiotic spindle assembly. Thus, the meiotic maturation process is an essential part of meiosis and prepares the oocyte for fertilization (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_controloocytematuration/controloocytematuration.html" role="_blank">Control of oocyte meiotic maturation and fertilization</ulink>).</para> 
        <para>In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, the processes of meiotic maturation, ovulation, and fertilization are temporally coupled:  sperm utilize the major sperm protein as a hormone to trigger oocyte meiotic maturation, and in turn, the maturing oocyte signals its own ovulation thereby facilitating fertilization. When the non-motile spermatids enter the spermatheca during the first ovulations, they undergo spermiogenesis to form motile fertilization-competent spermatozoa. Several sperm-specific integral membrane proteins have been identified that are required in sperm for efficient fertilization (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_spermatogenesis/spermatogenesis.html" role="_blank">Spermatogenesis</ulink>;  <ulink  url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_controloocytematuration/controloocytematuration.html" role="_blank">Control of oocyte meiotic maturation and fertilization</ulink>). These final events of fertilization bring the germ line full circle.</para>
</sect1>
</article>