<caption>
	<formalpara>
		<title>Figure 3. Two electrode voltage-clamp recording of <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes expressing <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> DEG/ENaC toxic mutant channel MEC-4(d).</title>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">(a)</emphasis> When an oocyte expressing MEC-4(d) (plus MEC-10(d), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MEC-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEC-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MEC-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEC-6</ulink>, designated as the MEC-4(d) channel complex) is exposed to a NaCl solution and is stimulated by voltages from <symbol role="symbolfont">&minus;</symbol>60 to &plus; 40 mV (holding potential was <symbol role="symbolfont">&minus;</symbol>30 mV), it generates voltage-independent Na<superscript>&plus;</superscript> current. Conversely exposure of the same oocyte to a CaCl<subscript>2</subscript> solution induces activation of a <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes endogenous Ca<superscript>2&plus;</superscript>-activated Cl<superscript>-</superscript> current <emphasis role="bold">(b)</emphasis>. <emphasis role="bold">(c)</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">(d)</emphasis> MEC-4(d) channel complex dependent Na<superscript>&plus;</superscript> currents and endogenous Cl<superscript>-</superscript> currents are not activated in non-injected oocytes. This implies that even the activation of the endogenous current is dependent on MEC-4(d) channel complex. <emphasis role="bold">(e)</emphasis> Average Cl<superscript>-</superscript> current at <symbol role="symbolfont">&minus;</symbol>160 mV recorded from oocytes injected with <emphasis>mec-4(d)</emphasis> channel complex and from non-injected oocytes; n = 56 and 16. Data are mean &plusmn; SE. <emphasis role="bold">(f)</emphasis> The amplitude of the Na<superscript>&plus;</superscript> current carried by MEC-4(d) channel complex is plotted against the amplitude of the Ca<superscript>2&plus;</superscript>-activated Cl<superscript>-</superscript> current for each oocyte. Data points were fitted to a linear regression (slope = 2.3). Correlation between the amplitudes of the two currents again points towards dependence of one current upon the other. The endogenous Cl<superscript>-</superscript> current activated by exposure to Ca<superscript>2&plus;</superscript> only in oocytes injected with the <emphasis>mec-4(d)</emphasis> channel complex is activated by rise of intracellular Ca<superscript>2&plus;</superscript> (<link linkend="bib24">Kuruma and Hartzell, 1999</link><!--; PMID 9886932-->) which is caused by entry of Ca<superscript>2&plus;</superscript> through MEC-4(d) (<link linkend="bib2">Bianchi et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15543143-->). This is one case in which a <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes endogenous channel (<link linkend="bib24">Kuruma and Hartzell, 1999</link><!--; PMID 9886932-->) was actually instrumental for discovering novel properties of an exogenous channel, namely MEC-4(d) permeability to Ca<superscript>2&plus;</superscript> ions, instead of being detrimental to electrophysiological recordings, (<link linkend="bib2">Bianchi et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15543143-->). Modified from (<link linkend="bib2">Bianchi et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15543143-->).</para>
	</formalpara>
</caption>