<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 14. Phenotypes of <emphasis>elt-5(RNAi)</emphasis> embryos and larvae</title>
        <para>(A,C, E, G) Wild-type; (B, D, F, H) <emphasis>elt-5(RNAi)</emphasis> animals. (A) Nomarski image of
            wild-type L1 larva. Arrow points to the buccal capsule, which is attached to the
            anterior end of the worm. (B) <emphasis>elt-5(RNAi)</emphasis> L1 larva showing lumps (arrowhead) and a
            detached buccal capsule (arrow) at the anterior end of the pharynx, which has contracted
            toward the posterior. (C-F) Embryos stained with mAb MH27 to visualize adherens
            junctions of epidermal cells. The asterisks mark the V1 seam cell. (C) Lateral view of a
            wild-type embryo at the 2.5-fold stage. The row of 10 lateral seam cells, all completely
            surrounded by adherens junctions, is prominently visible. (D) Lateral view of an
            <emphasis>elt-5(RNAi)</emphasis> embryo at the 2.5-fold stage. One of the seam cells, V1 (asterisk), does not
            show adherens junctions, indicating that it has fused with the neighboring hyp7
            syncytium on the dorsal and ventral sides. (E) Lateral view of a wild-type embryo
            slightly past the comma stage. All ten seam cells are visible, although part of the most
            posterior seam cell, T, is out of focus. (F) Lateral view of an <emphasis>elt-5(RNAi)</emphasis> embryo
            slightly past the comma stage. One of the seam cells, V1 (asterisk), is ventrally
            misplaced, and its neighbors, H2 and V2, inappropriately contact each other. (G, H)
            L1-stage larvae expressing the seam cell marker SCM (nuclear signal) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AJM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">AJM-1</ulink>::GFP, a
            maker for adherens junctions. (G) Wild-type larva showing SCM expression in seam cells
            only. (H) <emphasis>elt-5(RNAi)</emphasis> larva showing SCM expression in nuclei of syncytial cells
            (arrowheads) near a fused seam cell (arrow). Reproduced from <link linkend="bib72">Koh and Rothman (2001)</link><!--;
            PMID 11532911-->, Copyright (2002), with permission from The Company of Biologists.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>