<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 2. Changes in the morphology of apical junctions (AJ) reveal cell behavior
            during vulva formation</title>
        <para>The monoclonal antibody MH27 stains AJs that represent the apical borders of
            epithelial cells including all vulval and hypodermal cells in <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis>, <emphasis>P.pacificus</emphasis> and other nematodes (<link linkend="bib11">Baird et al.,
            1991</link><!--; PMID 1782863-->; <link linkend="bib44">Fitch, 1997</link><!--; PMID 11975351-->; <link linkend="bib73">Kolotuev and Podbilewicz, 2004</link><!--; PMID
            14738880-->; <link linkend="bib84">Louvet-Vallee et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12586702-->). Nuclear staining is used to
            confirm observations concerning the junctions. Shown are negative micrographs of the
            junctions and schematic drawings based on detailed analysis of rotations and 3D views of
            the particular image. Note that the apical side of the vulva primordium is facing the
            ventral region of the animal and during morphogenesis the apical junctions face the
            lumen of the vulva. (A) Graphical representation of immunofluorescent staining in
            epithelial cells. Green represents the AJ belt; red cylinders represent nuclei in cells.
            This is a simplified model of the fusion process at the border between two neighboring
            cells. The disappearance of the AJ borders represents the fusion process based on EM and
            other studies (<link linkend="bib103">Podbilewicz and White, 1994</link><!--; PMID 8313992-->; <link linkend="bib113">Sharma-Kishore et al., 1999</link><!--;
            PMID 9895317-->) (B) Stack of vulva with 8 toroidal cells (right, VulA-VulF) and the cross
            section through the vulva (left). The vulva is from a late J3 stage hermaphrodite of
                <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> after completion of invagination and intratoroidal
            fusions. Green lines represent AJs and red are nuclei. (C) A twenty cells stage vulva
            primordium after completion of cell proliferation but before initiation of cell fusion
            events in <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis>. Four toroids in the center are already formed. In the left side
            of the picture see the staining of AJs, the nuclei and the basolateral domains based on
            Nomarski images. Right side shows only the apical AJs without the nuclei and the
            estimated positions of the basolateral borders. (D) Nomarski image of vulva from middle
            J3 stage. AC – anchor cell. The dotted line represents the position of the vulF ring
            containing two nuclei and their nucleoli. The stage of vulva development in this
            micrograph corresponds almost exactly to the stage of vulva in panel E. Unlike the
            Christmas tree invagination shape of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> vulva, in
                <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> the vulva has a bell shape. (E) Double stained
            image of vulva middle J3 stage in <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis>. Green lines
            represent AJ and red are nuclei. Dotted line sketches estimated position of the vulF
            toroid based on many observations including Nomarski optics as shown in panel D. AC –
            anchor cell. Reproduced from <link linkend="bib73">Kolotuev and Podbilewicz (2004)</link><!--; PMID 14738880-->, Copyright
            (2004), with permission from Elsevier. </para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>