<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 5. Cell fusion is essential for normal behavior and morphogenesis in <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis></title>
        <para>Fluorescence negative images (A, B) and Nomarski (D-H) micrographs of wild-type and
           <emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=eff-1" role="_blank">eff-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. In all pictures anterior is to the left and dorsal up. (A, B)
            Staining of the apical domains of epithelial cells using the anti-ZA MH27 antibody. (A)
            In wild-type (WT) animals lateral hypodermal seam cells (se) divide with the successive
            fusion of the non-stem daughter cells to the hypodermal syncytium (red asterisk). The
            non-fusing seam cells ultimately form two lateral rows along the body (one row is seen
            in this focal plain). (B) In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=eff-1" role="_blank">eff-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant animals, after failing to fuse with the
            surrounding epidermis, the daughter cells of the seam cells migrate throughout the
            epidermis (arrowheads) and form a misarranged net (<link linkend="bib91">Mohler et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11879640-->).
            This abnormal migration is also exhibited in vulval ectopically unfused cells (vul) that
            extend across the ventral surface (black arrows) and meet with the migrating seam cells
            (red arrows). (C) Cell fusion defects in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=eff-1" role="_blank">eff-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants cause inhibition of elongation
            and result in short and dumpy animals. (D, E) Details of heads in wild-type (D) and
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=eff-1" role="_blank">eff-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant (E), showing a Lumpy phenotype expressed as hypodermal defects throughout
            the body and especially near the head (arrow). (F) In males, the correct patterning and
            positioning of special sensilla (rays), enveloped in a cuticular fan, is based on
            earlier cell fusion between four cells in the tip of the tail (<link linkend="bib41">Emmons and Sternberg,
            1997</link><!--; PMID-->). This event, followed by retraction of the newly-formed syncytium and
            secretion of fluid to the extracellular space, allows essential shape changes in the tip
            of the tail (<link linkend="bib99">Nguyen et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10049567-->). (G) When cell fusion is blocked, the
            cells cannot retract, and the normal formation of the male-specific tip of the tail is
            disrupted, resulting in altered rays and fan and in mating disability. (H) <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=eff-1" role="_blank">eff-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants
            are egg-laying defective. Embryos that fail to get out of the uterus, develop to L1
            larvae, eat their mother’s tissues and get out of their body (a “bag of worms”
            phenotype). Reproduced from <link linkend="bib118">Shemer and Podbilewicz (2003)</link><!--; PMID 12815722-->, Copyright
            (2003), with permission from Wiley. </para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>