<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 4. TEM of unfused epidermal and muscle cells</title>
        <para>(A) Transverse thin section of mutant <emphasis>eff-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=hy21;class=Variation" role="_blank">hy21</ulink>)</emphasis> L4 grown at the restrictive
            temperature shows normal ultrastructure of the hypodermal membranes, where the
            separation between apposing plasma membranes that failed to fuse is generally between 9
            to 13 nm as in wild-type. The ultrastructure of the AJs (arrows) and membranes appears
            normal. Here, a seam cell process (s) narrows and three neighboring hypodermal cells
            (h1, h2 and h3) remain unfused along the lateral body wall. Lateral cuticle lies along
            bottom edge of panel. (B–E) TEM of pharyngeal muscle pairs shows variable fusion failure
            in a mutant <emphasis>eff-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=hy21;class=Variation" role="_blank">hy21</ulink>)</emphasis> adult grown at the restrictive temperature or successful fusion
            in wild-type cells. (B) Two cells have failed to fuse, leaving a persistent cell border
            running from the neuron process (N) to the apical junction (AJ indicated by arrow).
            (C–D) Above the AJ, two pairs of <emphasis>eff-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=hy21;class=Variation" role="_blank">hy21</ulink>)</emphasis> mutant cells have formed microfusions
            (arrowheads), which are so small that no mitochondria (mt) could pass.(E) Two wild-type
            cells have fully fused below the neuron process (N), leaving behind a complete AJ on the
            plasma membrane of the fused cell pair.(F) Model showing a pathway for pharyngeal muscle
            homotypic fusion based on TEM intermediates. Zonula adherens (ZA) is a component of the
            AJ (<link linkend="bib69">Knust and Bossinger, 2002</link><!--; PMID 12471248-->) (B–E). The scale bars represent 100 nm.
            Reproduced from <link linkend="bib119">Shemer et al. (2004)</link><!--; PMID 15341747-->, Copyright (2004), with permission
            from Elsevier. </para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>