<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig7 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig7.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig7legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig7leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig8 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig8.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig8legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig8leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig9 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig9.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig9legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig9leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig10 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig10.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig10legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig10leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig11 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig11.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig11legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig11leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig12 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig12.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig12legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig12leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig13 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig13.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig13legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig13leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig14 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig14.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig14legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig14leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig15 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig15.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig15legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig15leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig16 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig16.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig16legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig16leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig17 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig17.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig17legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig17leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig18 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig18.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig18legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig18leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig19 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig19.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig19legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig19leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig20 SYSTEM 'VulvaFig20.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig20legend SYSTEM 'WBVulvafig20leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY WBVulva_Refs SYSTEM 'WBVulvarefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="Vulva_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <!--  PDF style sheetchanges
                        <xsl:attribute-set name="caption.para.spacing">
                          <xsl:attribute name="space-before.optimum">1.2em</xsl:attribute>
                          <xsl:attribute name="space-before.minimum">1em</xsl:attribute>
                          <xsl:attribute name="space-before.maximum">1.4em</xsl:attribute>
                          <xsl:attribute name="text-indent">0pt</xsl:attribute> 
                          </xsl:attribute-set> -->
        <title>Vulval development<footnote><para>Edited by Barbara J. Meyer. Last revised June 18, 2005. Published June, 25 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Sternberg, P.W., Vulval development (June, 25 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.6.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 Paul W. Sternberg. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
</footnote></title>
        <author>
            <firstname>Paul W.</firstname>
            <surname>Sternberg<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:pws@caltech.edu">pws@caltech.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Howard Hughes Medical Institute and Division of Biology, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA 91125 USA</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <para>
            <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">vulval development is an intensively studied example of animal organogenesis. A network of intercellular signaling, signal transduction, and transcriptional regulation underlies the precise formation of this organ, which is the connection between the hermaphrodite uterus and the outside of the nematode. A single cell of the somatic gonad, the anchor cell, organizes the development of the vulva from epidermal precursors as well as the physical connection of the epidermis with the uterus. WNT signaling acting via the HOX gene</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">renders six epidermal precursor cells competent to respond to other developmental signals. The anchor cell induces nearby epidermal precursor cells to generate vulval cells via an epidermal growth factor (EGF) signaling pathway. The precise pattern of vulval precursor cell fates involves the graded action of the EGF signaling and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> (Notch) mediated lateral signaling. EGF promotes the 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fate while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> promotes the 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fate. Both EGF and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> prevent precursor cells from adopting the 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fate, which generates non-specialized epidermis. EGF-receptor and Notch signaling are antagonistic: EGF-receptor signaling leads to down-regulation of the Notch-like receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>, while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> signaling induces negative regulators of EGF-receptor signaling such as MAP kinase phosphatase LIP-1 and the tyrosine kinase ARK-1. The 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> precursor cell generates vulE and vulF mature vulval cells; the pattern of vulE and vulF cells requires an additional signal from the anchor cell as well as WNT signaling. The two 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> precursor cells generate vulA, vulB1, vulB2, vulC and vulD cells but in mirror symmetric polar patterns: ABCD and DCBA. The reversed polarity of the posterior 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> precursor cell lineage requires WNT signaling mediated by both Frizzled class and Ryk class WNT-receptors <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-17;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-17</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-18;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-18</ulink>, respectively. A network of transcription factors controls the seven mature adult cell types; these include the LIM domain protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-11;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-11</ulink>, the Pax2/5/8 protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-38;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-38</ulink>, the zinc finger protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-29;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-29</ulink>, and the Nkx6.1/6.2 protein COG-1. The anchor cell also patterns nearby uterine cells, via the DSL ligand LAG-2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>, to generate the four uv1 cells that form the tight connection with the vulva. This connection is initiated by the anchor cell, which invades between the vulF cells in a process analogous to invasive behavior of metastatic tumor cells. During this invasion process, the basement membranes between the gonad and body wall are degraded. The extensive information about vulval development in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">has helped it become a paradigmatic case for identifying and studying a variety of regulatory pathways.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
    <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> hermaphrodite vulva develops during postembryonic (larval) development from ventral epidermal precursors, and connects the developing uterus to the external environment. In the adult, the vulva is necessary for egg-laying (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_egglaying/egglaying.html" role="_blank">Egg-laying</ulink>) and for copulation with males (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_malematingbehavior/malematingbehavior.html" role="_blank">Male mating behavior</ulink>). Vulval development has attracted general interest for three main reasons. First, it serves as a paradigm for organogenesis. In particular, vulva development represents a well-understood case in which invariant development arises from multiple cell-cell interactions. It is also a striking example of tissue remodeling: the formation of a hole at a precise location in an organism. Second, it has been important for the genetic analyses of signaling and signal transduction by epidermal growth factor (EGF)-receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> and RAS <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-60;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-60</ulink>; (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RTKRasMAPKsignaling/RTKRasMAPKsignaling.html" role="_blank">RTKRas/MAP kinase signaling</ulink>), LIN-12 (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_lin12Notch/lin12notch.html" role="_blank">LIN-12/Notch signaling in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>), and WNT (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_wntsignaling/wntsignaling.html" role="_blank">Wnt signaling</ulink>), as well as the functions of the SynMuv and mediator proteins (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transcriptionalregulation/transcriptionalregulation.html" role="_blank">Transcriptional regulation</ulink>). Third, it has become a paradigm for examining the interactions among regulatory pathways, notably the antagonism of EGF-receptor (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink>) and Notch (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>) pathways.</para>
<?newpage?>
	<sect2>
	<title>Steps in vulval development</title>
            <para>Vulval development is conveniently thought of as occurring in five steps (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). <emphasis role="bold">(1) Generation of VPCs:</emphasis> During the L1 and L2 stages, six vulval precursor cells (VPCs) are specified among the 11 Pn.p cells, which are located in the ventral epidermis. <emphasis role="bold">(2) Vulval Precursor Patterning:</emphasis> During the L3 stage, a signal from the gonad and signaling among the VPCs specifies three VPCs to generate vulval cells (<xref linkend="figure2"/>). The vulval lineages are of two types, 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> and 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>, each of which generate distinct sets of progeny. The uninduced VPCs generate a 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> lineage, which make epidermal cells that fuse with the large syncytial epidermis hyp7. In an intact, wild-type hermaphrodite, the VPCs adopt their fates in a precise spatial pattern: 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> (<xref linkend="figure3"/>). <emphasis role="bold">(3) Generation of the adult cells:</emphasis> The adult vulva comprises 22 nuclei in cells of seven types, vulA, vulB1, vulB2, vulC, vulD, vulE, and vulF, that differ in their patterns of gene expression and in details of their cell biology. <emphasis role="bold">(4) Anchor cell invasion:</emphasis> the anchor cell extends process to the center of the vulF cells and forms a hole in the epidermis. <emphasis role="bold">(5) Morphogenesis of the vulva:</emphasis> the seven types of vulval cells invaginate, and sequentially form seven distinct toroids, connects to the uterus, and everts as the hermaphrodite molts to adulthood. In addition, two aspects of uterine development are crucial to the development of the vulva. <emphasis role="bold">(A) Generation of the anchor cell.</emphasis> The anchor cell is specified from among two somatic gonadal cells during the end of the L2 stage (see AC/VU decision). <emphasis role="bold">(B) Uterine Patterning.</emphasis> The anchor cell also patterns the developing uterus, inducing the six pi cells, which generate the utse cell and uv1 cells. The uv1 cells attach to the vulF cells, while the anchor cell ultimately fuses with the utse.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
	<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
	    <imageobject><imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.5in" align="center"/></imageobject>
	    <textobject><phrase>Vulval development is a multi-step process</phrase></textobject>
	    &fig1legend; 
	    </mediaobject>
	    <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
	    <imageobject><imagedata entityref="fig2" width="3.3in" align="center"/></imageobject>
            <textobject><phrase>Nomarski images of developing vulva</phrase></textobject>
	    &fig2legend;
	    </mediaobject>
	   <mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
                <imageobject><imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4in" align="center"/></imageobject>
                <textobject><phrase>Simple view of vulval lineages</phrase></textobject>
		&fig3legend;
	</mediaobject>
        </sect2>
	<sect2>
            <title>Phenotypes of vulval development mutants</title>
	    <para>Mutations that affect vulva development often cause defects that are visible in the dissecting microscope. These phenotypes include the inability of hermaphrodites to lay eggs (EGg-Laying-defective; Egl), or morphological defects such as Protruding VuLva (Pvl) or abnormal Eversion of the vuLva (Evl). Specifically, mutants with defective vulval induction, e.g., mutations that decrease activity of the EGF-receptor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-23" role="_blank">let-23</ulink></emphasis> (see below) cause a VULvaless (Vul) phenotype. Vulvaless hermaphrodites have fertile eggs that hatch internally and eventually escape from the corpse of their mother. Hermaphrodites with defects in the vulval lineages or in the vulval-uterine connection have protruding vulvae or are egg-laying defective. Mutations that activate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink>, rendering it constitutive, result in a MUltiVulva (Muv) phenotype. Multivulva hermaphrodites typically have a single functional vulva and additional ventral protrusions, each a pseudovulva formed from vulval tissue. Mutants with reversed polarity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> lineage have a psuedovulva posterior to the normal vulva.</para>
            <para>In addition to screens for mutants with vulval defects (<link linkend="bib66">Horvitz and Sulston, 1980</link><!-- PMID 7262539 -->; <link linkend="bib39">Ferguson and Horvitz, 1985</link><!-- PMID 3996896 -->; <link linkend="bib110">Seydoux and Greenwald, 1993</link><!-- PMID 8500652 -->; <link linkend="bib34">Eisenmann and Kim, 2000</link><!--  PMID 11063687 -->; <link linkend="bib106">Palmer et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12482710 -->), suppressor screens proved useful in identifying new genes and alleles, including members of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> pathways and genes involved in other steps in vulval development (e.g., <link linkend="bib5">Beitel et al., 1990</link><!-- PMID 2123303 -->; <link linkend="bib52">Han et al., 1990</link><!-- PMID 2076820 -->; <link linkend="bib3">Aroian et al., 1991</link><!-- PMID 2071015 -->; <link linkend="bib26">Clark et al., 1992</link><!-- PMID 1372395 -->; <link linkend="bib27">Clark et al., 1992</link><!-- PMID 1339671 -->;<link linkend="bib24"> 1993</link>; <link linkend="bib55">Han et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8483497 -->; <link linkend="bib21">Clark, 1992</link>).</para>
        </sect2>
	      <sect2>
            <title>Note on phenotypes</title>
            <para>The phenotype of a hermaphrodite observed at the dissecting microscope level can
                sometimes be misleading, and thus the dissecting microscope phenotypes should always
                be confirmed by observation of anatomy in a compound microscope. For example, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-17" role="_blank">lin-17</ulink></emphasis> mutants often display a vulva (from P5.p and P6.p) and a posterior pseudo-vulva (from P7.p), appearing to be multivulva, but have a normal extent of vulval induction. A number of markers are now available to help distinguish different fates of VPCs (<link linkend="bib15">Burdine et al., 1998</link><!--  PMID 9463355 -->; <link linkend="bib145">Yoo et al., 2004</link><!--  PMID 14752159 -->) and of terminal vulval cells (<link linkend="bib75">Inoue et al., 2002</link><!--  PMID 14516686 -->).</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Generation of vulval precursor cells</title>
        <para>The eleven Pn.p cells (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P1.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P1.p</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P2.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P2.p</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P3.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P3.p</ulink>,..., <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P11.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P11.p</ulink>) are formed during the L1 larval
            stage as the posterior daughters of the Pn ventral neuro-ectoblasts (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P3;class=Cell" role="_blank">P3</ulink>, ....,
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P11;class=Cell" role="_blank">P11</ulink>), the anterior daughters of which generate primarily ventral cord neurons (<link linkend="bib130">Sulston
            and Horvitz, 1977</link><!--  PMID 838129 -->). The Pn cell nuclei migrate into the ventral cord during
            the L1 stage. The development of the vulva thus depends upon the generation of the Pn.p
            cells. Action of the Hox genes is responsible for specification of the VPCs <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P3.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P3.p</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P4.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P4.p</ulink>,
            ..., <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.p</ulink> (P(3-8).p; <xref linkend="figure4"/>). In particular,
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> is necessary for specification of the VPCs; in the absence
            of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> function, P(3-8).p fuse with hyp7 epidermis in the L1
            larval stage (<link linkend="bib108">Salser et al., 1993</link><!--  PMID 8103754 -->; <link linkend="bib24">Clark et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8101475 -->; <xref linkend="figure5"/>). In wild-type hermaphrodites, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P3.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P3.p</ulink> sometimes fuses with hyp7 during
            the L2 stage (<link linkend="bib130">Sulston and Horvitz, 1977</link><!--  PMID 838129 -->).</para>
	    <mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
                <imageobject><imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4in" align="center"/></imageobject>
                <textobject><phrase>Hox genes and VPC competence group</phrase></textobject>
		&fig4legend;
	</mediaobject>
	    <mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
                <imageobject><imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject><phrase>Roles of LIN-39</phrase></textobject>
		&fig5legend;
	</mediaobject>
        <sect2>
            <title>Vulval competence group</title>
            <para>In the intact, wild-type hermaphrodite grown under standard conditions, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink>
                and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> generate vulval cells. Ablation experiments indicated that the six cells
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P3.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P3.p</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P4.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P4.p</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.p</ulink> are competent to respond to intercellular
                signals and generate vulva. (<link linkend="bib132">Sulston and White, 1980</link><!-- PMID 7190941 -->; <link linkend="bib82">Kimble, 1981</link><!-- PMID 7286433 -->; <link linkend="bib127">Sternberg and Horvitz, 1986</link><!--  PMID 3753901 -->). For example, ablation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink>
                may result in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink> adopting the 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>
                fate and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P4.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P4.p</ulink> adopting the 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fate,
                or, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> may adopt the 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fate and
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.p</ulink> the 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fate. Ablation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink> may
                result in replacement by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P4.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P4.p</ulink>, whle ablation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> may result in replacement by
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.p</ulink>. Ablation of all VPCs but <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P3.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P3.p</ulink> results in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P3.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P3.p</ulink> becoming 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>. There is some variability, especially as a
                function of time at which the ablation occurs.</para>
            <para>Ablation of the gonad during the L1 stage (<link linkend="bib132">Sulston and White, 1980</link><!-- PMID 7190941 -->),
                or of the anchor cell prior to the L3 stage, results in all six VPCs becoming
                    3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> (<link linkend="bib82">Kimble, 1981</link><!-- PMID 7286433 -->; <xref linkend="figure6"/>). These experiments also indicate that the anchor
                cell induces the vulva.</para>
                 <mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig6" width="4.2in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase>Pattern of VPC fates and main defects in induction</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig6legend; </mediaobject>
            <para>Ablation of all six VPCs in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> did not result in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P2.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P2.p</ulink>
                or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P9.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P9.p</ulink> generating vulval progeny (<link linkend="bib132">Sulston and White, 1980</link><!-- PMID 7190941 -->; compare to
                    <emphasis>Panagrellus redivivus</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib125">Sternberg and Horvitz, 1982</link><!-- PMID 7128930 -->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_evoldevnematode/evoldevnematode.html">Evolution of development in nematodes closely related to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>), suggesting that only
                P3.p-P8.p form the "vulval equivalence group." Additional support for this
                conclusion comes from the observation that mutations that activate the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> or
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> signaling pathways (and hence allow VPCs to generate vulval cells independent
                of a signal from the gonad) only cause <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P3.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P3.p</ulink>-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.p</ulink> but <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P2.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P2.p</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P9.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P9.p</ulink> to adopt vulval
                fates (<link linkend="bib47">Greenwald et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6616618 -->; <link linkend="bib41">Ferguson et al., 1987</link><!-- PMID 2881214 -->;
                <link linkend="bib126">Sternberg, 1988</link><!-- PMID 3419532 -->). Moreover, when the gonad position relative to the
                VPCs is displaced by a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dig-1" role="_blank">dig-1</ulink></emphasis> mutation, the position of the
                    1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> cell can shift, no cells other
                than <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P3.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P3.p</ulink>-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.p</ulink> generate vulval cells (<link linkend="bib137">Thomas et al., 1990</link><!-- PMID 2401010 -->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Hox gene <emphasis>lin-39</emphasis>, competence, and fusion</title>
            <para>The hox gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> is a major determinant of the VPC group
                (<link linkend="bib24">Clark et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8101475 -->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P3.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P3.p</ulink>
                to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.p</ulink> (<link linkend="bib108">Salser et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8103754 -->). Lack of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis>
                activity results in lack of VPCs because the presumptive VPCs fuse with the hyp7
                epidermis. However, overexpression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> does not cause
                additional Pn.p cells such as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P2.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P2.p</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P9.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P9.p</ulink> to become competent.
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> has at least two roles: preventing fusion and
                stimulating cell division (<xref linkend="figure5"/>). A mutation in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=eff-1" role="_blank">eff-1</ulink></emphasis> results in lack of cell fusion (<link linkend="bib99">Mohler et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 11879640-->). Inactivation of both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=eff-1" role="_blank">eff-1</ulink></emphasis> and
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> results in VPCs that fail to fuse and fail to divide
                (<link linkend="bib114">Shemer and Podbilewicz, 2002</link><!-- PMID 12502736 -->). WNT signaling via <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=BAR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">BAR-1</ulink> beta-catenin
                is necessary to maintain expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> in the P(3-8).p (<link linkend="bib35">Eisenmann et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9716532 -->). Expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> is sufficient to
                bypass the requirement for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=BAR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">BAR-1</ulink> function in generating competent VPCs (<link linkend="bib35">Eisenmann et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9716532 -->). Using a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=bar-1" role="_blank">bar-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant to sensitize the
                VPCs for loss of competence, <link linkend="bib35">Eisenmann et al. (1998</link><!-- PMID 9716532 -->) showed that  <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-23" role="_blank">let-23</ulink></emphasis> and the somatic gonad were involved in establishing competence of VPCs.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Other genes affecting competence</title>
            <para>
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sem-4" role="_blank">sem-4</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a zinc finger protein, is necessary for
                full <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> expression, and overexpression of
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> can rescue the defect of a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sem-4" role="_blank">sem-4</ulink></emphasis>
                mutant (<link linkend="bib45">Grant et al., 2000</link><!--  PMID 1092678 -->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CEH-20;class=protein" role="_blank">CEH-20</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-62;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-62</ulink> are co-factors of
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-39;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-39</ulink> and as such affect vulval development (<link linkend="bib141">Yang et al., 2005</link><!--  PMID 15750187-->).
                Two redundant GATA factors, encoded by the adjacent <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-18" role="_blank">egl-18</ulink></emphasis> and
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elt-6" role="_blank">elt-6</ulink></emphasis> genes, are necessary for vulval competence, and are
                regulated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-39;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-39</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CEH-20;class=protein" role="_blank">CEH-20</ulink> (<link linkend="bib87">Koh et al., 2002</link><!--PMID 12399309-->). The translocation
                <emphasis>nT1</emphasis> has a highly penetrant VPC competence defect (<link linkend="bib39">Ferguson and Horvitz, 1985</link><!-- PMID 3996896 -->; <link linkend="bib41">Ferguson et al., 1987</link><!-- PMID 2881214 -->).
                <emphasis>nT1</emphasis> disrupts the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-18" role="_blank">egl-18</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elt-6" role="_blank">elt-6</ulink></emphasis> operon,
                preventing its expression in the vulva (<link linkend="bib86">Koh et al., 2004</link><!--  PMID 14975731 -->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Non-equivalence of the VPCs</title>
            <para>More detailed analysis indicates that the VPCs, while multipotential, are not
                equivalent in their ability to respond to the major inductive signal (<link linkend="bib23">Clandinin et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9073457 -->). In particular <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.p</ulink> are less sensitive to EGF-R
                signaling than is <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink> (<xref linkend="figure4"/>). This difference in sensitivity
                is dependent on the hox gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-5" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis>, which is expressed in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink>
                and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.p</ulink> but not P(3-6).p (<link linkend="bib108">Salser et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8103754 -->). Also,
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sem-4" role="_blank">sem-4</ulink></emphasis> is preferentially required in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink>, and this effect is in
                part due to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-5" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib45">Grant et al., 2000</link><!--  PMID 1092678 -->). The details of fate specification may differ between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink>. These differences are relatively subtle, but very intriguing in light of vulval development in other nematode species (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_evoldevnematode/evoldevnematode.html" role="_blank">Evolution of development in nematodes closely related to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>).</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Overview of VPC 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> pattern formation</title>
        <para>The 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>, 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>, and 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fates occur in a precise spatial pattern. Formation of the pattern of VPC fates involves several key elements. An inductive signal from the anchor cell acts via <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> to induce <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink> and to a lesser extent <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink>. Lateral signaling among induced VPCs via <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> that specifies 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fates and inhibits 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fates. Cross inhibition exists between the two pathways: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> signaling turns on inhibitors of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> signaling, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> signaling up-regulates ligand for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> and down-regulates the receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> (<xref linkend="figure7"/>). Inhibitors also act as if they are noise suppressors to ensure that fate specification is dependent upon signals. <xref linkend="figure8"/> shows the key signaling pathways involved in vulval patterning. The current view of vulval precursor cell patterning is that the two systems cooperate to give a precise pattern (reviewed by <link linkend="bib124">Sternberg, 2004</link><!-- PMID 14752152 -->; <link linkend="bib133">Sundaram, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15084301 -->). Vulval induction apparently involves both a graded signal (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> acting via <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink>) as well as a sequential, subordinate signal (DSL ligands acting via <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_lin12Notch/lin12notch.html" role="_blank">LIN-12/Notch signaling in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>).</para>
	<literallayout></literallayout>
	<mediaobject id="figure7" xreflabel="Figure 7">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig7" width="4in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Three-signal model for vulval patterning</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig7legend;</mediaobject>

	    <mediaobject id="figure8" xreflabel="Figure 8">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig8" width="4.2in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Three major signaling pathways patterning the vulva and uterus</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig8legend;</mediaobject>
        <sect2>
            <title>Specification and determination of the VPC fates</title>
            <para>VPC patterning is conveniently and appropriately thought of in terms of VPC level
                specification (<link linkend="bib127">Sternberg and Horvitz, 1986</link><!-- PMID 3753901 -->). A specified VPC generates
                a characteristic 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>, 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>or 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> lineage, and expresses markers that are
                characteristic of each fate.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Commitment to fates</title>
            <para>An open question in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> development concerns fate
                commitment. I use specification to mean a cell knows what to do but is not
                irreversibly committed to that fate; commitment is irreversible (within a reasonable
                set of perturbations). The rapidity of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> development,
                and the lack of long-term culture have precluded extensive tests of commitment. One
                can argue that cells are specified and then development proceeds without any need
                for long-term stability. One experiment with VPCs revealed that the 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fate VPCs are not committed (<link linkend="bib139">Wang and Sternberg, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10419682 -->). Expression of high levels of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> after the VPCs
                have divided in a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> activated mutant alters their fate such that they express
                    1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> lineage markers and display the
                morphological hallmarks of 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>
                lineages, such invagination; thus cells specified to become 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> are not committed even after they divide.
                The 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fate is irreversible after
                fusion with hyp7, about an hour after their cell division. The 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fates so far have not been altered after
                their division (<link linkend="bib1">Ambros, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10101128 -->; <link linkend="bib139">Wang and Sternberg, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10419682 -->).
                <link linkend="bib1">Ambros (1999</link><!-- PMID 10101128 -->) found that VPCs could become specified to become
                    1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> prior to the end of their S
                phase but specification of 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fates
                required the end of S phase. In this view, the cell cycle helps prioritize the
                specification process.</para>
            <para>Hybrid lineages arise by too little induction (for example ablation of the anchor
                cell before the VPCs are fully induced) or by late induction acting on the daughter
                cells (for example if <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> expression is induced after the VPCs divide; <link linkend="bib139">Wang and
                Sternberg, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10419682 -->). Fusion of VPC daughters (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P3.pa;class=Cell" role="_blank">P3.pa</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P3.pp;class=Cell" role="_blank">P3.pp</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P4.pa;class=Cell" role="_blank">P4.pa</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P4.pp;class=Cell" role="_blank">P4.pp</ulink>,
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.pa;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.pa</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.pp;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.pp</ulink>) occurs about an hour after they are formed, which eliminates their competence to respond to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink>.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>The cell cycle and vulval development</title>
            <para>Vulva development involves cell cycle in two distinct ways. Cell cycle regulation
                is one important consequence of vulval cell fate specification, and conversely, the
                cell cycle influences fate specification. One of the major differences between the
                uninduced 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> and the induced vulval
                    (1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> and 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>) VPC fates is in the extent of cell
                division. Cyclin E, encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cye-1" role="_blank">cye-1</ulink></emphasis> is necessary for
                proliferation of the VPCs (<link linkend="bib38">Fay and Han, 2000</link><!-- PMID 10952902 -->). In
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cye-1" role="_blank">cye-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants, there are fewer VPC divisions, but
                differentiation, assayed by expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-17" role="_blank">egl-17</ulink>::gfp</emphasis> occurs at
                the normal time. Moreover, <link linkend="bib10">Boxem and van den Heuvel (2002<!-- PMID 12062054 -->)</link> found that
                cell division could be uncoupled to some extent from differentiation.</para>
            <para>The heterochronic genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-4" role="_blank">lin-4</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-14" role="_blank">lin-14</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-28" role="_blank">lin-28</ulink> </emphasis> control the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=G1;class=Cell" role="_blank">G1</ulink> to S transition of VPCs (<link linkend="bib36">Euling and Ambros, 1996</link><!-- PMID 8625405 -->). The cell cycle inhibitor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cki-1" role="_blank">cki-1</ulink></emphasis> is one target of this heterochronic pathway (<link linkend="bib63">Hong et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9716524 -->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cki-1" role="_blank">cki-1</ulink>::GFP </emphasis> is expressed in the VPCs during their <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=G1;class=Cell" role="_blank">G1</ulink> phase. Inactivation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cki-1" role="_blank">cki-1</ulink></emphasis> results in VPC division during the L2 stage, and expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cki-1" role="_blank">cki-1</ulink></emphasis> in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink> under control of
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-17" role="_blank">egl-17</ulink></emphasis> transcriptional regulatory sequences blocks its mitosis
                (<link linkend="bib63">Hong et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9716524 -->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cki-1" role="_blank">cki-1</ulink></emphasis> expression in VPCs is
                reduced in the absence of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-14" role="_blank">lin-14</ulink></emphasis>, which results in precocious
                development of the VPCs.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Induction of the vulva by the anchor cell </title>
        <para>The anchor cell (AC) induces vulval formation directly by expressing the epidermal growth factor (EGF)-like ligand <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink>. The action of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> is graded and acts at a distance. The induction by the anchor cell can also be indirect, with induction of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>-mediated lateral signaling and possibly additional <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-3" role="_blank">lin-3</ulink></emphasis> signaling.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>The anchor cell is necessary and sufficient</title>
            <para>Ablation of the anchor cell or its ancestors prior to the L3 stage completely blocks vulval development, and the VPCs have 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fates (3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>). Ablation of all gonadal cells but the anchor cell results in full induction of the vulva (<link linkend="bib82">Kimble, 1981</link><!-- PMID 7286433 -->). Males will copulate with these vulvae but not transfer sperm (M. Barr, K. Liu and P. Sternberg, unpublished observations).</para>
            <para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-3" role="_blank">lin-3</ulink></emphasis> encodes the inductive signal from the anchor cell that induces the VPCs (<link linkend="bib62">Hill and Sternberg, 1992</link><!-- PMID 1641037 -->; <xref linkend="figure9"/>). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-3" role="_blank">lin-3</ulink></emphasis> is necessary for vulval induction (<link linkend="bib66">Horvitz and Sulston, 1980</link><!-- PMID 7262539 -->; <link linkend="bib131">Sulston and Horvitz, 1981</link><!-- PMID 7014288 -->; <link linkend="bib39">Ferguson and Horvitz, 1985</link><!-- PMID 3996896 -->; <link linkend="bib41">Ferguson et al., 1987</link><!-- PMID 2881214 -->; <link linkend="bib62">Hill and Sternberg, 1992</link><!-- PMID 1641037 -->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-3" role="_blank">lin-3</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in the anchor cell during the time induction takes place. Expression of the EGF domain of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> directed by a heat shock (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hsp-16" role="_blank">hsp-16</ulink></emphasis>) promoter/enhancer is sufficient to induce the vulva in the absence of the gonad and hence the anchor cell (<link linkend="bib62">Hill and Sternberg, 1992</link><!-- PMID 1641037 -->).</para>
            <mediaobject id="figure9" xreflabel="Figure 9">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig9" width="4.3in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase>Level of LIN-3 directs pattern of VPC cell fates</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig9legend; </mediaobject>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Action at a distance</title>
            <para>The anchor cell signals at a distance from the VPCs. Cell ablation studies reveal that a distal VPC can be induced to a 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> or 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fate (or some intermediate; <link linkend="bib127">Sternberg and Horvitz, 1986</link><!-- PMID 3753901 -->; <link linkend="bib80">Katz et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 7628018 -->; <link linkend="bib117">Sherwood and Sternberg, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12852849 -->). In addition, in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dig-1" role="_blank">dig-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants, a dorsally located anchor cell can induce patterns such as 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>, 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>or 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> (<link linkend="bib137">Thomas et al., 1990</link><!-- PMID 2401010 -->). The dorsally located anchor cell can extend a process ventrally, but this occurs after induction, and is fully consistent with the anchor cell invasion of the vulval epidermis (<link linkend="bib117">Sherwood and Sternberg, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12852849 -->).</para>
	    </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Graded action of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink></title>
            <para>The anchor cell signal is able to act at a distance and appears graded based on a
                correlation of distance from the anchor cell and the fate of individual VPCs
                (<link linkend="bib127">Sternberg and Horvitz, 1986</link><!-- PMID 3753901 -->). An individual VPC, after ablation of
                other VPCs, can have a 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fate. Also,
                in a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dig-1" role="_blank">dig-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant there can be 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> VPCs without 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> VPCs (<link linkend="bib137">Thomas et al., 1990</link><!-- PMID 2401010 -->). In
                addition, molecular genetic experiments (<link linkend="bib80">Katz et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 7628018 -->; <link linkend="bib81">Katz et
                al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8552080 -->) strongly support the possibility of a graded signal. The
                dose of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> was controlled in two ways. The EGF domain of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> along with a
                synthetic signal sequence was expressed under the transcriptional control of a
                heat-shock enhancer/promoter. By varying the duration and temperature of heat shock,
                different apparent doses of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> could be produced. A high dose results in 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fates; an intermediate dose in 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fates; and a low dose in 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fates. In most cases there is a distribution
                of fates as well as intermediate fates. A distinct set of experiments with partially
                activated <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> gave similar results (<link linkend="bib81">Katz et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8552080 -->).</para>
            <para>The graded expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-17" role="_blank">egl-17</ulink></emphasis>, the best-known target of
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> signaling in the 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> VPC
                (<link linkend="bib15">Burdine et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9463355 -->), provides a molecular correlate for a graded
                inductive signal. <emphasis>egl-17-CFP-LacZ</emphasis>, is initially expressed in
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> with higher expression in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink>, thereby indicating a graded
                signal (<link linkend="bib145">Yoo et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14752159 -->). Its expression is increased in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink> and decreased in
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> due to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> signaling as described below.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Non-graded action of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink>: sequential induction</title>
            <para>In addition to the strong support for a graded signal, there is also strong support for a sequential signaling mechanism in which activation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink> leads to activation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink>. Certain genetic mosaics lacking <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-23" role="_blank">let-23</ulink></emphasis> activity suggest that direct induction by the AC is not necessary for the 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fate: if <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-23" role="_blank">let-23</ulink>(<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x002B;</symbol>)</emphasis> is present in all cells, there is a wild-type vulva; if all cells are <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-23" role="_blank">let-23</ulink>(-)</emphasis> there is no vulva (<xref linkend="figure10"/>; <link linkend="bib121">Simske and Kim, 1995</link><!-- PMID 7753169 -->; <link linkend="bib85">Koga et al.,1995</link><!-- PMID 7671826 -->). If <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink> is <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-23" role="_blank">let-23</ulink>(<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x002B;</symbol>)</emphasis> but <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> are <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-23" role="_blank">let-23</ulink>(-)</emphasis>, then in almost all cases there was a normal vulva. Thus, a cell can become 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> without receiving <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink>. This key result is consistent with the observations that activation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> can specify a 2 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fate in the absence of an anchor cell (<link linkend="bib47">Greenwald et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6616618 -->) or of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> signaling (<link linkend="bib128">Sternberg and Horvitz, 1989</link><!-- PMID 2548732 -->; <link linkend="bib52">Han et al., 1990</link><!-- PMID 2076820 -->), and strongly makes the point that the direct induction of 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> by the anchor cell is not necessary. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> is expected to be the receptor for this 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-inducing signal: <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> activity is necessary and sufficient for the 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fate (<link linkend="bib47">Greenwald et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6616618 -->), and ligands for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> are up-regulated in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink> in response to the inductive signal (<link linkend="bib20">Chen and Greenwald, 2004</link><!-- PMID 14960273 -->).</para>
	<literallayout></literallayout>
           <mediaobject id="figure10" xreflabel="Figure 10">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig10" width="4in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase>Sequential signaling inferred from mosaic analysis of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-23" role="_blank">let-23</ulink></emphasis>
                    </phrase>
                </textobject> &fig10legend; </mediaobject>
            <para>The converse mosaic animals had a striking phenotype: if <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink> is
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-23" role="_blank">let-23</ulink>(-)</emphasis> but <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> are <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-23" role="_blank">let-23</ulink>(<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x002B;</symbol>)</emphasis>, then additional cells are
                induced (<link linkend="bib121">Simske and Kim, 1995</link><!-- PMID 7753169 -->; also see <link linkend="bib51">Hajnal et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9334333 -->). Hajnal et al. argue that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> might be sequestering <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> and preventing its spread to more distal cells.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Possible relay induction by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink></title>
            <para><link linkend="bib33">Dutt et al. (2004<!-- PMID 15455032 -->)</link> have suggested that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-3" role="_blank">lin-3</ulink></emphasis>
                expression in induced VPCs extends the range of induction, and that this role of
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-3" role="_blank">lin-3</ulink></emphasis> depends on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ROM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ROM-1</ulink>. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rom-1" role="_blank">rom-1</ulink></emphasis> encodes a
                protease related to <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> Rhomboid, which cleaves Spitz, a
                <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> protein related to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink>. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-3" role="_blank">lin-3</ulink></emphasis>
                encodes multiple isoforms that differ in the region between the EGF domain and the
                transmembrane domain (<link linkend="bib62">Hill and Sternberg, 1992</link><!-- PMID 1641037 -->; <link linkend="bib33">Dutt et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15455032 -->), a part of the protein that would likely be cleaved for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> in a relay
                mechanism. The B but not the A isoform of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> is <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ROM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ROM-1</ulink> dependent (<link linkend="bib33">Dutt et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15455032 -->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Nuclear targets of the LET-23-LET-60-MPK-1 pathway</title>
            <para>Two transcription factors, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-31;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-31</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-1;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-1</ulink> are likely targets of the MAPK pathway
                (<link linkend="bib134">Tan et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9604932 -->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-31;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-31</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-1;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-1</ulink> can both be phosphorylated by MAP
                kinase MPK-1. Inactivation of either <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-1" role="_blank">lin-1</ulink></emphasis> or
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-31" role="_blank">lin-31</ulink></emphasis> leads to a Multivulva phenotype. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-1;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-31;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-31</ulink> form a
                complex that is disrupted by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-31;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-31</ulink> phosphorylation (<link linkend="bib134">Tan et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9604932 -->).
                Increased expression of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-31;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-31</ulink> or a non-phosphorylatable <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-31;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-31</ulink> protein causes a
                vulvaless phenotype. During the L3 stage, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-31" role="_blank">lin-31</ulink></emphasis> mutants
                display both vulvaless and multivulva phenotypes (<link linkend="bib39">Ferguson and Horvitz, 1985</link><!-- PMID 3996896 -->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-31" role="_blank">lin-31</ulink></emphasis> mutants display inappropriate divisions of
                Pn.p cells during the L2 stage (<link linkend="bib41">Ferguson et al., 1987</link><!-- PMID 2881214 -->; <link linkend="bib148">Miller et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 11102360 -->), suggesting also a role in the proper specification of VPCs.</para>
            <para>
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> is upregulated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> signaling (<link linkend="bib95">Maloof and Kenyon, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9486792 -->) and is an excellent candidate for a direct target. Since
                overexpression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> does not result in gonad-independent
                vulval differentiation, it is unlikely to be the only target (<xref linkend="figure5"/>). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-17" role="_blank">egl-17</ulink></emphasis> is induced early in the induction
                process (<link linkend="bib15">Burdine et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9463355 -->; <link linkend="bib1">Ambros, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10101128 -->; <link linkend="bib139">Wang and Sternberg, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10419682 -->; <link linkend="bib30">Cui and Han, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12710960 -->; <link linkend="bib145">Yoo et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14752159 -->) and could be an early target of RAS-stimulated transcription.
                <link linkend="bib107">Romagnolo et al. (2002<!--  PMID 12074557-->)</link> used RNA from whole animals hybridized to
                microarrays to search for RAS-regulated genes and found 718; among these might be
                some that are physiologically relevant during vulval development.</para>
            <para>Mediator complex proteins, which link site-specific transcription factors to RNA
                polymerase, also are necessary for vulval development. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-25" role="_blank">lin-25</ulink></emphasis>
                and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sur-2" role="_blank">sur-2</ulink></emphasis> (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mdt-23" role="_blank">mdt-23</ulink></emphasis>) are defective in vulval
                induction and also have defects earlier and later during vulval development
                (<link linkend="bib41">Ferguson et al., 1987</link><!-- PMID 2881214 -->; <link linkend="bib138">Tuck and Greenwald, 1995</link><!--  PMID 7867931 -->; <link linkend="bib122">Singh
                and Han,1995</link><!-- PMID 7557379 -->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mdt-6" role="_blank">mdt-6</ulink></emphasis> is positive-acting (<link linkend="bib88">Kwon and Lee, 2001</link><!-- PMID 116885590 -->). It is striking that other Mediator components have
                negative effects, e.g., <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dpy-22" role="_blank">dpy-22</ulink></emphasis> (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mdt-12" role="_blank">mdt-12</ulink></emphasis>; <link linkend="bib98">Moghal et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12925583 -->; H. Sawa, unpublished observations). There are two
                extreme interpretations of this observation. First, there might be differential
                requirements for mediator components on distinct transcriptional targets. Second,
                there might be one main target for Mediator and there is a regulatory pathway
                acting among the Mediator components with some components acting in a positive and
                others in negative manner.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>WNT signaling and induction</title>
            <para>In addition to its role in VPC competence, activation of WNT signaling can
                increase the extent of vulval induction if the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> pathway is compromised
                (<link linkend="bib44">Gleason et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12023306 -->). It is not known whether WNT signaling can
                compensate for the complete absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> signaling.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Physiological inputs to vulval development</title>
        <para>The invariance of vulval development is not only due to the growth of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> under standardized laboratory conditions; however, when vulval development is partly compromised, a number of physiological effects are evident. <link linkend="bib39">Ferguson and Horvitz (1985<!-- PMID 3996896 -->)</link> observed that certain vulvaless mutations are suppressed by starvation during larval growth while others are suppressed by passage through the dauer phase. The suppression does not appear to correlate with genetic pathways, and might be due to some type of informational suppression (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_geneticsuppression/geneticsuppression.html" role="_blank">Genetic suppression</ulink>). Recently several other potentially physiological inputs (<link linkend="bib4">Battu et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12736202 -->; <link linkend="bib98">Moghal et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12925583 -->), and an important role for zinc have been identified (<link linkend="bib12">Bruinsma et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12015965 -->; <link linkend="bib144">Yoder et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14685271 -->).</para>
<?newpage?>
        <sect2>
            <title>G protein regulation</title>
            <para>The heterotrimeric G protein Gq (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-30;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-30</ulink>; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_heterotrimericGproteins/heterotrimericGproteins.html" role="_blank">Heterotrimeric G-proteins in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>) stimulates vulval induction under certain growth conditions, in particular growth in liquid (<link linkend="bib98">Moghal et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12925583 -->). Expression of activated <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-30;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-30</ulink> in neurons stimulates vulval induction. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-30;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-30</ulink> effect requires the voltage-gated calcium channel encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-19" role="_blank">egl-19</ulink></emphasis>. The site of action of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-19" role="_blank">egl-19</ulink></emphasis> for this effect is in muscle cells. These observations lead to the hypothesis that neuronal and muscle excitation can somehow affect vulval development. The positive signal from Gq acts in parallel to or downstream of RAS. Because the effect is of the magnitude of WNT signaling via <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=BAR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">BAR-1</ulink> <symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-catenin, it is possible that this is effect is via the WNT pathway (<link linkend="bib98">Moghal et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12925583 -->).</para>
            <para>A G protein coupled receptor, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SRA-13;class=protein" role="_blank">SRA-13</ulink>, acts negatively on vulval development via
                the G protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPA-5;class=protein" role="_blank">GPA-5</ulink> (<link linkend="bib4">Battu et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12736202 -->). Starvation decreases vulval
                induction, and this effect depends upon <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SRA-13;class=protein" role="_blank">SRA-13</ulink>. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sra-13" role="_blank">sra-13</ulink></emphasis> is
                expressed in chemosensory neurons as well as body-wall muscle (<link linkend="bib4">Battu et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12736202 -->) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gpa-5" role="_blank">gpa-5</ulink></emphasis> is also expressed in chemosensory
                neurons. The sites of action of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SRA-13;class=protein" role="_blank">SRA-13</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPA-5;class=protein" role="_blank">GPA-5</ulink> for vulval induction effects are
                not known. The relationship of the positive <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-30;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-30</ulink> (Gq) effect and negative <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPA-5;class=protein" role="_blank">GPA-5</ulink>
                effects is intriguing but not yet known. These findings highlight the importance of
                nematode physiology, revealed by growth conditions, on vulval development. The
                effect on vulval induction of growth in liquid (<link linkend="bib98">Moghal et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12925583 -->)
                and of starvation (<link linkend="bib4">Battu et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12736202 -->) were only revealed by using
                sensitized genetic backgrounds. I believe that there could be much plasticity lurking beneath the surface, a surface that can be scratched away by careful genetic analysis.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Zinc regulation</title>
            <para>Two genes identified by loss-of-function mutations that suppress activated <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-60;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-60</ulink>
                Ras encode cation diffusion facilitators that appear to regulate zinc. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CDF-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CDF-1</ulink> is a
                cation diffusion regulator, and has sites of action in the intestine as well as in
                the VPCs, consistent with it expression in both tissues (<link linkend="bib12">Bruinsma et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12015965 -->). Exogenous zinc negatively regulates <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> signaling (<link linkend="bib12">Bruinsma et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12015965 -->). SUR-7 encodes a distinct cation diffusion facilitator (<link linkend="bib144">Yoder et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14685271 -->). Yoder et al. (<link linkend="bib144">Yoder et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14685271 -->) argue
                that zinc regulation is at the level of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KSR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KSR-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink>, which somehow regulate
                LIN-45 Raf signaling (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RTKRasMAPKsignaling/RTKRasMAPKsignaling.html" role="_blank">RTKRas/MAP kinase signaling</ulink>).</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Negative regulation of induction</title>
        <para>A variety of negative regulators of vulval induction have been identified. Their roles
            in signal transduction by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> are described in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RTKRasMAPKsignaling/RTKRasMAPKsignaling.html" role="_blank">RTKRas/MAP kinase signaling</ulink>.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Nuclear negative regulators</title>
            <para>The synMuv genes are three classes (A, B and C) of broadly expressed nuclear
                proteins that in various combinations inhibit VPCs from adopting vulval fates.
                <link linkend="bib40">Ferguson and Horvitz (1989</link><!-- PMID 2806880 -->) described two redundant sets of genes,
                class A and B, where hermaphrodites defective in both A and B function have a
                Multivulva phenotype. Mutants defective in only A, or in only B, have normal vulval
                development. Molecular cloning revealed that many Class B synMuv genes encode
                proteins with mammalian orthologs that have been well-characterized as
                transcriptional regulators, including the synMuv genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-35" role="_blank">lin-35</ulink></emphasis>
                Rb , <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=efl-1" role="_blank">efl-1</ulink></emphasis> E2F, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hda-1" role="_blank">hda-1</ulink> </emphasis> histone
                deacytelase (<link linkend="bib94">Lu and Horvitz, 1998</link><!--  PMID 9875852 -->), as well as a zinc finger protein
                (<link linkend="bib96">Melendez and Greenwald, 2000</link><!-- PMID 10880475 -->) and components of the NuRD and SWI/SNF
                complexes (<link linkend="bib94">Lu and Horvitz, 1998</link><!--  PMID 9875852 -->; <link linkend="bib123">Solari and Ahringer, 2000</link><!--  PMID 10704416 -->; <link linkend="bib16">Ceol and Horvitz, 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib29">Cui et al., 2004</link><!--  PMID 15280233 -->). Other synMuv
                genes encode novel nuclear proteins.</para>
            <para>Epistasis experiments suggest that synMuv genes inhibit <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> pathway output
                (<link linkend="bib41">Ferguson et al., 1987</link>; <link linkend="bib68">Huang et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 8054684 -->). Site of action studies
                with synMuv genes suggest that they control a pathway of intercellular signaling
                from hyp7 to the VPCs, although no signal has been identified (<xref linkend="figure11"/>; <xref linkend="figure12"/>). <emphasis>lin-15AB</emphasis> and
                <emphasis>lin-37B</emphasis> mosaics suggested action not in the VPCs, and possibly
                in hyp7 (<link linkend="bib59">Herman and Hedgecock, 1990</link><!-- PMID 2234080 -->; <link linkend="bib58">Herman and Hedgecock, 1995</link><!--  PMID 8582642 -->); Mosaic analysis and tissue-specific rescue experiments indicate that the
                focus of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-35" role="_blank">lin-35</ulink></emphasis> is hyp7 (<link linkend="bib100">Myers and Greenwald, 2005</link><!-- PMID 15621535 -->). However, <emphasis>lin-36B</emphasis> mosaics suggest a site of action in
                the VPCs (<link linkend="bib136">Thomas and Horvitz, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10393123 -->), and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-15A" role="_blank">lin-15A</ulink></emphasis>
                mosaics and tissue-specific rescue experiments also suggest a VPC focus (A.
                Gonzalez-Serricchio and P. W. Sternberg, unpublished observations).</para>
	<mediaobject id="figure11" xreflabel="Figure 11">
                <imageobject><imagedata entityref="fig11" width="3in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject><phrase>Schematic transverse section through the developing vulva</phrase></textobject>
		&fig11legend;
	</mediaobject>
<literallayout></literallayout>
            <mediaobject id="figure12" xreflabel="Figure 12">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig12" width="4in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase>Synthetic multivulva mutants suggest signaling from hyp7 to VPCs </phrase>
                </textobject> &fig12legend; </mediaobject>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Signal transduction regulators</title>
            <para>Other negative regulators were identified as suppressors of hypomorphic mutations
                in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink>-RAS pathway components. These genes do not interact strongly with the
                synMuv genes, but do interact with each other. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sli-1" role="_blank">sli-1</ulink></emphasis>,
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-101" role="_blank">unc-101</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ark-1" role="_blank">ark-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gap-1" role="_blank">gap-1</ulink></emphasis>
                and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lip-1" role="_blank">lip-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib78">Jongeward et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 7789760 -->; <link linkend="bib90">Lee et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 8288128 -->; <link linkend="bib147">Yoon et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 7652556 -->; <link linkend="bib51">Hajnal et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9334333 -->;
                <link linkend="bib7">Berset et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11161219 -->; <link linkend="bib64">Hopper et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10949028 -->) are of this
                class. In addition, <link linkend="bib145">Yoo et al. (2004</link><!-- PMID 14752159 -->) found four additional negative
                regulators, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dpy-23" role="_blank">dpy-23</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lst-1" role="_blank">lst-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lst-2" role="_blank">lst-2</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lst-3" role="_blank">lst-3</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lst-4" role="_blank">lst-4</ulink></emphasis>. These four
                regulators, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lip-1" role="_blank">lip-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib7">Berset et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11161219 -->) are
                targets of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> lateral signaling.</para>
            <para>
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-101" role="_blank">unc-101</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=apm-1" role="_blank">apm-1</ulink></emphasis> each encode medium
                chains of the AP-1 adaptin, and these are inhibitory on vulval induction (<link linkend="bib90">Lee et
                al.,1994</link><!-- PMID 8288128 -->; <link linkend="bib119">Shim, 2000</link><!-- PMID 10930467 -->); while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> is a plausible target
                for these membrane trafficking proteins, the targets are not known.
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dpy-23" role="_blank">dpy-23</ulink></emphasis> encodes a medium chain of the AP-2 adaptin and is
                induced by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> (<link linkend="bib145">Yoo et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14752159 -->; see below).</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>-mediated lateral signaling</title>
        <para>The VPCs signal each other via a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>-mediated lateral signaling pathway. This
            pathway has two related roles: to prevent adjacent induced VPCs from both becoming
                1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>, and to induce VPCs that flank a
                1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> VPC to become 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> (<xref linkend="figure13"/>).</para>
                <mediaobject id="figure13" xreflabel="Figure 13">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig13" width="4in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Simple model of antagonism between 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> and 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> VPCs</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig13legend;</mediaobject>
        <sect2>
            <title>
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> genetics</title>
            <para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> is necessary and sufficient for specification of the 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> VPC fate (<link linkend="bib47">Greenwald et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6616618 -->). Null alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> lack 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> VPCs. Gain of function <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> mutants cause all six VPCs to generate 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> lineages, even in the absence of inductive signaling. As described in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_lin12Notch/lin12notch.html" role="_blank">LIN-12/Notch signaling in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> encodes a Notch-type transmembrane receptor (<link linkend="bib142">Yochem et al., 1988</link><!-- PMID 3419531 -->).</para>
            <para><emphasis>lin-12(lf)</emphasis> hermaphrodites have additional anchor cells, and
                this complicated somewhat the analysis of vulval induction (<link linkend="bib47">Greenwald et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6616618 -->). With two (or more) anchor cells, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> are 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P4.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P4.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.p</ulink> occasionally are 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> or one daughter is 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> like (<link linkend="bib128">Sternberg and Horvitz, 1989</link><!-- PMID 2548732 -->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Lateral signal</title>
            <para>The lateral signal involves at least three redundant genes, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=apx-1" role="_blank">apx-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lag-2" role="_blank">lag-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dsl-1" role="_blank">dsl-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib20">Chen and Greenwald, 2004</link><!-- PMID 14960273 -->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_lin12Notch/lin12notch.html" role="_blank">LIN-12/Notch signaling in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). APX-1 and LAG-2 are transmembrane ligands for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>. DSL-1 is a secreted ligand for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>. Expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lag-2" role="_blank">lag-2</ulink></emphasis> occurs in all VPCs prior to induction and is upregulated in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink>. Expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=apx-1" role="_blank">apx-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dsl-1" role="_blank">dsl-1</ulink></emphasis> appears to be initiated by induction of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink>. The main effect is to induce neighbors to become 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>, thereby inhibiting them from becoming 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>. The redundancy of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lag-2" role="_blank">lag-2</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dsl-1" role="_blank">dsl-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=apx-1" role="_blank">apx-1</ulink></emphasis> for VPC patterning appears to have prevented the discovery of their role by genetic screens. The targets of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> include a number of redundant negative regulators of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> signaling (<link linkend="bib145">Yoo et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14752159 -->; <xref linkend="figure14"/>).</para>
	    <mediaobject id="figure14" xreflabel="Figure 14">
	    <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig14" width="4in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase>Lateral signaling targets and negative regulation of LET-23 signaling</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig14legend; </mediaobject>
            <para>The pattern of VPC fates in a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-15" role="_blank">lin-15</ulink></emphasis> multitvulva mutant (1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>; <xref linkend="figure15"/>) is reminiscent of spacing patterns such as that of bristles in the insect abdomen and thus suggests a lateral inhibition mechanism whereby a specialized cell type (1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> VPC) inhibits adjacent cells from also becoming of that type and instead differentiating as some alternative (2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> VPCs). While adjacent 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> VPCs are common, adjacent 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> VPCs are rare. In a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-15" role="_blank">lin-15</ulink></emphasis> strain, which appears to have activat ed <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> signaling, a single VPC (e.g., <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink>) will become 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> in the absence of the gonad and of its neighbors (<link linkend="bib126">Sternberg, 1988</link><!-- PMID 3419532 -->). If there are two adjacent VPCs (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.p</ulink>), they will become 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>or 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>-1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>, with approximately equal probability. Thus, these cells signal each other.</para>
            <para>In the presence of the gonad, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> becomes 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.p</ulink> becomes 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>, indicating that the inductive
                signal can bias the stochastic lateral signaling among induced VPCs (<link linkend="bib126">Sternberg, 1988</link><!-- PMID 3419532 -->). Double mutant combinations among inductive signaling pathway
                genes and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> mutations support this view: a
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> loss-of-function mutation eliminates the lateral
                inhibition in a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-15" role="_blank">lin-15</ulink></emphasis> mutant resulting in all 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> VPCs (<link linkend="bib128">Sternberg and Horvitz, 1989</link><!-- PMID 2548732 -->).</para>
            <mediaobject id="figure15" xreflabel="Figure 15">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig15" width="4.5in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase>Lateral signaling</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig15legend; </mediaobject>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Coupling of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> signaling</title>
        <para>The antagonism of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> is fundamental to the specification of 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> and 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fates (<xref linkend="figure16"/>). As described above, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> activation leads to 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fates at high levels and 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> at low levels. The genetic requirements for this 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> specification has not been elucidated. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> lateral signaling is able to prevent adjacent cells from becoming 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> (<link linkend="bib126">Sternberg, 1988</link><!-- PMID 3419532 -->), and can induce a cell to become 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> (<link linkend="bib47">Greenwald et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6616618 -->; <link linkend="bib121">Simske and Kim, 1995</link><!-- PMID 7753169 -->; <link linkend="bib85">Koga and Ohshima, 1995</link><!-- PMID 7671826 -->). A presumptive 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> cell downregulates <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> protein (<link linkend="bib112">Shaye and Greenwald, 2002</link><!-- PMID: 12478297 -->). Conversely, a presumptive 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> cell downregulates <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> signaling (<link linkend="bib7">Berset et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11161219 -->; <link linkend="bib145">Yoo et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14752159 -->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> vulva development was the first case where the interplay of growth factor receptor and Notch signaling integration was discovered.</para>
        <para>Activation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> bypasses the requirement for the gonad or for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> (<link linkend="bib47">Greenwald
            et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6616618 -->; <link linkend="bib128">Sternberg and Horvitz, 1989</link><!-- PMID 2548732 -->). However, a strong
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> signal can override the effect of activated <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>, if a VPC is near the anchor
            cell (<link linkend="bib128">Sternberg and Horvitz, 1989</link><!-- PMID 2548732 -->), if <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-1" role="_blank">lin-1</ulink></emphasis> is
            removed (<link linkend="bib149">Beitel et al., 1995</link><!--PMID: 8543158-->), or if <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink>(EGF) is delivered by a heat shock construct
            (<link linkend="bib139">Wang and Sternberg, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10419682 -->). Validated targets of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> in presumptive
                2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> cells are
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lip-1" role="_blank">lip-1</ulink></emphasis>, encoding MAPK phosphatase (<link linkend="bib7">Berset et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11161219 -->), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dpy-23" role="_blank">dpy-23</ulink></emphasis> and the <emphasis>lst</emphasis> genes (<link linkend="bib145">Yoo et
            al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14752159 -->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lst-1" role="_blank">lst-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lst-2" role="_blank">lst-2</ulink></emphasis> and
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lst-4" role="_blank">lst-4</ulink></emphasis> also appear to be inhibited by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> (<xref linkend="figure14"/>), which creates the potential for interesting dynamics in the
            cross-t alk between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> signaling pathways.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Multiple redundancies program precision</title>
            <para>
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> VPC patterning involves multiple sources of
                information each of which would be capable, in principle, of generating a normal
                pattern. These include: the graded action of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-3" role="_blank">lin-3</ulink></emphasis> from the
                anchor cell, sequential signaling from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink> via <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>, sequential ROM-1-dependent
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> signaling; and non-equivalence of the VPCs due to HOX gene action. The fact
                that WNT signaling can increase vulval induction (<link linkend="bib44">Gleason et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12023306 -->) and that WNTs are expressed in the anchor cell (<link linkend="bib74">Inoue et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15369677 -->) raises the possibility that WNT signaling is another way in which the
                vulval might be induced. These pathways might act in combination to generate an
                exquisitely precise pattern. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> the graded anchor
                cell <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> signal and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>-mediated lateral signaling are the major players. In
                other species, the other pathways might predominate.</para>
                  <mediaobject id="figure16" xreflabel="Figure 16">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig16" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Model of VPC pattern formation</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig16legend;</mediaobject>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Patterning of adult cell types</title>
        <para>There are seven vulval cell types formed from the fusion of defined cells produced by
            vulval lineages: vulA, vulB1, vulB2, vulC, vulD, vulE and vulF. They each have distinct
            functions and patterns of gene expression (<link linkend="bib15">Burdine et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9463355 -->;
            <link linkend="bib111">Sharma-Kishore et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 9895317 -->; <link linkend="bib75">Inoue et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 14516686 -->; <link linkend="bib83">Kiroauc and Sternberg, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12710959 -->; <link linkend="bib76">Inoue et al., 2005</link><!--  PMID 15749820 -->). For example, the
            vulval muscles vm1 insert between the vulE and vulF cells, while the vm2 muscles insert
            between the vulC and vulD cells. The vulF cells are the main contact with the anchor
            cell and then uv1 (<link linkend="bib102">Newman et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8951077 -->; <link linkend="bib117">Sherwood and Sternberg, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12852849 -->).</para>
        <para>Transcription factors encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-38" role="_blank">egl-38</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib17">Chamberlin et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9374390 -->), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cog-1" role="_blank">cog-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib106">Palmer et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12482710 -->), and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-11" role="_blank">lin-11</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib43">Freyd et al., 1990</link><!--  PMID 1970421 -->) are responsible in part for the identities of specific vulval cell types. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-38" role="_blank">egl-38</ulink></emphasis> is necessary for expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-3" role="_blank">lin-3</ulink></emphasis> in vulF cells (<link linkend="bib19">Chang et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10074449 -->), and is involved in repressing <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-17" role="_blank">egl-17</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=zmp-1" role="_blank">zmp-1</ulink></emphasis> in these same cells (<link linkend="bib76">Inoue et al., 2005</link>). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cog-1" role="_blank">cog-1</ulink></emphasis>, which is expressed in all the terminal vulval cells but with different levels and dynamics, regulates gene expression in vulB1, vulB2, vulC, vulD and vulE (<link linkend="bib106">Palmer et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12482710 -->; <link linkend="bib76">Inoue et al., 2005</link><!--  PMID 15749820 -->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-11" role="_blank">lin-11</ulink></emphasis>, which is more highly expressed in the vulC and vulD cells than in vulA and vulB cells, regulates gene expression in mature vulval cell types (<link linkend="bib43">Freyd et al., 1990</link><!-- PMID 1970421-->; <link linkend="bib49">Gupta et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12736204 -->). The transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-29;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-29</ulink> has been proposed to regulate vulval cell-type genes in a temporal window (<link linkend="bib101">Newman et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10556057 -->; <link linkend="bib75">Inoue et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 14516686-->; <link linkend="bib76">Inoue et al., 2005</link><!--  PMID 15749820 -->).</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>&#x000A0;1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> lineage</title>
            <para>The 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> lineage generates two cell
                types, vulE and vulF, in a mirror symmetric pattern EFFE around the anchor cell
                    (<xref linkend="figure17"/>). The anchor cell is necessary for this pattern
                after it induces the 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> VPC (<link linkend="bib140">Wang and
                Sternberg, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11060231 -->). WNT receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-17;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-17</ulink> is necessary as well, but the
                phenotype of a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-17" role="_blank">lin-17</ulink></emphasis> mutation has only been seen in the
                absence of the anchor cell. Transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-38;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-38</ulink> is necessary for
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-3" role="_blank">lin-3</ulink></emphasis> expression in the vulF cells (<link linkend="bib19">Chang et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10074449 -->), which signals to the uterine uv1 cells (<xref linkend="figure18"/>). The
                peptidase-like protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-26;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-26</ulink> is expressed in the membranes of vulE cells and is
                necessary for vulF morphogenesis (<link linkend="bib57">Hanna-Rose and Han, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11784109 -->).
                Transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=COG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">COG-1</ulink>, expressed in most vulva cells, has a related phenotype
                to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-26;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-26</ulink> (<link linkend="bib106">Palmer et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12482710 -->), but the relationship among these
                genes is not known.</para>
	<literallayout></literallayout>
            <mediaobject id="figure17" xreflabel="Figure 17">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig17" width="3.5in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase>Patterning of the 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> lineage</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig17legend; </mediaobject>
<literallayout></literallayout>
            <mediaobject id="figure18" xreflabel="Figure 18">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig18" width="4in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase>uvl specification</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig18legend; </mediaobject>
        </sect2>
<?newpage?>
        <sect2>
            <title>Polarity of 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> lineages</title>
            <para>The cell division pattern and cell fates of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> lineages are mirror
                images, ABCD and DCBA respectively (<xref linkend="figure19"/>). The asymmetry
                within in each of these lineages is independent of the gonad, as for example, a
                single VPC in a gonad-ablated <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-23" role="_blank">let-23</ulink>(gf)</emphasis> mutant has asymmetry
                (<link linkend="bib81">Katz et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8552080 -->). WNT signaling, likely from the gonad, reverses
                polarity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> (<link linkend="bib74">Inoue et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15369677 -->). The WNT protein MOM-2 is
                expressed in the anchor cell (<link linkend="bib74">Inoue et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15369677 -->) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-44;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-44</ulink> might be
                expressed in the anchor cell or uterus based on weak GFP signal (<link linkend="bib74">Inoue et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15369677 -->) and in situ hybridization (Y. Kohara, personal communication).
                There are two parallel genetic pathways: one involves the WNT protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-44;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-44</ulink> and the
                Frizzled type receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-17;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-17</ulink>; the second involves the WNT MOM-2 and the Ryk type
                receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-18;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-18</ulink> (<link linkend="bib41">Ferguson et al., 1987</link><!-- PMID 2881214 -->; <link linkend="bib129">Sternberg and Horvitz, 1988</link><!-- PMID 3181641 -->; <link linkend="bib109">Sawa et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8804313 -->; <link linkend="bib74">Inoue et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15369677 -->).
                The levels of TCF/LEF protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=POP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink>, a WNT target, correlates with WNT signaling:
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink> daughters express <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=POP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> in a High-Low (HL) pattern, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P5.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P5.p</ulink> granddaughters
                express in an HLHL pattern, while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> has a LH then a LHLH pattern of protein level
                (<link linkend="bib32">Deshpande et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID 15649465-->). Thus, the pattern of POP-1 expression in
                the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> neage is reversed from the default by WNT signaling through <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-17;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-17</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-18;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-18</ulink>.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
            <mediaobject id="figure19" xreflabel="Figure 19">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig19" width="3.3in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase>Polarity of P7.p2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> lineage</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig19legend; </mediaobject>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>The vulval-uterine connection</title>
        <para>The anchor cell is the key organizer of the vulva and the connection to the somatic gonad (<link linkend="bib102">Newman et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8951077 -->; <xref linkend="figure1"/>). Once specified during the L2 molt (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_hermcellfate/hermcellfate.html" role="_blank">Hermaphrodite cell-fate specification</ulink>), the anchor cell induces and patterns the vulva via <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink>. The anchor cell then patterns the ventral uterus, inducing the uterine pi cells via LAG-2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> signaling (<link linkend="bib104">Newman et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 7768171 -->; <link linkend="bib22">Cinar et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 11518514 -->; <xref linkend="figure20"/>).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure20" xreflabel="Figure 20">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig20" width="4in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Uterine picell induction</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig20legend;</mediaobject>
        <sect2>
            <title>pi cell induction and function</title>
            <para>
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-13" role="_blank">egl-13</ulink></emphasis> (a.k.a. <emphasis>cog-2</emphasis>), which encodes Sox
                domain transcription factor expressed in the uterine pi cells, is necessary for the
                fusion of the anchor cell and the utse (<link linkend="bib56">Hanna-Rose and Han, 1999</link><!-- PMID 9834196 -->; <link linkend="bib22">Cinar et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 11518514 -->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-11" role="_blank">lin-11</ulink></emphasis>, another transcription
                factor, is also required for differentiation of pi cells progeny and is regulated by
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> signaling in pi cells (<link linkend="bib103">Newman et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 11114514 -->). Sumoylation of
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-11;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-11</ulink> is necessary for its function in pi cell specification (<link linkend="bib11">Broday et al.,
                2004</link><!-- PMID 15466489 -->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>uv1 induction</title>
            <para>The anchor cell induces six of 12 VU granddaughters to become pi cells, which are
                distinguished from the uninduced VU.xx cells by the lineage they generate. The pi
                cell undergo only one round of cell divisions while the uninduced cells undergo two
                rounds of cell division. The pi cells generate the four uv1 cells that connect to
                the vulF cells. Specification of the uv1 cells requires vulF cells, which express
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-3" role="_blank">lin-3</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib19">Chang et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10074449 -->). The anchor cell
                apparently responds to cues from vulF (and possibly negative cues from vulE) to
                locate the vulF cells (<link linkend="bib117">Sherwood and Sternberg, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12852849 -->). Meanwhile, the
                anchor cell helps pattern the vulE and vulF cells via <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-60;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-60</ulink> RAS (<link linkend="bib140">Wang and
                Sternberg, 2000</link><!-- PMID 1106023 -->). Moreover, a WNT signal, likely from the anchor cell
                reverses the polarity of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7.p</ulink> lineage (<link linkend="bib74">Inoue et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15369677 -->;
                <link linkend="bib32">Deshpande et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID 15649465-->). The anchor cell then fuses with the utse
                syncytium (<link linkend="bib102">Newman et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8951077 -->). The relative timing of the signaling
                involved in these events has not been fully resolved.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>AC invasion</title>
            <para>The anchor cell breaks down the basement membranes, secreted by the gonad and the
                epidermis, that separates these two tissues. The anchor cell then extends a process
                towards the developing 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> lineage.
                This invasion requires the vulva; although in ~20% of vulvaless animals, the anchor
                cell will nonetheless invade the basement membrane (<link linkend="bib117">Sherwood and Sternberg,
                2003</link><!-- PMID 12852849 -->). The anchor cell can pass by the vulE cells and locate the vulF
                cells. The signal from the vulval to the invading AC acts at a distance because a
                distant 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> VPC, indicated by
                expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-17" role="_blank">egl-17</ulink>::yfp</emphasis> during the L3 stage, can attract
                extension of the anchor cell.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Morphogenesis</title>
        <para>During the L4 larval stage, the vulval cells move towards the anchor cell, invaginate, fuse into seven toroids (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_cellfusion/cellfusion.html" role="_blank">Cell fusion</ulink>), and during the L4-to-adult molt evert. The epidermal cells of the vulva organize the egg-laying system.</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Invagination</title>
            <para>The ability of the vulval invagination to form is regulated by eight <emphasis>sqv</emphasis> genes (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sqv-1" role="_blank">sqv-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sqv-2" role="_blank">sqv-2</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sqv-3" role="_blank">sqv-3</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sqv-4" role="_blank">sqv-4</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sqv-5" role="_blank">sqv-5</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sqv-6" role="_blank">sqv-6</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sqv-7" role="_blank">sqv-7</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sqv-8" role="_blank">sqv-8</ulink></emphasis>; <link linkend="bib61">Herman et al., 1999</link>:<!-- PMID 9927677 -->). Hermaprodites with decreased <emphasis>sqv</emphasis> function have only a rudimentary invagination (SQuashed Vulva phenotype). The <emphasis>sqv</emphasis> genes encodes enzymes of a glycosaminoglycan biosynthesis (<link linkend="bib60">Herman and Horvitz, 1999</link><!-- PMID 9927678 -->; <link linkend="bib6">Berninsone et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11259660 -->; <link linkend="bib69">Hwang and Horvitz, 2002a</link><!-- PMID 12391314 -->; <link linkend="bib70">Hwang and Horvitz, 2002b</link><!-- PMID 12391315 -->; <link linkend="bib71">Hwang et al., 2003a</link><!-- PMID 12761549 -->; <link linkend="bib72">Hwang et al., 2003b</link><!-- PMID 12584198 -->). The <emphasis>sqv</emphasis> genes are expressed broadly in the vulva with the exception of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sqv-4" role="_blank">sqv-4</ulink></emphasis>, which is expressed in vulC, D, E and F (<link linkend="bib70">Hwang and Horvitz, 2002b</link><!-- PMID 12391315 -->).</para> 
            <para>Morphogenesis also involves cytoskeletal reorganization, and proteins such as the ARL2 ortholog <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EVL-20;class=protein" role="_blank">EVL-20</ulink> (<link linkend="bib2">Antoshechkin and Han, 2002</link><!-- PMID 12015966 -->). The Rac proteins encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mig-2" role="_blank">mig-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ced-10" role="_blank">ced-10</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib84">Kishore and Sundaram, 2002</link><!--  PMID 11784116 -->) are necessary for appropriate morphogenesis of the vulva. The different vul cells extend processes toward the developing vulval lumen, contact each other and fuse to form toroidal adult vulval cells (<link linkend="bib111">Sharma-Kishore et al. 1999</link><!-- PMID 9895317 -->). A plexin homolog (a semaphorin receptor) is expressed sequentially from vulF to vulA as the toroids fuse (<link linkend="bib31">Dalpe et al., 2005</link><!--  PMID 15716342 -->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Organization of neurons and muscles</title>
            <para>The vulval epithelium organizes the development of the muscles and neurons that
                mediate egg-laying (<link linkend="bib93">Li and Chalfie, 1990</link><!-- PMID 2344407 -->). This is most obviously seen
                in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dig-1" role="_blank">dig-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants in which the gonad is shifted anteriorly and
                the vulva, vulval muscles and neurons are all similarly shifted anteriorly (<link linkend="bib137">Thomas et al., 1990</link><!-- PMID 2401010 -->). Specific gene products expressed in subsets of vulval
                cells direct details of development of individual neurons.
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=bam-2" role="_blank">bam-2</ulink></emphasis> is necessary for axonal branch termination of the VC
                motoneurons, and is expressed in the vulF cells (<link linkend="bib28">Colavita and Tessier-Lavigne,
                2003</link><!-- PMID 14551437 -->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syg-1" role="_blank">syg-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syg-2" role="_blank">syg-2</ulink></emphasis> are
                required for synapse formation by the HSN neurons (<link linkend="bib115">Shen and Bargmann, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12628183 -->; <link linkend="bib116">Shen et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15035988 -->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syg-2" role="_blank">syg-2</ulink></emphasis> is expressed
                in vulE cells and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=syg-1" role="_blank">syg-1</ulink></emphasis> in the HSNs.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Concluding remarks</title>
        <para>There is now a reasonable conceptual model for understanding how the pattern of VPCs is established, but many components remain to be identified and the precise relationship among many of the genes has not been established. By contrast, there is only a rudimentary model for how the pattern of the seven vulval cell types are established, and even less of a picture of how the vulval cells undergo morphogenesis to form the adult structure. Similarly, our understanding of the control of timing of vulval development is also incomplete, and the relationship of the cell cycle to fate specification remains intriguing. In spite of these limitations, the extensive knowledge of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> vulval development makes it an interesting case for computational modeling studies (e.g., <link linkend="bib42">Fisher et al., 2005</link><!--  PMID 15684055 -->). The precision of the wild-type pattern of VPC fates stands in stark contrast to the variable phenotypes of many mutants and perturbations; I view these phenotypes as providing a rich source of information about the underlying mechanisms and their dynamics.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Acknowledgments</title>
        <para>I am grateful to all my colleagues over the past 25 years who have studied vulval development or at least been willing to discuss it, especially Bob Horvitz, John Sulston, Judith Kimble, Chip Ferguson, Iva Greenwald, Victor Ambros, John White, Bill Fixsen, Jim Thomas, Tim Schedl, Stuart Kim, Meera Sundaram, Hitoshi Sawa, Alex Hajnal, Ira Herskowitz, Geraldine Seydoux, David Eisenmann, and in my laboratory, Raffi Aroian, Russell Hill, Gregg Jongeward, Min Han, Hiroyuki Mori, Andy Golden, Paul Kayne, Linda Huang, Helen Chamberlin, Jane Mendel, Junho Lee, Kyria Tietze, Robert Palmer, Wendy Katz, Ralf Sommer, Anna Newman, Giovanni Lesa, Jing Liu, Tom Clandinin, Marie-Anne Felix, Keith Brown, Minqin Wang, Pheobe Tzou, Yvonne Hajdu-Cronin, Chris Lacenere, Charles Yoon, Neil Hopper, Chieh Chang, Nadeem Moghal, Rene Garcia, Aidyl Gonzalez-Serricchio, Martha Kirouac, Shahla Gharib, Bhagwati Gupta, David Sherwood, Byung Hwang, Takao Inoue, Cheryl Van Buskirk, Jolene Fernandes, Ted Ririe, David Goulet, and Edo Israeli. I thank Cheryl Van Buskirk and Iva Greenwald for helpful editorial comments.</para>
        <para>I am grateful to the following sources that funded vulval development research in my laboratory: Searle Foundation (1988-1991); National Institutes of Health HD23690 (1988 -2000), March of Dimes (1988-1994), National Science Foundation (1988-1991), U.S. Army Breast Cancer Research Program (1992-1997) and the Howard Hughes Medical Institute (1989-present), as well as postdoctoral fellowships from American Cancer Society, Human Frontier Science Program, Life Sciences Research Foundation, Lymphoma and Leukemia Society, Damon Runyon Cancer Research Foundation, California Breast Cancer Research Program, European Molecular Biology Organization, National Institutes of Health, U.S.A. I am an Investigator with the <ulink url="http://www.hhmi.org/" role="_blank">Howard Hughes Medical Institute</ulink>.</para>
	</sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
		&WBVulva_Refs;
		<para/>
	</sect1>
</article>