<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 2. Punnett square showing normal progeny genotypes and phenotypes that result from selfing a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dpy-18" role="_blank">dpy-18</ulink>/eT1 III</emphasis>; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-46" role="_blank">unc-46</ulink>/eT1 V</emphasis> heterozygote</title>
	<para>Phenotypes are indicated for each progeny class. Genotypes for gametes and zygotes are given in gene and rearrangement names according to standard nomenclature, and in drawings representing normal and translocation chromosomes with genetic markers in place. The normal LG III is shown as a black bar, with a vertical line indicating the position of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dpy-18" role="_blank">dpy-18</ulink></emphasis> mutation. The normal LG V is shown as a shaded bar, with a vertical line indicating the position of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-46" role="_blank">unc-46</ulink></emphasis> mutation. The half-translocation <emphasis>eT1 (III)</emphasis> is shown as a half-black, half-shaded bar with a vertical line indicating the position of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-36" role="_blank">unc-36</ulink></emphasis> mutation caused by the translocation breakpoint on LG III. The half-translocation <emphasis>eT1 (V)</emphasis> is shown as a half-black, half-shaded bar with no vertical line. Boxes of the square representing viable progeny are unshaded. Boxes representing aneuploid progeny, all of which arrest during development, are shaded. All wild-type progeny are heterozygous for the translocation chromosomes and the normal chromosomes. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-36" role="_blank">unc-36</ulink></emphasis> progeny are <emphasis>eT1</emphasis> homozygotes, and Dpy Unc progeny are <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dpy-18" role="_blank">dpy-18</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-46" role="_blank">unc-46</ulink></emphasis> homozygotes. Aneuploid progeny account for 10/16ths of the total.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>