<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 3.Neuronal specification programs can be divided into genetically distinct steps</title>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">(A)</emphasis> "X" and "Y" indicate a gene regulatory factor(s) that determine pan-neuronal ("1") versus cell type specific characters ("2", "3"). Factor Y (which should be considered not necessarily as a single factor but a combination of several regulatory factors that form a specific "code") induces neuron-class specific features both directly ("2") and indirectly, via other gene regulatory factors ("3"; factors Z1, Z2, etc.). The principle of a cell-fate determinant acting both directly and indirectly on terminal differentiation markers is a widespread theme. 
	
	One example is shown in panel B. Other examples include the organ selector gene <emphasis>pha-4</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib24">Gaudet and Mango, 2002</link>), the <emphasis>unc-86</emphasis> gene (<link linkend="bib21">Finney and Ruvkun, 1990</link>; <link linkend="bib97">Xue et al., 1993</link>; <link linkend="bib18">Duggan et al., 1998</link>) or, in other systems, the eye-selector Pax-6/eyeless (<link linkend="bib25">Gehring, 2002</link>). <emphasis role="bold">(B,C)</emphasis> Examples and elaborations of the concept shown in panel A. <emphasis role="bold">(B)</emphasis> Differentiation of the AIY interneuron class. TTX-3 and CEH-10 proteins bind directly as a heterodimer to the <emphasis>cis</emphasis>-regulatory region of terminal differentiation marker genes such as the genes coding for vesicular neurotransmitter transporters (<emphasis>unc-17</emphasis>), neurotransmitter receptors (<emphasis>gar-2</emphasis> and others) and scores of other genes identified by genome wide searches (<link linkend="bib89">Wenick and Hobert, 2004</link>). TTX-3 and CEH-10 also activate intermediate factors such as CEH-23, which are required for the expression of specific subfeature of the neuron (<link linkend="bib1">Altun-Gultekin et al., 2001</link>). The "?" indicates that the <emphasis>wrk-1</emphasis> gene is expressed in a <emphasis>ttx-3/ceh-10</emphasis> dependent manner, but contains no <emphasis>ttx-3/ceh-10</emphasis> binding motif, hence invoking an intermediate transcription factor. <emphasis role="bold">(C)</emphasis> Differentiation of the ASE neuron class, composed of ASEL and ASER. Both cells are bilaterally symmetric in terms of morphology and the expression of many terminal differentiation markers (such as <emphasis>flp-6</emphasis> or <emphasis>hen-1</emphasis>, as well as many others), yet express distinct chemoreceptors, encoded by the <emphasis>gcy</emphasis> genes.  A bistable loop composed of transcription factors and miRNAs (<link linkend="bib41">Johnston et al. 2005</link>) drives differentiation into the ASEL state (<emphasis>gcy-7</emphasis> expression) or the ASER state (<emphasis>gcy-5</emphasis> expression).</para>
	</formalpara>
</caption>