<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 5. Sequential repression of neuronal fates</title>
        <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">(A)</emphasis> Cascades of sequentially acting negative regulatory factors
            induce specific cell fates. Left panel: The presence of "A" in a given cell type induces
            a given cell fate, exemplified by gene "C" through repression of factor B, which is a
            repressor of C. A selected set of examples in which this scheme has been found to apply,
            namely in ventral cord motorneurons in vertebrates (V1 motorneurons; <link linkend="bib58">Muhr et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID: 11290324 -->) and worms DB-type motorneurons (<link linkend="bib20">Esmaeili et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID: 11861469 -->),
            worm chemosensory neurons (ASEL neuron; <link linkend="bib12">Chang et al., 2003</link><!--  PMID: 12952888 -->) and worm
            postdeirid neurons ("PD fate") formed from the V5 ectoblasts are shown. In the case of
            the DB motorneurons, the VAB-7 protein not only inhibits the <emphasis>unc-4</emphasis>
            gene, but also positively regulates DB fate (X = <emphasis>vab-7</emphasis>). In the
            case of the ASE neurons, latent transcriptional activation is conferred by the CHE-1 Zn
            finger protein (X= <emphasis>che-1</emphasis>). Its activity is sequentially repressed
            and de-repressed by <emphasis>cog-1</emphasis>, <emphasis>lim-6</emphasis> and other
            repressors (<link linkend="bib12">Chang et al., 2003</link><!--  PMID: 12952888 -->; <link linkend="bib11">Chang et al., 2004</link><!--  PMID: 15306811 -->).
                <emphasis role="bold">(B)</emphasis> Evolvability of gene expression profiles based on
            sequential repression. An ontogenetic and/or phylogenetic ground state is defined by the
            expression of set of characters (circles indicate the expression of the character).
            During development and/or evolution (indicated by arrows), sequential repression can
            create diverse cell fates, which are defined by the cell-type specific combinatorial
            expression of a subset of the characters. </para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>