<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'nervfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'nervfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'nervfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'nervfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'nervfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'nervfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'nervfig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'nervfig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'nervfig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'nervfig5leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY nervous_Refs SYSTEM 'nervrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="nervous_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
	
	<title>Specification of the nervous system<footnote>
<para>Edited by Erik M. Jorgensen and Joshua M. Kaplan. Last revised July 22, 2005. Published August 8, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Hobert, O. Specification of the nervous system (August 8, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.12.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 Oliver Hobert. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
</footnote>
        </title>

        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 7/22/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory> 
-->
        <author>
            <firstname>Oliver</firstname>
            <surname>Hobert<remark><footnote>
	    <para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:or38@columbia.edu">or38@columbia.edu</ulink></para>
                    </footnote></remark></surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biophysics, Columbia University Medical Center, New York, NY 10032 USA</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Nervous systems are characterized by an astounding degree of cellular diversity. The
            nematode</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">has served as a valuable model
            system to define the genetic programs that serve to generate cellular diversity in the
            nervous system. This review discusses neuronal diversity in</emphasis>
            <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">and provides an overview of the molecular mechanisms that
            define and specify neuronal cell types in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans.</emphasis></emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
    
    <sect1>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>The nervous system represents the most complex organ of
            <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. It is the organ with the most cells (302 neurons and 56
            glial cells make up 37% of the somatic cells in a hermaphrodite) and the largest
            cellular diversity (at least 118 different neuron classes). Its cellular complexity
            makes the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> nervous system a prime model system to study a
            central question in developmental neurobiology, namely how neuronal diversity is
            genetically programmed. This question can be broken down into four separate steps that
            will be discussed in this chapter. First, a cell must make a global choice between
            neuronal and non-neuronal fate. Second, specific neuronal lineage
            decisions must be made. Third, neurons must be instructed to
            terminally differentiate into specific classes after their last cell division. Fourth,
            within defined classes of neurons that share many different properties, subtle but
            critical differences between individual class members must be established. I will give a
            brief summary and several examples of molecular mechanisms that are involved in neuronal
            specification on these levels. Rather than comprehensively discussing all known neuronal
            specification genes, I will try to carve out a few general principles of neuronal
            specification, using selected examples. Many aspects of neuron specification in
            <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have been discussed in several previous reviews to which
            the reader is referred for more in-depth discussions (<link linkend="bib68">Ruvkun, 1997</link>; <link linkend="bib52">Melkman and Sengupta, 2004</link><!-- PMID 14732394 -->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Neuronal vs. non-neuronal</title>
        <para>At first sight, perhaps the most striking difference between neuronal specification in
            <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and many other well characterized systems concerns the
            lineage history of individual neurons. While in many species the nervous system
            originates from defined precursor cells in specific regions of the developing embryo, a
            brief look at the lineage of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> illustrates, strikingly,
            that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> neurons are largely non-clonally derived from many
            different lineages (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). However, in analogy to vertebrate
            neuronal development (<link linkend="bib29">Hemmati-Brivanlou and Melton, 1997</link><!-- PMID 9056707 -->), it is
            conceivable that non-neuronal cells produced within largely neuron-producing lineages
            may be derived from a "neuronal ground state", which would be actively repressed in
            non-neuronal cells. Consistent with such a notion, mutants have been described in which
            non-neuronal cells "revert" to a neuronal fate. For example, in animals that lack the
            basic helix-loop-helix (bHLH) factor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-22" role="_blank">lin-22</ulink></emphasis> or the Zn finger
            transcription factor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-26" role="_blank">lin-26</ulink></emphasis>, specific sets of hypodermal cells
            inappropriately adopt a neuronal fate (<link linkend="bib35">Horvitz et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6586368 -->; <link linkend="bib45">Labouesse et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 7956818 -->; <link linkend="bib95">Wrischnik and Kenyon, 1997</link><!-- PMID 9247331 -->; <xref linkend="figure2"/>A, B). Moreover, depletion of the transcriptional co-factor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=p300;class=Variation" role="_blank">p300</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cbp-1" role="_blank">cbp-1</ulink></emphasis>
            de-represses neuronal fate in many cell types (<link linkend="bib77">Shi and Mello, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9531533 -->).
            Lastly, an embryonic induction mediated by the Notch gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> can
            be considered a diversification from a neuronal ground state; in the absence of this
            induction both bilaterally homologous <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABara;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABara</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABala;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABala</ulink> lineages produce only neurons,
            while in the presence of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis>, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABara;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABara</ulink> lineage produces neuronal
            and non-neuronal cells (<link linkend="bib38">Hutter and Schnabel, 1994</link><!-- PMID 7925009 -->). Taken together, in
            analogy to the vertebrate system, neuronal fate may be the "default" specification
            program in many lineages that is modified through the action of specific gene products.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig1" width="5.6in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 1</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig1legend; </mediaobject>

            <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig2" width="2.9in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase> figure 2</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig2legend; </mediaobject>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Neuron lineage specification</title>
        <para>Once a lineage is fated to produce neurons, several genes are required to determine
            the type of neuronal lineage program that is executed. Consequently, in the absence of
            these genes, neuroblasts are either not specified correctly or undergo aberrant lineage
            patterns. Genes that fall into this category include the classic examples of the
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-86" role="_blank">unc-86</ulink></emphasis> homeobox gene and the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-32" role="_blank">lin-32</ulink></emphasis> bHLH gene
            (reviewed in <link linkend="bib68">Ruvkun, 1997</link>); more recently described examples include the
            <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> NeuroD homolog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cnd-1" role="_blank">cnd-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib27">Hallam et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10976055 -->), the <emphasis>daughterless</emphasis> homolog
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hlh-2" role="_blank">hlh-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib64">Portman and Emmons, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11076762 -->) and the
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pag-3" role="_blank">pag-3</ulink></emphasis> Zn finger factor (<link linkend="bib7">Cameron et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 11923211 -->). While
            all genes in this category act by definition in neuroblasts to affect descendants of
            these blast cells, it is notable that some of the genes have also later roles in
            terminal neuron differentiation. For example, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-86" role="_blank">unc-86</ulink></emphasis> affects the
            lineage that generates the touch sensory neurons, but also acts in the mature touch
            neurons to directly regulate the expression of terminal differentiation features
            (<link linkend="bib10">Chalfie and Sulston, 1981</link><!-- PMID 7227647 -->; <link linkend="bib18">Duggan et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9735371 -->). A similar
            scenario holds for the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-32" role="_blank">lin-32</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hlh-2" role="_blank">hlh-2</ulink></emphasis> bHLH
            genes (<link linkend="bib64">Portman and Emmons, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11076762 -->). Re-utilization, or co-option, of
            transcription factors in different contexts is a common theme in many developmental
            pathways. </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Neuron class specification</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>General considerations about neuron classification</title>
            <para>If one wishes to discuss the genetic specification of individual neuron classes,
                it is important to first consider what defines a neuron class. The most trivial
                classification of neurons divides them into sensory, inter- and motorneurons.
                However, there is little lineage relation among neurons that are predominantly of
                the sensory-, inter- or motorneuron type in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. That is,
                there is no defined neuroblast that exclusively produces each class. Nevertheless,
                genetic analysis has revealed two common genetic specification programs. The
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=daf-19" role="_blank">daf-19</ulink></emphasis> transcription factor was found to be required for the
                development of specific differentiated aspects of all ciliated sensory neurons, even
                though most of them are unrelated by lineage (<link linkend="bib80">Swoboda et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10882127 -->). The
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cnd-1" role="_blank">cnd-1</ulink></emphasis> bHLH transcription factor is required for ventral nerve
                cord (VNC) motorneuron specification (<link linkend="bib27">Hallam et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10976055 -->). These
                observations indicate that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=daf-19" role="_blank">daf-19</ulink></emphasis> and
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cnd-1" role="_blank">cnd-1</ulink></emphasis> may sample lineage specific cues (e.g. by having complex
                promoters, responsive to transcription factors produced in different lineages) to
                drive a specific type of differentiation program in cells derived from distinct lineages.</para>
		
            <para>Another broadly applied classification of neurons is based on the type of
                neurotransmitter that a neuron produces ("neurotransmitter phenotype"). However,
                    <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> neurons with the same neurotransmitter phenotype
                show little if any lineage relation. Also, there are as yet no common specification
                programs identified for the complete set of neurons classified by neurotransmitter
                phenotypes. Rather, the neurons in this classification scheme appear to be generated
                in a "mosaic" manner, best illustrated by the 26 GABAergic neurons. Two defining
                features of GABAergic neurons are their production of a GABA-producing enzyme
                (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis>) and a vesicular GABA transporter
                (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-47" role="_blank">unc-47</ulink></emphasis>). GABAergic ventral cord motorneurons require the
                transcription factor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-30" role="_blank">unc-30</ulink></emphasis> to express
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-47" role="_blank">unc-47</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib40">Jin et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 7997265 -->; <link linkend="bib19">Eastman et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10414952 -->). However, other GABAergic neurons do
                not express <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-30" role="_blank">unc-30</ulink></emphasis> and require a different set of transcription
                factors to express the GABAergic phenotype. For example, the GABAergic <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVL;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVL</ulink>
                neurons require the homeobox gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lim-6" role="_blank">lim-6</ulink></emphasis> to express
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis>, but not <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-47" role="_blank">unc-47</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib34">Hobert et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10068647 -->). Although expressing <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lim-6" role="_blank">lim-6</ulink></emphasis>, the RME neuron
                class does not require <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lim-6" role="_blank">lim-6</ulink></emphasis> to express the GABAergic fate.</para>
            <para>Another classification of neurons that relates directly to neuronal specification
                goes along the lines of functional units. In the fly nervous system, neurons and
                support cells that form a sensory sensillum derive from a common sublineage that are
                jointly specified by gene regulatory programs (<link linkend="bib56">Modolell, 1997</link><!-- PMID 9171442 -->). In
                contrast, cells that form specific types of sensory sensilla in worms (neuron,
                sheath, socket) rarely have a common lineage history (<xref linkend="figure1"/>)
                with the notable exception of the postdeirid sensory sensillum (<xref linkend="figure2"/>C). The V5.pa neuroblast creates a sensory neuron, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PDE;class=Cell" role="_blank">PDE</ulink>, its
                sheath (PDEsh) and socket (PDEso), but also a different type of sensory neuron, PVD.
                Hence, the V5.pa lineage is not specialized to exclusively produce components of a
                sensory sensillum. However, genetic removal of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-86" role="_blank">unc-86</ulink></emphasis>
                homeobox gene causes the aberrant production of an extra <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PDE;class=Cell" role="_blank">PDE</ulink> neuron at the expense
                of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PVD;class=Cell" role="_blank">PVD</ulink> neuron (<link linkend="bib10">Chalfie and Sulston, 1981</link><!-- PMID 7227647 -->; <xref linkend="figure2"/>C). Therefore, the lineage is now transformed to only produce
                sensory sensillum components. It is perhaps a common principle that there is an
                underlying, perhaps ancient, relationship between cells of a given lineage branch
                (in the case of the V5.pa lineage branch, a sensory sensillum fate), but
                transcriptional regulators (e.g., <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-86" role="_blank">unc-86</ulink></emphasis>) are "superimposed" onto this lineage to diversify individual cell types within this
                lineage. This is the same principle as mentioned above for neuronal vs. non-neuronal
                fate programs; the latter may be superimposed onto a neuronal ground state.</para>

            <para>A more refined classification of neuronal cell types does not go along the lines of sensory vs. inter vs. motorneuron, but rather makes use of classifying neurons based on specific anatomical features, such as axodendritic morphology, cell body placement and synaptic connectivity. Based on their electron microscopy work, White et al. defined 118 neuron classes (<link linkend="bib92">White et al., 1986</link>), with members of individual neuron classes mostly distinguished by their relative position to the anterior/posterior or left/right axis (for examples, please see WormAtlas: <ulink url="http://www.wormatlas.org/neurons.htm/aiy.htm">www.wormatlas.org/neurons.htm/aiy.htm</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormatlas.org/neurons.htm/rme.htm">www.wormatlas.org/neurons.htm/rme.htm</ulink>). Our understanding of the genetic mechanisms of neuronal specification on this single class level is extensive for individual cases and examples are summarized in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>. The overall emerging scheme is that each of these neuron types have their own "specification cassette", that is, a set of gene regulatory factors that specifies individual fates, as described in the next section.</para>
<?newpage?>
            <table id="table1" frame="all">
                <title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1. Gene regulatory factors that control neuron class specification.</emphasis> Genes are grouped into three different categories according to the defects that are caused by their absence ("All  known features lost", "Subfeatures lost", "Alternative or default program executed"). Categorization can only be made within the limitations of current knowledge, meaning the current extent to which neuron properties are known and have been examined in the individual mutants. For example, at present it can not be excluded that a gene such as <emphasis>ttx-3</emphasis> controls hundreds of, but not quite all AIY-defining genes.  Also note that this list is not comprehensive. Examples that do not clearly fall into any of these categories are also not shown. Ubiquitously expressed co-factors that affect specific neuronal differentiation events by interacting with cell-type specific transcription factors, such as <emphasis>unc-37</emphasis> or <emphasis>lin-49</emphasis> and others, are not shown here. Transcription factors that broadly affect embryonic patterning, therefore obscuring any potential neuronal specification role, or factors that may affect neuronal specification indirectly are also not shown.</title>
                
		<tgroup cols="5">
     <!--          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="0.5in" align="center" />
		<colspec colname="c2" colwidth="1in" align="center" />
		<colspec colname="c3" colwidth="1.5in" align="center" />
		<colspec colname="c4" colwidth="1.6in" align="center" />
		<colspec colname="c5" colwidth="2in" align="left" />     -->
		
		<colspec colname="c1" colwidth="0.5*" align="center" />
		<colspec colname="c2" colwidth="0.35*" align="center" />
		<colspec colname="c3" colwidth="0.6*" align="center" />
		<colspec colname="c4" colwidth="1.0*" align="center" />
		<colspec colname="c5" colwidth="1.4*" align="center" />
                <thead>
                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry valign="middle"><emphasis role="bold">Defect</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry valign="middle"><emphasis role="bold">Gene name</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry valign="middle"><emphasis role="bold">Gene class</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry valign="middle"><emphasis role="bold">Neurons affected</emphasis></entry>
                        <entry valign="middle"><emphasis role="bold">Reference</emphasis></entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                 <row valign="middle">
				<entry morerows="12">All known features lost</entry>
			<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-36" role="_blank">ceh-36</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Homeobox</entry>
                        <entry>AWC sensory neurons</entry>
                        <entry>
				<simplelist>
					<member><link linkend="bib47">Lanjuin et al., 2003</link>; </member>
					<member><link linkend="bib44">Koga and Ohshima, 2004</link></member>
				</simplelist>
			</entry>					    
		</row>

                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-37" role="_blank">ceh-37</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Homeobox</entry>
                        <entry>AWB sensory neurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib47">Lanjuin et al., 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
		    
		    <row valign="middle">
						<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=che-1" role="_blank">che-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Zn finger</entry>
                        <entry>ASE sensory neurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib12">Chang et al., 2003</link>; <link linkend="bib85">Uchida et al., 2003</link></entry>
			</row>

                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry>
                            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-44" role="_blank">egl-44</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-46" role="_blank">egl-46</ulink></emphasis>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Zn-finger and TEF-type</entry>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HOB;class=Cell" role="_blank">HOB</ulink> sensory neurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib98">Yu et al., 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry>
                            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-11" role="_blank">lin-11</ulink></emphasis>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>LIM homeobox</entry>
                        <entry>
				<simplelist>
					<member>AWA sensory neurons</member>
					<member><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVG;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVG</ulink> interneuron</member>
				</simplelist>
			</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib70">Sarafi-Reinach et al., 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib37">Hutter, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
		    
                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry>
                            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lim-4" role="_blank">lim-4</ulink></emphasis>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>LIM homeobox</entry>
                        <entry>AWB sensory neurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib69">Sagasti et al., 1999</link></entry>
                    </row>
		    
		   <row valign="middle">
			<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mec-3" role="_blank">mec-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>LIM homeobox</entry>
                        <entry>Touch neurons</entry>
                        <entry>
				<simplelist>
					<member><link linkend="bib88">Way and Chalfie, 1988</link>; </member>
					<member><link linkend="bib101">Zhang et al., 2002</link></member>
				</simplelist>
			</entry>
                    </row>
		    
		     <row valign="middle">
                        <entry>
                            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=odr-7" role="_blank">odr-7</ulink></emphasis>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Nuclear hormone receptor</entry>
                        <entry>AWA sensory neurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib75">Sengupta et al., 1994</link></entry>
                    </row>
		    
                   <row valign="middle">
                        <entry>
                            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-1" role="_blank">ttx-1</ulink></emphasis><footnote id="t1f1"><para>Affects the maintenance but not initiation of all known differentiated features of the AFD neurons.</para></footnote>
			</entry>
			<entry>Homeobox</entry>
                        <entry>AFD sensory neurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib72">Satterlee et al., 2001</link></entry>
                    </row>
		    
		    
		   <row valign="middle">
                        <entry>
                            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>LIM homeobox</entry>
                        <entry>AIY interneurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib33">Hobert et al., 1997</link></entry>
                    </row>

                     <row valign="middle">
                        <entry>
                            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-30" role="_blank">unc-30</ulink></emphasis>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Homeobox</entry>
                        <entry>D-type motorneurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib40">Jin et al., 1994</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry>
                            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-86" role="_blank">unc-86</ulink></emphasis>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>POU homeobox</entry>
                        <entry>Many</entry>
                        <entry>
				<simplelist>
					<member><link linkend="bib22">Finney et al., 1988</link>; </member>
					<member><link linkend="bib21">Finney and Ruvkun, 1990</link>; </member>
					<member><link linkend="bib81">Sze et al., 2002</link></member>
				</simplelist>
			</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row valign="middle">
						<entry>
                            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-130" role="_blank">unc-130</ulink></emphasis>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Forkhead</entry>
                        <entry>ASG sensory neurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib71">Sarafi-Reinach and Sengupta, 2000</link></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row valign="middle"><?dbfo keep-together="always" ?>
						<entry morerows="15">Subfeatures lost</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-2" role="_blank">ceh-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Homeobox</entry>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M3;class=Cell" role="_blank">M3</ulink> motorneuron</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib2">Aspock et al., 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
			
                    <row valign="middle"><?dbfo keep-together="always" ?>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-10" role="_blank">ceh-10</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Homeobox</entry>
                        <entry>CAN neuron<footnote id="t1f2"><para>It is possible that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-10" role="_blank">ceh-10</ulink></emphasis> affects all known aspects of CAN cell differentiation. </para></footnote></entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib23">Forrester et al., 1998</link></entry>
                    </row>			
			
		    <row valign="middle"><?dbfo keep-together="always" ?>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-14" role="_blank">ceh-14</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Homeobox</entry>
                        <entry>AFD sensory neurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib8">Cassata et al., 2000</link></entry>
			
                    </row>

                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-17" role="_blank">ceh-17</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Homeobox</entry>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ALA;class=Cell" role="_blank">ALA</ulink>, SIA neurons </entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib66">Pujol et al., 2000</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry>
                            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-23" role="_blank">ceh-23</ulink></emphasis>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Homeobox</entry>
                        <entry>AIY interneurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib1">Altun-Gultekin et al.,2001</link></entry>
                    </row>
		    
		    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-5" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>HOX cluster </entry>
                        <entry>HSN motorneurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib17">Desai et al., 1988</link></entry>
                    </row>		   

                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-43" role="_blank">egl-43</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ham-2" role="_blank">ham-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Zn finger</entry>
                        <entry>HSN motorneurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib5">Baum et al., 1999</link></entry>
                    </row>
		    
                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fax-1" role="_blank">fax-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Nuclear hormone receptor </entry>
                        <entry>AVK interneurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib57">Much et al., 2000</link></entry>
                    </row>		    
		    
		  <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-11" role="_blank">lin-11</ulink></emphasis></entry>
			<entry>LIM homeobox </entry>
                        <entry>AIZ interneurons, VC motorneurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib31">Hobert et al., 1998</link></entry>
                    </row>
 
		   <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-5" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis></entry>
			<entry>HOX cluster</entry>
                        <entry>Q neuroblasts</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib43">Kenyon, 1986</link>; <link linkend="bib13">Clark et al., 1993</link></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lim-4" role="_blank">lim-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>LIM homeobox</entry>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RID;class=Cell" role="_blank">RID</ulink> motorneuron</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib84">Tsalik et al., 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
   
		    
		    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lim-6" role="_blank">lim-6</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>LIM homeobox </entry>
                        <entry>
				<simplelist>
					<member><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink> motorneuron, </member>
					<member><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RIS;class=Cell" role="_blank">RIS</ulink> interneuron</member>
				</simplelist>
			</entry>
                        <entry>
				<simplelist>
				<member><link linkend="bib34">Hobert et al., 1999</link>; </member>
				<member><link linkend="bib84">Tsalik et al., 2003</link></member>
				</simplelist>
			</entry>
                    </row>
		    
                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>LIM homeobox </entry>
                        <entry>AIA interneurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib1">Altun-Gultekin et al., 2001</link></entry>
                    </row>

                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-3" role="_blank">unc-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Zn finger</entry>
                        <entry>ASI, ventral cord motorneurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib65">Prasad et al., 1998</link></entry>
                    </row>
		    
                 <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-42" role="_blank">unc-42</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Homeobox</entry>
                        <entry>
				<simplelist>
					<member>Command interneurons,</member>
					<member>RMD motorneurons, </member>
					<member>ASH sensory neurons</member>
				</simplelist>
			</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib3">Baran et al., 1999</link>; <link linkend="bib6">Brockie et al., 2001</link></entry>
                    </row>
		    
		    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=zag-1" role="_blank">zag-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Zn finger</entry>
                        <entry>Many neurons</entry>
                        <entry>
				<simplelist>
					<member><link linkend="bib14">Clark and Chiu, 2003</link>; </member>
					<member><link linkend="bib87">Wacker et al., 2003</link></member>
				</simplelist>
			</entry>
                    </row>
		    
		    
                   <row valign="middle">
						<entry morerows="13">Alternative or "default" program executed</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ahr-1" role="_blank">ahr-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Zn finger</entry>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RMED;class=Cell" role="_blank">RMED</ulink>/V vs. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RMEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">RMEL</ulink>/R motorneurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib36">Huang et al., 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
		    
		    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-36" role="_blank">ceh-36</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cog-1" role="_blank">cog-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lim-6" role="_blank">lim-6</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Homeobox</entry>
                        <entry morerows="2"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASEL</ulink> vs. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink></entry>
                        <entry morerows="2">
				<simplelist>
					<member><link linkend="bib12">Chang et al., 2003</link>; </member>
					<member><link linkend="bib42">Johnston and Hobert, 2003</link>;</member>
					<member><link linkend="bib11">Chang et al., 2004</link></member>
				</simplelist>
			</entry>
                    </row>
		    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=die-1" role="_blank">die-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Zn finger</entry>
                    </row>
		    <row valign="middle">
		    <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lsy-6" role="_blank">lsy-6</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mir-273" role="_blank">mir-273</ulink></emphasis></entry>
		    <entry>miRNA</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cfi-1" role="_blank">cfi-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>ARID</entry>
                        <entry>URA vs.CEM sensory neurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib76">Shaham and Bargmann, 2002</link></entry>
                    </row>		
	
                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry>
                            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-5" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-5" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>HOX gene</entry>
                        <entry morerows='1'>Male sensory rays</entry>
                        <entry morerows='1'><link linkend="bib51">Lints et al., 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
		    
                    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-18" role="_blank">mab-18</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Pax gene</entry>
                    </row>

                    <row valign="middle">
		    	<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-44" role="_blank">egl-44</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        	<entry>TEF-family</entry>
			<entry morerows='1'>Represses touch fate</entry>
			<entry><link linkend="bib96">Wu et al., 2001</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row valign="middle">
                     	<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-46" role="_blank">egl-46</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sem-4" role="_blank">sem-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        	<entry>Zn finger</entry>
			<entry><link linkend="bib96">Wu et al., 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib82">Toker et al., 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
		    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry>
                            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mec-3" role="_blank">mec-3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-86" role="_blank">unc-86</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Homeobox</entry>
                        <entry>FLP vs. touch neurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib55">Mitani et al., 1993</link></entry>
                    </row>
		    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pag-3" role="_blank">pag-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Zn finger </entry>
                        <entry>BDU vs. ALM</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib39">Jia et al., 1996</link></entry>
                    </row>
		    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-4" role="_blank">unc-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Homeobox</entry>
                        <entry>VA vs. VB motorneurons DA vs. DB motorneurons <footnote id="t1f3"><para>The switch in VA/VB and DA/DB differentiation programs entails synaptic connectivity, but not all aspects of axon anatomy.</para>
                                    </footnote></entry>
                        <entry>
				<simplelist>
					<member><link linkend="bib93">Winnier et al., 1999</link>; </member>
					<member><link linkend="bib20">Esmaeili et al., 2002</link></member>
				</simplelist>
			</entry>
                    </row>
		    
		    <row valign="middle">
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-55" role="_blank">unc-55</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>Nuclear hormone receptor</entry>
                        <entry>DD vs. VD motorneurons</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib102">Zhou and Walthall, 1998</link></entry>
                    </row>

		    <row valign="middle">
		    <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=vab-7" role="_blank">vab-7</ulink></emphasis></entry>
		    <entry>Homeobox</entry>
		    <entry>DA vs. DB motorneurons</entry>
		    <entry><link linkend="bib20">Esmaeili et al., 2002</link></entry>
		    </row>
		    </tbody>
		</tgroup>
            </table>
        </sect2>
<?newpage?>
        <sect2>
            <title>Genetic programs for neuron class specification</title>
            <para>Genes that control neuronal specification have traditionally been identified
                through forward genetic screens for mutants in which individual neuron classes with
                easily scorable functions or morphologies (for example motorneurons or sensory
                neurons) either do not differentiate or function appropriately, resulting, for
                example, in characteristic sensory defects. The focus on individual neuron classes
                introduced somewhat of a bias to the types of genes identified. Rather than
                identifying genes that control early patterning in the nervous system (whose loss
                would be expected to cause pleiotropic effects), these screens largely identified
                gene regulatory factors that act at late stages of neuronal development, most often
                during terminal differentiation of specific subsets of postmitotic neurons (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). The preponderance of transcription factors is consistent with the
                cell-autonomous programming of cell fate and corroborates early laser ablation
                experiments (<link linkend="bib79">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6684600 -->). A notable exception is the
                involvement of TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signaling in
                determining the terminal identity of ray sensory lineages in males (<link linkend="bib50">Lints and Emmons, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10572056 -->; <link linkend="bib51">Lints et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15081363 -->).</para>

            <para>One theme emerging from the genetic analysis of neuronal specification programs is that there appear to be three separable types of genetic programs operating in a given neuron type (<xref linkend="figure3"/>A). The well-characterized AIY interneuron class (<ulink url="http://www.wormatlas.org/neurons.htm/aiy.htm">www.wormatlas.org/neurons.htm/aiy.htm</ulink>) provides a paradigm for this notion (<xref linkend="figure3"/>B; <link linkend="bib1">Altun-Gultekin et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11493519 -->; <link linkend="bib89">Wenick and Hobert, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15177025 -->). One genetic specification program is the induction of pan-neuronal features, which include the expression of many "generic" genes required non-specifically for neuronal function, such as components of the synaptic vesicle machinery. The adoption of pan-neuronal features is genetically separable from a parallel program, the induction of cell-type specific features. Rather than there being many transcription factors, each inducing one subaspect of AIY differentiation, the two homeobox genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-10" role="_blank">ceh-10</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis> jointly control all known cell-type specific features of AIY, but have little impact on the expression of pan-neuronal features. Third, while <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-10" role="_blank">ceh-10</ulink></emphasis>/<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis> control expression of many terminal differentiation genes by directly binding to their <emphasis>cis</emphasis>-regulatory elements, they also induce the expression of intermediary transcription factors that regulate the expression of very specific subfeatures of AIY (<link linkend="bib1">Altun-Gultekin et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11493519 -->; <xref linkend="figure3"/>B).</para>

	    <para>Genes that specify other neuronal differentiation programs often fall into one of these types. For example, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=che-1" role="_blank">che-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-36" role="_blank">ceh-36</ulink></emphasis>,
                    <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-30" role="_blank">unc-30</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mec-3" role="_blank">mec-3</ulink></emphasis> also affect all
                neuron-class specific features of the AWE and AWC chemosensory neurons, D-type motorneurons
                and touch sensory neurons, respectively (<xref linkend="figure3"/>C and <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> for
                references), while <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-14" role="_blank">ceh-14</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-42" role="_blank">unc-42</ulink></emphasis>, for
                example, affect only sub-features of the differentiation programs in AFD and command
                interneurons, respectively (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). A more detailed review of motor neuron specification in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> can be found in Von Stetina et al. (in press).</para>		
		
		        <para>Based on their anatomical features, ventral cord motor neurons can be divided into
            specific classes, which are diversified by the action of specific transcription factors. For example, the D-type motor neurons can be subdivided
            into embryonically and post-embryonically born D-type motor neurons, with distinct
            muscle innervation properties. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-55" role="_blank">unc-55</ulink></emphasis> nuclear hormone receptor
            is required to distinguish these two distinct classes. In the absence of
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-55" role="_blank">unc-55</ulink></emphasis>, the VD-class adopts the fate of the DD-class (<link linkend="bib102">Zhou and Walthall, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9852581 -->). In animals lacking the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-4" role="_blank">unc-4</ulink></emphasis> homeobox gene, the postembryonically born A-type motor neurons (VA subclass) adopt aspects of the fate of the B-type neurons (VB subclass; <link linkend="bib53">Miller and Niemeyer, 1995</link><!-- PMID 7555714 -->; <link linkend="bib93">Winnier et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10557206 -->).</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Neuron subclass specification</title>
        <para>Members of the 118 neuron classes defined by White et al. are distinguished by their
            differential anterior/posterior, dorsal/ventral and left/right position. For example,
            many head ganglia neuron classes are composed of a pair of two left/right symmetric
            cells (example: AIY neurons:
            <ulink url="http://www.wormatlas.org/neurons.htm/aiy.htm">www.wormatlas.org/ neurons.htm/aiy.htm</ulink>), while ventral cord
            motor neuron classes are composed of many longitudinally aligned class members (example: DA1 through DA9 neurons <ulink url="http://www.wormatlas.org/neurons.htm/DAn.htm">www.wormatlas.org/neurons.htm/DAn.htm</ulink>). Individual class members can be distinguished by subtle functional criteria (see ASE or AWC examples mentioned below) or by slightly distinct axodendritic projection patterns (for example, DA neuron class members).</para>
            <mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig3" width="3in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase> figure 3</phrase>
                </textobject>&fig3legend;</mediaobject>
	    <para>Genetic specification programs that distinguish individual class members are only beginning to be discovered. The RME motorneurons, composed of four radially symmetric cells, RME left, RME right, RME dorsal and RME ventral (<ulink url="http://www.wormatlas.org/neurons.htm/rme.htm">www.wormatlas.org/neurons.htm/rme.htm</ulink>) provide an illuminating example (<link linkend="bib36">Huang et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14757639 -->). Here, the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ahr-1" role="_blank">ahr-1</ulink></emphasis>
            transcription factor imposes a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RMEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">RMEL</ulink>/R "fate" onto an apparent "RMED/V" ground state that
            is executed by all four neurons. That is, loss of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ahr-1" role="_blank">ahr-1</ulink></emphasis> causes all
            four RME neurons to express <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RMED;class=Cell" role="_blank">RMED</ulink>/V markers, while ectopic expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ahr-1" role="_blank">ahr-1</ulink></emphasis> in all four RME neurons induced <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RMEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">RMEL</ulink>/R fate. A tempting conclusion from
            this study is that neuron subclasses are diversified from a "neuron class ground state"
            common to all class members. Notably, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RMED;class=Cell" role="_blank">RMED</ulink>/V and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RMEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">RMEL</ulink>/R neurons show little if any
            lineage relationship.</para>

        <para>Another more recent, and anatomically unexpected subclassification of neuron classes can be observed across the L/R axis. Most neuron classes in the nervous system are composed of a pair of two bilaterally symmetric neurons (<link linkend="bib78">Sulston, 1983</link><!-- PMID 6586366 -->; <link linkend="bib32">Hobert et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12154364 -->). While most known L/R bilateral analogs are indistinguishable from one another based on anatomic, functional and gene expression criteria, the bilaterally symmetric AWC olfactory (<ulink url="http://www.wormatlas.org/neurons.htm/awc.htm">www.wormatlas.org/neurons.htm/awc.htm</ulink>) and ASE gustatory neurons (<ulink url="http://www.wormatlas.org/neurons.htm/ase.htm">www.wormatlas.org/neurons.htm/ase.htm</ulink>) express different spectra of putative chemoreceptors and, therefore, have diverged their chemosensory capacities (<link linkend="bib99">Yu et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9096403 -->; <link linkend="bib83">Troemel et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10571181 -->; <link linkend="bib63">Pierce-Shimomura et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11287956 -->; <link linkend="bib90">Wes and Bargmann, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11287957 -->). In the case of ASE, this appears to be programmed in an invariant manner into the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASEL</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink> lineages. Diversifying from a "bilaterally symmetric ground state", induced by the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=che-1" role="_blank">che-1</ulink></emphasis> Zn finger transcription factor, a regulatory network of several homeobox genes and microRNAs is required to make <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASEL</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink> different from each other (<link linkend="bib12">Chang et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12952888 -->; <link linkend="bib42">Johnston and Hobert, 2003</link><!-- PMID 14685240 -->; <link linkend="bib11">Chang et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15306811 -->). Interestingly, these factors do not act linearly, but constitute a "bistable feedback loop" (<xref linkend="figure3"/>C; <link linkend="bib41">Johnston et al., 2005</link>). The negative regulatory interaction between individual regulatory factors in this loop ensures that the loop can exist in two states (hence "bistable"). In the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASEL</ulink> cell, the output of the loop is the induction of a very specific subset of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASEL</ulink> fate markers, while in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink> cell, the loop operates with the "opposite" sign, thus causing the induction of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASER;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASER</ulink> fate. What determines the cell-type specific activity of the loop is currently unknown. Yet this example illustrates that neurons have come up with very sophisticated regulatory devices to ensure their functional diversification. Another notable aspect of ASE cell fate determination is its illustration of the power of forward genetic analysis and the limitation of reverse genetic analysis, the predominant tool of, for example, mouse genetics. Genetic mutant screens for ASE fate determinants have uncovered hypo- and antimorphic alleles of genes whose null phenotype is either absent due to genetic redundancy, or is too pleiotropic. For example, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=die-1" role="_blank">die-1</ulink></emphasis> null mutants die before ASE is generated, while <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=die-1" role="_blank">die-1</ulink></emphasis> hypomorphic alleles revealed by genetic screening are viable yet display ASE fate defects (<link linkend="bib11">Chang et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15306811 -->). Similarly, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-36" role="_blank">ceh-36</ulink></emphasis> null alleles show no significant ASE cell fate defect, likely due to redundancy with an as yet unknown factor, yet presumptive antimorphic alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-36" role="_blank">ceh-36</ulink></emphasis> allowed to implicate the gene in ASE fate determination (<link linkend="bib12">Chang et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12952888 -->; <link linkend="bib47">Lanjuin et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14536063 -->).</para>
	
			           

        <para>Another interesting issue relates to the similarity, rather than difference, of
            individual neuron class members. 98 neuron classes are composed of pairs of left/right
            symmetric neurons, which, with the notable exception of the case of ASE and AWC
            mentioned above, are indistinguishable in terms of all known morphological, functional
            or gene expression criteria. Yet 35 of these 98 pairs are composed of cells that derive
            from distinct embryonic lineages (<link linkend="bib78">Sulston, 1983</link><!-- PMID 6586366 -->). On the one hand, it is
            tempting to speculate that positional information instructs lineally unrelated
            neuroblasts to adopt similar, left/right symmetric fates (<link linkend="bib73">Schnabel, 1996</link><!-- PMID 8757938 -->).
            On the other hand, the patterned expression of HOX cluster members along the
            anterior/posterior axis is not determined by absolute positional information, but by
            intrinsic lineage cues (<link linkend="bib15">Cowing and Kenyon, 1996</link><!-- PMID 8684464 -->; <link linkend="bib94">Wittmann et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9334268 -->), indicating that positional information can be lineally encoded.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Maintenance and plasticity of neuronal specification</title>
        <para>Many of the transcription factors that determine the differentiated state of a neuron
            autoregulate their expression and thereby maintain their expression throughout the life
            of the animal. Although not experimentally tested in any of these cases, this strongly
            suggests that once a terminally differentiated state is chosen, it is actively
            maintained by the same factors that initiated the differentiation program. However, a
            unique feature of the nervous system is its plasticity, that is, its ability to alter
            specific properties at either defined developmental stages or under changes in external
            conditions. This has been well documented in the chemosensory system of
            <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. While the terminally differentiated state of many
            chemosensory neurons is defined by the expression of specific sets of orphan 7TMRs,
            their expression profiles can change under defined environmental conditions and upon
            changes in neuronal activity (<link linkend="bib61">Peckol et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11572964 -->; <link linkend="bib59">Nolan et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12464635 -->; <link linkend="bib100">Zhang et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14998926 -->). TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signaling plays an important role in the
            environmental induced alteration of 7TMR expression profiles; TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signaling is also required to maintain specific
            7TMR expression profiles (<link linkend="bib59">Nolan et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12464635 -->). Another prominent example
            of the plasticity of the worm nervous system is its re-wiring of synaptic connection of
            a class of ventral cord motorneurons at a specific developmental stage (<link linkend="bib91">White et al.,
            1978</link>). This rewiring process is under control of a ubiquitous developmental timer, the
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-14" role="_blank">lin-14</ulink></emphasis> gene (<link linkend="bib28">Hallam and Jin, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9738501 -->).</para>
    </sect1>
<?newpage?>
    <sect1>
        <title>Concepts in neuronal fate specification in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
        </title>
	
        <sect2>
            <title>Combinatorial codes of gene regulatory factors</title>
            <para>Individual cell types are defined by the combinatorial co-expression of terminal differentiation genes ("gene batteries"; <xref linkend="figure4"/>). Similarly, combinatorial codes of transcription factors control the composition of cell-type specific gene batteries (<link linkend="bib16">Davidson, 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib30">Hobert, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15337119 -->; <link linkend="bib46">Lanjuin and Sengupta, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15018934 -->).  This point is well exemplified by the AIY interneuron class, whose differentiation program is comparatively well defined by scores of terminal differentiation marker genes (<link linkend="bib1">Altun-Gultekin et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11493519 -->; <link linkend="bib89">Wenick and Hobert, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15177025 -->). Each of the AIY terminal differentiation genes (including neurotransmitter transporters, neurotransmitter receptors, putative adhesion molecules, etc.; <xref linkend="figure4"/>) is more broadly expressed, but expression of these genes uniquely overlaps in AIY, thereby defining a AIY-specific gene battery. The co-expression of all AIY-class specific genes is lost exclusively in AIY in animals that lack either the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis> or the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-10" role="_blank">ceh-10</ulink></emphasis> homeobox gene. Neither factor alone has the capability to determine AIY interneuron fate, a notion that is derived from the observations that (1) these factors are expressed in more cells than just AIY (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis> is expressed also in AIA, ADL and ASI, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-10" role="_blank">ceh-10</ulink></emphasis> in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RID;class=Cell" role="_blank">RID</ulink> and CAN) and (2) that ectopic expression of either of these factors alone does not broadly induce AIY fate. It is rather the unique co-expression in AIY that allows <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-10" role="_blank">ceh-10</ulink></emphasis> to act together in a complex to directly activate the expression of neuron class-specific genes, through their binding to a motif that is common to most AIY-expressed genes (<link linkend="bib89">Wenick and Hobert, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15177025 -->). The "combinatorial code" of co-expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-10" role="_blank">ceh-10</ulink></emphasis> is however still not a sufficient determinant for AIY fate. Forced co-expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-10" role="_blank">ceh-10</ulink></emphasis> in many other neuron classes, causes some but not all neuron classes to execute the AIY differentiation program. The example of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-10" role="_blank">ceh-10</ulink></emphasis> thus highlights the context-dependency of transcription factor action and, like many other examples, seriously questions the concept of single "master regulators" of cell fate determination. That is, rather than there being a single master-regulator, it is the unique combination of gene regulatory factors present in a given neuron class that determines its fate (<link linkend="bib16">Davidson, 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib30">Hobert, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15337119 -->; <link linkend="bib46">Lanjuin and Sengupta, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15018934 -->; <link linkend="bib51">Lints et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15081363 -->).
	    </para>
	    <mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig4" width="3in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase> figure 4</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig4legend; </mediaobject>
	    
            <para>Consistent with the concept of combinatorial interaction of gene regulatory
                factors, the coupling of gene regulatory factors to specific effector outputs is not
                conserved in individual cell types. For example, the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lim-6" role="_blank">lim-6</ulink></emphasis>
                homeobox gene regulates the expression of the GABA synthesizing enzyme
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis> and the glutamate receptor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis> in
                the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RIS;class=Cell" role="_blank">RIS</ulink> interneuron, but, although expressed in the RME motorneurons, it does not
                regulate the expression of either gene in this cell type (<link linkend="bib84">Tsalik et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14568548 -->). Other examples are the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis> and
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-23" role="_blank">ceh-23</ulink></emphasis> homeobox genes whose expression overlaps in both AIY and
                ADL; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis> regulates <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-23" role="_blank">ceh-23</ulink></emphasis> in AIY, but
                not in ADL (<link linkend="bib1">Altun-Gultekin et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11493519 -->). From the perspective of
                terminal differentiation genes (e.g., <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis>,
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glr-1" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis>), one can therefore conclude that rather than being under
                control of a common regulatory factor in different cell types, they are under
                control of cell-type specific combinations of gene regulatory factors. </para>
		
            <para>The principle of combinatorial coding also rationalizes the effect that a loss of
                a cell-fate determinant has on neuronal cell fate. In some cases, loss of the
                determinant (e.g. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=che-1" role="_blank">che-1</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis>; <xref linkend="figure3"/>B, C)
                causes a loss of overall identity of a neuron, while in other cases (e.g.
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-4" role="_blank">unc-4</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-130" role="_blank">unc-130</ulink></emphasis>,
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cfi-1" role="_blank">cfi-1</ulink></emphasis>; <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>) an alternative fate is adopted. These
                differential effects may reflect the information content of specific gene regulatory
                codes. For example, assume that transcription factor X regulates aspects of terminal
                differentiation but also represses transcription factor V. Moreover, assume that the
                transcription factors X, Y, Z determines fate "A" and the code V, Y, Z determines
                fate "B". Loss of the factor X leads to a transformation from "A" fate (defined by
                XYZ) to "B" (VYZ) since the "left-over" code still carries instructive information.
                If the code left after removal of one transcription factors (e.g. remove factor Z)
                does not specify any cell type, the neuron may remain undifferentiated.</para>
            <para>The combinatorial coding by co-expression of defined transcription factors relays
                the problem of neuronal fate specification to more "upstream" levels. In the case of
                AIY, an upstream code of co-expressed transcription factors likely determines
                co-expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-10" role="_blank">ceh-10</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ttx-3" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis>
                specifically in AIY. Neuronal fate specification can therefore be considered as the
                interpretation of multiple, hierarchical layers of transcription factor codes (<xref linkend="figure4"/>). An individual transcription factor can be a part of a code at
                different levels; for example, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-86" role="_blank">unc-86</ulink></emphasis> works at different stages
                in the development of neuroblast lineage and presumably interacts with distinct sets
                of factors at different stages (<link linkend="bib21">Finney and Ruvkun, 1990</link><!-- PMID 2257628 -->; <link linkend="bib18">Duggan et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9735371 -->; <link linkend="bib81">Sze et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12135927 -->), so does the
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-32" role="_blank">lin-32</ulink></emphasis> bHLH gene (<link linkend="bib64">Portman and Emmons, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11076762 -->). It
                is in these hierarchical layers of transcription factor codes where one could see
                how cell lineage and history are coupled to terminal neuronal fates. At each
                developmental stage (<xref linkend="figure1"/>), an individual neuroblast contains a
                specific and unique combination of transcription factors which are required to
                select the next level of transcription factor code. Lineage-specific transcription
                factor codes may be brought about by a lineage-intrinsic coordinate system. 
		This coordinate system could be determined by a combination of early blastomere induction events and the ensuing differential anterior/posterior segregation of cell fate determinants into only one daughter cells after a cell division, demonstrated to occur for the POP-1 transcription factor (<link linkend="bib49">Lin et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9458047 -->). HAM-1, a novel protein with no obvious homologs, also appears to have a role in determining the asymmetric fate of the daughters of a neuroblast cell division (<link linkend="bib26">Guenther and Garriga, 1996</link><!-- PMID 8951066 -->). Another component of this coordinate system may be the temporally controlled induction of transcription factors in analogy to what has been observed in fly neuroblast determination (<link linkend="bib60">Pearson and Doe, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15473854 -->). A necessity to  time transcription factor activity precisely has recently been demonstrated during cell fate determination in the AWA sensory neuron class. To make this neuron class different from its sister neuron AWG, a brief pulse of expression of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-11" role="_blank">lin-11</ulink></emphasis> homeobox is required; forced prolonged expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-11" role="_blank">lin-11</ulink></emphasis> disrupts AWA cell fate (<link linkend="bib70">Sarafi-Reinach et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11546744 -->).</para>
		
            <para>The concept of combinatorial coding of gene regulatory factors is not limited to
                transcriptional regulation but includes a class of small regulatory factors,
                microRNAs. miRNAs are small RNA molecules that bind to complementary sequences in
                the 3'UTR of target genes and prevent their translation (<link linkend="bib4">Bartel, 2004</link><!-- PMID 14744438 -->). Originally identified as regulators of developmental timing of
                non-neuronal cell division patterns (<link linkend="bib48">Lee et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 15055592 -->; <link linkend="bib67">Reinhart et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10706289 -->), recent genetic and reverse genetic studies have shown
                that miRNAs play a role in neuronal specification as well. Specifically, the two
                miRNAs <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lsy-6" role="_blank">lsy-6</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mir-273" role="_blank">mir-273</ulink></emphasis> are involved in
                diversifying the fates of a two members of a class of bilaterally symmetric sensory
                neurons, the ASE neurons (<link linkend="bib42">Johnston and Hobert, 2003</link><!-- PMID 14685240 -->; <link linkend="bib11">Chang et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15306811 -->; <xref linkend="figure3"/>C). Animal genomes contain an
                abundance of miRNA genes, the vast majority of which are uncharacterized. Expression
                pattern analysis in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> reveals neuron-class specific
                expression profiles of many miRNAs (Penney, E. B. and O.H., unpubl. data). Together with the
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lsy-6" role="_blank">lsy-6</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mir-273" role="_blank">mir-273</ulink></emphasis> data, one can expect
                that miRNAs fulfill widespread roles in neuronal specification. As clearly
                demonstrated in the case of the ASE neurons, miRNAs can work much like transcription
                factors as necessary and sufficient switches to trigger cellular specification
                programs. In analogy to transcription factor codes, combinatorial codes of miRNAs
                within a given cell-type may similarly contribute to cellular differentiation, also
                by acting through differentially occupied <emphasis>cis</emphasis>-regulatory
                elements which are in the case of miRNAs located in 3'UTRs (for a more in-depth
                discussion of the conceptual similarity of transcription factors and miRNAs, see <link linkend="bib30">Hobert, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15337119 -->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Repressing alternative or default programs and sequential repression</title>
            <para>The importance of repression of alternative or default programs has long been
                recognized in a variety of contexts (<xref linkend="figure5"/>). Two classic examples operate in motorneurons
                and touch neurons. In the absence of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-4" role="_blank">unc-4</ulink></emphasis> homeobox gene,
                the VA motorneurons execute many but not all of the fates normally characteristic
                for the VB motorneuron fate (<link linkend="bib53">Miller and Niemeyer, 1995</link><!-- PMID 7555714 -->; <link linkend="bib93">Winnier et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10557206 -->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-4" role="_blank">unc-4</ulink></emphasis> therefore prevents VB cell
                fate to be expressed in the VA neurons. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-4" role="_blank">unc-4</ulink></emphasis> exerts its
                repressive activity in conjunction with the transcriptional co-repressor
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-37" role="_blank">unc-37</ulink></emphasis>/Groucho (<link linkend="bib54">Miller et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 7904971 -->; <link linkend="bib62">Pflugrad et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9165118 -->). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-86" role="_blank">unc-86</ulink></emphasis> and
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mec-3" role="_blank">mec-3</ulink></emphasis> homeobox genes have the capacity to combinatorially drive
                touch neuron fate in several cell types, but are prevented from doing so in a subset
                of these cells, such as the FLP cells, where <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-86" role="_blank">unc-86</ulink></emphasis>/<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mec-3" role="_blank">mec-3</ulink></emphasis>
                activity is genetically masked by the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-44" role="_blank">egl-44</ulink></emphasis> and
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-46" role="_blank">egl-46</ulink></emphasis> genes (<link linkend="bib55">Mitani et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8187641 -->). Other
                examples are listed in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>. One of these examples warrants specific attention
                since it illustrates both concepts of repression of defaults states and
                combinatorial transcription factor codes. The HOX cluster gene
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-5" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> imposes specific male sensory ray neuronal identities
                (ray 3&#x02013;5) on a common ground state (normally executed only by ray 2). It does so
                either alone in ray 3 (or with an unknown co-factor), together with the HOX cluster
                gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-5" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> (in ray 4), the Pax gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-18" role="_blank">mab-18</ulink></emphasis>
                (in ray 5) or a SMAD-type TGF<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>
                effector (in ray 6; <link linkend="bib51">Lints et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15081363 -->).</para>
		
            <mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase> figure 5</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig5legend; </mediaobject>
		
            <para>The concept of cell fate induction by repressing a default state has been
                significantly expanded to include several layers of sequential repressive
                interactions, thus making cell fate induction a "de-repression" phenomenon. This is
                well illustrated in the vertebrate spinal cord (<link linkend="bib58">Muhr et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11290324 -->)
                but also in several cases in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> nervous system. One
                first glimpse in this direction came from the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-22" role="_blank">lin-22</ulink></emphasis> gene. In
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-22" role="_blank">lin-22</ulink></emphasis> mutants, several hypodermal cell lineages, derived from
                the V1,V2, V3, V4, and V6 ectoblasts, inappropriately adopt neuronal character (<xref linkend="figure2"/>; <link linkend="bib35">Horvitz et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6586368 -->). Thus,
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-22" role="_blank">lin-22</ulink></emphasis> serves to repress neuronal fate in these lineages.
                However, the V5 cell normally executes the neuronal differentiation program that is
                executed inappropriately in V1, V2, V3, V4 and V6 in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-22" role="_blank">lin-22</ulink></emphasis>
                mutants. Therefore, the inhibitory activity of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-22" role="_blank">lin-22</ulink></emphasis> on
                neuronal fate is repressed in V5 (<xref linkend="figure2"/>). The overall scheme
                emerging from this analysis is that a specific fate is not necessarily induced by a
                positive inducer, but by sequential de-repression of a common ground state, as
                illustrated in <xref linkend="figure5"/>. This scheme is not only emerging in the
                vertebrate spinal cord, but is also apparent in the fly nervous system as well as in
                other instances of the worm nervous system. For example, the
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=vab-7" role="_blank">vab-7</ulink></emphasis> homeobox gene induces DB fate by repressing the
                expression of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-4" role="_blank">unc-4</ulink></emphasis> homeobox gene, which represses DB fate
                specification (<link linkend="bib20">Esmaeili et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 11861469 -->). In the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASEL</ulink> sensory neuron,
                the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lsy-6" role="_blank">lsy-6</ulink></emphasis> miRNA represses the expression of the
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cog-1" role="_blank">cog-1</ulink></emphasis> homeobox gene, a repressor of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ASEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">ASEL</ulink> fate (<link linkend="bib12">Chang et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12952888 -->; Johnston et al., 2003). In many cases described above (vertebrate spinal cord, DB
                fate, ASE fate), a critical and evolutionarly ancient component of the repressive
                interactions is the Groucho co-repressor protein (<link linkend="bib62">Pflugrad et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9165118 -->; <link linkend="bib58">Muhr et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11290324 -->; <link linkend="bib12">Chang et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12952888 -->). <xref linkend="figure5"/>B illustrates how sequential repression could contribute to the
                potential evolvability of gene expression profiles, an important feature for an
                organ that needs to maintain a set of commonly expressed genes (pan-neuronal genes)
                but needs to "invent" novel gene expression profiles in order to generate neuronal diversity.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Perspectives</title>
        <para>Terminal neuronal differentiation programs have been revealed in several cases on a
            single neuron basis, therefore fulfilling the promises of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
            as a model system. However, much remains to be learned in regard to the mechanisms of
            lineage programming, particularly in the less accessible mid-embryonic stages. With the
            abundance of cell-type specific <emphasis>gfp</emphasis> markers and the SNP-based facilitation of
            traditional mapping and cloning approaches, it will be possible to now perform much
            larger scale screens for neuronal fate mutants. As the examples mentioned above
            illustrate, the key to success will be the ease with which specific phenotypes can be
            screened for. Rather than using terminal differentiation marker, which bias for the
            retrieval of genes involved in terminal differentiation, it is important to move to <emphasis>gfp</emphasis> markers that label earlier lineage decisions and to use a four-dimensional video
            microscopy system (<link linkend="bib74">Schnabel et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 913343 -->) to assist precise phenotypic
            scoring of lineage defects. Genome wide analysis of expression patterns of gene
            regulatory factors such as transcription factors and miRNAs, if done with single cell
            resolution and at embryonic stages, will also provide testable hypotheses about the
            existence of "codes" that are characteristic for individual lineages and will open the
            door to a reverse genetic analysis of these codes.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Acknowledgments</title>
        <para>Work in the author's laboratory is funded by the HHMI, NIH, the McKnight Foundation and Irma
            T. Hirschl Trust. I am indebted to many colleagues for ongoing discussions and comments
            on the manuscript, particularly David Miller, and apologize to all colleagues whose work
            could not be appropriately discussed due to space constraints.</para>
	    </sect1>
		<sect1>
			<title>References</title>
			<para/>
			&nervous_Refs;</sect1>
</article>