<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 4. Polarity and spindle positioning in two to six-cell stage embryos.</title>
<para>(A) Early two-cell stage.  As a result of asymmetric spindle elongation during anaphase, the first division is unequal and generates a larger anterior blastomere <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> and a smaller posterior blastomere P<subscript>1</subscript>.  <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> are initially present around the entire cortex of P<subscript>1</subscript> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 localization is similar to that at the end of the one-cell stage; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> (not shown) is initially present at the cell contact region. (B) After the centrosomes migrate on to a transverse plane, the P<subscript>1</subscript> nucleus rotates 90&deg; during late prophase, aligning the centrosomes on the AP axis. By this time, asymmetric PAR domains have been reestablished, and a band of cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> becomes detectable. For simplicity, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> is shown as a band, but lower levels are present throughout the remaining cortex of both P<subscript>1</subscript> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink>. During mitosis (not shown), higher levels of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 are present at the posterior cortex in P<subscript>1</subscript> and asymmetric spindle elongation occurs. (C) At third cleavage, the spindles in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cells initially set up along the left/right plane and the centrosomes in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> are also on the left/right plane. PAR domains become established in the P<subscript>2</subscript> cell, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 become enriched at the P<subscript>2</subscript>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> cell contact. (D) In the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cells, the spindles shift slightly anteriorly during telophase, such that the left daughters assume a more anterior position. In <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink>, the nucleus rotates to align on the AP axis, and the P<subscript>2</subscript> nucleus rotates so that one centrosome is adjacent to the P<subscript>2</subscript>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> cell contact. Cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> is present as a lateral band in P<subscript>2</subscript> by this time; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> is also present at all other cell-cell contacts but is reduced at the P<subscript>2</subscript>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> cell contact (not shown).</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>