<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 3. Centrosome and spindle positioning in one-cell stage embryos.</title>
<para>(A, B) Schematics of centrosome positioning during centration/rotation (A) and spindle positioning during anaphase (B), with the distribution of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink>. For simplicity, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> is shown as a band, but lower levels are present throughout the remaining cortex and in the cytoplasm. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> are also present throughout the cytoplasm and prominently around the microtubule asters. (A) During centration/rotation, the centrosomes and pronuclei move as a unit towards the cell center, while rotating by 90&deg; such that centrosomes become aligned with the AP axis. This process appears to be driven by force generators acting both in the cytoplasm and at the cell cortex, as depicted. Note that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> are present more extensively on the anterior side at this stage. (B) During metaphase/anaphase spindle positioning, unequal net pulling forces act on the two spindle poles, with larger pulling forces acting on the posterior spindle pole. This process is thought to be driven by an imbalance of active cortical force generators. Note that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> are present more extensively on the posterior side at this stage. (C) Assembly and mechanism of action of cortical force generators. The ternary complex is comprised of a G&alpha; protein (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49147;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink>), which interacts with the membrane via myristoylation and with the Goloco motif of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1/2</ulink>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE24910#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 in turn interact with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink>. LIN-5 associates with the dynein complex, which is thus recruited to the cell cortex below the plasma membrane. Cortical dynein is thought to exert a pull on the plus end of astral microtubules by virtue of attempted minus-end motility and/or by remaining associated with force-generating depolymerizing microtubules (not depicted per se). A related complex may be acting in the cytoplasm. See text for details. </para>
</formalpara>
</caption>