<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'acd2fig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'acd2fig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'acd2fig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'acd2fig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'acd2fig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY movie1 SYSTEM 'acd2movie1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY movie2 SYSTEM 'acd2movie2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY movie3 SYSTEM 'acd2movie3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY movie4 SYSTEM 'acd2movie4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY movie5 SYSTEM 'acd2movie5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY table1 SYSTEM 'acd2table1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY table2 SYSTEM 'acd2table2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY table3 SYSTEM 'acd2table3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'acd2fig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'acd2fig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'acd2fig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'acd2fig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'acd2fig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY movie1legend SYSTEM 'acd2movie1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY movie2legend SYSTEM 'acd2movie2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY movie3legend SYSTEM 'acd2movie3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY movie4legend SYSTEM 'acd2movie4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY movie5legend SYSTEM 'acd2movie5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY table1legend SYSTEM 'acd2table1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY table2legend SYSTEM 'acd2table2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY table3legend SYSTEM 'acd2table3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY asymcelldiv.2_ref SYSTEM 'asymcelldiv.2_ref.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="asymcelldiv.2">
<articleinfo>
<title>Polarity establishment, asymmetric division and segregation of fate determinants in early <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos<footnote><para>Edited by: Joel H. Rothman and Andrew Singson. Last Revised Nov. 26, 2013. Published December 30, 2014. This chapter should be cited as: Rose L. and G&ouml;nczy P. Polarity establishment, asymmetric division and segregation of fate determinants in early <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos (December 30, 2014), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.30.2, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2014 Lesilee Rose and Pierre G&ouml;nczy. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para></footnote></title>
<author><othername>Lesilee Rose<superscript>1&sect;</superscript> and Pierre G&ouml;nczy<superscript>2</superscript><remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Email: <ulink url="mailto:lsrose@ucdavis.edu">lsrose@ucdavis.edu</ulink> or <ulink url="mailto:Pierre.Gonczy@epfl.ch">Pierre.Gonczy@epfl.ch</ulink></para></footnote></remark></othername>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>1</superscript>Department of Molecular &amp; Cellular Biology, University of California, Davis, Davis, CA USA 95616</orgname></affiliation>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>2</superscript>Swiss Institute for Experimental Cancer Research (ISREC), School of Life Sciences, Swiss Federal Institute of Technology (EPFL),  Lausanne, Switzerland</orgname></affiliation>
</author></articleinfo>
<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Polarity establishment, asymmetric division, and acquisition of cell fates are critical steps during early development. In this review, we discuss processes that set up the embryonic axes, with an emphasis on polarity establishment and asymmetric division.  We begin with the first asymmetric division in the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> embryo, where symmetry is broken by the local inactivation of actomyosin cortical contractility. This contributes to establishing a polarized distribution of PAR proteins and associated components on the cell cortex along the longitudinal embryonic axis, which becomes the anterior-posterior (AP) axis.  Thereafter, AP polarity is maintained through reciprocal negative interactions between the anterior and posterior cortical domains. We then review the mechanisms that ensure proper positioning of the centrosomes and the mitotic spindle in the one-cell embryo by exerting pulling forces on astral microtubules. We explain how a ternary complex comprised of G&alpha; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE05311#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/protein/GPA-16" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink>), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE24910#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE00107?query=GPR-2#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> is essential for anchoring the motor protein dynein to the cell cortex, where it is thought to exert pulling forces on depolymerizing astral microtubules. We proceed by providing an overview of cell cycle asynchrony in two-cell embryos, as well as the cell signaling and spindle positioning events that underly the subsequent asymmetric divisions, which establish the dorsal-ventral and left-right axes. We then discuss how AP polarity ensures the unequal segregation of cell fate regulators via the cytoplasmic proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE26846?query=MEX-6#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-6</ulink> and other polarity mediators, before ending with an overview of how the fates of the early blastomeres are specified by these processes.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Overview</title>
<para>During development, cells acquire distinct fates, and one prominent mechanism by which this is achieved is asymmetric division. In the early embryo of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, five asymmetric divisions produce six founder cells: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0001975#01--10" role="_blank">E</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0001781#01--10" role="_blank">C</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0001909#01--10" role="_blank">D</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/P4" role="_blank">P<subscript>4</subscript></ulink> (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). The first asymmetric division cleaves the one-cell zygote into a larger anterior blastomere, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink>, and a smaller posterior blastomere, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006770?query=P1#01--10" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink>. Thereafter, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006770?query=P1#01--10" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink> undergoes an asymmetric division that gives rise to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006771?query=P2#01--10" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink>. Subsequent asymmetric divisions of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> into <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0001975#01--10" role="_blank">E</ulink>, then of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006771?query=P2#01--10" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink> into <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0001781#01--10" role="_blank">C</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006772?query=P3#01--10" role="_blank">P<subscript>3</subscript></ulink>, and finally of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006772?query=P3#01--10" role="_blank">P<subscript>3</subscript></ulink> into <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0001909#01--10" role="_blank">D</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/P4" role="_blank">P<subscript>4</subscript></ulink>, complete the generation of the six founder cells whose descendants each produce specific cell types (<link linkend="bib165">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!--: PMID 6684600-->) (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The three body axes are set up during these early cleavage divisions. First, the anterior-posterior (AP) axis is established in the one-cell embryo, with the sperm-derived centrosome determining the future posterior side. This leads to a series of asymmetries between the anterior and posterior parts of the embryo derived from the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> and P<subscript>1</subscript> cells, respectively. Second, the dorso-ventral (DV) axis is established by the four-cell stage, with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> dictating the ventral side. Third, the left-right (LR) axis becomes apparent by the six-cell stage, with the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABal;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABal</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABpl;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABpl</ulink> cells defining the left side. During these early divisions, asymmetries in cellular inheritance combined with cell signaling events act to refine the fates of the founder cells and their daughters.</para>
<para>This review provides an overview of the mechanisms governing polarity establishment, asymmetric division and segregation of cell fate determinants in early <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos. We focus on events taking place in the one-cell embryo, as well as on the generation of cytoplasmic asymmetries in the early embryo. The names and localization within the early embryo of the principal proteins covered in this review are summarized in Tables <link linkend="table1">1</link>, <link linkend="table2">2</link>, and <link linkend="table3">3</link>. We refer readers to other publications for detailed coverage of the processes governing cell fate specification (e.g., <link linkend="bib182">Wang and Seydoux, 2013</link><!--: PMID 22872473-->; <link linkend="bib146">Sawa, 2012</link><!--: PMID 23140625-->; <link linkend="bib135">Pohl, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21509174-->; <link linkend="bib101">Maduro, 2010</link><!--: PMID 20108317-->; <link linkend="bib115">Munro and Bowerman, 2009</link><!--: PMID 20066102-->). This review is related to our 2005 WormBook chapter <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>, with which it overlaps in part for structure and content, since many of the fundamentals have remained unchanged. Nevertheless, the field witnessed important progress in the past several years, which we attempted to cover in the present rendition. Due to space constraints, some aspects that were covered extensively previously could not be mentioned in detail here; readers should refer to the 2005 contribution and the references therein in those cases.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Generating the anterior-posterior embryonic axis in the one-cell embryo</title>
<para>The AP embryonic axis is put in place during the first cell cycle and this process can be decomposed into three principal steps: symmetry breaking, establishment of AP polarity, and maintenance of this polarity (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). These three steps are discussed in turn below and can be viewed with high temporal and spatial resolution using simple time-lapse Differential Interference Contrast (DIC) microscopy (<link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link>).</para>
<mediaobject id="movie1" xreflabel="Movie 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="movie1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>movie 1</phrase>
</textobject> &movie1legend;</mediaobject>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<sect2 id="sec2-1">
<title>Symmetry breaking: local inactivation of actomyosin contractility</title>
<para>Fertilization occurs in the spermatheca, with the union of a mature oocyte and a sperm cell. The newly fertilized zygote is then displaced into the uterus where meiosis is completed and early embryogenesis takes place. Starting from the time of anaphase of meiosis II, the entire actomyosin network located in the cell cortex that underlies the plasma membrane undergoes contractions that depend on the non-muscle myosin II heavy chain <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> and the associated non-muscle myosin light chain 4 <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01531;class=Protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink> (<link linkend="bib116">Munro et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15363415-->; <link linkend="bib156">Shelton et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10427096-->) (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2A</link>). Moreover, such surface contractions require the Rho family GTPase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25369;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHO-1</ulink> and the Rho-binding kinase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE08098;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-502</ulink>, which together promote <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> activity and contraction of the cortical actomyosin network (<link linkend="bib93">Kumfer et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 19923324-->; <link linkend="bib113">Motegi and Sugimoto, 2006</link><!--: PMID 16921365-->; <link linkend="bib152">Schonegg and Hyman, 2006</link><!--: PMID 16899536-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="table1" xreflabel="Table 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="table1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>table 1</phrase>
</textobject> &table1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Fertilization initiates a cascade of events that leads to breaking the symmetry of the oocyte, as evidenced by a local cessation of actomyosin contractility. What is the nature of the symmetry-breaking cue? It is not the sperm entry site nor paternal genetic material (<link linkend="bib145">Sadler and Shakes, 2000</link><!--: PMID 19696886--> <link linkend="bib59">Goldstein and Hird, 1996</link><!--: PMID 8625834-->). Instead, centrioles are key. As in most metazoan organisms, the sperm contributes the sole pair of centrioles to the zygote. These centrioles recruit pericentriolar material (PCM) from maternal stores and thus assemble centrosomes that nucleate microtubules. After an initial phase during which centrosome maturation is suppressed (<link linkend="bib107">McNally et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22465668-->), the earliest sign of symmetry-breaking is the local cessation of surface contractions where centrosomes become juxtaposed to the cortex after a random walk that relies on short cortical microtubules (<link linkend="bib22">Bienkowska and Cowan, 2012</link><!--: PMID 22425158-->; <link linkend="bib31">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15186741-->; <link linkend="bib35">Cowan and Hyman, 2004b</link><!--: PMID 15343338-->; <link linkend="bib116">Munro et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15363415-->; <link linkend="bib38">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12588843-->). Centrosomes can also break symmetry at a slight distance from the cortex, although subsequent AP polarity establishment is delayed in these instances, as is the case when microtubules are lacking and, as a consequence, centrosomes approach the cortex only after a lag time (<link linkend="bib22">Bienkowska and Cowan, 2012</link><!--: PMID 22425158-->). This partial reliance on cortical microtubules may help resolve apparent contradictions in the literature concerning the requirement of microtubules for polarization in the one-cell embryo (<link linkend="bib176">Tsai and Ahringer, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17967950-->; <link linkend="bib35">Cowan and Hyman, 2004b</link><!--: PMID 15343338-->; <link linkend="bib159">Sonneville and G&ouml;nczy, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15215208-->). Microtubules from the meitoic spindle can also induce polarization in the absence of centrosomes in embryos arrested in metaphase of meiosis I (<link linkend="bib181">Wallenfang and Seydoux, 2000</link><!--: PMID 11081513-->). However, during embryogenesis centrosomes, or short microtubules that they nucleate, appear essential for symmetry breaking, as demonstrated by experiments in which centrosomes are ablated with a laser-microbeam (<link linkend="bib35">Cowan and Hyman, 2004b</link><!--: PMID 15343338-->). By contrast, removal of most or all microtubules does not prevent polarity establishment (<link linkend="bib176">Tsai and Ahringer, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17967950-->; <link linkend="bib35">Cowan and Hyman, 2004b</link><!--: PMID 15343338-->; <link linkend="bib159">Sonneville and G&ouml;nczy, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15215208-->). Compatible with interactions between centrosomes and the cell cortex being critical, symmetry breaking is compromised in embryos carrying mutations in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE10790;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAM-1</ulink> aminopeptidase, in which centrosomes remain far from the cortex (<link linkend="bib50">Fortin et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20599902-->; <link linkend="bib99">Lyczak et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 17021038-->). Interestingly, forcing centrosomes to remain at the cortex in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003914;class=Gene" role="_blank">pam-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos by depleting the dynein heavy chain <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE23997;class=Protein" role="_blank">DHC-1</ulink> rescues symmetry breaking, further indicating the importance of centrosome-cortex interactions in this process (<link linkend="bib50">Fortin et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20599902-->). Defective interaction between centrosomes and the cell cortex is also observed in embryos depleted of the deubiquitylating enzymes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE16183;class=Protein" role="_blank">MATH-33</ulink> and USP-47, and rescued also in these cases by the additional depletion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE23997;class=Protein" role="_blank">DHC-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib105">McCloskey and Kemphues, 2012</link><!--: PMID 23209443-->). These observations raise the possibility that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE16183;class=Protein" role="_blank">MATH-33</ulink> and USP-47 contribute to stabilizing one or several components critical for mediating centrosome-cortex interaction.</para>
<para>What are the mechanisms leading to the local cessation of cortical contractions following symmetry breaking? A critical event is the inactivation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25369;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHO-1</ulink> in the vicinity of centrosomes. Like other small G proteins, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25369;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHO-1</ulink> is regulated positively by guanine-nucleotide-exchange factors (GEFs) and negatively by GTPase-activating proteins (GAPs). Thus, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25369;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHO-1</ulink> GEF <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01671;class=Protein" role="_blank">ECT-2</ulink> promotes generation of active <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25369;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHO-1</ulink>-GTP, and the novel protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49498;class=Protein" role="_blank">NOP-1</ulink> is important for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01671;class=Protein" role="_blank">ECT-2</ulink> activity (<link linkend="bib177">Tse et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22918944-->). Interestingly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01671;class=Protein" role="_blank">ECT-2</ulink> is distributed uniformly on the cortex before symmetry breaking, but removed in the vicinity of centrosomes concomitantly with the appearance of non-contractile cortex (<link linkend="bib113">Motegi and Sugimoto, 2006</link><!--: PMID 16921365-->; <link linkend="bib152">Schonegg and Hyman, 2006</link><!--: PMID 16899536-->). How the presence of centrosomes results in local <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01671;class=Protein" role="_blank">ECT-2</ulink> removal is not clear. In addition, the GAP <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18872;class=Protein" role="_blank">CYK-4</ulink>, which might promote the generation of inactive <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25369;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHO-1</ulink>-GDP, has been proposed to play a role (<link linkend="bib84">Jenkins et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16873611-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18872;class=Protein" role="_blank">CYK-4</ulink> is present in sperm and persists in the newly fertilized zygote on membranous organelles in the vicinity of the centrosome, as well as on the cortex, where it could conceivably contribute to local <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25369;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHO-1</ulink> inactivation. In line with this view, depletion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18872;class=Protein" role="_blank">CYK-4</ulink> from sperm compromises symmetry breaking, with the cortical actomyosin network remaining uniformly contractile in a fraction of embryos (<link linkend="bib84">Jenkins et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16873611-->). However, the mechanisms by which <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18872;class=Protein" role="_blank">CYK-4</ulink> may contribute to polarity establishment remain to be further clarified, and it has been suggested that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18872;class=Protein" role="_blank">CYK-4</ulink> might be largely inactive during this stage (<link linkend="bib177">Tse et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22918944-->).</para>
<para>In summary, centrosomes are critical for breaking symmetry of the oocyte and thus for setting into motion the sequence of events that results in establishing polarity along the AP axis. Although <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25369;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHO-1</ulink> inactivation in the vicinity of the centrosome plays a major role in initiating AP polarity establishment, more recent work revealed the existence of a partially redundant mechanism relying on the PAR protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink>, which is discussed in <link linkend="sec2-3">Section 2.3</link> after the PAR proteins have been introduced just below.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-2">
<title>Polarity establishment: the central role of PAR proteins</title>
<para>After symmetry breaking, the non-contractile cortical area expands towards the anterior of the embryo until reaching &sim;50% egg-length (<link linkend="bib77">Hird and White, 1993</link><!--: PMID 8509454-->) (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2B</link>). This anterior movement entails a flow of cortical material away from centrosomes, which is compensated by posterior-directed streaming of cytoplasmic material (<link linkend="bib77">Hird and White, 1993</link><!--: PMID 8509454-->). Quantitative analysis and computer simulations confirm that the hydrodynamic properties of the cytoplasm can explain such compensatory streaming (<link linkend="bib120">Niwayama et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21730185-->).</para>
<para>What are the properties of the actomyosin network during the anteriorly-directed flow of cortical material? An answer comes from experiments in which the actomyosin network was severed locally with a laser microbeam and the resulting surface movements perpendicular to the cut monitored as a measure of the underlying cortical tension (<link linkend="bib103">Mayer et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20852613-->). Performing such severing along the longitudinal axis demonstrated that cortical tension orthogonal to the AP axis is twice as high in the anterior, contractile, region than in the posterior, non-contractile, region. By contrast, performing such severing along the shorter axis established that cortical tension along the AP axis is uniform throughout the embryo. Thus, there is an anisotropy in cortical tension in the anterior, being higher orthogonal to the AP axis. Such cortical anisotropy is lacking in embryos that do not have anteriorly-directed cortical flows (for instance, following defective centrosome assembly), compatible with cortical anisotropy being a consequence of such flows (<link linkend="bib103">Mayer et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20852613-->). A physical model of these phenomena that treats the cortex as a thin film of active viscous fluid demonstrates that local contractions of the actomyosin network can result in long-range movements of the cell cortex towards the embryo anterior (<link linkend="bib103">Mayer et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20852613-->). Thus, anterior-restricted anisotropy in cortical contractility can be instrumental in polarity establishment.</para>
<para>The partitioning of the cortex into a retracting anterior contractile domain and an expanding posterior non-contractile domain is accompanied by the asymmetric distribution of PAR proteins at the cell cortex. The six <emphasis>par</emphasis> genes (for <emphasis>par</emphasis>titioning defective) were identified amongst maternal-effect mutations as having defective AP polarity, resulting in the generation of daughter cells with altered fate, size, spindle positioning and cell cycle progression (reviewed in <link linkend="bib60">Goldstein and Macara, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17981131-->; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>; <link linkend="bib143">Rose and Kemphues, 1998a</link><!--: PMID 9928490-->; <link linkend="bib86">Kemphues and Strome, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413241-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49082;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40130;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> are PDZ-containing proteins that, together with the atypical protein kinase C <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02604;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink>, form the so-called &ldquo;anterior PAR complex&rdquo;. Both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27410;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-4</ulink> are Ser/Thr kinases, whereas <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> is a RING-finger protein and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06200;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-5</ulink> a 14-3-3 protein. The anterior PAR complex marked by GFP::PAR-6 is present throughout the cortex initially, but recedes from the posterior following symmetry breaking, concomitant with the anteriorly-directed movement of the contractile cortex (<link linkend="bib116">Munro et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15363415-->; <link linkend="bib38">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12588843-->). Conversely, GFP::PAR-2 is first detected on the posterior cortex shortly after the local cessation of cortical contractions and then expands anteriorly to approximately 50% egg-length (<link linkend="movie2">Movie 2</link>) (<link linkend="bib22">Bienkowska and Cowan, 2012</link><!--: PMID 22425158-->; <link linkend="bib38">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12588843-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> is also enriched on the posterior cortex (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>), while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27410;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-4</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06200;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-5</ulink> are present uniformly in both cytoplasm and cortex.</para>
<mediaobject id="movie2" xreflabel="Movie 2">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="movie2" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>movie 2</phrase>
</textobject> &movie2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Although anteriorly-directed movement of the contractile actomyosin network marked by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink>::GFP foci occurs concomitantly with expansion of the posterior domain marked by GFP::PAR-2, the dynamics of these two cortical components differs (<link linkend="bib132">Petrasek et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18805921-->). Indeed, beam-scanning fluorescence correlation spectroscopy (FCS) experiments revealed that the motility of GFP::PAR-2 is greater than that of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink>::GFP (<link linkend="bib132">Petrasek et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18805921-->). This suggests that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> distribution is somehow uncoupled from actomyosin dynamics, which is also in line with the finding that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> can bind phospholipids (<link linkend="bib114">Motegi et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21983565-->; see below in this section).</para>
<para>The dynamics of anterior and posterior PAR proteins have been investigated using fluorescence recovery after photobleaching (FRAP) (<link linkend="bib55">Goehring et al., 2011a</link><!--: PMID 21518794-->; <link linkend="bib31">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15186741-->). These experiments indicate that exchange between the cytoplasmic and the cortical pool, while occuring (<link linkend="bib31">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15186741-->), is slow compared to lateral diffusion (<link linkend="bib55">Goehring et al., 2011a</link><!--: PMID 21518794-->). In addition, analysis by Total Internal Reflection Fluorescence Microscopy (TIRF) reveals that GFP::PAR-6 resides in puncta that have a limited residency time at the cell cortex (<link linkend="bib82">Hyenne et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22545101-->). Together, these studies illustrate that PAR proteins constitute a dynamic ensemble, whose kinetics must be taken into consideration when reflecting upon the mechanisms of polarity establishment.</para>
<para>Anteriorly directed movement of the actomyosin network is critical for polarity establishment, as evidenced, for instance, by the fact that movements of cortical GFP::PAR-6 are attenuated in embryos partially depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib116">Munro et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15363415-->). Polarity establishment is also altered in other cases in which cortical contractility is compromised, such as in embryos with impaired <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25369;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHO-1</ulink> activity, including those depleted for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49498;class=Protein" role="_blank">NOP-1</ulink> as mentioned earlier, or of the TAO kinase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32936;class=Protein" role="_blank">KIN-18</ulink> (<link linkend="bib160">Spiga et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23064028-->; <link linkend="bib177">Tse et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22918944-->). Reciprocally, <emphasis>par</emphasis> genes are required for efficient anteriorly-directed cortical flows. Thus, anteriorly-directed movements of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink>::GFP are nearly abolished in embryos lacking <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003918;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-3</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003919;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-4</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003920;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-5</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003921;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-6</ulink></emphasis> function, as well as in embryos depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6, two partially redundant CCCH finger proteins that contribute to polarity establishment (<link linkend="bib31">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15186741-->; <link linkend="bib116">Munro et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15363415-->; <link linkend="bib38">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12588843-->; <link linkend="bib153">Schubert et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10882103-->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003917;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-2</ulink></emphasis>(<emphasis>RNAi</emphasis>) embryos, by contrast, cortical flows are normal initially (<link linkend="bib31">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15186741-->; <link linkend="bib116">Munro et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15363415-->), in line with the fact that anterior movements of GFP::PAR-6 are not altered during the establishment phase (<link linkend="bib38">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12588843-->).</para>
<para>In summary, polarity establishment entails contraction of the active actomyosin network towards the embryo anterior, accompanied by the segregation of anterior and posterior PAR proteins into two largely mutually exclusive domains.</para>
<para>Recent work has unveiled a role for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> during the early steps of polarization that is masked by the principal mechanism discussed above relying on local inactivation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25369;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHO-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib114">Motegi et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21983565-->; <link linkend="bib187">Zonies et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20392744-->). Embryos carrying a partial loss-of-function allele of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002297;class=Gene" role="_blank">ect-2</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002297;class=Gene" role="_blank">ect-2</ulink></emphasis>(<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00275585;class=Variation" role="_blank">ax751</ulink></emphasis>), exhibit inefficient anteriorly-directed cortical flows and delayed <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49082;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> clearance from the posterior cortex, but eventually achieve a polarized distribution of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49082;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> (<link linkend="bib187">Zonies et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20392744-->). Because <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003917;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-2</ulink></emphasis> is essential for such delayed polarization in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002297;class=Gene" role="_blank">ect-2</ulink></emphasis>(<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00275585;class=Variation" role="_blank">ax751</ulink></emphasis>) embryos, it was proposed that there is a partially redundant pathway dependent on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> for polarity initiation that is revealed when the actomyosin network is compromised (<link linkend="bib187">Zonies et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20392744-->).</para>
<para>What are the mechanisms that enable <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> to exert this function? Live imaging revealed that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> associates with centrosomes, whereas biochemical experiments established that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> is a microtubule binding protein (<link linkend="bib114">Motegi et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21983565-->). Interestingly, microtubule association protects <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> from phosphorylation by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02604;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink> <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis>. Thus, <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>, association of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> with microtubules emanating from the centrosomes at the posterior would prevent the action of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02604;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink>,  which would otherwise inhibit <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> cortical localization (<link linkend="bib114">Motegi et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21983565-->). In search of a mechanism underlying this protective effect, it was discovered that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> binds phospholipids <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis>. This binding is curbed upon phosphorylation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02604;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink>, but this negative regulation does not operate when microtubules are present in addition. Furthermore, membrane-bound <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> recruits more <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink>, creating a positive feedback loop that promotes expansion of the posterior domain. Whilst important when the principal pathway of polarity establishment is lacking, this PAR-2-dependent pathway is not essential under normal circumstances. Thus, although embryos expressing only a mutant version of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> that cannot bind microtubules initiate polarity with slower kinetics, they manage to establish it correctly thereafter (<link linkend="bib114">Motegi et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21983565-->), consistent with the notion that microtubules contribute to but are not essential for polarity establishment (<link linkend="bib176">Tsai and Ahringer, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17967950-->; <link linkend="bib35">Cowan and Hyman, 2004b</link><!--: PMID 15343338-->; <link linkend="bib159">Sonneville and G&ouml;nczy, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15215208-->;).</para>
<para>In summary, initiation of polarity establishment in the vicinity of centrosomes is aided by a PAR-2-dependent pathway that relies on the ability of this protein to bind microtubules and thus be shielded from PKC-3-mediated phosphorylation.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-3">
<title>Polarity maintenance by mutual inhibition of anterior and posterior cortical domains</title>
<para>The phase of polarity establishment is followed by a maintenance phase during which centrosome ablation no longer interferes with AP polarity (<link linkend="bib35">Cowan and Hyman, 2004b</link><!--: PMID 15343338-->), although microtubules have been suggested to contribute to refining polarity during this phase (<link linkend="bib5">Ai et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21533050-->). During polarity maintenance, mutual inhibition between the anterior and posterior cortical domains is critical and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003917;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-2</ulink></emphasis> is essential to maintain the anterior PAR complex restricted to the embryo anterior. Thus, in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003917;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants, GFP::PAR-6, which had been restricted to the anterior during the establishment phase, returns to the posterior to occupy the entire cortical circumference (<link linkend="bib38">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12588843-->), concomitantly with abnormal posterior-directed cortical movements of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink>::GFP (<link linkend="bib116">Munro et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15363415-->). Although it has been proposed that these <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> movements contribute to preventing the maintenance of PAR asymmetries (<link linkend="bib116">Munro et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15363415-->), more recent evidence indicates that cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> plays a minor role in this phase (<link linkend="bib14">Beatty et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23536568-->).</para>
<para>FRAP experiments indicate that GFP::PAR-6 and GFP::PAR-2 can diffuse slightly across the boundary during this maintenance phase, highlighting the absence of a strict physical separation between the two domains (<link linkend="bib55">Goehring et al., 2011a</link><!--: PMID 21518794-->). What, then, are the mechanisms preventing the spread of anterior PAR proteins to the posterior and reciprocally? Phosphorylation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02604;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink> is again part of the answer (<link linkend="bib75">Hao et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16459299-->). Structure/function analysis led to the identification of a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> fragment that is sufficient for localization to the posterior cortex and which contains 7 predicted <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02604;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink> phosphorylation sites. Atypical protein kinase C can phosphorylate this <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> fragment <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis>, and mutating these 7 serine/threonine residues to non-phosphorylatable alanine leads to GFP::PAR-2 being present throughout the cortex. Conversely, altering these residues to phosphomimetic glutamic acid prevents GFP::PAR-2 cortical localization (<link linkend="bib75">Hao et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16459299-->). The RING finger of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> is critical to counteract the impact of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02604;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink>, perhaps by making <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> a poorer substrate for the kinase (<link linkend="bib75">Hao et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16459299-->). In turn, the presence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> at the cell cortex promotes the recruitment of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> through a direct interaction between the two proteins (<link linkend="bib114">Motegi et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21983565-->), although <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> can localize to the cortex in a PAR-2-independent manner when <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49082;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> is lacking (reviewed in <link linkend="bib86">Kemphues and Strome, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413241-->). In addition, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> can phosphorylate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49082;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> kinase activity is required for the exclusion of the anterior PAR complex from the posterior cortex in embryos that rely solely on the PAR-2-dependent pathway described above (<link linkend="bib114">Motegi et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21983565-->).</para>
<para>Apart from the actomyosin network and the PAR proteins, other components participate in generating AP polarity in the one-cell embryo. This includes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45655;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGL-1</ulink>, the worm homologue of the <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> tumor-suppressor protein Lethal Giant Larvae, which functions redundantly with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> during polarity maintenance (<link linkend="bib13">Beatty et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 21041363-->; <link linkend="bib78">Hoege et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20579886-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45655;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGL-1</ulink> is enriched on the posterior cortex, and its depletion, while not resulting in a phenotype on its own, affects the distribution of cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> and enhances the lethality incurred from partial <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> inactivation. Conversely, increasing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45655;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGL-1</ulink> levels alleviates aspects of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003917;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-2</ulink></emphasis>(<emphasis>RNAi</emphasis>) phenotype. Therefore, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45655;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGL-1</ulink> can be thought of as defining a second pathway that contributes to polarity establishment in the absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink>. What restricts <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45655;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGL-1</ulink> cortical distribution to the posterior? Phosphorylation by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02604;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink> is key here as well. Mutating three <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02604;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink> predicted phosphorylation sites to non-phosphorylatable residues leads to uniform cortical distribution of GFP::LGL-1, whereas the converse phosphomimetic variant does not localize (<link linkend="bib78">Hoege et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20579886-->) or localizes less well (<link linkend="bib13">Beatty et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 21041363-->) to the cell cortex. These and other observations suggest that a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40130;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49082;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45655;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGL-1</ulink> complex forms initially, but that PKC-3-mediated phosphorylation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45655;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGL-1</ulink> prevents its localization on the anterior side during the course of polarity establishment (<link linkend="bib13">Beatty et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 21041363-->; <link linkend="bib78">Hoege et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20579886-->).</para>
<para>Two other components important for the maintenance of AP polarity are <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39286;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-37</ulink>, an Hsp90 co-chaperone that in other systems stabilizes kinases, and the small G protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink>. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39286;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-37</ulink> appears to function primarily by stabilizing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02604;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink>, such that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021097;class=Gene" role="_blank">cdc-37</ulink></emphasis>(<emphasis>RNAi</emphasis>) embryos exhibit defective mutual exclusion of the anterior and posterior cortical domains (<link linkend="bib15">Beers and Kemphues, 2006</link><!--: PMID 16943281-->).  However, slight differences between the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021097;class=Gene" role="_blank">cdc-37</ulink></emphasis>(<emphasis>RNAi</emphasis>) and the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004034;class=Gene" role="_blank">pkc-3</ulink></emphasis>(<emphasis>RNAi</emphasis>) phenotypes are suggestive of additional roles for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39286;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-37</ulink> (<link linkend="bib15">Beers and Kemphues, 2006</link><!--: PMID 16943281-->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink>, like its homologue in other organisms, physically interacts with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40130;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> (<link linkend="bib65">Gotta et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11412997-->), and the two components are mutually dependent for their cortical localization (<link linkend="bib1">Aceto et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16996049-->). Furthermore, embryos expressing a mutant version that cannot interact with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> as sole source of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40130;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> exhibit polarity defects mirroring those of partial <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> depletion (<link linkend="bib1">Aceto et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16996049-->). Where does active <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> GTP localize in one-cell embryos? A transgenic line expressing GFP fused to a binding domain of the Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32572;class=Protein" role="_blank">WSP-1</ulink> that specifically interacts with the GTP-bound form of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> (GFP::GBDWSP-1) has been generated to address this question (<link linkend="bib93">Kumfer et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 19923324-->). This reporter revealed that cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> GTP is enriched initially on the posterior, then on the anterior, before becoming undetectable. A targeted RNAi screen amongst potential GEFs and GAPs using this reporter led to the identification of the GEF <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47800;class=Protein" role="_blank">CGEF-1</ulink> and the GAP <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39208;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHIN-1</ulink> as regulators of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> activity (<link linkend="bib93">Kumfer et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 19923324-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47800;class=Protein" role="_blank">CGEF-1</ulink> depletion results in lower cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> GTP throughout the cell cycle, whereas <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39208;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHIN-1</ulink> depletion affects <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> activity specifically when GFP::GBDWSP-1 is normally present on the anterior cortex. Compatible with antagonistic influences on cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47800;class=Protein" role="_blank">CGEF-1</ulink> depletion leads to reduction of the domain occupied by cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40130;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink>, whereas <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39208;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHIN-1</ulink> depletion leads to an increase in this domain (<link linkend="bib14">Beatty et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23536568-->). Embryos lacking both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45655;class=Protein" role="_blank">LGL-1</ulink> function still exhibit polarized <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> GTP distribution in a CGEF-1- and CHIN-1-dependent manner. Together with other supporting evidence, these results suggests that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39208;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHIN-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47800;class=Protein" role="_blank">CGEF-1</ulink> are part of a third pathway that acts in parallel to the principal PAR-2-dependent pathway and the redundant LGL-1-dependent pathway for polarity maintenance (<link linkend="bib14">Beatty et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23536568-->). Moreover, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30818;class=Protein" role="_blank">MRCK-1</ulink> kinase is needed for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> GTP cortical enrichment when it is normally present on the anterior (<link linkend="bib93">Kumfer et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 19923324-->). Although <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000390;class=Gene" role="_blank">cdc-42</ulink></emphasis>(<emphasis>RNAi</emphasis>) embryos have been reported to have defects primarily in the maintenance phase of polarization (<link linkend="bib65">Gotta et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11412997-->; <link linkend="bib85">Kay and Hunter, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11412996-->), upon more severe RNAi-mediated depletion, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> becomes critical for cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40130;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> distribution also during polarity establishment (<link linkend="bib152">Schonegg and Hyman, 2006</link><!--: PMID 16899536-->). This earlier role appears to be mediated through removal of cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink>, since <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40130;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> remains present at the cell cortex in embryos doubly depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib152">Schonegg and Hyman, 2006</link><!--: PMID 16899536-->). Overall, these observations indicate that binding of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40130;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> plays a critical role in setting up and maintaining AP polarity.</para>
<para>Additional components, including ones that are important for basic cellular processes, are harnessed to ensure polarity maintenance. For instance, the dynamin GTPase, a universal modulator of endocytosis, membrane trafficking, and actin dynamics, participates in polarity maintenance in one-cell <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos (<link linkend="bib117">Nakayama et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19531359-->). Embryos partially depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07832;class=Protein" role="_blank">DYN-1</ulink> exhibit less cortical GFP::PAR-6 on the anterior side during the maintenance phase and, conversely, an expansion of the GFP::PAR-2 domain. Moreover, FRAP analysis reveals that dynamin promotes association of GFP::PAR-6 with the cell cortex during this phase. Compatible with this view, embryos expressing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07832;class=Protein" role="_blank">DYN-1</ulink>::GFP and mCherry::PAR-6 exhibit green and red puncta that are often juxtaposed, raising the possibility that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40130;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> associates in a dynamin-dependent manner with endocytic vesicles (<link linkend="bib82">Hyenne et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22545101-->; <link linkend="bib117">Nakayama et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19531359-->). Interestingly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07832;class=Protein" role="_blank">DYN-1</ulink>::GFP is present initially throughout the cortex as small punctae, but becomes restricted to the anterior cortex during polarity establishment, in a manner analogous to GFP::PAR-6, and this in a PAR-6- and PAR-3-dependent manner (<link linkend="bib117">Nakayama et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19531359-->). Moreover, the distribution of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07832;class=Protein" role="_blank">DYN-1</ulink>::GFP is altered in embryos depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06090;class=Protein" role="_blank">RACK-1</ulink>, which was identified for its role in cytokinesis, but whose depletion results in polarity phenotypes reminiscent of those observed in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001130;class=Gene" role="_blank">dyn-1</ulink></emphasis>(<emphasis>RNAi</emphasis>) embryos (<link linkend="bib5">Ai et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21533050-->). Whereas dynamin contributes to polarity maintenance, conversely, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40130;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49082;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02604;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02020;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> regulate endocytosis (<link linkend="bib9">Balklava et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17704769-->), indicative of a mutual interplay between the anterior PAR complex and the trafficking machinery.</para>
<para>Just like dynamin, the early endosomal protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE09711;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAB-5</ulink> is enriched on the anterior side during the maintenance phase, in a manner that depends on AP polarity cues (<link linkend="bib6">Andrews and Ahringer, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17551574-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE09711;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAB-5</ulink> depletion results in a slight alteration of the GFP::PAR-6 domain, albeit without an accompanying alteration in the GFP::PAR-2 domain (<link linkend="bib82">Hyenne et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22545101-->). However, pleiotropic phenotypes often complicate analyzing the consequences of depleting components required for basic cellular processes. For instance, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE09711;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAB-5</ulink> depletion also alters the actin cytoskeleton (<link linkend="bib82">Hyenne et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22545101-->; <link linkend="bib8">Audhya et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17591921-->), and it may be that the impact on GFP::PAR-6 is secondary to alterations in actin distribution or dynamics. Overall, whether trafficking events are instructive for directing AP polarity or merely elements that contribute in a more passive manner through their general requirement for cell physiology remains to be clarified.</para>
<para>In summary, the maintenance of AP polarity relies principally on the mutual inhibition of anterior and posterior cortical domains, which, together with associated components, ensures the robust maintenance of polarity along the AP embryonic axis.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-4">
<title>Modeling polarization</title>
<para>The wealth of information regarding the relationships between anterior and posterior polarity components, as well as knowledge about their dynamics and that of the underlying actomyosin network, have fueled mathematical modeling of how AP polarity is achieved in one-cell <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos. An initial model captured the essence of the behavior of the actomyosin network, as well as of the PAR proteins and of their relationships (<link linkend="bib175">Tostevin and Howard, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18621845-->). This model consists of reaction-diffusion equations that rest on the assumption that PAR protein dynamics at the cell cortex result from their diffusion within the cortical plane and from exchange with the cytoplasmic pool. A further assumption is that association of anterior PAR proteins with the contractile actomyosin cortex increases over time. In the output from this model, anterior PAR proteins exclude posterior PAR proteins (and reciprocally), generating effective positive feedback loops that lead to mutually exclusive cortical distributions. The molecular tenets of such mutual exclusion remain open in the model, but could correspond for instance to phosphorylation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02604;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink> in the case of inhibition of the posterior complex by the anterior one. This initial model left open several questions, including how a postulated asymmetry in the distribution of microtubules that is essential in the model to maintain polarity relates to the situation <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>. Further modeling indicates that mutual inhibition can maintain distinct domains even without a contribution of the actomyosin network, provided oligomerization of the anterior PAR proteins is included (<link linkend="bib42">Dawes and Munro, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21943422-->). Interestingly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49082;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> proteins are known to dimerize in other systems and have thus been postulated to correspond to the molecular basis for such oligomerization. This revised model features a non-linear relationship in mutual cortical exclusion, which predicts that polarity should be lost abruptly below a threshold level of anterior PAR proteins, which is indeed observed experimentally (<link linkend="bib42">Dawes and Munro, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21943422-->). A related but more elaborate model incorporating quantitative analysis of parameters that characterize the behavior of GFP::PAR-6 and GFP::PAR-2 has been developed (<link linkend="bib56">Goehring et al., 2011b</link><!--: PMID 22021673-->). In this model, the cell cortex is considered as a thin film that transports embedded molecules towards the anterior by advection, much like a river would carry leaves floating on the water surface. Compatible with this model, simulations indicate that advection by such fluid flow can indeed displace anterior PAR proteins transiently and thus be critical for polarization of one-cell <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos (<link linkend="movie3">Movie 3</link>).</para>
<mediaobject id="movie3" xreflabel="Movie 3">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="movie3" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>movie 3</phrase>
</textobject> &movie3legend;</mediaobject>
<para>In summary, mutual interactions between anterior and posterior PAR proteins have lent themselves to mathematical modeling, and future work in this direction is anticipated to unveil further tenets of the underlying mechanisms of AP polarity.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Centrosome and spindle positioning during the first asymmetric division</title>
<para>Once properly established and maintained, AP polarity is translated into several processes that contribute to correct asymmetric division of the one-cell embryo, including centrosome and spindle positioning (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). These processes are crucial for correct asymmetric division because, in animal cells, the cleavage furrow is specified so as to bisect the position of the mitotic spindle at the end of anaphase, thus dictating the relative size and the spatial relationship of daughter cells. Anaphase spindle position is determined by the location of the two centrosomes prior to mitosis, as well as that of the two spindle poles derived from the centrosomes during mitosis. In the one-cell <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo, both centrosome and spindle positioning are regulated by AP polarity cues, ensuring coordination with the segregation of cell fate determinants (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>) (reviewed in <link linkend="bib106">McNally, 2013</link><!--: PMID 23337115-->; <link linkend="bib112">Morin and Bellaiche, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21763612-->; <link linkend="bib36">Cowan and Hyman, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17287245-->; <link linkend="bib52">Galli and van den Heuvel, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18710303-->; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>; <link linkend="bib21">Betschinger and Knoblich, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15324689-->; <link linkend="bib34">Cowan and Hyman, 2004a</link><!--: PMID 15473847-->).</para>
<para>Centrosome and spindle positioning in one-cell <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos can be readily observed by simple differential interference contrast (DIC) time-lapse microscopy (<link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link>). Centrosomes and the associated male pronucleus are located initially close to the posterior cortex, and then migrate jointly towards the anterior. Concomitantly, the female pronucleus migrates towards the posterior, resulting in the meeting of the two pronuclei in the posterior half of the embryo. Migration of both male and female pronuclei depends on microtubules and microtubule associated proteins, including the minus-end directed motor dynein and members of the dynein complex (reviewed in <link linkend="bib106">McNally, 2013</link><!--: PMID 23337115-->; <link linkend="bib112">Morin and Bellaiche, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21763612-->; <link linkend="bib52">Galli and van den Heuvel, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18710303-->). Dynein present on the surface of the female pronucleus is thought to capture the plus-ends of astral microtubules nucleated by the centrosomes, and thus power migration of the female pronucleus towards the male pronucleus associated with the centrosomes (<link linkend="bib63">G&ouml;nczy et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10508861-->). After pronuclear meeting, the centrosomes and the joined pronuclei move towards the embryo center, while undergoing a 90&deg; rotation. This process is referred to collectively as centration/rotation and results in the centrosomes becoming aligned along the AP axis in preparation for cell division. Following nuclear envelope breakdown (NEBD), the spindle assembles in the cell center and along the AP axis, but is displaced posteriorly during metaphase and anaphase (reviewed in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>). Moreover, the posterior spindle pole exhibits vigorous transverse oscillations during anaphase. As a result of the asymmetric spindle position achieved at the end of mitosis, the first cleavage is unequal and generates the larger anterior blastomere <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> and the smaller posterior blastomere P<subscript>1</subscript>.</para>
<sect2 id="sec3-1">
<title>Pulling forces acting on astral microtubules</title>
<para>What is the nature of forces acting during male pronuclear migration, centration/rotation and spindle positioning? The available evidence indicates that forces pulling on astral microtubules play a major role in all three instances, although the location from which pulling forces are exerted appears to vary. For male pronuclear migration, computer simulations indicate that pulling forces act in a length-dependent manner, with larger forces pulling on longer microtubules (<link linkend="bib88">Kimura and Onami, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15866166-->). A related type of mechanism has been proposed to predominate during centration/rotation (<link linkend="bib89">Kimura and Kimura, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21173218-->). In a length-dependent type of mechanism, force generators must be distributed throughout the cytoplasm, for instance by being anchored on endomembranes, which could thus generate pulling forces on astral microtubules and associated centrosomes. It has been suggested that small movements of endomembranes towards the minus-end of microtubules could generate a net overall movement of the centrosome in the opposite direction (<link linkend="bib51">Kimura and Kimura, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21173218-->). In support of this mechanism, there is a good correlation between centrosome-directed movements of early endosomes marked by GFP::EEA-1 and that of centrosomes in the opposite direction (<link linkend="bib51">Kimura and Kimura, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21173218-->). A mathematical model indicates that a combination of microtubule length-dependent forces and the viscous drag of the pronuclei could explain male pronuclear migration as well as centration/rotation (<link linkend="bib158">Shinar et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21670261-->).</para>
<para>Whereas force generators distributed throughout the cell appear important for force generation during male pronuclear migration and centration/rotation, forces driving posterior spindle displacement seem to be cortically-based. Severing of the spindle or fragmentation of the spindle poles with a UV laser microbeam results in outward movements of the liberated spindle poles or spindle pole fragments (<link linkend="bib95">Labb&eacute; et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15492042-->; <link linkend="bib71">Grill et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12881570-->; <link linkend="bib70">Grill et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11214323-->). Because these fragments move all the way to the cortex, the force generators acting during mitosis appear to be cortically-based (<link linkend="bib95">Labb&eacute; et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15492042-->; <link linkend="bib71">Grill et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12881570-->; <link linkend="bib70">Grill et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11214323-->). Compatible with this view, pulling forces can be observed as invaginations of the plasma membrane following weakening of the actomyosin cytoskeleton (<link linkend="bib138">Redemann et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20808841-->). The frequency of these invaginations is dramatically reduced when the spindle is severed with a UV laser microbeam or in embryos lacking components required for force generation (see <link linkend="sec3-2">Section 3.2</link> below). Importantly, the spindle severing and spindle pole fragmentation experiments also establish that the net pulling force acting on the posterior spindle pole is larger than that acting on the anterior one, thus explaining the overall posterior spindle displacement (<link linkend="bib71">Grill et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12881570-->; <link linkend="bib70">Grill et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11214323-->). This asymmetry in net pulling forces is under the control of AP polarity cues and serves to couple cell polarity with spindle positioning during the first division (<link linkend="bib70">Grill et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11214323-->).</para>
<para>In summary, pulling forces acting on astral microtubules are critical for centrosome and spindle positioning in one-cell <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos. Forces appear to be exerted primarily from the cytoplasm in a length-dependent manner during pronuclear migration and centration/rotation, and from the cell cortex during mitosis. However, there is also evidence indicating that cortical forces contribute to centration/rotation (see <link linkend="sec3-2">Section 3.2</link> below) and, conversely, length-dependent forces might conceivably also contribute to spindle positioning.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-2">
<title>A ternary complex critical for generating pulling forces</title>
<para>What is the molecular nature of the force generators that exert pulling forces on centrosomes and spindle poles? The available evidence indicates that the same components are utilized during male pronuclear migration, centration/rotation and spindle positioning, either at the cell cortex and/or in the cytoplasm. Because most experiments aimed at elucidating the nature and the mechanism of action of these components were focused initially on spindle positioning, this will be discussed first.</para>
<para>A ternary complex is critical for generating pulling forces on astral microtubules. This ternary complex is comprised of two partially redundant G&alpha; subunits, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49147;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink>, two essentially identical GoLoco containing proteins, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00107;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink>, as well as the large coiled-coil protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> (<link linkend="bib32">Colombo et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12750478-->; <link linkend="bib67">Gotta et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12814548-->; <link linkend="bib161">Srinivasan et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12730122-->; <link linkend="bib179">Tsou et al., 2003a</link><!--: PMID 14534135-->; <link linkend="bib65">Gotta and Ahringer, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11231580-->). The data indicates that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> binds <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2, which associate through their GoLoco motif with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49147;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink> bound to GDP (<link linkend="bib90">Kotak et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23027904-->; <link linkend="bib130">Park and Rose, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18234174-->; <link linkend="bib33">Couwenbergs et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17908918-->; <link linkend="bib118">Nguyen-Ngoc et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17922003-->; <link linkend="bib161">Srinivasan et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12730122-->). As G&alpha; proteins are myristoylated, the entire ternary complex is anchored at the plasma membrane, and perhaps at endomembrane compartments. Spindle severing and spindle pole fragmentation experiments established that the ternary complex, presumably acting at the cell cortex, is required for generating pulling forces during mitosis (<link linkend="bib118">Nguyen-Ngoc et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17922003-->; <link linkend="bib32">Colombo et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12750478-->; <link linkend="bib71">Grill et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12881570-->).</para>
<para>How does the ternary complex result in asymmetric net pulling forces on the two spindle poles? Although the answer to this important question is not entirely clear, the asymmetry in net pulling forces correlates with an asymmetric distribution of some ternary complex components, and this in a PAR-dependent manner. Thus, whereas the cortical distribution of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49147;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink> appears uniform (<link linkend="bib130">Park and Rose, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18234174-->; <link linkend="bib4">Afshar et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16162648-->; <link linkend="bib3">Afshar et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15479639-->; <link linkend="bib65">Gotta and Ahringer, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11231580-->; <link linkend="bib111">Miller and Rand, 2000</link><!--: PMID 11102364-->), that of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 is slightly asymmetric during metaphase and thereafter, with more protein present on the posterior side (<link linkend="bib32">Colombo et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12750478-->; <link linkend="bib67">Gotta et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12814548-->; <link linkend="bib179">Tsou et al., 2003a</link><!--: PMID 14534135-->) (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). It should be noted also that some mitotic embryos exhibit bipolar asymmetry, in which both anterior and posterior cortices have higher <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 levels than the lateral cortex (<link linkend="bib130">Park and Rose, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18234174-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> distribution is bipolar in most mitotic embryos, yet all embryos undergo posterior spindle displacement (<link linkend="bib130">Park and Rose, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18234174-->), indicating that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> does not need to be asymmetrically distributed for such displacement to occur (see <link linkend="sec3-3">Section 3.3</link> below). Importantly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 asymmetry is under the control of AP polarity cues, indicating that it could be critical for the observed asymmetry in net pulling forces (<link linkend="bib32">Colombo et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12750478-->; <link linkend="bib67">Gotta et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12814548-->; <link linkend="bib161">Srinivasan et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12730122-->; <link linkend="bib179">Tsou et al., 2003a</link><!--: PMID 14534135-->; <link linkend="bib65">Gotta and Ahringer, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11231580-->). Further support for the levels of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 being key comes from transgenic animals that express YFP-GPR-1 in addition to endogenous <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2, and which exhibit exaggerated spindle oscillations (<link linkend="bib90">Kotak et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23027904-->; <link linkend="bib139">Redemann et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21278743-->). Moreover, during centration/rotation, levels of cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> also correlate with the direction of pulling forces, with more protein present on the anterior cortex (<link linkend="bib130">Park and Rose, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18234174-->). This observation supports the notion that cortical force generators play a role also during centration/rotation. A further correlation is observed in embryos depleted of the casein kinase I <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29604;class=Protein" role="_blank">CSNK-1</ulink>, which exhibit an increase of cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 levels and accompanying exaggerated centration/rotation movements (see also <link linkend="sec3-4">Section 3.4</link>).</para>
<para>In summary, these findings indicate that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and probably <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> are critical for imparting the proper extent of pulling forces on centrosomes and spindle poles in one-cell <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos. The mechanisms that regulate the distribution or function of ternary complex components are described in <link linkend="sec3-4">Section 3.4</link>, after we discuss the mechanical basis of cortical force generators below.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-3">
<title>Mechanical basis of pulling forces: dynein and microtubules</title>
<para>How does the ternary complex generate pulling forces on astral microtubules? Dynamic microtubules are an important component. Indeed, spindle severing experiments revealed that pulling forces are lacking when microtubules are stabilized by taxol in wild-type embryos or compromised in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006537;class=Gene" role="_blank">tbb-2</ulink></emphasis>(<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00241284;class=Variation" role="_blank">qt1</ulink></emphasis>) embryos, which carry a temperature-sensitive mutation in a &beta;-tubulin gene confering resistance to microtubule depolymerization (<link linkend="bib118">Nguyen-Ngoc et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17922003-->). In addition, the minus-end directed microtubule dependent motor protein dynein is required. Spindle severing experiments established that pulling forces are compromised in embryos carrying a temperature-sensitive reduction-of-function allele of the dynein heavy chain gene <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE23997;class=Protein" role="_blank">DHC-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib118">Nguyen-Ngoc et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17922003-->; <link linkend="bib150">Schmidt et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15616192-->). Similarly, pulling forces are compromised upon depletion of the dynein light chain <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03731;class=Protein" role="_blank">DYRB-1</ulink> or the dynein-interacting protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29339;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIS-1</ulink>, both of which co-immunoprecipitate with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> (<link linkend="bib33">Couwenbergs et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17908918-->; <link linkend="bib118">Nguyen-Ngoc et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17922003-->).</para>
<para>Importantly, ternary complex components are required for the presence of dynein and of associated proteins at the cell cortex (<link linkend="bib118">Nguyen-Ngoc et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17922003-->). Given that the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> homologue NuMA can associate with dynein in vertebrate systems (<link linkend="bib90">Kotak et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23027904-->; <link linkend="bib109">Merdes et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8898198-->), a plausible working model is that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> likewise mediates association with the dynein complex, thus anchoring the motor at the cell cortex (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3B</link>). Dynein could function as a <emphasis>bona fide</emphasis> motor protein, generating force by attempting to move towards the minus end of astral microtubules. With dynein anchored at the cell cortex, this would result in a pull on the astral microtubule. Alternatively, dynein could merely serve as a coupling device to retain interaction with the plus-end of depolymerizing microtubules, which would be generating force in this scenario. Intriguingly, levels of cortical YFP-GPR-1 increase locally after mechanical stimulation of the embryo with a glass needle, indicating that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 distribution is modulated by mechanical properties of the cell (<link linkend="bib28">Bringmann, 2012</link><!--: PMID 22927044-->). Furthermore, this observation raises the possibility that local increase of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 serves as a positive feedback mechanism to promote dynein anchorage at sites experiencing a cortical pull.</para>
<para>An important step forward came from elegant imaging experiments in which cortical events were visualized with high spatial and temporal resolution (<link linkend="bib91">Kozlowski et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17482544-->). Microtubule plus-ends in the immediate vicinity of the cortex were imaged using GFP::&beta;tubulin, which marks both polymerizing and depolymerizing microtubules, as well as with GFP::EB2, which marks strictly the plus-end of growing microtubules (<link linkend="movie4">Movie 4</link>). These experiments established that the cortical residency time of microtubule plus-ends is &sim;1 second (<link linkend="bib91">Kozlowski et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17482544-->), significantly lower than previously estimated (<link linkend="bib94">Labb&eacute; et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12725727-->). Interestingly in addition, imaging during spindle oscillations revealed that contacts between microtubules and the cortex are more frequent on the lateral side towards which the spindle pole is moving (<link linkend="bib91">Kozlowski et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17482544-->). Moreover, the posterior spindle pole moves with a velocity that correlates with the maximal polymerization speed of microtubules over a range of temperatures. These observations led to a 3D model of spindle displacement (<link linkend="bib91">Kozlowski et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17482544-->). In this model, differences in net pulling forces between the anterior and posterior could be due either to a higher attachment rate of microtubules to cortical force generators on the posterior, to a larger fraction of cortical force generators being active on that side or to differential mechanical properties of the actin cytoskeleton, for instance higher rigidity in the anterior. Each force generator in this model is estimated to exert a pull of &sim;50 pN. Since this value is similar to the force that can be exerted by a single depolymerizing microtubule, but about 7 times higher than that exerted by a single dynein molecule, it was suggested that microtubule depolymerization is more likely to power force generation, with dynein merely serving as a coupling device (<link linkend="bib91">Kozlowski et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17482544-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="movie4" xreflabel="Movie 4">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="movie4" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>movie 4</phrase>
</textobject> &movie4legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Another study postulated that modulation of dynein processivity is central for spindle displacement (<link linkend="bib131">Pecreaux et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 17084695-->). It was observed that partial depletion of a dynein light intermediate chain or of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 abolishes oscillations, whereas posterior spindle displacement is nevertheless achieved. These findings indicate that a threshold of force generation must be reached for oscillations to occur (<link linkend="bib131">Pecreaux et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 17084695-->). Modeling suggests that all the features of oscillations in the wild-type, including their onset and their termination, can be accounted for by an increase in the processivity of a motor, for instance dynein. Further analysis of oscillation frequencies lead to the proposal that such an increase could, in principle, result from a decrease in the detachment rate of microtubules (<link linkend="bib131">Pecreaux et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 17084695-->).</para>
<para>A major change in cortical residency times of microtubules occurs in embryos depleted of the small G protein of the ARF family <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40826;class=Protein" role="_blank">EFA-6</ulink> (<link linkend="bib121">O&apos;Rourke et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 21076413-->), which was identified as a suppressor of the lethality provoked by conditional dynein inactivation (<link linkend="bib122">O&apos;Rourke et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17676955-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00013223;class=Gene" role="_blank">efa-6</ulink></emphasis>(<emphasis>RNAi</emphasis>) embryos fail to undergo spindle oscillations and exhibit drastic prolongations of microtubule cortical residency times, although the mechanisms by which this occurs remain to be determined (<link linkend="bib121">O&apos;Rourke et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 21076413-->). GFP::EFA-6 is enriched on the anterior cortex, and rescue experiments with truncated fusion proteins indicate that the N-terminal domain and the PH domain that anchors <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40826;class=Protein" role="_blank">EFA-6</ulink> to the cortex, but not its GTPase activity, are required for spindle oscillations. Other phenotypes observed upon <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40826;class=Protein" role="_blank">EFA-6</ulink> depletion include transient separation of centrosomes from the nuclear envelope and increased pole-to-pole distance during mitosis, suggestive of excess pulling forces (<link linkend="bib121">O&apos;Rourke et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 21076413-->). Whereas it remains to be determined whether this is the case, for instance through spindle severing or spindle pole fragmentation experiments, this raises the possibility that excess and perhaps uniform pulling forces also prevents oscillations.</para>
<para>Interactions between the plus-end of astral microtubules and the cell cortex are numerous, and it is likely that most are not productive for force generation, given that merely &sim;50 force generators have been estimated to be active at any given time (<link linkend="bib71">Grill et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12881570-->). Therefore, changes that are relevant for force generators may be difficult to identify among a large number of unproductive events at the cell cortex. An attempt has been made to monitor the activity of cortical dynein using a so-called EB1 velocity assay (EVA) (<link linkend="bib73">Gusnowski and Srayko, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21825072-->). This assay is conducted in mutant embryos in which microtubules are released from the centrosomes due to a dominant mutation in the katanin <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32479;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEI-1</ulink>, thus allowing observation of microtubule fragments gliding along the cortex. The fastest amongst such movements are dependent on dynein activity and have been dubbed &ldquo;dynein dependent microtubule velocities&rdquo; (ddMTVs). Such ddMTVs are reduced in embryos depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink>, but not of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 or of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49147;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink>. This suggests, first, that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> can exert some function independently of other ternary complex components, and second, that ddMTVs do not reflect cortical pulling forces responsible for centrosome and spindle displacement. ddMTVs are more numerous during pronuclear migration and centration/rotation (<link linkend="bib73">Gusnowski and Srayko, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21825072-->), potentially reflecting the fact that the former type of interaction is more important during these earlier stages.</para>
<para>In summary, the ternary complex serves to anchor dynein to the plasma membrane, and perhaps to endomembranes. Together with microtubule depolymerization, this generates pulling forces on astral microtubules, thus enabling proper centrosome and spindle positioning during the first asymmetric division of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-4">
<title>Regulation of pulling forces</title>
<para>Because G&alpha; proteins are an integral part of the ternary complex, modulating their availability has an impact on pulling forces. Depleting the G&beta; protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02186;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPB-1</ulink> or the G&gamma; protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE20656;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPC-2</ulink>, which could normally associate with the G&alpha; proteins in a heterotrimeric configuration, results in excess movements during centration/rotation as well as increased net pulling forces on the anterior spindle pole during mitosis (<link linkend="bib4">Afshar et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16162648-->; <link linkend="bib3">Afshar et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15479639-->;  <link linkend="bib179">Tsou et al., 2003a</link><!--: PMID 14534135-->). These results are compatible with the G&beta;&gamma; dimer acting as a negative regulator of force generation, presumably by competing with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 for binding to G&alpha;-GDP. Consistent with this interpretation, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 distribution in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001679;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpb-1</ulink></emphasis>(<emphasis>RNAi</emphasis>) embryos increases during centration/rotation and becomes uniform during mitosis (<link linkend="bib174">Thyagarajan et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21652650-->; <link linkend="bib179">Tsou et al., 2003a</link><!--: PMID 14534135-->). Furthermore, the phenotypes generated by depletion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02186;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPB-1</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE20656;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPC-2</ulink> are suppressed by the concomitant depletion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49147;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink> (<link linkend="bib179">Tsou et al., 2003a</link><!--: PMID 14534135-->). The potential for negative regulation offered by the G&beta;&gamma; dimer appears to be harnessed to ensure appropriate cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 distribution in the wild-type (<link linkend="bib174">Thyagarajan et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21652650-->). Indeed, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02186;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPB-1</ulink> levels at the cell membrane are lower during mitosis, which correlates with increased cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2. As in other systems, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02186;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPB-1</ulink> traffics through the endosomal network in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib174">Thyagarajan et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21652650-->), and because RAB-5-positive early endosomes are enriched on the anterior in a PAR-dependent manner (<link linkend="bib6">Andrews and Ahringer, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17551574-->), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02186;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPB-1</ulink> trafficking may be more pronounced on the anterior side. Compatible with this view, asymmetric accumulation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02186;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPB-1</ulink> is observed inside cells, presumably in the endosomal network, following partial inactivation of intracellular trafficking (<link linkend="bib174">Thyagarajan et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21652650-->). Overall, these results suggest that modulation of G&beta;&gamma; trafficking plays a critical role during the first asymmetric division of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos.</para>
<mediaobject id="table2" xreflabel="Table 2">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="table2" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>table 2</phrase>
</textobject> &table2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Other components regulate the distribution or function of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49147;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink>, thereby modulating pulling forces. Thus, both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29404;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-7</ulink> are required for proper spindle positioning most likely through an impact on the G&alpha; proteins (<link linkend="bib33">Couwenbergs et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17908918-->; <link linkend="bib3">Afshar et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15479639-->; <link linkend="bib76">Hess et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15479638-->; <link linkend="bib111">Miller and Rand, 2000</link><!--: PMID 11102364-->). <emphasis>In vitro</emphasis>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> exhibits guanine nucleotide exchange activity (GEF) towards <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink>, but not <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49147;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink> (<link linkend="bib4">Afshar et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16162648-->; <link linkend="bib3">Afshar et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15479639-->; <link linkend="bib76">Hess et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15479638-->). Conversely, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> is needed for cortical enrichment of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49147;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink>, but not <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib4">Afshar et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16162648-->; <link linkend="bib3">Afshar et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15479639-->). As a result of this dual requirement, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> inactivation severely impairs cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 enrichment and leads to a spindle positioning phenotype analogous to that of depleting ternary complex function (<link linkend="bib3">Afshar et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15479639-->). By contrast, loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29404;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-7</ulink>, a GTPase activating protein (GAP) for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink>, leads to lower net pulling forces on the anterior spindle pole (<link linkend="bib76">Hess et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15479638-->), perhaps indicative of transit through the G&alpha; cycle being important on that side.</para>
<para>Modulation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> provides an interesting link between polarity cues and spindle positioning (<link linkend="bib51">Galli et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21857670-->). SILAC-based mass spectrometry identified four serine residues of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> that are phosphorylated in a PKC-3-dependent manner <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> and that can also be phosphorylated by atypical protein kinase C <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis>. Phospho-specific antibodies recognizing one of these residues, phospho-S737, label the anterior cortex during centration/rotation and early mitosis, compatible with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> being phosphorylated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02604;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink> <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>. Embryos depleted of endogenous <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> by RNAi and expressing RNAi-resistant <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> in which the four <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02604;class=Protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink> phosphorylation sites are mutated to non-phosphorylatable alanine (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> 4A) exhibit exaggerated centration/rotation and a slight increase in net anterior pulling forces during mitosis. Conversely, expression of a quadruple phosphomimetic version (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> 4E) dampens spindle oscillations. Most embryos expressing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> 4A or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> 4E nevertheless undergo posterior spindle pole displacement and unequal division, in contrast to embryos depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink>, indicating that PKC-3-mediated inactivation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> on the anterior side represents a partially redundant mechanism (<link linkend="bib51">Galli et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21857670-->).</para>
<para>Components have also been identified that regulate the levels of cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink>. This is the case for the casein kinase I <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29604;class=Protein" role="_blank">CSNK-1</ulink>, whose depletion leads not only to exaggerated centration/rotation, as mentioned above, but also to excess net pulling forces during spindle positioning (<link linkend="bib129">Panbianco et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18694560-->). These phenotypes correlate with the presence of excess <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> at the cortex. Simultaneous depletion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29604;class=Protein" role="_blank">CSNK-1</ulink> and of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> suppresses the phenotypes observed upon <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29604;class=Protein" role="_blank">CSNK-1</ulink> depletion alone, suggestive of the changes in ternary complex distribution being responsible for the phenotype. Because polarity cues are not affected upon <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29604;class=Protein" role="_blank">CSNK-1</ulink> depletion, this component acts downstream of, or in parallel to, PAR proteins to mediate centrosome and spindle positioning. What is the substrate of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29604;class=Protein" role="_blank">CSNK-1</ulink> relevant for force generation? An attractive candidate is the phosphatidylinositol-4-phosphate PI(4)P5 (PIP) kinase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30541;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPK-1</ulink> that converts PIP into PIP<subscript>2</subscript> (<link linkend="bib129">Panbianco et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18694560-->), the homologue of which is phosphorylated by casein kinase I in budding yeast. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30541;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPK-1</ulink> is enriched on the posterior cortex in a manner that depends on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29604;class=Protein" role="_blank">CSNK-1</ulink>, as well as on polarity cues. Interestingly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30541;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPK-1</ulink> depletion results in decreased cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and lower net pulling forces. These results suggest a model whereby PAR proteins modulate the asymmetric distribution or activity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29604;class=Protein" role="_blank">CSNK-1</ulink>, which restricts the distribution of cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30541;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPK-1</ulink> to the posterior (<link linkend="bib129">Panbianco et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18694560-->). Such posterior accumulation might lead to higher levels of PIP<subscript>2</subscript> on that side, although no such asymmetry has been reported using the PIP<subscript>2</subscript> biomarker GFP::PH(PLC1&delta;1) (<link linkend="bib8">Audhya et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17591921-->). Therefore, how the presence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30541;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPK-1</ulink> on the posterior would result in increased cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> remains to be clarified.</para>
<para>Another component that regulates the levels of cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> is the phosphatase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31433;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPH-6</ulink> and its associated partner <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41110;class=Protein" role="_blank">SAPS-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib2">Afshar et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20040490-->). Depletion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31433;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPH-6</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41110;class=Protein" role="_blank">SAPS-1</ulink> results in phenotypes analogous to those observed following partial depletion of ternary complex components, including decreased net pulling forces on the spindle poles. Accordingly, levels of cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> are decreased in embryos depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31433;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPH-6</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41110;class=Protein" role="_blank">SAPS-1</ulink>. Embryos simultaneously depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41110;class=Protein" role="_blank">SAPS-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29604;class=Protein" role="_blank">CSNK-1</ulink> are indistinguishable from those depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41110;class=Protein" role="_blank">SAPS-1</ulink> alone, indicating that modulation of pulling forces by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29604;class=Protein" role="_blank">CSNK-1</ulink> depends on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31433;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPH-6</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41110;class=Protein" role="_blank">SAPS-1</ulink> function, although the exact relationship between these components is not yet clear (<link linkend="bib2">Afshar et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20040490-->). Regardless, these observations indicate that phosphorylation of a given substrate, perhaps of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink>, normally restricts force generation. It will be interesting to identify the nature of the responsible kinase and the identity of the substrate that it phosphorylates. One tempting possibility is that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31433;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPH-6</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41110;class=Protein" role="_blank">SAPS-1</ulink> counteracts PKC-3-mediated phosphorylation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> (<link linkend="bib51">Galli et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21857670-->), as the phenotype of embryos expressing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> 4E resembles that of embryos depleted of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31433;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPH-6</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41110;class=Protein" role="_blank">SAPS-1</ulink> complex. However, there are also differences between the two conditions; for instance, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 distribution does not appear to be altered during mitosis in embryos expressing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> 4E, in contrast to those depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31433;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPH-6</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41110;class=Protein" role="_blank">SAPS-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib51">Galli et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21857670-->; <link linkend="bib2">Afshar et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20040490-->).</para>
<para>In addition to components that regulate the overall levels of cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink>, the boundaries of these domains on the cell cortex can also be modulated, as exemplified by the action of the DEP domain protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> (<link linkend="bib178">Tsou et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12223405-->; <link linkend="bib144">Rose and Kemphues, 1998b</link><!--: PMID 9477332-->). In wild-type embryos, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> is localized asymmetrically in a cortical band at the lateral-posterior cortex and the highest levels of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> correlate with the lowest levels of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>).  In embryos lacking <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002368;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-99</ulink></emphasis> function, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> are distributed in a uniform manner and, probably as a consequence, centration/rotation and spindle displacement are aberrant (<link linkend="bib130">Park and Rose, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18234174-->; <link linkend="bib178">Tsou et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12223405-->).  Indeed, spindle severing and spindle pole fragmentation experiments indicate that in wild-type embryos, forces pulling from the anterior and posterior cortices are stronger than those pulling from the lateral cortex, where <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> is located (<link linkend="bib92">Krueger et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20421425-->).  The cortical asymmetry of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> is PAR-dependent. Interestingly, cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49082;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> levels are lowest where <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> levels are highest, raising the possibility that these two PAR proteins negatively regulate the presence of cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink>, thus explaining its accumulation in a cortical band in the wild type. Moreover, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> co-immunoprecipitates with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> kinase activity is needed for proper <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> localization, together suggesting that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> phosphorylates <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> to mediate its restricted cortical localization (<link linkend="bib185">Wu and Rose, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17761536-->).</para>
<para>The actomyosin network appears to also modulate force generation. Indeed, partial depletion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> to an extent that does not affect AP polarity compromises centration/rotation and can suppress the incomplete centration phenotype in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002368;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-99</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos (<link linkend="bib68">Goulding et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17893243-->). Conversely, depletion of the myosin phosphatase-targeting subunit <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32567;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEL-11</ulink>, a negative regulator of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink>, compounds the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002368;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-99</ulink></emphasis> centration/rotation phenotype. Cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> particles undergo short-range anterior movements during centration/rotation, which have been suggested to generate anteriorly directed pulling forces on astral microtubules (<link linkend="bib68">Goulding et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17893243-->). However, whether the role of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> is mediated entirely through <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> and its impact on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 distribution or instead by a separate means remains to be determined. The contribution of the actomyosin network appears to differ during spindle displacement, since acute treatment with the actin-depolymerizing drug latrunculin leads to increased net forces pulling on the anterior side, suggestive of negative regulation on that side during mitosis (<link linkend="bib17">Berends et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23699393-->; <link linkend="bib2">Afshar et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20040490-->), compatible with a prediction of the 3D model of spindle displacement (<link linkend="bib91">Kozlowski et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17482544-->).</para>
<para>In addition to the spatial regulation of pulling forces, temporal regulation is important to ensure coupling with cell cycle progression. Spindle displacement begins shortly after the completion of chromosome congression (<link linkend="bib104">McCarthy Campbell et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19385718-->; <link linkend="bib123">Oegema et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11402065-->), and experimental modulation of the master regulator of mitosis Cdk1 leads to corresponding alterations in the timing of spindle displacement (<link linkend="bib104">McCarthy Campbell et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19385718-->). The available evidence that stems from these experiments supports a model in which spindle displacement is retarded in the wild type until the anaphase promoting complex (APC/C) inactivates Cdk1, thus coupling cell cycle progression and spindle positioning.</para>
<para>In summary, centrosome and spindle positioning rely on the correct levels, distribution and function of the G&alpha;/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> ternary complex. Through mechanisms that are becoming increasingly better understood, AP polarity cues ensure that this ternary complex functions appropriately to ensure asymmetric cell division. Interestingly, this relationship is not unidirectional: small alterations in AP polarity that persist after the maintenance phase are corrected prior to cell division, in a manner that depends on the function of the ternary complex (<link linkend="bib147">Schenk et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20430749-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Polarity and spindle positioning at the second and third cleavages</title>
<para>After the first asymmetric division, the embryo has an AP axis, with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> and P<subscript>1</subscript> having inherited different PAR domains (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4A</link>), as well as different cytoplasmic factors that influence cell fate (see <link linkend="sec5">Section 5</link>, <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>). At second cleavage, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cell undergoes a symmetric division in which the spindle is oriented perpendicular to the previous division axis; however, due to the constraints of the eggshell, one <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> daughter shifts more posteriorly and is thus designated <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4C</link>). In contrast, the P<subscript>1</subscript> cell exhibits polarized domains and divides asymmetrically again on the AP axis to produce <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> and P<subscript>2</subscript>; the position of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> cell defines the ventral side of the embryo (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>, <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>) (reviewed in <link linkend="bib101">Maduro, 2010</link><!--: PMID 20108317-->; <link linkend="bib151">Schnabel and Priess, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413232-->). The division of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABa;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABa</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> cells at third cleavage results in the left-hand <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> daughter cells being more anterior in position, which ultimately defines the left/right axis of the worm (see <link linkend="sec5">Section 5</link>), while the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> and P<subscript>2</subscript> cells both undergo asymmetric, oriented divisions (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>, <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4D</link>). Not only are division orientations during these cleavages highly defined, but also division timing is specific to each blastomere and its progeny. Thus, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> and P<subscript>1</subscript> exhibit cell cycle asynchrony, with P<subscript>1</subscript> dividing later than <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink>; similarly, after the asymmetric division of  P<subscript>1</subscript>, the P<subscript>2</subscript> daughter divides later than <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>). In this section, we first outline what is known about the molecular basis of cell cycle asynchrony at the two-cell stage and then cover polarity and spindle positioning at the second and third cleavages.</para>
<sect2 id="sec4-1">
<title>Cell cycle asynchrony in the two-cell stage</title>
<para>The P<subscript>1</subscript> cell divides approximately 2 minutes after the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cell in wild-type animals; this difference depends on AP polarity cues, as <emphasis>par</emphasis> mutants exhibit synchronous divisions. This could reflect a role for the PAR proteins in either directly segregating a cell cycle regulator, or in influencing cell cycle rates through the unequal first cleavage, which could generate cells with different amounts of a uniformly localized cell cycle regulators. The available evidence indicates that both mechanisms play a role.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 4</phrase>
</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
<para>In support of the first mechanism, a candidate approach revealed that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink> and CDC-25, two positive regulators of mitotic entry, are enriched in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> compared to P<subscript>1</subscript> (<link linkend="bib29">Budirahardja and G&ouml;nczy, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18305005-->; <link linkend="bib119">Nishi et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18199581-->; <link linkend="bib141">Rivers et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18316412-->). Across eukaryotic evolution, polo-like kinases and Cdc25 phosphatases promote entry into mitosis through activation of the cyclin dependent kinase Cdk1. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, the polo-like kinase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink> also promotes entry into mitosis and is thought to act by phosphorylating <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11778;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-25.1</ulink>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink> is present at higher levels in the cytoplasm of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cell than in the P<subscript>1</subscript> cell (<link linkend="bib29">Budirahardja and G&ouml;nczy, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18305005-->; <link linkend="bib119">Nishi et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18199581-->; <link linkend="bib141">Rivers et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18316412-->; <link linkend="bib30">Chase et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10660671-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11778;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-25.1</ulink> is also asymmetrically distributed; the nucleus of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> contains more <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11778;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-25.1</ulink>, apparently because PLK-1-dependent nuclear import occurs more readily in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> than in P<subscript>1</subscript> (<link linkend="bib141">Rivers et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18316412-->). Determining the significance of these asymmetries for cell cycle duration in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> versus P<subscript>1</subscript> has proven difficult because complete depletion by RNAi results in earlier cell cycle arrest, and partial depletion slows the cell cycles of both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> and P<subscript>1</subscript>. Nonetheless, several lines of evidence from partial RNAi experiments support a role for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11778;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-25.1</ulink> in regulating cell cycle asynchrony (<link linkend="bib29">Budirahardja and G&ouml;nczy, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18305005-->; <link linkend="bib141">Rivers et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18316412-->). First, the observed changes in cell cycle rates in various <emphasis>par</emphasis> mutants correlate with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink> and CDC25.1 localization. For example in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003918;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-3</ulink></emphasis> mutants, the cell cycle rates of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> and P<subscript>1</subscript> are like that of a wild-type P<subscript>1</subscript> cell, and the levels of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink> and CDC25.1 in both cells are similar to those in a wild-type P<subscript>1</subscript> cell. Second, although partial depletion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11778;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-25.1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink> does not abolish asynchrony, it does produce a more profound effect of slowing the P<subscript>1</subscript> cell cycle. This result indicates that P<subscript>1</subscript> is more sensitive than <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> to reduction of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11778;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDC-25.1</ulink>, consistent with these proteins being key regulators of cell cycle asynchrony between the two blastomeres in the wild-type.</para>
<para>The second mechanism for cell cycle asynchrony is coupled to the unequal first cleavage. The observation that interference with DNA replication has a stronger effect on delaying entry into mitosis in P<subscript>1</subscript> compared to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> pointed to a potential role for checkpoint control in influencing cell cycle asynchrony (<link linkend="bib26">Brauchle et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12747829-->). Such delayed entry into mitosis results from the activation of a DNA replication checkpoint utilizing the conserved ATL and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33867;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHK-1</ulink> kinases. Importantly, depletion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25103;class=Protein" role="_blank">ATL-1</ulink> and/or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33867;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHK-1</ulink> in wild-type embryos, without interfering with DNA replication, results in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> and P<subscript>1</subscript> cell cycles being closer together (<link linkend="bib26">Brauchle et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12747829-->). Further, examination of RNAi-treated embryos that have normal polarity but an equal first cleavage revealed a similar decrease in the time difference. These and other results are consistent with the model that DNA replication factors are uniformly distributed in the one-cell and become rate limiting in the P<subscript>1</subscript> cell because of its smaller size after unequal division (<link linkend="bib26">Brauchle et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12747829-->). This activates the checkpoint and preferentially slows the P<subscript>1</subscript> cell cycle. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink> asymmetry is normal in embryos lacking <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25103;class=Protein" role="_blank">ATL-1</ulink> and/or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33867;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHK-1</ulink> function, and analysis of embryos simultaneously compromised for the two pathways suggests that they act in parallel (<link linkend="bib29">Budirahardja and G&ouml;nczy, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18305005-->; <link linkend="bib141">Rivers et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18316412-->). Thus, the preferential slowing of the P<subscript>1</subscript> cell cycle by checkpoint activity, combined with the preferential acceleration of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cell cycle by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink> together contribute to the final cell cycle asynchrony observed in wild-type embryos. Similar mechanisms may contribute to setting the specific cell cycle rates exhibited after subsequent asymmetric divisions.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4-2">
<title>Polarity and spindle positioning during the second and third cleavages</title>
<para>Asymmetric division of P<subscript>1</subscript> likely depends on the PAR proteins. Although <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> are initially present around the entire cortex in P<subscript>1</subscript> (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4A</link>), an anterior <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49082;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> domain forms during prophase, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> recede to the posterior cortex (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4B</link>) (reviewed in <link linkend="bib153">Schubert et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10882103-->; <link linkend="bib86">Kemphues and Strome, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413241-->). These observations suggest that polarity is actively reestablished in P<subscript>1</subscript> in a manner that mirrors the situation in P<subscript>0</subscript>, a view supported by the observation that GFP::PAR-6 localization is coincident with an anteriorly-directed flow of cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink>::GFP also in P<subscript>1</subscript> (<link linkend="bib116">Munro et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15363415-->).</para>
<para>Although PAR dynamics during P<subscript>1</subscript> polarization are similar to those in P<subscript>0</subscript>, there also appear to be unique requirements for P<subscript>1</subscript> polarity based on the phenotypes of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003868;class=Gene" role="_blank">ooc-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003870;class=Gene" role="_blank">ooc-5</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib11">Basham and Rose, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11714689-->; <link linkend="bib134">Pichler et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10769231-->; <link linkend="bib10">Basham and Rose, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10545235-->). In embryos derived from <emphasis>ooc</emphasis> mutant mothers, PAR localization is largely normal in the one-cell, but not in P<subscript>1</subscript>. The transmembrane protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE19661;class=Protein" role="_blank">OOC-3</ulink> and the torsin family member <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28284;class=Protein" role="_blank">OOC-5</ulink> both localize to the endoplasmic reticulum and contiguous nuclear envelope. In addition, depletion of a subset of nuclear pore complex proteins results in analagous P<subscript>1</subscript> polarity defects (<link linkend="bib148">Schetter et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16325795-->). These observations suggest a link between nuclear envelope biology and polarity that remains to be elucidated.</para>
<para>The movements that determine spindle position in response to PAR polarity domains in P<subscript>1</subscript> are also similar to those described for P<subscript>0</subscript> (reviewed in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>; <link linkend="bib86">Kemphues and Strome, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413241-->). The P<subscript>1</subscript> spindle orients on the AP axis via a 90&deg;  rotation of centrosomes and the associated nucleus prior to mitosis (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4B</link>). Mutation or depletion of G&alpha;, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> show that all these components are required for nuclear rotation in P<subscript>1</subscript> (<link linkend="bib32">Colombo et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12750478-->; <link linkend="bib67">Gotta et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12814548-->; <link linkend="bib161">Srinivasan et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12730122-->; <link linkend="bib179">Tsou et al., 2003a</link><!--: PMID 14534135-->). Analysis of temperature sensitive mutations likewise reveals a role for dynein and some of its regulators (<link linkend="bib186">Zhang et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18187449-->). Embryos with impaired G&beta;&gamma; function have abnormal centrosome positioning and retarded rotation in P<subscript>1</subscript> (<link linkend="bib65">Gotta and Ahringer, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11231580-->), but it remains to be determined if these defects are due to excess G&alpha;, as for P<subscript>0</subscript>, or whether G&beta;&gamma; plays a separate role in P<subscript>1</subscript> spindle positioning.  Anaphase spindle positioning has not been analyzed extensively in P<subscript>1</subscript>, but the posterior spindle pole oscillates as in P<subscript>0</subscript>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 are similarly localized (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>).</para>
<para>There are several other genes required for P<subscript>1</subscript> nuclear rotation, but their precise roles remain to be determined. For example, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004984;class=Gene" role="_blank">spn-4</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos exhibit a P<subscript>1</subscript> spindle orientation perpendicular to the AP axis (<link linkend="bib62">Gomes et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11684665-->). However, as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07598;class=Protein" role="_blank">SPN-4</ulink> is known to be involved in translational regulation (see <link linkend="sec5">Section 5</link>), this phenotype is likely due to defects in properly translating a yet-to-be identified protein. Regardless, an interesting aspect of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004984;class=Gene" role="_blank">spn-4</ulink></emphasis> phenotype is that PAR domains in P<subscript>1</subscript> are initially normal, but then realign with the transverse spindle later in the cell cycle (<link linkend="bib62">Gomes et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11684665-->). This suggests the existence of a mechanism that reinforces alignment of the spindle with cell polarity in P<subscript>1</subscript>, which could be analogous to the refinement of polarity domains during cytokinesis in the one-cell embryo mentioned earlier (<link linkend="bib147">Schenk et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20430749-->).</para>
<para>PAR domains are also established prior to the asymmetric divisions of P<subscript>2</subscript> and P<subscript>3</subscript>, but their positions are reversed with respect to the earlier divisions, with spindle positioning being similarly reversed (reviewed in <link linkend="bib86">Kemphues and Strome, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413241-->). That is, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39258;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> domain is located along the ventral side of P<subscript>2</subscript> and the P<subscript>2</subscript>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> contact site, rather than at the posterior of P<subscript>2</subscript> (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4C, D</link>). The P<subscript>2</subscript> nucleus rotates so that one centrosome is associated with the P<subscript>2</subscript>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> cell contact (or the P<subscript>3</subscript>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink> contact) and the spindle sets up with a dorsal/ventral tilt; as a consequence, the smaller P cell is born &ldquo;anteriorly&rdquo; and ventrally, adjacent to the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink> cell (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>, <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>).  Cell recombination experiments in which wild-type blastomeres were separated and then put back together with different partners revealed that the cue for polarity reversal is contact with the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> cell (<link linkend="bib7">Arata et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20823070-->). Polarity reversal requires the activity of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49528;class=Protein" role="_blank">SRC-1</ulink> pathway. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink> has similarity to receptor tyrosine kinases and is enriched at the cell contact region of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> and P<subscript>2</subscript>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink> is required in both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> and P<subscript>2</subscript> to induce polarity reversal, while the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49528;class=Protein" role="_blank">SRC-1</ulink> tyrosine kinase is only required in P<subscript>2</subscript> (<link linkend="bib7">Arata et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20823070-->; <link linkend="bib16">Bei et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12110172-->; <link linkend="bib20">Berkowitz and Strome, 2000</link><!--: PMID 11003841-->; <link linkend="bib86">Kemphues and Strome, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413241-->).</para>
<para>Spindle positioning in P<subscript>2</subscript> likely utilizes some of the same components as in P<subscript>0</subscript>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> are enriched at the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink>/P<subscript>2</subscript> cell contact site prior to division of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> and P<subscript>2</subscript> (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4C</link>) (<link linkend="bib161">Srinivasan et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12730122-->; <link linkend="bib179">Tsou et al., 2003a</link><!--: PMID 14534135-->). Elegant cell recombination experiments using cells differentially labeled with YFP-GPR-1 and mCherry::GPR-1 revealed that the enrichment at the contact site occurs in P<subscript>2</subscript> rather than in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> (<link linkend="bib184">Werts et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21903670-->). Therefore, the asymmetry of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> at the cell contact likely reflects PAR dependent pathways for localization of these proteins operating in the P<subscript>2</subscript> cell and needed for P<subscript>2</subscript> spindle orientation. Indeed, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49528;class=Protein" role="_blank">SRC-1</ulink> are required for the localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 at the P<subscript>2</subscript> cell contact and for P<subscript>2</subscript> spindle orientation, consistent with their roles in polarity domain reversal.</para>
<para>The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> cell also undergoes an asymmetric division. A nuclear rotation event positions the spindle on the AP axis of the embryo, and one spindle pole becomes positioned at the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink>/P<subscript>2</subscript> contact site (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4C, D</link>). These movements coupled with cell polarization result in one daughter, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink> cell, being born next to P<subscript>2</subscript> and assuming endodermal fate (see <link linkend="sec5">Section 5</link>). PAR domains are not polarized with respect to AP polarity in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> cell. Once again, cell isolation and reconstitution experiments illustrated that signals from P<subscript>2</subscript> both polarize <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> for cell fate and induce spindle positioning. Both processes are regulated redundantly by the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49528;class=Protein" role="_blank">SRC-1</ulink> pathway and a Wnt signaling pathway (<link linkend="bib146">Sawa, 2012</link><!--: PMID 23140625-->; <link linkend="bib183">Werts and Goldstein, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21807106-->; <link linkend="bib184">Werts et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21903670-->; <link linkend="bib16">Bei et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12110172-->; <link linkend="bib149">Schlesinger et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10444600-->; <link linkend="bib58">Goldstein, 1995b</link><!--: PMID 7744956-->). Only some of the Wnt pathway components used to specify the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink> cell (see <link linkend="sec5">Section 5</link>) are also used for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> spindle positioning. For example, upstream components, including the Wnt signal (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17806;class=Protein" role="_blank">MOM-2</ulink>), the Frizzled receptor (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE14048;class=Protein" role="_blank">MOM-5</ulink>), and Disheveled family proteins are required.  Recent studies determined that the divergent &beta;-catenin homolog <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26743;class=Protein" role="_blank">WRM-1</ulink> also participates in regulating <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> spindle orientation, although not through transcription as predicted for canonical Wnt signaling. Instead, a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26743;class=Protein" role="_blank">WRM-1</ulink>::GFP reporter becomes asymmetrically depleted from the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink>/P<subscript>2</subscript> side of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> cell in a Wnt pathway-dependent manner (<link linkend="bib87">Kim et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23431196-->; <link linkend="bib168">Takeshita and Sawa, 2005</link><!--: PMID 16077003-->). Genetic analysis indicates that it is the removal of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26743;class=Protein" role="_blank">WRM-1</ulink> from the posterior (P<subscript>2</subscript> interacting cortex) that is key, rather than its presence in the cell (<link linkend="bib87">Kim et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23431196-->). This explains why previous studies failed to uncover a role for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26743;class=Protein" role="_blank">WRM-1</ulink> in spindle orientation. Surprisingly however, cell isolation and reconstitution experiments have shown that a Wnt expressing P<subscript>2</subscript> cell can actively orient the spindle (<link linkend="bib61">Goldstein et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16516841-->). Thus, the Wnt pathway may influence spindle positioning in more than one way, or other factors influence spindle orientation in intact embryos.</para>
<para>Although there is no obvious asymmetry of G protein pathway components in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink>, the analysis of temperature sensitive alleles of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49147;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink> indicates that these proteins are nonetheless important for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> spindle orientation (<link linkend="bib186">Zhang et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18187449-->; <link linkend="bib179">Tsou et al., 2003a</link><!--: PMID 14534135-->). Further, the defects observed in these mutants appear stronger than those observed following single loss of the Wnt or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink> pathways. This result could indicate that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06147;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49147;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink> function in both pathways, or alternatively act in a separate parallel pathway promoting spindle orientation. In addition, analysis of the dynactin components GFP::DNC-1 and GFP::DNC-2 showed that these proteins are enriched at the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink>/P<subscript>2</subscript> contact site (<link linkend="bib186">Zhang et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18187449-->). Although cell reconstitution experiments like those utilizing tagged-GPR fusions should be conducted to definitively determine if dynactin is asymmetrically localized in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> cell, dynactin localization is dependent on both MES and Wnt signaling. Further, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001017;class=Gene" role="_blank">dnc-1</ulink></emphasis>(<emphasis>RNAi</emphasis>) results in partial failures of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> rotation. Thus, asymmetric dynactin accumulation may provide a useful tool to further dissect how Wnt signaling regulates spindle movements. For example, it will be of interest to detemine if the removal of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26743;class=Protein" role="_blank">WRM-1</ulink> is necessary for dynactin accumulation in EMS.</para>
<para>Although the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cell and its daughters divide symmetrically, their division pattern is nonetheless tightly regulated. The centrosome migration pattern around the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> nucleus results in the spindle poles being perpendicular to the AP axis at NEBD, and no rotation events are seen in wild-type embryos. However, in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003918;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-3</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003921;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-6</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004034;class=Gene" role="_blank">pkc-3</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> nuclear centrosome complex rotates on to the AP axis, as in the P<subscript>1</subscript> cell (reviewed in <link linkend="bib86">Kemphues and Strome, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413241-->). Cell shape manipulations revealed that the nuclear centrosome complex rotates towards flat cell contact areas in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003918;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-3</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib180">Tsou et al., 2003b</link><!--: PMID 12642612-->). Thus the anterior PARs act not only to orient spindles onto a specific axis, but to prevent cell shape from affecting division pattern, through an unknown mechanism.</para>
<para>After division of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cell, the centrosomes migrate in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABa;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABa</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> so that they are on the future left/right embryonic axis, and the spindles set up in this orientation. However, at telophase, the future left spindle pole shifts anteriorly so that the spindles are skewed 30&deg; relative to the precise left/right axis (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>) (<link linkend="bib135">Pohl, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21509174-->; <link linkend="bib18">Bergmann et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9842711-->). The only well-characterized component to play a role in this spindle skew is the G&alpha; protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49147;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink> (<link linkend="bib19">Bergmann et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14534142-->). Temperature sensitive <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001678;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpa-16</ulink></emphasis> mutants raised at semi-permissive temperature can have normal first and second divisions, but variable <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABa;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABa</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> spindle positions. In some cases, the telophase shift in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABa;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABa</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> is reversed, which correlates with the production of adult worms with reversed handedness. It remains to be determined if <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49147;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink> is part of the cue for left/right handedness, or whether the G protein pathway is acting with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> to orient spindles responding to an asymmetry established earlier during development.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Generation of cytoplasmic asymmetries that govern cell fate specification</title>
<para>After AP polarity domains have been established in the one-cell embryo, several components act downstream of the PAR proteins to generate cytoplasmic asymmetries (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>), which contribute to specifying the fates of blastomeres or their daughter cells during early embryogenesis (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). In the following we refer to such components as polarity mediators because they are involved in the asymmetric localization of multiple downstream cell fate regulators and act in many cells. Polarity mediators include several proteins that contain tandem CCCH zinc-finger domains: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26846;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-6</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28097;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-1</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink>. In addition, the KH domain protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> and the RRM domain protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07598;class=Protein" role="_blank">SPN-4</ulink> act as polarity mediators. The CCCH zinc-finger, KH, and RRM protein domains interact with mRNAs, and most of these polarity mediators have been implicated in translational control (reviewed in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RNAbindingproteins/RNAbindingproteins.html">RNA-binding proteins</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transctrlmaternalRNAs/transctrlmaternalRNAs.html">Translational control of maternal RNAs</ulink>). We use the term cell fate regulators for those molecules that directly regulate the fate of one or a few founder cells. These regulators include <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05121;class=Protein" role="_blank">NOS-2</ulink> (P cell fate), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46967;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> fates), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44166;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink> (C and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=D;class=Cell" role="_blank">D</ulink> fate), as well as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00237;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLP-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30819;class=Protein" role="_blank">APX-1</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> fates) (reviewed in <link linkend="bib182">Wang and Seydoux, 2013</link><!--: PMID 22872473-->; <link linkend="bib146">Sawa, 2012</link><!--: PMID 23140625-->; <link linkend="bib101">Maduro, 2010</link><!--: PMID 20108317-->; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RNAbindingproteins/RNAbindingproteins.html">RNA-binding proteins</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_notchembryo/notchembryo.html">Notch signaling in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transctrlmaternalRNAs/transctrlmaternalRNAs.html">Translational control of maternal RNAs</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_wntsignaling/wntsignaling.html">Wnt signaling</ulink>; <link linkend="bib151">Schnabel and Priess, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413232-->; <link linkend="bib23">Bowerman, 1995</link><!--: PMID 7786286-->). The localization patterns of these regulators are described below in <link linkend="sec5-2">Sections 5.2</link>-<link linkend="sec5-4">5.4</link>, and their developmental activities will be explained in <link linkend="sec5-5">Section 5.5</link>.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 5</phrase>
</textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
<sect2 id="sec5-1">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> kinase activity produces a cytoplasmic gradient of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink></title>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26846;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-6</ulink> are almost identical proteins that act partially redundantly and thus will be referred to as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6, unless studies were carried out on one protein only. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 are required to generate asymmetric localization of the other polarity mediators in addition to downstream cell fate determinants, and thus can be considered primary polarity mediators.</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> is localized at higher levels in the anterior cytoplasm by the end of the one-cell stage, and thus is inherited primarily by the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> daughter cell upon division (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5A, B</link>) (<link linkend="bib38">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12588843-->; <link linkend="bib153">Schubert et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10882103-->). Analysis of the dynamics of GFP::MEX-5 fusions gave no evidence for directed transport to the anterior, but revealed that the cytoplasmic mobility of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> is faster in the posterior compared to the anterior (<link linkend="bib40">Daniels et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20627961-->; <link linkend="bib171">Tenlen et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18842813-->). Examination of a photoconvertible Dendra::MEX-5 fusion, which allows proteins to be marked and then monitored over time, yielded similar results and further showed that neither degradation nor synthesis promotes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> asymmetry (<link linkend="bib69">Griffin et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21925318-->). Several sites in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> are phosphorylated <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> in a PAR-4- and PAR-1-dependent manner and are needed for normal <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> asymmetry and function (<link linkend="bib69">Griffin et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21925318-->; <link linkend="bib171">Tenlen et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18842813-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> is likely to be the direct regulator of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> asymmetry. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> is present in a cortical and cytoplasmic gradient that correlates with the gradient of increased diffusivity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> in wild type. Although it remains to be determined how the cytoplasmic <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> gradient is produced, this kinase can phosphorylate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> at serine residue 404 (S404) <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis>. Further, mutation of S404 in Dendra::MEX-5 results in slower mobility and loss of asymmetry, similar to what is observed for unaltered Dendra::MEX-5 in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003916;class=Gene" role="_blank">par-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos. Conversely, knockdown of the catalytic subunit of PP2A phosphatase, which is uniformly distributed in the cytoplasm, results in increased <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> mobility (<link linkend="bib69">Griffin et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21925318-->). Mutations in the tandem zinc-finger domains of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>, including ones that alter the affinity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> for RNA, also cause an increase in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> mobility and loss of asymmetry (<link linkend="bib69">Griffin et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21925318-->; <link linkend="bib171">Tenlen et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18842813-->; <link linkend="bib127">Pagano et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17264081-->). Finally, FCS experiments and biochemical analyses indicate that multiple <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> complexes exist <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib69">Griffin et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21925318-->; <link linkend="bib40">Daniels et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20627961-->). These results, along with mathematical modeling, lead to the proposal that phosphorylation by a gradient of cytoplasmic <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> promotes the release of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> from RNA-containing complexes in the posterior (<link linkend="bib69">Griffin et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21925318-->). The resulting increased mobility of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> allows it to diffuse to the anterior where the lower levels of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> are insufficient to counteract dephosphorylation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> by PP2A. Dephosphorylated <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> associates with RNP complexes and cannot redistribute into the posterior as readily, generating a stable anterior to posterior gradient of MEX-5.</para>
<para>In summary, by the end of the one-cell stage, anterior-posterior polarity of cortical PAR proteins has been translated into opposing cytoplasmic gradients of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>. MEX-5/6 then regulate further downstream asymmetries as outlined below.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5-2">
<title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 promote the asymmetric localization of multiple factors</title>
<para>The mechanism by which <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 restrict the localization of the polarity mediators <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28097;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-1</ulink>, as well as the cell fate regulator <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink>, to the germ cell precursors is well understood (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>). Live imaging of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink>::GFP showed that the fusion protein is localized in two steps (<link linkend="movie5">Movie 5</link>) (<link linkend="bib140">Reese et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10983990-->). First, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink>::GFP becomes enriched in the posterior cytoplasm of the one-cell embryo before division. Second, any protein remaining in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cell is degraded, and a similar degradation occurs in the somatic daughter cell of subsequent P cell divisions. The degradation events are dependent on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> contains tandem CCCH finger domains, as do <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28097;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-1</ulink>, even though the overall sequence of these proteins is distinct. A structure/function analysis of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink>::GFP revealed that the first zinc finger ZF1 is necessary and sufficient for degradation in the anterior cell. ZF1 binds to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34193;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZIF-1</ulink>, a SOCS box protein that is a substrate recruitment factor for the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32775;class=Protein" role="_blank">CUL-2</ulink> E3 Ubiquitin ligase complex (<link linkend="bib43">DeRenzo et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12894212-->). The ZF1 of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28097;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-1</ulink> are likewise necessary for their degradation in somatic cells (<link linkend="bib140">Reese et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10983990-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="movie5" xreflabel="Movie 5">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="movie5" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>movie 5</phrase>
</textobject> &movie5legend;</mediaobject>
<para>How do <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 activate protein degradation in somatic cells? Regulation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34193;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZIF-1</ulink> by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> at the translational level is key. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006977;class=Gene" role="_blank">zif-1</ulink></emphasis> mRNA appears uniformly distributed, but the expression of a reporter transgene bearing only the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006977;class=Gene" role="_blank">zif-1</ulink></emphasis> 3&rsquo;UTR is repressed during oogenesis and then in the P lineage of embryos (<link linkend="bib125">Oldenbroek et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22265679-->; <link linkend="bib74">Guven-Ozkan et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20826530-->). Analysis of reporter gene expression in different mutant backgrounds indicates that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07598;class=Protein" role="_blank">SPN-4</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> all act negatively on <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006977;class=Gene" role="_blank">zif-1</ulink></emphasis> mRNA translation in the embryo, while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 act positively. All of these factors bind to the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006977;class=Gene" role="_blank">zif-1</ulink></emphasis> 3&rsquo;UTR <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> bind to the same region of the 3&rsquo;UTR, with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 binding being preferred. These and other data suggest that <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>, high levels of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 antagonize translational repression of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006977;class=Gene" role="_blank">zif-1</ulink></emphasis> mRNA, allowing its expression in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> and other somatic cells (<link linkend="bib125">Oldenbroek et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22265679-->). Because <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34193;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZIF-1</ulink> also promotes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> degradation in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink>, this further relieves <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006977;class=Gene" role="_blank">zif-1</ulink></emphasis> mRNA translational repression in somatic cells, whereas the high levels of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> in the germ line precursors keep <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006977;class=Gene" role="_blank">zif-1</ulink></emphasis> expression off (<link linkend="bib140">Reese et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10983990-->). Moreover, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> has been suggested to repress <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26846;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-6</ulink> translation based on <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> binding to the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003231;class=Gene" role="_blank">mex-6</ulink></emphasis> 3&rsquo;UTR and genetic analysis (<link linkend="bib172">Tenlen et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 17028349-->). Such mutual antagonism of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> would reinforce their asymmetric localization patterns and thus those of their downstream targets.</para>
<para>While the studies above suggest a role in translational regulation, other work indicates that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 can also mediate asymmetry through interactions at the protein level. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 are required for the anterior cytoplasmic enrichment in the one-cell embryo of the polo-like kinases <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink>, which are important for cell cycle asynchrony at the two-cell stage as described earlier (<link linkend="bib29">Budirahardja and G&ouml;nczy, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18305005-->; <link linkend="bib119">Nishi et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18199581-->; <link linkend="bib141">Rivers et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18316412-->). Both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink> bind to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26846;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-6</ulink> in yeast two hybrid assays via their polo box domains (PBD), and a PBD::GFP fusion protein is anteriorly enriched in embryos. These and other results suggest that physical association with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 generates the asymmetric localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink>/2.  Conversely, mutations that affect the ability of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> to bind to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink>/2 do not affect <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> asymmetry, but do affect <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> activity, including its ability to promote <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> degradation (<link linkend="bib119">Nishi et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18199581-->).</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 also appear to regulate the anterior distribution of the polarity mediator <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> at the protein level. Based on quantitative analysis of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> levels, the activity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 stabilizes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> lineage, potentially protecting it from degradation. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26846;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-6</ulink> can physically associate with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> in yeast two-hybrid assays and this interaction could promote <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> stability (<link linkend="bib79">Huang et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11830574-->). For example, the association of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26846;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-6</ulink>, and thus <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink>/2, could modify <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> stability through phosphorylation. Alternatively, because <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 both bind to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006977;class=Gene" role="_blank">zif-1</ulink></emphasis> mRNA (<link linkend="bib125">Oldenbroek et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22265679-->), the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26846;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-6</ulink> protein interaction could instead reflect a transient association that is part of the mechanism for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006977;class=Gene" role="_blank">zif-1</ulink></emphasis> regulation.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5-3">
<title>Polarity mediators interact to generate additional asymmetries of fate regulators</title>
<para>By the end of the two-cell stage, the polarity mediators <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28097;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-1</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> are asymmetrically localized (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>), while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07598;class=Protein" role="_blank">SPN-4</ulink> is still uniform at this stage. In addition to their role in repressing <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006977;class=Gene" role="_blank">zif-1</ulink></emphasis> translation discussed above, these polarity mediators determine the protein localization patterns of several cell fate regulators (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>) (<link linkend="bib124">Ogura et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12702662-->; <link linkend="bib62">Gomes et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11684665-->; <link linkend="bib167">Tabara et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 9834181-->; <link linkend="bib72">Guedes and Priess, 1997</link><!--: PMID 9043088-->; <link linkend="bib44">Draper et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8861905-->). The best characterized examples involve translational repression by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE04629?query=POS-1#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink>.</para>
<mediaobject id="table3" xreflabel="Table 3">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="table3" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>table 3</phrase>
</textobject> &table3legend;</mediaobject>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> negatively regulates <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44166;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink>, a caudal family transcription factor needed for C and D fates. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44166;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink> protein is first observed at the 4-cell stage in P<subscript>2</subscript> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink>, and then is present in their descendants through the 12-cell stage (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>) (<link linkend="bib81">Hunter and Kenyon, 1996</link><!--: PMID 8861906-->). The absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44166;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink> in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> lineage is due to translational repression by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink>, which is present at high levels in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cell and binds the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003912;class=Gene" role="_blank">pal-1</ulink></emphasis> 3&rsquo;UTR <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib126">Pagano et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19915141-->; <link linkend="bib81">Hunter and Kenyon, 1996</link><!--: PMID 8861906-->).  Similarly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> is needed for the restricted localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05121;class=Protein" role="_blank">NOS-2</ulink>, a translational factor required for P cell fate (<link linkend="bib126">Pagano et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19915141-->; <link linkend="bib83">Jadhav et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18417623-->; <link linkend="bib163">Subramaniam and Seydoux, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10518502-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> binds the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003784;class=Gene" role="_blank">nos-2</ulink></emphasis> 3&rsquo;UTR and the expression of a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003784;class=Gene" role="_blank">nos-2</ulink></emphasis> 3&rsquo;UTR reporter in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003229;class=Gene" role="_blank">mex-3</ulink></emphasis> mutants is consistent with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> negatively regulating <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003784;class=Gene" role="_blank">nos-2</ulink></emphasis> mRNA translation. However, in contrast to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44166;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05121;class=Protein" role="_blank">NOS-2</ulink> protein is repressed throughout the embryo until the 28-cell stage when it appears in the P<subscript>4</subscript> cell only, indicating that other factors cooperate with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25000;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07598;class=Protein" role="_blank">SPN-4</ulink> appears to be one such factor, because <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05121;class=Protein" role="_blank">NOS-2</ulink> is ectopically present in somatic cells in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004984;class=Gene" role="_blank">spn-4</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos (<link linkend="bib83">Jadhav et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18417623-->).</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> plays a role in repressing translation of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001609;class=Gene" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> mRNA in the P<subscript>1</subscript> lineage. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00237;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLP-1</ulink>, a Notch family receptor important for diversifying <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cell fates, is only present on plasma membranes of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> lineage cells (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5B-D</link>) (reviewed in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_notchembryo/notchembryo.html">Notch signaling in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transctrlmaternalRNAs/transctrlmaternalRNAs.html">Translational control of maternal RNAs</ulink>; <link linkend="bib151">Schnabel and Priess, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413232-->). This restricted localization is mediated through specific sequences in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001609;class=Gene" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> 3&rsquo;UTR, which can bind to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib124">Ogura et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12702662-->). An adjacent region of the 3&rsquo;UTR also binds <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE14096;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLD-1</ulink>, a KH domain protein enriched in the P<subscript>1</subscript> cell, which was originally characterized for its role in repressing germ line expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001609;class=Gene" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis>. Interestingly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> is also required for the restricted pattern of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30819;class=Protein" role="_blank">APX-1</ulink>, which is the ligand for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00237;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLP-1</ulink> in the four-cell embryo (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5C</link>). However, in this case, loss of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004078;class=Gene" role="_blank">pos-1</ulink></emphasis> results in the absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30819;class=Protein" role="_blank">APX-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib167">Tabara et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 9834181-->). Similarly, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004078;class=Gene" role="_blank">pos-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants fail to express <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05121;class=Protein" role="_blank">NOS-2</ulink> in the germ line precursor cell P<subscript>4</subscript> (<link linkend="bib167">Tabara et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 9834181-->). Given the role of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> in repression outlined above, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> may therefore act indirectly through other proteins to positively regulate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30819;class=Protein" role="_blank">APX-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05121;class=Protein" role="_blank">NOS-2</ulink>. Surprisingly however, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> directly binds the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003784;class=Gene" role="_blank">nos-2</ulink></emphasis> 3'UTR and competition experiments combined with genetic data suggested that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> antagonizes the repressive effects of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07598;class=Protein" role="_blank">SPN-4</ulink> on translation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05121;class=Protein" role="_blank">NOS-2</ulink> in the P cells (<link linkend="bib83">Jadhav et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18417623-->). These and related findings highlight the complexities of translational regulation and suggest that unique combinations of proteins interacting with the 3'UTR or other modifications can change the ultimate effect of RNA binding proteins like <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/protein/WP:CE04629?query=POS-1#05--10;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5-4">
<title>Additional mechanisms contribute to the asymmetry of cell fate regulators</title>
<para>Although the mechanisms described above can account for many of the asymmetric protein localizations in the early embryo, interesting variations on these themes contribute to the segregation of other components.</para>
<para>For instance, the pre-divisional posterior enrichment of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> has been linked to its diffusional mobility, reminiscent of the studies of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> gradient, but in this case with diffusion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink>::GFP being slower in the posterior. Pre-division enrichment is separable from somatic degradation and involves a region of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> protein that includes the second CCCH-finger (ZF2) (<link linkend="bib41">Daniels et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19221192-->; <link linkend="bib140">Reese et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10983990-->). It has been postulated that the formation of complexes of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> with P granules and/or RNA could slow <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> diffusion in the posterior and prevent its redistribution (<link linkend="bib41">Daniels et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19221192-->); however, an asymmetric distribution of P granules is not needed for proper <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> localization (<link linkend="bib53">Gallo et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 21127218-->; <link linkend="bib181">Wallenfang and Seydoux, 2000</link><!--: PMID 11081513-->). Although in theory <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> could phosphorylate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> to regulate diffusion, this seems unlikely given that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 act downstream of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45159;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> and are required for the pre-division enrichment of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink>, in addition to regulating <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> after division (<link linkend="bib38">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12588843-->; <link linkend="bib153">Schubert et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10882103-->).</para>
<para>Mobility regulated by the state of assembly may also play a role in the localization of P granules to the germ cells (<link linkend="bib53">Gallo et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 21127218-->; <link linkend="bib25">Brangwynne et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19460965-->; <link linkend="bib31">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15186741-->).  P granules were initially thought to move towards the posterior with the internal cytoplasmic flow in the early one-cell embryo, with P granules left in the anterior postulated to be degraded (reviewed in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>). However, more recent studies show that P granules also travel anteriorly with subcortical flow, such that flow <emphasis>per se</emphasis> would not provide an efficient localization mechanism (<link linkend="bib53">Gallo et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 21127218-->; <link linkend="bib25">Brangwynne et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19460965-->; <link linkend="bib31">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15186741-->). Further, detailed quantitative analysis of fluorescent P granule reporters showed that the major mechanism for posterior enrichment involves regulated assembly and disassembly (<link linkend="bib53">Gallo et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 21127218-->; <link linkend="bib31">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15186741-->), which can be modeled as a system of condensing versus dissolving liquid droplets (<link linkend="bib25">Brangwynne et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19460965-->). In particular, P granulexs grow and shrink throughout the cell cycle, with the portions of the cell destined to the P lineage showing a higher degree of assembly. Mutations in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012348;class=Gene" role="_blank">pptr-1</ulink></emphasis> gene (protein phosphatase 2a regulatory subunit) prevent P granules assembly during mitosis and lead to a lack of their enrichment in the P cells (<link linkend="bib53">Gallo et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 21127218-->). However, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012348;class=Gene" role="_blank">pptr-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants exhibit normal posterior enrichment of several other germ line proteins. In addition, although <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 act to promote P granule disassembly in the anterior cytoplasm in wild-type embryos, double mutant analysis indicates that this effect is separable from that of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32003;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPTR-1</ulink> in the posterior (<link linkend="bib53">Gallo et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 21127218-->).  These and other results suggest that this assembly mechanism is distinct from the other <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 dependent posterior localization mechanisms described earlier.</para>
<para>Another mechanism ensures the segregation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink>, a bZip-like transcription factor needed for the fates of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> and its daughter blastomeres (<link linkend="bib24">Bowerman et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID 8348611-->; reviewed in <link linkend="bib101">Maduro, 2010</link><!--: PMID 20108317-->; <link linkend="bib100">Maduro, 2006</link><!--: PMID 16998834-->, <link linkend="bib151">Schnabel and Priess, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413232-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> protein is enriched in the nucleus of the P<subscript>1</subscript> cell and its daughters, due to enrichment in the P<subscript>1</subscript> cell combined with degradation in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cell. Although its posterior localization depends on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> does not have a CCCH-type finger that could mediate its degradation via the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34193;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZIF-1</ulink> pathway. Instead, reduction of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cells is regulated in part by a different E3 ligase, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE48619;class=Protein" role="_blank">EEL-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib128">Page et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17537795-->). The polarity mediator <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28097;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-1</ulink> is also needed for proper <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> distribution. However whether <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28097;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-1</ulink> are involved in the degradation or posterior enrichment of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> remains to be determined.</para>
<para>In contrast to some organisms, the localization of mRNAs to specific cells does not appear to play a major role in the restricted localization of most proteins in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transctrlmaternalRNAs/transctrlmaternalRNAs.html">Tranlational control of maternal RNAs</ulink>; <link linkend="bib151">Schnabel and Priess, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413232-->). Although the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004078;class=Gene" role="_blank">pos-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003228;class=Gene" role="_blank">mex-1</ulink></emphasis> mRNAs are enriched in the P<subscript>1</subscript> cell, the corresponding proteins are also subjected to regulation at the level of degradation as described earlier. In addition, a number of mRNAs are localized specifically to the germ cell precursor P<subscript>4</subscript> by the 28 cell stage, but this is due to degradation in the somatic blastomeres beginning at the 4-cell stage. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/6 are required for this degradation via a mechanism that appears distinct from their role in localizing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04629;class=Protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> to the P<subscript>4</subscript> cell (<link linkend="bib39">D&apos;Agostino et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16499902-->; <link linkend="bib170">Tenenhaus et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11316796-->).  In addition, germ-line restricted mRNAs are likely regulated at the level of translation as well, as illustrated above for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003784;class=Gene" role="_blank">nos-2</ulink></emphasis>.</para>
<para>In summary, although the details regarding the mechanisms underlying some of these interactions remain to be elucidated, their existence adds to the diversity of means to localize proteins in the early embryo. Further, for many of the proteins described here and earlier, localization patterns are generated through more than one of these mechanisms, presumably conferring robustness to the system.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5-5">
<title>Refinement of cell fates</title>
<para>The division pattern of the embryo leads to a specific arrangement of cells, which, combined with cytoplasmic asymmetries, results in spatially restricted cell signaling events that further refine the fates of the early blastomeres. As mentioned earlier, contact with the P<subscript>2</subscript> cell induces <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> to divide asymmetrically to produce <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink>, the precursor of all intestinal tissue, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink>, a major muscle precursor (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>, <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>) (reviewed in <link linkend="bib146">Sawa, 2012</link><!--: PMID 23140625-->; <link linkend="bib115">Munro and Bowerman, 2009</link><!--: PMID 20066102-->; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_notchembryo/notchembryo.html">Notch signaling in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_wntsignaling/wntsignaling.html">Wnt signaling</ulink>; <link linkend="bib151">Schnabel and Priess, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413232-->). Additional asymmetric divisions in the P lineage produce C, a muscle and hypodermis precursor, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=D;class=Cell" role="_blank">D</ulink>, a muscle precursor and P<subscript>4</subscript>, the germ-line precursor (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1D</link>). Concurrently, signals from P<subscript>2</subscript> influence <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> so that it generates a different set of cell types than those produced by its more ventral sister <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABa;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABa</ulink>. In addition, the specific cell contacts generated by the skew in the division of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABa;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABa</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> cells at third cleavage leads to cell-signaling events that determine the left/right axis of the embryo (reviewed in <link linkend="bib135">Pohl, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21509174-->; <link linkend="bib151">Schnabel and Priess, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413232-->).</para>
<para>How does contact with the P<subscript>2</subscript> cell result in such different outputs in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> descendants versus the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> descendants? The answer is that the signaling pathways involved are distinct. The specification of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABa;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABa</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> will be discussed below, together with the establishment of left/right differences, as both involve the Notch signaling pathway. In contrast, the specification of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink> versus <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink> depends on an asymmetric division induced by Wnt and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49528;class=Protein" role="_blank">SRC-1</ulink> signaling pathways introduced earlier. Cell isolation and reconstitution experiments using wild-type and mutant cells indicated that the Wnt signal (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17806;class=Protein" role="_blank">MOM-2</ulink>) is required in P<subscript>2</subscript>, while the Frizzled receptor (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE14048;class=Protein" role="_blank">MOM-5</ulink>) and other downstream components are needed in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> for endoderm specification (<link linkend="bib59">Goldstein and Hird, 1996</link><!--: PMID 8625834-->; <link linkend="bib57">Goldstein, 1995a</link><!--: PMID 7743934-->; <link linkend="bib58">Goldstein, 1995b</link><!--: PMID 7744956-->;  reviewed in <link linkend="bib183">Werts and Goldstein, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21807106-->; <link linkend="bib151">Schnabel and Priess, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413232-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink>, on the other hand, is required in both P<subscript>2</subscript> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> for proper specification of endoderm (<link linkend="bib16">Bei et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12110172-->; <link linkend="bib149">Schlesinger et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10444600-->). It remains to be determined how early polarity cues localize Wnt and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink> activity.</para>
<para>The outcome of both Wnt and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49528;class=Protein" role="_blank">SRC-1</ulink> signaling is that the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> daughter cell closest to P<subscript>2</subscript>,<subscript></subscript> the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink> cell, exhibits lower nuclear levels of the TCF family transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46967;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib164">Sugioka et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21925317-->; <link linkend="bib166">Sumiyoshi et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21575624-->; <link linkend="bib97">Lin et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9458047-->; <link linkend="bib173">Thorpe et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9288749-->; <link linkend="bib98">Lin et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7585963-->; reviewed in <link linkend="bib146">Sawa, 2012</link><!--: PMID 23140625-->; <link linkend="bib115">Munro and Bowerman, 2009</link><!--: PMID 20066102-->). The most progress has been made in determining how Wnt signals polarize <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46967;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> levels. In particular, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink> cell has higher nuclear levels of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26743;class=Protein" role="_blank">WRM-1</ulink>, which correlates with the loss of cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26743;class=Protein" role="_blank">WRM-1</ulink> prior to the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> division (<link linkend="bib87">Kim et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23431196-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26743;class=Protein" role="_blank">WRM-1</ulink> is important for the nuclear export of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46967;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink> nucleus. Another &beta;-catenin family protein, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27209;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYS-1</ulink>, is also enriched in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink> cell nucleus. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27209;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYS-1</ulink> acts as a transcriptional co-activator with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46967;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink>, similar to &beta;-catenin in other systems.  The  <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46967;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> remaining in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink> cell nucleus appears to complex with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27209;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYS-1</ulink> and thus activate endodermal (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink> cells) gene targets. In contrast, the high levels of nuclear <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46967;class=Protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink>, where only low levels of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27209;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYS-1</ulink> co-activator are present, results in repression of endoderm genes; body wall and pharyngeal muscle gene targets are expressed in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink> instead (<link linkend="bib164">Sugioka et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21925317-->; <link linkend="bib80">Huang et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17567664-->; <link linkend="bib133">Phillips et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17296929-->; <link linkend="bib142">Rocheleau et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10380924-->; <link linkend="bib157">Shin et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10488343-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> is required for activation of gene targets in both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink>, and thus it is the specific combination of activators and repressors that leads to differential gene expression and determines their respective fates.</para>
<para>The fates of the somatic daughters of P<subscript>2</subscript> and P<subscript>3</subscript> appear to result mainly from the presence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44166;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink>, a caudal domain transcription factor that activates genes required for the production of muscle cell types (reviewed in <link linkend="bib101">Maduro, 2010</link><!--: PMID 20108317-->; <link linkend="bib151">Schnabel and Priess, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413232-->). As described in <link linkend="sec5-3">Section 5.3</link>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44166;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink> protein is restricted to the nuclei in the posterior half of the embryo, but it is not specific for C and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=D;class=Cell" role="_blank">D</ulink> (<link linkend="bib81">Hunter and Kenyon, 1996</link><!--: PMID 8861906-->). Given the overlap in posterior localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44166;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink>, why do the C and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=D;class=Cell" role="_blank">D</ulink> cells activate different targets than the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> daughters? The timing of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> protein availability is thought to be the reason, since <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> is present from the 2-cell stage but remains at only low levels by the 12-cell stage (<link linkend="bib24">Bowerman et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID 8348611-->). By contrast, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44166;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink> is present at similar levels from the 4- to the 12-cell stage, and thus remains at high levels when the C and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=D;class=Cell" role="_blank">D</ulink> founders are generated.</para>
<para>Although present, neither <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> nor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44166;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink> activates gene expression in the P cells. This is because the germ line precursors are protected from activating somatic programs of gene expression by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink>, which is restricted to the P cell at each asymmetric division (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>) (<link linkend="bib108">Mello et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8751440-->). Germ-line precursors in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, as in many organisms, are transcriptionally quiescent. Inhibition of transcription correlates with the failure to phosphorylate the C-terminal domain of RNA polymerase on Serine-5 (Ser-5) and Ser-2, which are needed for transcription initiation and elongation, respectively. These phophorylation events are inhibited by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> in the P cells of early <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos (<link linkend="bib169">Tenenhaus et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9705228-->). <emphasis>In vitro</emphasis> studies indicate that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> directly binds to, and inhibits, the kinase needed for Ser-2 phosphorylation (<link linkend="bib12">Batchelder et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 9925644-->). Altered forms of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> that do not bind the kinase fail to inhibit Ser-2 phosphorylation <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>, but can still suppress transcription and promote germ-line fate through effects on Ser-5 phosphorylation (<link linkend="bib54">Ghosh and Seydoux, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18202370-->). Inhibition of transcription is thought to prevent <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44166;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink> and other transcription factors from activating gene expression in the P cells. However, after asymmetric division of P<subscript>2</subscript>, the degradation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> from the somatic daughter via the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE21237;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34193;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZIF-1</ulink> pathway described above relieves transcriptional repression, allowing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> activation of target genes in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink>. Similarly, after the P<subscript>2</subscript> and P<subscript>3</subscript> divisions, disappearance of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> allows <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44166;class=Protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink> activation of target genes to commence. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> is also important for activating the translation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05121;class=Protein" role="_blank">NOS-2</ulink> in the P<subscript>4</subscript> cell; although the mechanism is unknown, this function of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28134;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> is separable from its role in preventing transcription (<link linkend="bib39">D&apos;Agostino et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16499902-->; <link linkend="bib170">Tenenhaus et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11316796-->).</para>
<para>At the same time that signals from P<subscript>2</subscript> induce the asymmetry of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink>, P<subscript>2</subscript> contact influences the fate of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> via a separate signaling pathway involving <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00237;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLP-1</ulink>, a Notch family receptor (reviewed in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_notchembryo/notchembryo.html">Notch signaling in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transctrlmaternalRNAs/transctrlmaternalRNAs.html">Translational control of maternal RNAs</ulink>; <link linkend="bib151">Schnabel and Priess, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413232-->). Only the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> daughters express the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00237;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLP-1</ulink> receptor (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>; see <link linkend="sec5-3">Section 5.3</link>) due to the repressive actions of polarity mediators in the posterior (<link linkend="bib37">Crittenden et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9015263-->; <link linkend="bib47">Evans et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID 8168128-->). Conversely, only P<subscript>2</subscript> has the ligand for the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00237;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLP-1</ulink> receptor, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30819;class=Protein" role="_blank">APX-1</ulink> (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5C</link>) (<link linkend="bib110">Mickey et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8674418-->). Thus, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00237;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLP-1</ulink> signaling can only be stimulated in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cells, and it is asymmetrically activated because only <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> makes contact with P<subscript>2</subscript>. This signaling interaction induces ABp&apos;s descendants to produce dorsal cell types (<link linkend="bib110">Mickey et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8674418-->; <link linkend="bib155">Shelton and Bowerman, 1996</link><!--: PMID 8681785-->; <link linkend="bib102">Mango et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID 7925031-->).</para>
<para>The formation of the left/right (LR) body axis also requires Notch signaling (reviewed in <link linkend="bib135">Pohl, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21509174-->; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_notchembryo/notchembryo.html">Notch signaling in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo</ulink>; <link linkend="bib151">Schnabel and Priess, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413232-->). Although <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is overtly bilaterally symmetric, there are specific left/right differences in cell types and organ positioning, which are virtually invariant in wild-type worms. The mechanism that establishes left/right handedness begins at the third cleavage (see <link linkend="sec4">Section 4</link>); the initial anterior shift in position of the left-hand <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> daughter cells is amplified by coordinated cell movements that ultimately result in specific cell contacts between certain <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> descendants and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink> cell (<link linkend="bib136">Pohl and Bao, 2010</link><!--: PMID 20833362-->; <link linkend="bib19">Bergmann et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14534142-->; <link linkend="bib18">Bergmann et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9842711-->). Physical manipulation during the third cleavage such that the right <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> daughters are more anteriorly positioned results in a reversal of cell arrangements and produces viable worms with reversed left/right handedness. These observations and the lack of any asymmetric localization of cell fate regulators within the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> lineage suggest that most aspects of the left-right axis are specified by cell-cell signaling events. Indeed,  the use of a temperature sensitive <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001609;class=Gene" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> allele and cell ablations revealed that the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00237;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLP-1</ulink> receptor and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink> cell are required for the distinct lineages on the left and right sides; however the ligand in this case is not <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30819;class=Protein" role="_blank">APX-1</ulink> and remains to be identified (reviewed in <link linkend="bib135">Pohl, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21509174-->; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_notchembryo/notchembryo.html">Notch signaling in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo</ulink>; <link linkend="bib151">Schnabel and Priess, 1997</link><!--: PMID 21413232-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Perspectives</title>
<para>The early <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo has emerged as a major model for the study of asymmetric division. In addition to the usual benefits of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, such as excellent genetic and genomic tools, the transparency of the worm embryo has allowed for major advances in imaging subcellular processes with utmost spatial and temporal resolution, through the use of countless fusion proteins. Combined with laser manipulations to test biophysical aspects of these process, as well as mathematical modeling and computational simulations, this has translated into a comprehensive approach to tackle fundamental biological questions during polarization and asymmetric division of the one-cell <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo. In addition to elucidating the mechanisms that transform an initially isotropic system into a polarized one in the first cell cycle, studies of the subsequent early divisions have yielded insights into how cell-signaling events build upon the initial polarity to further refine cell fates. Comparative studies will be of particular interest to investigate how subtle variations on these themes may explain the fascinating diversity among early nematode embryos (<link linkend="bib154">Schulze and Schierenberg, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21929824-->; <link linkend="bib27">Brauchle et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19643102-->).</para>
<para>Many findings made in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo system have had an important impact on understanding related processes in other organisms. Since the discovery of the PAR proteins in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> over 20 years ago, homologs have been identified in numerous vertebrates, in other invertebrates such as <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> and even sponges (reviewed in <link linkend="bib112">Morin and Bellaiche, 2011</link><!--: PMID 21763612-->; <link linkend="bib49">Fahey and Degnan, 2010</link><!--: PMID 21040426-->; <link linkend="bib162">St Johnston and Ahringer, 2010</link><!--: PMID 20510924-->; <link linkend="bib52">Galli and van den Heuvel, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18710303-->; <link linkend="bib21">Betschinger and Knoblich, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15324689-->). PAR proteins are localized in reciprocal cortical domains not only in asymmetrically dividing cells during development, but also after differentiation in polarized epithelial cells and neurons. Where examined, the PAR proteins have been shown to play important roles in establishing or maintaining polarity in these diverse cell types. Similarly, the use of heterotrimeric G proteins to link PAR polarity cues to spindle positioning is conserved in many organisms and cell types. Finally, the principles underlying the formation of cytoplasmic asymmetries and refinement of cell fates by signaling events in the early embryo have parallels in other systems. At the same time, the work in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is yielding new paradigms such as asymmetric cytoplasmic localization generated by regulated diffusion. Further analysis in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as well as studies in various other organisms are likely to continue to synergize in the future to further our knowledge of universal polarity mechanisms.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>We are grateful to Eugenel Espiritu, Sachin Kotak, Zolt&aacute;n Spir&oacute;, Michael VanGompel, and the reviewers for critical reading of the manuscript. We thank Eugenel Espiritu for help with the tables, Simon Blanchoud and Zolt&aacute;n Spir&oacute; for contributing Movies 1-4, as well as Ed Munro for providing the images of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27133;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink>::GFP in <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>.  Research on asymmetric division in the G&ouml;nczy laboratory is supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation (grants 3100A0-102087 and 3100A0-122500/1), that in the Rose laboratory by the NIH (R01GM068744).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>References</title>
<para/>
&asymcelldiv.2_ref;
</sect1>
</article>


