<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 1.</title>
        <para>(A). Summary of spermatogenesis. Asymmetric partitioning of cellular constituents
            occurs at three points during <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> spermatogenesis, as indicated by double-headed
            red arrows at the red numbers. 1, syncytial pachytene spermatocytes with many FB-MOs bud
            from the rachis and divide to form secondary spermatocytes (FB-MOs are shown in green);
            2, spermatids selectively retain FB-MOs as they bud from the residual body; 3, FB-MOs
            fuse with the spermatid plasma membrane as a pseudopod extends from the cell body during
            spermiogenesis. Nuclei are the circles in the center of each cell. Nuclei are patterned
            with lines to represent stages when chromatin is in condensed meiotic chromosomes or
            filled (in black) after chromatin forms a single highly condensed sphere. (B) Summary of
            morphogenesis of the FB-MO complex. 1, The fibrous body (FB) develops in close
            association with, and is surrounded by, the membranous organelle (MO) within the primary
            spermatocyte. The MO is separated by a collar region (c) into a head (h; speckled region
            at left) and body (b; region to the right of the collar); 2, the FB-MO complex reaches
            its largest size within primary spermatocytes. The double layered MO-derived membrane
            surrounds the FB, which is composed of the major sperm protein filaments; 3, the
            MO-derived membranes surrounding the FB retract and fold up while FB filaments
            depolymerize and disperse as spermatids bud from the residual body; 4, the head of each
            MO (arrow) moves to a position just below the plasma membrane (pm) of the spermatid
            after the FBs have depolymerized and disappeared. The irregular shapes within the FB
            represent retracted membrane that had covered the exterior of the FB; 5, the head of the
            MO fuses at the collar to the plasma membrane and exocytoses its contents (dots at
            arrow) onto the cell surface. A permanent fusion pore remains at the point of each MO
            fusion (each cell has many MO's; B is modified from <link linkend="bib19">L'Hernault and Arduengo, 1992</link><!--; PMID 1527173-->).</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>