<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'gmmddch6-1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'gmmddch6-1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'gmmddch6-2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'gmmddch6-2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'gmmddch6-3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'gmmddch6-3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'gmmddch6-4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'gmmddch6-4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY gmmddch6_Refs SYSTEM 'gmmddch6refs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="WMgmmddch6_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title>Genetic mapping and manipulation: Chapter 6-Mapping with deficiencies and duplications<footnote>
				<para>Edited by Victor Ambros. Last revised April 5, 2006. Published June 14, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Fay, D. Genetic mapping and manipulation: Chapter 6-Mapping with deficiencies and duplications (June 14, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.95.2, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 David Fay. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
<!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 5/05/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
-->
		<author>
			<firstname>David</firstname>
			<surname>Fay<remark>
					<footnote>
						<para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:davidfay@uwyo.edu">davidfay@uwyo.edu</ulink></para>
					</footnote>
				</remark>
			</surname>
			<affiliation>
				<address>Department of Molecular Biology, University of Wyoming, Laramie, Wyoming 82071-3944 USA</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<sect1>
		<title>Basics</title>
		<para>Deficiency (<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis></emphasis>) mapping works great, when it works! Deficiencies refer to specific deleted regions within chromosomes. The sizes of <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Dfs</emphasis></emphasis> vary greatly from just a few cosmids wide to the absence of a large portion of the chromosome. The endpoints of the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis></emphasis> may have been determined precisely using molecular techniques or may be rough guesses based on genetic tests with various mutations. Homozygous <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis></emphasis> animals are almost always embryonic lethals, as removal of multiple genes usually includes some that are necessary during early development. One of the traditional strengths of <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis></emphasis> mapping is that it can provide clear-cut irrefutable endpoints for ones region of interest (as opposed to the statistical arguments often associated with three-point mapping). The problem in mapping with <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Dfs</emphasis></emphasis> is that although positive results are generally unambiguous, negative results can be more difficult to nail down. In addition, the availability of SNPs to define true endpoints has to some extent removed much of the allure of working with deficiencies. Nevertheless, <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Dfs</emphasis></emphasis> are still extremely useful for certain types of genetic analyses, such as determining whether or not mutations are null (also see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_dominantmutations/dominantmutations.html" role="_blank">Dominant mutations</ulink>). The basics of <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis></emphasis> mapping strategy are shown in <xref linkend="figure1"/>.</para>
			<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
					<textobject><phrase> Mapping with deficiencies and duplications Figure 6-1</phrase></textobject> &fig1legend;
			</mediaobject>
<?newpage?>
		<para>In the case on the left, the deficiency (indicated by the dashed line) deletes the gene of interest and as a result fails to complement (does not rescue) the mutant allele on the opposite chromosome. Animals with such a genetic configuration will generally show the original mutant (<emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis>) phenotype. An exception to this can occur when the mutation is a hypomorph (partial loss of function). In this case, <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m/Df</emphasis></emphasis> animals may show a new "<emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis>" phenotype that is more severe than the phenotype of <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m/m</emphasis></emphasis> animals. In the case on the right, the mutation is outside the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis></emphasis> and the <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> phenotype will not be displayed. If the breakpoint of the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis></emphasis> is near <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis>, one may have generated a well-balanced heterozygote, as recombination is often reduced in the immediate vicinity of the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis></emphasis>. Nevertheless, it is important to keep in mind that recombination might occur between the right breakpoint and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis>, thereby destroying the balanced stock.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Setting up crosses with deficiencies</title>
		<para>The way most deficiency mapping is done is as follows: You set up a situation where you are looking for a mutant phenotype in the F1 generation of the cross. For example, as shown in <xref linkend="figure2" />, your mutation, which is linked to an <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis> or some other visible marker in cis, is crossed to male animals (step 2) that were created by mating N2 males into a balanced deficiency strain (step 1; provided <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis></emphasis> is not on X). In this case, the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis> mutation linked to your mutation is known to be outside this particular <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis></emphasis>. In this scenario, if the mutation is within the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis></emphasis>, you will observe <emphasis role="bold">non-Unc</emphasis> animals displaying the <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> phenotype in the F1 generation (step 3). The presence of the linked <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis> marker is necessary here to clearly identify cross-progeny. For <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis></emphasis> mapping, it is important to set up as many mating plates as possible (10-15 is not an excessive number) to guarantee generation and detection of the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m/Df</emphasis></emphasis> genotype. Failure to observe the <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> phenotype would indicate that <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> is outside the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis></emphasis>, provided that on most of your mating plates you observe good numbers of <emphasis role="bold">non-Unc</emphasis> cross-progeny. However, to ensure a correct interpretation of negative results, it is necessary to test whether animals of the genotype <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m/Df</emphasis></emphasis> have a wild-type phenotype. Such an animal can be identified by the segregation of <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis> (usually embryonic lethal) phenotypes in the F1.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
			<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
					<textobject><phrase> Mapping with deficiencies and duplications Figure 6-2</phrase></textobject> &fig2legend;
				</mediaobject>
		<para>As an alternative approach, shown in <xref linkend="figure3" />, you can also mate your mutation via the male into the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis></emphasis> strain (step 2) and look for your <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> phenotype in the first generation of cross-progeny (step 3). In this case, it is best to have the linked <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis> mutation (or other cis marker) inside the <emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis> so that cross-progeny of the desired phenotype can easily be identified via the <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> phenotype. This approach can also be used without any linked marker where one just looks directly for the appearance of the M phenotype in the F1 generation. As with the previous example, if the result appears negative (the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> is outside the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis></emphasis>), it is important to try and verify this by cloning supposed F1 cross-progeny and making sure that some of the phenotypically wild-type F1s throw progeny of both <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Df</emphasis> phenotypes.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
			<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
				<imageobject>
			<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="3.4in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject><phrase> Mapping with deficiencies and duplications Figure 6-3</phrase></textobject> &fig3legend;
			</mediaobject>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Mapping with duplications</title>
		<para>Duplications (the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Dps</emphasis></emphasis>) are used less frequently than <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Dfs</emphasis></emphasis> and are probably of less utility. Free duplications are autonomous pieces of DNA derived from normal chromosomes. They are usually relatively small as compared with full-length chromosomes and exhibit segregation properties that are independent of other chromosomes, including the chromosome from which they were derived. In many ways they most resemble extrachromosomal arrays and, like arrays, tend to be significantly less stable (especially meiotically) than normal chromosomes. <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Dps</emphasis></emphasis> will vary significantly in their genetic stability, and some published information exists describing the properties of various <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Dps</emphasis></emphasis>. Animals that contain a <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Dp</emphasis></emphasis> will effectively be triploid for the genes that lie within the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Dp</emphasis></emphasis>. <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Dps</emphasis></emphasis> are often used to balance a homozygous lethal mutation.</para>
		<para>The idea in mapping with free <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Dps</emphasis></emphasis> is to determine whether or not the mutation of interest lies within the duplicated region. If it does, then one would observe "rescue" of the mutant phenotype. To do this, one will set up crosses that ultimately lead to the isolation of the genotype shown in <xref linkend="figure4" />. This can in theory be accomplished using several approaches but usually takes a number of steps as one must re-homozygose animals for <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis>. Having a marker linked to (<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis>) but outside the region covered by the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Dp</emphasis></emphasis> can be useful for identifying candidate (<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m/m</emphasis></emphasis>) animals. As with <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Dfs</emphasis></emphasis>, it will generally be quite obvious when one's mutation lies within the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Dp</emphasis></emphasis> but rather more difficult to prove that it definitely lies outside. Creating a chromosome where the mutation is flanked by two visible markers (one outside and one inside the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Dp</emphasis></emphasis>) can help to clarify this issue.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
			<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="1.8in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject><phrase> Mapping with deficiencies and duplications Figure 6-4</phrase></textobject> &fig4legend;
			</mediaobject>
<para>One phenomenon to be aware of if you are introducing a free Dp into your genetic background via a male concerns the behavior of some free Dps during male meiosis. Namely, certain Dps (including some derived from the autosomes) tend to pair and subsequently disjoin from the lone X chromosome, leading to sperm that contain either the X <emphasis>or</emphasis> the Dp, but not both (<link linkend="bib1">Herman et al., 1979</link>). The functional consequence of this is that the majority of Dp-containing cross progeny tend to be males, which may not be particularly useful if the next step in your strategy is to self the Dp-containing hermaphrodites. Thus, it may be prudent to set up additional mating plates and pick more potential Dp-containing hermaphrodites in these situations to ensure that sufficient hermaphrodites containing the Dp are obtained.</para>
	</sect1>
<sect1>
	<title>References</title>
	&gmmddch6_Refs;
	<para/>
</sect1>
</article>