<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY esg_Refs SYSTEM 'esgrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="esg_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Essential genes<remark>
               <footnote>
                    <para>Edited by Jonathan Hodgkin and Philip Anderson. Last revised March 4, 2005. Published December 24, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Kemphues K. Essential Genes (December 24, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.57.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 Kenneth Kemphues, This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
            </remark>
        </title>
        <!--            <revhistory>
                        <revision>
                                <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
                                <date>Last revised 3/4/05</date>
                        </revision>
                </revhistory>
-->
        <author>
            <firstname>Kenneth</firstname>
            <surname>Kemphues<remark>
                    <footnote>
                        <para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:kjk1@cornell.edu">kjk1@cornell.edu</ulink>
                        </para>
                    </footnote>
                </remark>
            </surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Department of Molecular Biology and Genetics, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY, 14853, USA</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Understanding the biology of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">relies on identification and analysis of
            essential genes, genes required for growth to a fertile adult. Approaches for
            identifying essential genes include several types of classical forward genetic screens,
            genome-wide RNA interference screens and systematic targeted gene knockout. Based on
            most estimates made from screening results thus far, from 15&#x02013;30% of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">genes
            appear to be essential. Genetic redundancy masks some essential functions and pleiotropy
            of many essential genes poses a challenge for a full understanding of their functions.
            Temperature sensitive mutations are valuable tools for studies of essential genes, but
            our ability to analyze essential genes would benefit from development of new tools for
            conditional inactivation or activation of specific genes.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
    <sect1>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>Understanding the biology of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> relies on identification and analysis of
            essential genes. An essential gene is defined here as a gene necessary for growth to a
            fertile adult. Some essential genes were identified fortuitously, but most essential
            genes have been identified through mutant screens designed specifically to isolate
            lethal and sterile mutations. Starting with Sydney Brenner&apos;s pioneering genetic
            analysis, many <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> geneticists have sought to understand the nature of the genome
            by estimating the fraction of the genome devoted to essential functions. Based on the
            frequency of X chromosome lethal mutations, Brenner estimated that the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome
            had about 2000 essential genes (<link linkend="bib3">Brenner, 1974</link><!--; PMID 4366476-->). Inclusion of sterile
            mutations raised this estimate to about 3000, and a number of screens for lethal and
            sterile mutations in specific genomic regions in the 1970s and 80s yielded gene
            frequencies raising the upper limit of this estimate to as high as 30% of the genome or
            about 5700. (See <link linkend="bib16">Herman, 1978</link><!--; PMID 631558--> and <link linkend="bib23">Johnsen and Baillie, 1997</link><!--; PMID-->) for
            references and discussion. Also see (<link linkend="bib9">Feichtinger, 1995</link><!--; PMID-->, for alternative
            statistical analyses arriving at an estimate of about 8500.) With the sequencing of the
            genome and the development of methods to target specific genes, it is now within our
            power to obtain loss-of-function mutations in every gene in the worm, and efforts are
            under way to do just that. However, even with this new ability to systematically knock
            out genes, many essential functions can remain cryptic due to genetic redundancy or to pleiotropy.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
	<title>Types of essential genes</title>
	<para>There are three types of mutations that identify essential
        functions: zygotic lethal mutations (lethals), maternal-effect lethal mutations
        (maternal-effect lethals) and sterile mutations (steriles). Zygotic lethals prevent the
        development to adult of individuals homozygous for the mutation. Zygotic lethals are broadly
        categorized, based on the time of developmental arrest, as embryonic or larval lethals.
        Maternal-effect lethals are a special class of sterilizing mutations that prevent the
        development of the progeny of hermaphrodites homozygous for the mutation. Such mutations
        define genes whose expression in the mother is required for embryonic development. Sterile
        mutations prevent the production of fertilized eggs by individuals homozygous for the
        mutation. Sterility could arise due to defects in germline development, somatic gonad
    development, oogenesis, spermatogenesis, ovulation or fertilization.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Methods for identifying essential genes</title>
		<para>Classically, most lethal and sterile mutations have been identified by
        random mutagenesis followed by either of two types of screens: genome-wide screens for
        conditional lethals, such as temperature-sensitive mutations, and screens for
        non-conditional lethals and steriles in particular genomic regions for which balancers are
        available. More recently this approach has been augmented and, to a certain extent, replaced
        by approaches that target individual genes for knockdown or knockout. Two different
        large-scale screening methods are being used: systematic RNA interference (RNAi) and
        PCR-based screens for intragenic deletions after mutagenesis.</para>
		<sect2>
		<title>Classical mutant hunts</title>
	<para>Genome wide screens for temperature-sensitive embryonic lethal mutations carried out in the late
        1970s and early 80s provided the first stocked lethal mutants for studies of development.
        Genes identified in these early screens are named either <emphasis>emb</emphasis> (arrest in embryogenesis) or
        <emphasis>zyg</emphasis> (zygote defective) depending on the lab where the work was done, but operationally the
        screens were identical. Their analysis provided a foundation for understanding the
        complexity of lethal phenotypes as well as insight into the relative contributions of
        maternal vs. zygotic gene expression to the developmental process (see <link linkend="bib48">Wood, 1988</link><!--; PMID-->
        for references and discussion). Conclusions from the work were that many genes are required
        at multiple times in development and maternal gene expression plays a major role in
        embryogenesis. Temperature-sensitive lethal mutations are extremely valuable because they
        can be used to analyze essential genes with roles in multiple processes and are discussed
        more below.</para>
		<para>Non-conditional lethal and sterile mutations must be maintained in the
        heterozygous condition, requiring constant selection to avoid loss of the mutation. This
        problem can be partially overcome by using closely linked visible markers to &#x0201C;balance&#x0201D; the
        lethal mutation. Because of this, early screens for lethal and sterile mutations were
        limited to small regions of the genome with convenient visible markers (e.g., <link linkend="bib38">Rogalski et
        al., 1982</link><!--; PMID 7187364-->; <link linkend="bib39">Rose and Baillie, 1980</link><!--; PMID 7262541-->). However, the development of
        free duplications and crossover-suppressing chromosomal rearrangements (balancer
        chromosomes) allowed easy maintenance of lethals and steriles, thus making it feasible to
        carry out large-scale screens for non-conditional lethal mutations (see <link linkend="bib7">Edgley et al.,
        1995</link><!--; PMID 8531724--> for a detailed discussion of balancer chromosomes). Such screens are
        restricted to regions of the genome for which balancers are available. However, because such
        balancers cover much of the genome it has been possible to collect mutations representing
        more than 860 essential loci by this method (for example <link linkend="bib4">Clark et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID 3396868-->;
        <link linkend="bib13">Gonczy et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10085292-->; <link linkend="bib16">Herman, 1978</link><!--; PMID 631558-->; <link linkend="bib17">Howell et al., 1987</link><!--; PMID-->;
        <link linkend="bib18">Howell and Rose, 1990</link><!--; PMID 2249758-->; <link linkend="bib21">Johnsen and Baillie, 1988</link><!--; PMID 3419443-->; <link linkend="bib22">Johnsen and
        Baillie, 1991</link><!--; PMID 1752418-->; <link linkend="bib25">Kemphues et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID 3224814-->; <link linkend="bib29">McKim et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID
        8608931-->; <link linkend="bib30">McKim et al., 1992</link><!--; PMID 1603066-->; <link linkend="bib32">Meneely and Herman, 1979</link><!--; PMID 574105-->; <link linkend="bib38">Rogalski
        et al., 1982</link><!--; PMID 7187364-->; <link linkend="bib39">Rose and Baillie, 1980</link><!--; PMID 7262541-->; <link linkend="bib40">Rosenbluth et al., 1983</link><!--;
        PMID-->; <link linkend="bib44">Sigurdson et al., 1984</link><!--; PMID 6500256-->; <link linkend="bib46">Stewart et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9862482-->; <link linkend="bib49">Zetka and
        Rose, 1992</link><!--; PMID 1644275-->). Genes identified in these screens are named <emphasis>let</emphasis> (lethal), <emphasis>ooc</emphasis>
        (oocyte defective), <emphasis>mel</emphasis> (maternal-effect lethal), and <emphasis>spe</emphasis> (spermatogenesis defective) or <emphasis>fer</emphasis>
        (fertilization defective &#x02014; identical to <emphasis>spe</emphasis> mutants in phenotype). For <emphasis>mel</emphasis> and <emphasis>spe</emphasis> mutants
        it has been possible to develop genome-wide screens for non-conditional mutations in the
        absence of balancer chromosomes. In these screens, F1 progeny of mutagenized hermaphrodites
        are picked singly onto plates and the phenotypes are scored in the F2. In the case of
        spermatogenesis defective mutations, the homozygotes are identified as hermaphrodites that
        produce only unfertilized eggs and whose embryo production can be rescued by mating to wild-type males (for example <link linkend="bib1">Argon and Ward, 1980</link><!--; PMID 7196361-->; <link linkend="bib27">L'Hernault et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID
        3197956-->; <link linkend="bib47">Ward and Miwa, 1978</link><!--; PMID 580424-->). In the case of<emphasis> mel</emphasis> mutations, the homozygous
        mutant animals are identified in the genetic background of an egg-laying defective mutation
        (<link linkend="bib26">Kemphues et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID 3345562-->; <link linkend="bib37">Priess et al., 1987</link><!--; PMID 3677169-->). Because egg-laying
        defects allow larvae to hatch inside the mother, killing her at a young age, mutations that
        block production of larval progeny allow survival of the F2 animals into old age.
        Maternal-effect lethal mutations can be distinguished from sterile mutations by the
        accumulation of fertilized but unhatched eggs in the uterus. Unfertilized eggs do not form
        light-refracting eggshells. </para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
		<title>RNAi</title>
		<para>Identification and analysis of essential genes has been
        greatly facilitated by RNA interference (RNAi; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_introreversegenetics/introreversegenetics.html">Reverse genetics</ulink>).RNAi leads to
        gene-specific mRNA degradation and is triggered by double stranded RNAi specific for the
        target gene. The double stranded RNA can be delivered by microinjection, by uptake of dsRNA
        by worms in solution (soaking), or by feeding worms bacteria engineered to synthesize the
        RNA of interest. Whole genome screens have been carried out by RNAi feeding in a wild-type
        genetic background (<link linkend="bib10">Fraser et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11099033-->; <link linkend="bib24">Kamath et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529635-->)
        and in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rrf-3" role="_blank">rrf-3</ulink></emphasis> sensitized genetic background (<link linkend="bib45">Simmer et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14551910-->). Because
        RNAi is susceptible to false negatives and often gives incompletely penetrant phenotypes
        (see below), it can only provide a minimum estimate for essential genes in the genome.
        Although the screens in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rrf-3" role="_blank">rrf-3</ulink></emphasis> genetic background were more sensitive for viable RNAi
        phenotypes, they identified slightly fewer essential genes than found in the wild-type
        background. Based on RNAi results in the wild-type background, the minimum number of
        essential genes is about 1750. (1170 genes with lethal and sterile RNAi phenotypes adjusted
        for a false negative rate of 22% and 86% genome coverage; <link linkend="bib24">Kamath et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID
        12529635-->) Screens have also been carried out using RNAi administered by injection or
        soaking worms in dsRNA solutions (<link linkend="bib12">Gonczy et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11099034-->; <link linkend="bib28">Maeda et al., 2001</link><!--;
        PMID 11231151-->; <link linkend="bib35">Piano et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11137018-->; <link linkend="bib36">Piano et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12445391-->).
        Comparison of these results to each other and to results from classical genetic screens has
        revealed some limitations of RNAi for discovering gene function: some genes appear to be
        insensitive to RNAi and outcomes can vary. Some essential genes will give no RNAi
        phenotypes, give very weak phenotypes or give phenotypes other than lethality or sterility.
        Furthermore, the efficiency of RNAi differs somewhat with different techniques for
        introducing the dsRNA triggers (<link linkend="bib36">Piano et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12445391-->) and even from trial to
        trial with the same technique (<link linkend="bib45">Simmer et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14551910-->). Another limitation, not
        restricted to RNAi, is genetic redundancy (discussed below and see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_geneduplication/geneduplication.html">Gene duplications and genetic redundancy in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>).</para>
		</sect2>
        <sect2>
		<title>Generating loss-of-function alleles by targeted intragenic deletion</title>
		<para>Two approaches have been used to generate targeted loss-of-function mutations by intragenic deletion. Common to both
        is the PCR-based screening of populations of randomly mutagenized worms to identify rare
        deletions in targeted genes. The worms carrying the deletions are enriched and eventually
        isolated by sibling selection schemes. Initially, transposon insertions in targeted genes
        were isolated in the expectation that the insertions would be mutagenic (<link linkend="bib42">Rushforth et al.,
        1993</link><!--; PMID 8380898-->), but because of a high frequency of silent insertions (<link linkend="bib41">Rushforth and
        Anderson, 1996</link><!--; PMID 8524324-->; <link linkend="bib42">Rushforth et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8380898-->) a two-step process of
        first isolating insertion-bearing worms and then screening populations of these worms for
        imprecise excision events was developed (<link linkend="bib50">Zwaal et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8395047-->). Chemical
        mutagenesis, which proved to be more efficient, has now replaced the use of transposon
        excision for generating deletions (<link linkend="bib20">Jansen et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID-->). The procedure is
        labor-intensive, and not efficient for a single target gene. Therefore, two groups have
        organized large scale efforts and are now generating intragenic deletions based on requests
        from members of the research community: the <ulink url="http://celeganskoconsortium.omrf.org/" role="_blank"><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Gene Knockout Consortium</ulink>
        and the <ulink url="http://www.grs.nig.ac.jp/c.elegans/index.jsp" role="_blank">National Bioresource Project for the Experimental Animal <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>
Based on results to date, about 1800 genes
        have been knocked out with 20-24% being essential (Shohei Mitani, Don Moerman and Bob
        Barstead, personal communications). Projecting the higher frequency to the whole genome
        (19,727 CDS; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/" role="_blank">Wormbase</ulink>, release WS136, 12/3/05) yields an estimate of 4645
        essential genes. However, this is likely to be inaccurate because gene knockouts are not
        being done randomly, but rather are biased toward genes with known functions in other
        organisms, or towards genes with known mutant or RNAi phenotypes.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
	<title>Redundancy of essential genes</title>
	<para>Many genes are members of multigene families and members of these families can often
        have redundant functions. In rare cases where nucleotide sequence is highly conserved, RNAi
        with a single trigger molecule can target multiple family members (e.g., <link linkend="bib5">Colombo et al.,
        2003</link><!--; PMID 12750478-->). If the number of family members is small, it is possible to reveal
        redundancies by double or triple knockout or knockdown (e.g., <link linkend="bib43">Schubert et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID
        10882103-->; <link linkend="bib15">Gotta and Ahringer, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11231580-->). Redundant pathways, in which different
        processes can accomplish the same essential function, are more cryptic and are not likely to
        be detected except by fortuitous double mutant combinations or screens for synthetic lethal        mutations (enhancers). See <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_geneduplication/geneduplication.html">Gene duplications and genetic redundancy in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink> for further consideration of redundancy and
        <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_geneticenhancers/geneticenhancers.html" role="_blank">Genetic enhancers</ulink> for further discussion of enhancers.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Pleiotropic essential gene phenotypes</title>
		<para>Many essential genes function repeatedly during the life of the worm and can have different
        essential roles in different tissues. (See <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_geneticmosaics/geneticmosaics.html">Genetic mosaics</ulink>) However, null mutant phenotypes
        often reveal only one essential role, leading to incomplete understanding of the gene&apos;s
        role. A clear example is the Notch family member <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis>. Null mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> are sterile
        mutations. Analysis of the null alleles revealed that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> was required for germline
        proliferation (<link linkend="bib2">Austin and Kimble, 1987</link><!--; PMID 3677168-->). Expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> during oogenesis
        is also required for cell fate specification in the early embryo. However, this function is
        masked in animals homozygous for the null allele by the failure of these animals to produce
        embryos. The embryonic role of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> was revealed by the recovery of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e2072;class=Variation" role="_blank">e2072</ulink></emphasis>, a special
        non-conditional allele that did not affect germline proliferation, and three
        temperature-sensitive mutations (<link linkend="bib37">Priess et al., 1987</link><!--; PMID 3677169-->). Analysis of these
        mutations revealed that signaling through the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLP-1</ulink> protein plays major roles in cell fate
        specification at multiple times in the early embryo (<link linkend="bib19">Hutter and Schnabel, 1994</link><!--; PMID
        7925009-->; <link linkend="bib31">Mello et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 8156602-->; <link linkend="bib33">Moskowitz et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7720570-->; <link linkend="bib37">Priess et
        al., 1987</link><!--; PMID 3677169-->). Clearly, null alleles generated by targeted deletions will be
        inadequate for full understanding of essential gene functions. </para><para>The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> example illustrates
        not only the problem of pleiotropy but also one solution &#x02014; the recovery and analysis of
        temperature-sensitive mutations. Temperature-sensitive mutations, as discussed above, are
        being used effectively for analysis of many essential <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes. Judicious
        temperature shifts can reveal multiple functions for a given gene. For example, shifting
        from permissive to restrictive temperature for brief periods early in embryogenesis revealed
        distinct roles for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> at the four-cell and the 12-cell stage (<link linkend="bib31">Mello et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID
        8156602-->). Therefore the continued screening for temperature-sensitive lethal mutations
        (e.g., <link linkend="bib8">Encalada et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11112326-->; <link linkend="bib11">Golden et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11134076-->; <link linkend="bib34">O'Connell et
        al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9649522-->) will provide reagents for specific analyses that often benefit the
        community at large. The relative rarity of temperature-sensitive mutations and the extreme
        difficulty of targeting such mutations to specific genes restricts their utility.</para>
<para>Another
        solution to the pleiotropy problem, conditional gene expression, used effectively in other
        genetic models like fruit flies and mice, has not yet been developed for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. In this
        approach, transgenes that have conditional promoters driving the gene of interest or that
        have strategically-placed recombination sequences are transformed into null mutant
        backgrounds. These constructs can be designed for gene activation or inactivation in
        specific tissues, at specific developmental times or in response to drug applications.
        Systems for conditional gene expression include the GAL4-UAS system applied effectively in
        fruit flies (<link linkend="bib6">Duffy, 2002</link><!--; PMID 12324939-->) and the Cre/lox and tetracycline inducible systems
        being used in mouse (<link linkend="bib14">Gossen and Bujard, 2002</link><!--; PMID 12429690-->). Adaptation of these tools for
        <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> would greatly facilitate analysis of essential genes.</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<para>The number of essential genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as estimated by gene knockout, RNAi and classical genetic
        screens appears to be less than 30% of the genome. The combination of RNAi and targeted gene
        knockouts ensures the identification of most essential <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes in the foreseeable
        future. Genetic redundancy could mask a significant number of essential functions, but
        construction of double and triple mutants or polygenic RNAi has the potential to identify
        many of these cases. Studies of null mutations can identify many roles of essential genes,
        but some roles of essential genes can be masked by early developmental arrest. Although
        temperature-sensitive mutations can overcome this problem, the difficulty of targeting
        temperature-sensitive mutations to specific genes makes it desirable to develop additional
        tools for conditional inactivation or activation of essential genes.</para>
</sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
		<para/>
		&esg_Refs;</sect1>
</article>
