<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY anthelmin_Refs SYSTEM 'anthelminrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="anthelmin_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title>Anthelmintic drugs<footnote>
			<para>Edited by Villu Maricq and Steven L. McIntire. Submitted November 15th., 2006. Last revised May 22, 2007. Published October 29, 2007. This chapter should be cited as: Holden-Dye, L. and Walker, R.J. Anthelmintic drugs (October 29, 2007), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.143.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2007 Lindy Holden-Dye and Robert J. Walker. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
		<author>
			<othername>Lindy Holden-Dye<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: 44 (0) 23 8059 4295; Fax: 44 (0) 23 80594459. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:lmhd@soton.ac.uk">lmhd@soton.ac.uk</ulink></para></footnote></remark> and Robert J. Walker</othername>
<affiliation><address>School of Biological Sciences, University of Southampton, Bassett Crescent East, Southampton SO16 7PX, UK</address></affiliation>
</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<abstract>
		<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
		<para><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">is sensitive to the majority of anthelmintic drugs that are used against parasitic worm infections of humans and livestock. This has provided the opportunity to use molecular genetic techniques in the worm for mode of action studies. These approaches continue to be of considerable value to the field of parasitology. In addition, there are numerous examples of anthelmintic drugs providing exceptionally useful pharmacological tools to delineate fundamental aspects of cell signalling in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans.</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">This has primarily been achieved through the use of anthelmintics in forward genetic screens followed by the mapping and characterization of genes that confer altered susceptibility to the drug. Less fruitful so far, but nonetheless useful, has been the direct use of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">for anthelmintic discovery programmes. In this brief review we provide an introduction to the use of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">as a &#x02018;model parasite&#x02019;, outline the actions of the main classes of anthelmintics, and highlight approaches that have been of particular value.</emphasis></para>
	</abstract>
<?newpage?>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction to anthelmintics</title>
<para>Anthelmintics are drugs that are used to treat infections with parasitic worms. This includes both flat worms, e.g., flukes and tapeworms and round worms, i.e., nematodes. They are of huge importance for human tropical medicine and for veterinary medicine. The World Health Organization estimates that a staggering 2 billion people harbour parasitic worm infections (<ulink url="http://www.who.int/wormcontrol/statistics/" role="_blank">http://www.who.int/wormcontrol/statistics/</ulink>). Parasitic worms also infect livestock and crops, affecting food production with a resultant economic impact. Also of importance is the infection of domestic pets. Indeed, the companion animal market is a major economic consideration for animal health companies undertaking drug discovery programmes.</para>
<para>Despite the prevalence of parasitic worms, anthelmintic drug discovery is the poor relation of the pharmaceutical industry. The simple reason is that the nations which suffer most from these tropical diseases have little money to invest in drug discovery or therapy. It comes as no surprise therefore that the drugs available for human treatment were first developed as veterinary medicines. There is thus a pitifully small repertoire of chemotherapeutic agents available for treatment (see <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). In some respects, this situation has been exacerbated by the remarkable success of ivermectin over the last twenty years (<link linkend="bib22">Geary, 2005</link><!--; PMID 16126457-->), which has decreased motivation for anthelmintic drug discovery programmes (<link linkend="bib23">Geary, Sangster and Thompson, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10456419-->). This prompts concern, as anthelmintic resistance has been widely reported in livestock and it may also only be a matter of time before this phenomenon occurs in parasites of humans.</para>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="100%">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1. Key drugs registered for the treatment of parasitic worms in humans.</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c2" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><emphasis role="bold">schistosomias (blood fluke)</emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis role="bold">Intestinal round worms</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Antimonials</entry>
<entry>Piperazine</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Metrifonate</entry>
<entry>Benzimidazoles</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Oxamnaquine</entry>
<entry>Morantel</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Praziquantel</entry>
<entry>Pyrantel</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry></entry>
<entry>Levamisole</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis role="bold">Cestodiasis (tape worm)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Avermectins and milbemycins</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Niclosamide</entry>
<entry>Closantel (and halogenated salicylamides)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Benzimidazoles</entry>
<entry>Emodepside</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Praziquantel</entry>
<entry></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis role="bold">Fasciolasis (liver fluke)</emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis role="bold">Filariasis (tissue round worms)</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Praziquantel</entry>
<entry>Diethylcarbmazine</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Closantel</entry>
<entry>Suramin</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>(and halogenated salicylamides)</entry>
<entry>Ivermectin</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>Broad spectrum anthelmintics are effective against parasitic flat worms and nematodes. However, the majority of drugs are more limited in their action, e.g., praziquantel, a drug used in the treatment of schistosomiasis and thought to act by disrupting calcium homeostasis (<link linkend="bib27">Greenberg, 2005</link><!--; PMID 16569296-->), has no activity against nematodes (see <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). For the purpose of this review we will focus on drugs used in human and veterinary medicine to treat parasitic nematode infection.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Is <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> a model &#x02018;parasite&#x02019;?</title>
<para>Parasitic nematodes are not an ideal laboratory animal for many reasons, not least of which is the problem with maintaining sometimes complex life-cycles. Thus <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has routinely been exploited as a more &#x02018;user-friendly&#x02019; model system that is also highly tractable to molecular genetic techniques. However, the life-style of the free-living worm <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is very different to that of the parasites, and therefore parasitologists have given careful thought to its relevance (<link linkend="bib24">Geary and Thompson, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11707307-->). In terms of overall &#x02018;body plan&#x02019; there is no doubt that all the species in the phylum Nematoda exhibit similarity despite their very different habitats. More detailed consideration has been given to a comparison of the genetics, e.g., the arrangement of the genome, synteny and homology between specific genes (<link linkend="bib58">Mitreva et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16099532-->). Overall, there would seem to be considerable molecular diversity between the different species in the phylum. It is probably safe to conclude that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is no more dissimilar to parasitic nematodes than each individual species of parasite is to another. Using <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> permits the application of powerful molecular genetic approaches and it has been extensively, and successfully, exploited as a model system to define molecular components of signalling pathways that underpin nematode physiology.</para>
<para>Indeed, it could be argued that the most relevant consideration for using <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as a model to study anthelmintics is the comparative physiology and pharmacology of the Nematoda. Most anthelmintics target the neuromusculature and therefore similarities here become of particular importance. The wiring diagram for the neuromuscular system is similar between <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and the parasitic nematode <emphasis>Ascaris suum</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib2">Angstadt, Donmoyer and Stretton, 1989</link><!--; PMID 2754041-->) as are the major neurotransmitters; acetylcholine in the excitatory motorneurones (<link linkend="bib38">Johnson and Stretton, 1985</link><!--; PMID 4020429-->), GABA in the inhibitory motorneurones (<link linkend="bib39">Johnson and Stretton, 1987</link><!--; PMID 3543249-->) and glutamate providing input onto the motorneurones (<link linkend="bib16">Davis, 1998</link><!--; PMID 9614330-->). A striking feature of the pharmacology of the nematode nervous system is the abundance of neuropeptides. The majority, conceivably all of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, neurones express neuropeptides along with their classical neurotransmitters (for review see <link linkend="bib53">Li, 2005</link><!--; PMID 16569285-->). Many of these peptides have potent effects in parasitic nematodes, specifically on musculature which regulates vital nematode processes including feeding, locomotion and egg-laying (<link linkend="bib10">Brownlee, Holden-Dye and Walker, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10751940-->). Further evidence for an important functional role for peptidergic signalling has been provided by analysis of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> mutants. In these studies mutants for the enzymes involved in the processing of neuropeptides, the proconvertase <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-3</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib44">Kass et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11717360-->) and carboxypeptidase <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-21;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-21</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib37">Jacob and Kaplan, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12657671-->), have been shown to be severely depleted in neuropeptide content (<link linkend="bib36">Husson et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16945111-->) and to have altered behaviours consistent with the idea that neuropeptides have modulatory roles within the neural networks that direct a range of important worm behaviours.</para>
<para>Neuropeptides are present throughout the animal phyla and also subserve pivotal roles in the nervous systems of the mammalian hosts of parasitic nematodes. However, neuropeptides, unlike the small molecule &#x02018;classical&#x02019; transmitters e.g. acetylcholine, have diverged considerably in structure during evolution and this presents the promise that drugs targeting peptidergic signalling in nematodes may have low mammalian toxicity. There has thus been considerable interest in the prospect of developing peptidomimetics as a novel approach for nematode control. A comparative analysis of the neuropeptide content for a range of nematodes has been comprehensively reviewed (<link linkend="bib59">McVeigh et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16076468-->) and may become an important consideration if this strategy is to be pursued.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Approaches for the study of anthelmintics in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
<para>There is a large body of literature describing the study of bioactive compounds in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and the proposal to use it for the study of anthelmintics precedes the publication of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome sequence by nearly 20 years. <link linkend="bib66">Rand and Johnson (1995</link><!--; PMID 8531725-->) coined the term &#x02018;genetic pharmacology&#x02019; to describe this approach. These studies generally hinge on the ability of a drug to elicit a significant, ideally quantifiable, change in the worm&apos;s growth, development, metabolism, and/or behaviour. Pharmacokinetic considerations include the method and duration of drug exposure. For the vast majority of experiments the anthelmintics are applied to intact <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. There are thus two ways in which the drug can gain access to target tissues, namely by ingestion or by diffusion across the cuticle. In this regard it should be noted that for many drugs the cuticle presents a significant permeability barrier. Thus the lipophilicity of drugs has a strong bearing on the concentration that is achieved in target tissues following external application. It is not uncommon for polar drugs to be applied at a concentration 1000 fold higher than their predicted affinity for the target. It may be possible to ameliorate this problem to some extent by employing animals that have a compromised cuticle (<link linkend="bib26">Gravato-Nobre et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16079230-->). Once the effect of a particular drug on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has been defined, two different strategies may be adopted to investigate the molecular basis for its biological activity. The first follows a hypothesis led approach in which strains with mutations in genes of known function are tested for altered sensitivity to the drug. The alternate strategy is to conduct a forward genetic screen. This is a powerful and objective approach that provides novel insight into the signalling pathways that mediate anthelmintic action. Often the impact of these studies extends beyond the interests of parasitologists and into the broader context of cellular and molecular neuroscience. This is because the vast majority of anthelmintics exert their effects in the neuromuscular system and key transduction molecules in the nervous system are highly conserved across the phyla from worm to human. Thus anthelmintic resistance screens can promote the discovery and characterisation of genes that have important roles in neurotransmission. An excellent example of the utility of this approach is provided by genetic screens employing the organophosphate cholinesterase inhibitors, in particular aldicarb. The detail of these studies is beyond the scope of this review as organophosphates are not widely used as anthelmintics. (Toxicity limits their use to highly regulated applications for plant parasitic nematodes). However, aldicarb screens provide an excellent example of &#x02018;genetic pharmacology&#x02019; and the interested reader is directed to <link linkend="bib61">Nguyen et al., 1995</link><!-- (PMID 7498734)-->; <link linkend="bib57">Miller et al., 1996</link><!-- (PMID 8901627)-->; and <link linkend="bib72">Seiburth et al., 2005</link><!-- (PMID 16049479)-->.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Classes of anthelmintic drugs</title>
<para>Anthelmintics are separated into classes on the basis of similar chemical structure and mode of action. There are only a few main classes and each is briefly discussed in turn below. For the most part, information on the physiological and pharmacological actions of anthelmintics has been obtained from studies on the large parasitic nematode <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis>. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, on the other hand, has been valuable in defining molecular targets.</para>
<sect2 id="sec4_1">
<title>Piperazine</title>
<para>Piperazine was first used as an anthelmintic in the 1950s and it is still the active constituent of over the counter remedies for thread worm infection in children. Its mode of action has primarily been studied in <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis>. There is surprisingly no literature on its action in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> though there is no indication that it acts differently from its effects in <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis>. In <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> it acts as a weak GABA-mimetic and causes a flaccid, reversible paralysis of body wall muscle. Single channel recordings provide evidence that it is a low efficacy, partial agonist at GABA-gated chloride channels (<link linkend="bib54">Martin, 1985</link><!--; PMID 2579701-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_2">
<title>Benzimidazoles</title>
<para>The first of this class, thiabendazole, was discovered in 1961 and subsequently a number of further benzamidazoles were introduced as broad spectrum anthelmintics. There is an extensive literature on these compounds reporting a number of different biochemical effects. Nonetheless, it is clear that their anthelmintic efficacy is due to their ability to compromise the cytoskeleton through a selective interaction with <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-tubulin (<link linkend="bib6">Borgers and de Nollin, 1975</link><!--; PMID 1117352-->; for review see <link linkend="bib49">Lacey, 1990</link><!--; PMID 15463312-->). The effects of benzimidazoles on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, which include impaired locomotion, reproduction and a detrimental effect on oocytes, are consistent with disruption of processes requiring integral microtubules. The sensitivity of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to benzimidazoles is mediated by a single gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ben-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ben-1</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-tubulin (<link linkend="bib18">Driscoll et al., 1989</link><!--; PMID 2592410-->). This has provided a platform to investigate the molecular basis of benzimidazole resistance in parasitic nematodes. It has been noted that benzimidazole resistance in <emphasis>Haemonchus contortus</emphasis> seems to be associated with the presence of specific alleles for <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-tubulin in the drug resistant isolates (<link linkend="bib47">Kwa et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7911975-->). Whether or not a specific <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-tubulin isoform could confer resistance to the drug was tested by experiments which showed that the sensitivity of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ben-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ben-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants to benzimidazole can be rescued by expressing a <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> allele of <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-tubulin from benzimidazole susceptible isolates but cannot be rescued by the allele present in the resistant isolates (<link linkend="bib48">Kwa et al., 1995</link><!--; PMID 7877171-->). This unequivocally demonstrated that a single amino acid sustitution, Y for F, in <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-tubulin, can confer anthelmintic resistance. This is the first elegant example of a 'model hopping' approach in which the genetic tractability of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is directly exploited to define gene function in a parasitic worm.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_3">
<title>Levamisole, pyrantel and morantel</title>
<para>These anthelmintics are nicotinic receptor agonists (<link linkend="bib1">Aceves et al., 1970</link><!--; PMID 5445688-->; <link linkend="bib3">Aubry et al., 1970</link><!--; PMID 5417856-->) and elicit spastic muscle paralysis due to prolonged activation of the excitatory nicotinic acetylcholine (nACh) receptors on body wall muscle. Their precise mode of action has been carefully studied at the single-channel level on the body wall muscle preparation of <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> (see <link linkend="bib55">Martin et al., 2005</link> for review<!--; PMID 16569294-->). Pharmacological analysis has provided evidence for subtypes of nACh receptor (<link linkend="bib64">Qian et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 17056760-->), an N-type (preferentially activated by nicotine), a B-type (preferentially activated by bephenium) and an L-type (preferentially activated by levamisole and associated with levamisole resistance). Levamisole, and related compounds, also cause spastic paralysis and egg-laying in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Indeed, recordings from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> body wall muscle using levamisole and nicotine as agonists have provided further evidence that there are muscle subtypes of nACh receptor and that these subtypes have different nACh receptor subunit compositions. At least four subunits, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-38;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-38</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-29;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-29</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-63;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-63</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lev-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-1</ulink></emphasis> contribute to the levamisole receptor (<link linkend="bib13">Culetto et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15280391-->; for further information on the nACh receptor subunit family see <link linkend="bib65">Rand, 2007</link>). Thus, these anthelmintics are providing pharmacological tools to dissect subtypes and stoichiometries of native nematode nicotinic receptors.</para>
<para>Perhaps more importantly, levamisole has been extremely productive in forward genetic screens. In the earliest studies tetramisole was used (<link linkend="bib7">Brenner, 1974</link><!--; PMID 4366476-->) and later this was replaced by the more active isomer, levamisole (<link linkend="bib52">Lewis et al., 1980</link><!--; PMID 7203008-->). These screens have provided a resource of mutants that have been used over the last two decades to assign function to genes expressed at the neuromuscular junction. Some of these are nACh receptor subunits, but others interestingly are not and serve to either regulate nicotinic receptors or muscle function (see <link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>).</para>
<table id="table2" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="100%">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 2. A summary of gene function for</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">levamisole resistant mutants.</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="0.8*"/>
<colspec colname="c2" align="left" colwidth="1.5*"/>
<colspec colname="c3" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Gene</entry>
<entry>Function</entry>
<entry>Reference</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row rowsep="0">
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-38;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-38</ulink></emphasis><superscript>1</superscript></entry>
<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-like nACh receptor subunit</entry>
<entry morerows="2" valign="middle" rowsep="1"><link linkend="bib19">Fleming et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9221782--></entry>
</row>
<row rowsep="0">
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-29;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-29</ulink></emphasis><superscript>1</superscript></entry>
<entry>Non <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-like nACh receptor subunit</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lev-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-1</ulink></emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></entry>
<entry>Non <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-like nACh receptor subunit</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-63;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-63</ulink></emphasis><superscript>1</superscript></entry>
<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-like nACh receptor subunit</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib13">Culetto et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15280391--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-22;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-22</ulink></emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></entry>
<entry>Twitchin</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib60">Moerman et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID 2833427--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-50;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-50</ulink></emphasis><superscript>1</superscript></entry>
<entry>Transmembrane protein required for receptor trafficking.</entry>
<entry>Bessereau<superscript>3</superscript><!-- WBPaper00027505--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-68;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-68</ulink></emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></entry>
<entry>Ryanodine receptor</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib56">Maryon et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8769414--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lev-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-9</ulink></emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></entry>
<entry>Putative secreted protein required for levamisole nACh receptor clustering</entry>
<entry>Bessereau<superscript>3</superscript><!-- WBPaper00027509--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lev-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-11</ulink></emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></entry>
<entry>Tropomyosin</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib41">Kagawa et al., 1995</link><!--; PMID 7666414--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lev-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-8</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=acr-13;class=Gene" role="_blank">acr-13</ulink>)</emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></entry>
<entry><symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-like nACh receptor subunit</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib74">Towers et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15773900--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lev-10;class=Gene" role="_blank">lev-10</ulink></emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></entry>
<entry>CUB/LDL protein; receptor clustering</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib21">Gally et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15457263--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ric-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">ric-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>Required for maturation of nACh receptor</entry>
<entry><link linkend="bib31">Halevi et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11867529--></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="c1" nameend="c3" align="left">Isolated and identified as levamisole resistant by <superscript>1</superscript><link linkend="bib7">Brenner (1974)</link>, <superscript>2</superscript><link linkend="bib52">Lewis et al. (1980)</link>. <superscript>3</superscript>Unpublished data, see <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org" role="_blank">www.wormbase.org</ulink></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_4">
<title>Paraherquamide</title>
<para>Paraherquamide A and marcfortine A are both members of the oxindole alkaloid family, originally isolated from <emphasis>Penicillium paraherquei</emphasis> and <emphasis>Penicillium roqueforti</emphasis>, respectively (<link linkend="bib81">Zinser et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12213111-->). Marcfortine A was found to be active against <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> in a high throughput screen (<link linkend="bib51">Lee et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12052190-->). A specific, high affinity binding site for paraherquamide has been identified in a membrane preparation isolated from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, with an apparent Kd of 263nM (<link linkend="bib71">Schaeffer et al., 1992</link><!--; PMID 1540222-->). Paraherquamide and its derivative, 2-deoxy-paraherquamide, induce flaccid paralysis in parasitic nematodes, <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis>. Pharmacological analysis of the effects of these drugs on acetylcholine-stimulated body wall muscle contractions in <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> muscle strips <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> has shown that they act as typical competitive antagonists, shifting the concentration-response curves to the right in a parallel fashion (<link linkend="bib67">Robertson et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12183640-->). These drugs have no apparent direct effect on <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> body wall muscle tension or membrane potential (<link linkend="bib51">Lee et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12052190-->). Paraherquamide also blocks the actions of other nicotinic agonists, but not equipotently (<link linkend="bib81">Zinser et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12213111-->; <link linkend="bib67">Robertson et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12183640-->). Interestingly, this antagonist seems to distinguish nicotinic receptor subtypes on the muscle and has a greater affinity for the receptors mediating the response to levamisole and pyrantel, than the receptors that mediate the response to nicotine. One might therefore expect that paraherquamide would be an effective antagonist of the levamisole-selective receptor on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> body wall muscle. Importantly, the mode of action of this class of anthelmintics differs from the more established drugs that interfere with cholinergic transmission, e.g., levamisole, in that they act as competitive antagonists rather than cholinomimetics. The use of paraherquamide in forward genetic screens has not yet been reported but could potentially generate interesting new mutants. As it is a competitive inhibitor of the body wall nACh receptor it would be predicted that mutations that increase transmitter release should confer resistance. Thus a forward genetic screen might reveal further negative regulators of neurotransmitter release.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_5">
<title>Ivermectin (macrocylic lactones and milbemycins)</title>
<para>Ivermectin was introduced as an anthelmintic in the 1980s by Merck. It is a semi-synthetic derivative of avermectin which is a large macrocyclic lactone fermentation product of the micro-organism <emphasis>Streptomyces avermitilis</emphasis>. It is remarkably potent (~1nM) and persistent in its effect and its discovery enthused other companies to invest in the development of ivermectin analogues which include moxidectin, milbemycin oxime, doramectin, selamectin, abamectin and eprinomectin. Here <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> played a role as it was employed in a screen for further macrocyclic lactones with ivermectin-like activity (<link linkend="bib30">Haber et al., 1991</link><!--; PMID 1719935-->).</para>
<para>Ivermectin elicits a potent and persistent paralysis of nematode pharyngeal (<link linkend="bib9">Brownlee, Holden-Dye and Walker, 1997</link><!--; PMID 9368907-->; <link linkend="bib62">Pemberton et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11306685-->) and body wall musculature (<link linkend="bib42">Kass et al., 1980</link><!--; PMID 6255481-->; <link linkend="bib43">Kass et al., 1982</link><!--; PMID 7128715-->). It has been shown to interact with a range of ligand-gated ion channels including <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>7 nACh receptors (<link linkend="bib46">Krause et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9463487-->), acetylcholine-gated chloride channels (<link linkend="bib5">Bokisch and Walker, 1986</link><!--; PMID 2873943-->), GABA-gated chloride channels (<link linkend="bib68">Robertson, 1989</link><!--; PMID 2478243-->; <link linkend="bib34">Holden-Dye and Walker, 1990</link><!--; PMID 2175874-->), histamine-gated chloride channels (<link linkend="bib80">Zheng et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11714703-->), glycine receptors (<link linkend="bib73">Shan et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11278873-->) and P2X4 receptors (<link linkend="bib45">Khakh et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10460235-->). However, it is its high affinity for nematode glutamate-gated chloride channels (GluCl) that correlates with its potent anthelmintic activity. This was defined by the team at Merck which succeeded in expression cloning GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> and GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol> ion channel subunits from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib14">Cully et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7935817-->). Both subunits were expressed either singly, or together, in <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes. GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> responds to micromolar ivermectin, but not to glutamate whilst GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol> responds to glutamate but not ivermectin. Co-expression of GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> and GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol> yields a channel which responds to glutamate and is positively allosterically modulated by nanomolar ivermectin. Subsequently a small family of nematode genes encoding GluCl channels has been identified (see <link linkend="bib79">Yates, Portillo and Wolstenholme for review, 2003</link><!--; PMID 13678634-->). The nomenclature is confusing as the same genes have been discovered by both homology screening approaches and from forward genetic screens for ivermectin resistance genes. Essentially there are four <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes encoding GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> subunits, two of which are alternately spliced yielding the GluCl channels: GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>1 encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=glc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-1</ulink></emphasis>; GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>2A and B encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=avr-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis>; GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>3A and B encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=avr-14;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink></emphasis>; GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>4 encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=glc-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-3</ulink></emphasis>. There is just one GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol> subunit encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=glc-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-2</ulink></emphasis> and a further gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=glc-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-4</ulink></emphasis>, which is divergent from the genes encoding <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> and <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol> subunits. Although the pharmacology of channels assembled from these GluCl subunits has been defined in heterologous expression systems, the important question of the subunit stoichiometry and pharmacology of the native channels is much more poorly defined. Further studies on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are providing a better understanding of this by delineating the expression pattern for GluCl subunits in the nervous system. For example, the pharyngeal muscle expresses <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=avr-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=glc-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-2</ulink></emphasis>, (<link linkend="bib17">Dent, Davis and Avery, 1997</link><!--; PMID 9312045-->; <link linkend="bib50">Laughton, Lunt and Wolstenholme, 1997</link><!--; PMID 9192499-->). Thus it might be expected that GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>2 and GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol> subunits co-assemble to form a native ivermectin sensitive channel. Whether or not other subunits contribute to the functional receptor is not yet clear. However, the pharyngeal muscle of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=avr-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> mutants does not respond to ivermectin (<link linkend="bib17">Dent, Davis and Avery, 1997</link><!--; PMID 9312045-->; <link linkend="bib62">Pemberton et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11306685-->) clearly indicating an involvement of GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>2. An important point to note in terms of the site of anthelmintic action of ivermectin is that although the pharynxes of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=avr-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> mutants are not inhibited by ivermectin, populations of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=avr-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> mutants exposed to ivermectin are still paralyzed. Thus GluCl channels in the pharynx are not required for the paralytic effect. This may also be true for parasitic nematodes. For example, ivermectin has anthelmintic activity against <emphasis>Ascaridia galli</emphasis> and yet the pharynx of this species is not inhibited by the drug (<link linkend="bib35">Holden-Dye and Walker, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16442540-->). In order to obtain a better understanding of the role of GluCl channels in mediating the paralytic actions of ivermectin it is probably more informative to consider their role in the motornervous system. Currently most information is available for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=avr-14;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=avr-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis>. These genes are expressed in the motor nervous system of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib17">Dent et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9312045-->; <link linkend="bib82">Dent et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10716995-->) and there is immunostaining for GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>3A and B in motorneurones of the parasitic nematode <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis>, (<link linkend="bib63">Portillo, Jagannathan, Wolstenholme 2003</link><!--; PMID 12794744-->). One role of these GluCl channels in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> involves regulation of the duration of forward movement, a well established glutamatergic-regulated behaviour (<link linkend="bib8">Brockie and Maricq, 2006</link>). This function may be conserved between <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> as <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> GluCl<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>3 subunits expressed in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=avr-14;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink></emphasis> mutants restore the wild type pattern of movement (<link linkend="bib12">Cook et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16527366-->). It is most likely that the paralytic action of ivermectin derives from its potent activation of GluCl in the motornervous system of nematodes. However, the precise role of individual GluCl channels in mediating the effects of ivermectin on these circuits is yet to be established. The mechanism of resistance to ivermectin has also been studied in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. High level resistance is a complex phenomenon which requires mutations in at least three genes, namely in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=glc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=avr-14;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=avr-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis>. Further genes, regulating membrane permeability (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=osm-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">osm-1</ulink></emphasis>) and gap junctions (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-7</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-9</ulink></emphasis>), are also involved (<link linkend="bib82">Dent et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10716995-->). Defining the role of GluCl mutations in conferring ivermectin resistance to parasitic nematodes in the field is a less tractable and more controversial problem (<link linkend="bib78">Wolstenholme et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15363440-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_6">
<title>Emodepside (cyclodepsipeptides, PF1022A)</title>
<para>The cyclodepsipeptide molecule, emodepside, is a semi-synthetic derivative of PF1022A, a fermentation product obtained from the fungus, <emphasis>Mycelia sterilia</emphasis>, of <emphasis>Camelia japonica</emphasis>. Its discovery and anthelmintic activity has recently been reviewed (<link linkend="bib32">Harder, von Samson-Himmelstjerna, 2002</link><!--; PMID 12107468-->). It is effective against isolates of parasites that are resistant to benzimidazole, levamisole and ivermectin indicating, importantly, that it has a novel mode of action. The molecule has pore-forming properties in planar lipids, however, this does not appear to be important in conferring its anthelmintic potency as an optical isomer of emodepside, with similar pore forming properties, does not have anthelmintic action. Thus it would appear that it may act through stereospecific binding to a receptor. Studies in <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> have highlighted muscle paralysis and point to a calcium- and potassium-dependent mechanism of action (<link linkend="bib76">Willson et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12613766-->). A candidate receptor for the cyclodepsipeptides has been cloned from a <emphasis>H. contortus</emphasis> cDNA library by immunoscreening with an antibody to PF1022 A. This receptor, designated HC110R, has been expressed in HEK293 cells and shown to gate calcium flux in a PF1022 A-dependent manner (<link linkend="bib69">Saeger et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11344131-->). It has homology to mammalian latrophilins, a class of G protein-coupled receptors which bind the neurotoxin, latrotoxin. Latrotoxin paralyses mammals by triggering neurotransmitter release, and thus the identification of latrophilin as an emodepside receptor raised the intriguing possibility that emodepside may cause paralysis of nematodes by stimulating excessive neurotransmitter release at neuromuscular sites.</para>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is very susceptible to the effects of emodepside at nanomolar concentrations (<link linkend="bib11">Bull et al., 2007</link><!--; PMID 17157854-->). The effects include slowed development, inhibition of pharyngeal pumping, decreased locomotion (forward movement is most affected at low concentrations), and inhibition of egg-laying leading to &#x02018;bagging&#x02019; in adult hermaphrodites. Thus <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has provided an excellent model in which to define the molecular target, or targets, through which emodepside exerts its pleiotropic actions and indeed, to test whether latrophilins are involved.</para>
<para>There are two genes encoding candidate latrophilins in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lat-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lat-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">lat-2</ulink></emphasis>. The role of these latrophilins in mediating the inhibitory effects of emodepside on feeding and locomotion has been investigated using RNAi and gene knockouts (<link linkend="bib77">Willson et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15296755-->; <link linkend="bib11">Bull et al., 2007</link><!--; WBPaper00027500-->; <link linkend="bib29">Guest et al., 2007</link>). The pharyngeal system of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lat-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lat-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants show a reduced sensitivity to emodepside but their locomotor activity is inhibited in a similar fashion to wild-type animals (<link linkend="bib29">Guest et al., 2007</link>). Emodepside does not exert its inhibitory effect on locomotion through the other latrophilin, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LAT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAT-2</ulink>, as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">lat-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants respond just like wild-type animals. Nor is there redundancy of function between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LAT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAT-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LAT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAT-2</ulink> in terms of the effect of emodepside on locomotion, as the double mutant <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">lat-2</ulink>,lat-1</emphasis> responds to emodepside in a similar fashion to the single mutant, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lat-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lat-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib29">Guest et al., 2007</link>). Clearly, emodepside has latrophilin-independent actions.</para>
<para>Recently, forward genetic screens have provided further insight into the mechanism through which emodepside exerts its inhibitory action on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> muscle. A chemical mutagenesis screen of twenty thousand genomes for mutants that could move and propagate on micromolar emodepside recovered nine alleles of a single gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis>. Strains carrying functional null alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> are highly resistant to the inhibitory effects of emodepside on locomotion and feeding. Furthermore, strains carrying gain-of-function alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> behave in a similar manner to emodepside-treated animals but are not themselves emodepside hypersensitive. These data strongly support the contention that emodepside activates a SLO-1-dependent pathway to bring about neuromuscular inhibition.</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> is a calcium-activated potassium channel (<link linkend="bib75">Wang et al. 2001</link><!--; PMID 11738032-->) homologous to the mammalian BK channels. Thus the discovery of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> as an important effector for emodepside resonates with earlier work on <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis> muscle which showed a calcium and potassium-dependent hyperpolarisation (<link linkend="bib76">Willson et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12613766-->). This channel is highly conserved throughout the animal phyla and plays a pivotal role in regulating neuronal and muscle cell excitability (for review, <link linkend="bib70">Salkoff et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 17115074-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> it is widely expressed in the nervous system and body wall muscle, but not in pharyngeal muscle. By expressing a wild-type copy of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> in specific subsets of cells in a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> null background it has been shown that emodepside can inhibit locomotor activity when <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> is present in neurones or body wall muscle but it can only inhibit feeding if <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> is present in neurones (<link linkend="bib29">Guest et al., 2007</link>). Earlier studies showed that mutations in a number of genes encoding synaptic proteins confer altered sensitivity to the effect of emodepside on feeding consistent with the idea that it acts in the neuronal network to disrupt rhythmic feeding behaviour (<link linkend="bib77">Willson et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15296755-->).</para>
<para>The discovery of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> as a mediator of the inhibitory effects of emodepside on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is an important development in this field which in the light of ivermectin resistance has an urgent need for such breakthroughs. In the broader context, there is an emerging body of evidence indicating that BK channels such as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> may play a pivotal role in conferring sensitivity to neuroactive drugs, including ethanol and local anaesthetics (<link linkend="bib15">Davies et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14675531-->; <link linkend="bib33">Hawasli et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15514057-->) and in regulating the pattern of activity of neural networks (<link linkend="bib70">Salkoff et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 17115074-->). Thus, an additional and valuable facet of these studies is that emodepside provides a new tool to dissect the functional role of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> in neural networks using the power of molecular genetics in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_7">
<title>Nitazoxanide</title>
<para>Nitazoxanide, a pyruvate ferredoxin oxidoreductase inhibitor, acts against a broad spectrum of protozoa and helminths that occur in the intestinal tract. It is currently used for the treatment of protozoal infections (and is therefore not listed in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). The site of action of this compound has not been established in nematodes although anaerobic electron transport enzymes may be a potential target (<link linkend="bib25">Gilles and Hoffman 2002</link><!--; PMID 11854075-->). The effect of nitazoxanide has been examined on growth and development of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib20">Fonseca-Salamanca et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14574563-->). After seven days culture, nitazoxanide 100 &#x003BC;M, only reduced population growth by 33&#x00025;. In contrast mebendazole, 5&#x003BC;M, and albendazole, 1 &#x003BC;M, reduced growth by over 90&#x00025;. Nitazoxanide, 100 &#x003BC;M, had no effect on either embryonation or hatching in <emphasis>Heligmosomoides polygyrus.</emphasis> Therefore the efficacy of this compound is relatively low compared to other anthelmintic agents.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>The future</title>
<para>A particular challenge for companies engaged in anthelmintic research, not shared by its more wealthy cousin the pharmaceutical industry, is that for the anthelmintic market cost-effectiveness is a prime concern. Furthermore, for tropical medicine, anthelmintics must be used in mass chemotherapy programmes in regions where clinical support is sparse and therefore drugs need to be very well tolerated in humans. For the last twenty years a small repertoire of drugs, especially ivermectin, has addressed this need. Indeed, ivermectin has been hugely successful both in veterinary and tropical medicine and its use in Africa has transformed the lives of populations previously devastated by the tropical disease Onchocerciasis (river blindness).</para>
<para>The most pressing concern for the future is the emergence of resistance to all the currently used anthelmintics, including ivermectin. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> was pivotal in defining the mode of action for the majority of these drugs and can also contribute to understanding mechanisms of resistance especially through the adoption of a &#x02018;model-hopping&#x02019; approach whereby the functionality of parasite genes is assessed by using <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as an expression system.</para>
<para>Of equal importance for the future is the use of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as a model system for drug discovery. It is to be hoped that this will provide new anthelmintics that have novel modes of action and thus will circumvent the problem of anthelmintic resistance. The advent of RNAi and high throughput techniques for analysis of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has led to renewed interest in drug discovery using chemical genetic screens (<link linkend="bib4">Behm et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15734653-->; <link linkend="bib40">Jones, Buckingham and Sattelle, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15803195-->). The molecular targets for the drugs that come out of these screens, or from other pipe-lines, can be defined using the powerful approach of forward genetics in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and may uncover new effectors for anthelmintic action. Recently advances have been made exploiting <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> for such mode of action studies and have highlighted a new effector, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink>, in the anthelmintic action of the latest drug to hit the market, emodepside (Profender).</para>
<para>More targeted approaches to anthelmintic drug discovery are also ongoing. These are providing fundamental information on nematode neurobiology with the aim of identifying signalling molecules that have pivotal roles in neural circuits that underpin vital behaviours. Here it will be interesting to see whether or not the ambition to target peptidergic signalling pathways translates into a marketable drug (<link linkend="bib28">Greenwood, Williams and Geary, 2005</link><!--; PMID 16569288-->).</para>
<para>In conclusion, it is clear that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has, and will continue to prove an exceptionally tractable and informative model system for parasitic nematodes and mode of action studies for anthelmintics. The future holds the promise that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> may also directly contribute to drug discovery. These efforts are of utmost importance in view of the increasing threat to live-stock and humans from anthelmintic resistant strains of parasite.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
	<title>References</title>
	&anthelmin_Refs;
	<para/>
</sect1>
</article>