<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 3. Molecular model of sex determination</title>
        <para>Diagram illustrates likely relationships between sex determining proteins from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HER-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HER-1</ulink>
            to the terminal global regulator <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink>. Masculinizing proteins are blue, and feminizing
            proteins are pink. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HER-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HER-1</ulink> is present only in XO males due to XX-specific transcriptional
            repression by the SDC proteins. In XO animals <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HER-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HER-1</ulink> binds the transmembrane receptor
            TRA-2A, blocking the ability of an intracellular domain of TRA-2A to inhibit FEM
            activity, and consequently the FEM proteins can inhibit TRA-1A. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-3;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-3</ulink> protease may cleave TRA-2A to generate a fragment, TRA-2ic, with stronger feminizing activity. In XX
            animals active TRA-2A or TRA-2ic binds and inhibits <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-3;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-3</ulink>. As <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-3;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-3</ulink> can bind <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-2;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-2</ulink>, this
            regulation may inhibit or sequester both proteins. The FEM proteins are targeted for
            proteasomal degradation by the F box protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SEL-10;class=protein" role="_blank">SEL-10</ulink>. When active (in XO animals) the FEM
            proteins somehow inhibit the activity of the transcriptional repressor TRA-1A. Active
            TRA-1A in XX animals binds DNA and blocks transcription driven by nearby enhancer
            elements in genes including <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-1" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> and probably <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-30" role="_blank">ceh-30</ulink></emphasis>, thereby establishing sexually dimorphic expression of specific genes in specific cell types. A number of
            molecular details remain poorly understood. In particular, it is not yet clear how
            TRA-2A inhibits the FEM proteins or how the FEM proteins inhibit TRA-1A.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>