<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'somaticsexdetfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'somaticsexdetfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'somaticsexdetfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'somaticsexdetfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'somaticsexdetfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'somaticsexdetfig3leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY somaticsexdet_Refs SYSTEM 'somaticsexdetrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="somaticsexdet_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Somatic sex determination<remark>
                <footnote>
                    <para>Edited by Barbara J. Meyer. Last revised February 8, 2005. Published February 10, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Zarkower, D. Somatic sex determination (February 10, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.84.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 David Zarkower. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
                </footnote>
            </remark>
        </title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 2/88/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
-->
        <author>
            <firstname>David</firstname>
            <surname>Zarkower<remark>
                    <footnote>
                        <para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:zarko001@umn.edu">zarko001@umn.edu</ulink></para>
                    </footnote>
                </remark>
            </surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Department of Genetics, Cell Biology, and Development, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN 55455 USA</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">occurs in two natural sexes, the XX hermaphrodite and
            the XO male, which differ extensively in anatomy, physiology, and behavior. All somatic
            differences between the sexes result from the differential activity of a “global” sex
            determination regulatory pathway. This pathway also controls X chromosome dosage
            compensation, which is coordinated with sex determination by the action of the three SDC
            proteins. The SDC proteins control somatic and germline sex by transcriptional
            repression of the</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">gene. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HER-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HER-1</ulink> is a secreted protein that
            controls a regulatory module consisting of a transmembrane receptor, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-2;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-2</ulink>, three
            intracellular FEM proteins, and the zinc finger transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink>. The
            molecular workings of this regulatory module are still being elucidated. Similarity of
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-2;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-2</ulink> to patched receptors and of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> to GLI proteins suggests that parts of the
            global pathway originally derived from a Hedgehog signaling pathway. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> controls all
            aspects of somatic sexual differentiation, presumably by regulating a variety of tissue-
            and cell-specific downstream targets, including the cell death regulator <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-1</ulink> and the
            male sexual regulator <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-3;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-3</ulink>. Sex determination evolves rapidly, and conservation of
            sexual regulators between phyla has been elusive. An apparent exception involves DM
            domain proteins, including <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-3;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-3</ulink>, which control sexual differentiation in nematodes,
            arthropods, and vertebrates. Important issues needing more study include the detailed
            molecular mechanisms of the global pathway, the identities of additional sexual
            regulators acting in the global pathway and downstream of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink>, and the evolutionary
            history of the sex determination pathway. Recently developed genetic and genomic
            technologies and comparative studies in divergent species have begun to address these issues.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
    <sect1>
        <title>A global sex determination pathway controls sexual dimorphism</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Two highly dimorphic sexes</title>
            <para>The two natural sexes of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are the XX hermaphrodite
                and the XO male (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). Hermaphrodites are somatically female
                but can reproduce either by self-fertilization or by mating with males. Mating
                generates broods of half XX and half XO progeny. Self progeny mostly are XX, but
                about 1/500 are XO males, due to meiotic X chromosome nondisjunction, which ensures
                genetic exchange between individuals. The level of X chromosome nondisjunction, and
                hence the proportion of males in a population can be greatly increased by <emphasis>him</emphasis> (<emphasis role="underline">h</emphasis>igh
               <emphasis role="underline">i</emphasis>ncidence of <emphasis role="underline">m</emphasis>ales) mutations (<link linkend="bib26">Hodgkin et al., 1979</link><!-- PMID-->). Because the two sexes
                differ in X chromosome dosage, a dosage compensation system has evolved to equalize
                expression of X-linked genes between XX and XO animals. This is accomplished by
                specifically reducing transcription of X-linked genes in XX animals (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_dosagecomp/dosagecomp.html" role="_blank">X-chromosome dosage compensation</ulink>). Sexual dimorphism is extensive in <emphasis>C.
                elegans</emphasis>, with most tissues and organs differing between the sexes in
                anatomy or physiology (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). Indeed, at least 40<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of male and 30<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of hermaphrodite cells are sexually
                specialized (<link linkend="bib58">Sulston and Horvitz, 1977</link><!-- PMID 838129-->). For further description of
            male- and hermaphrodite-specific development, see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_maledevelopment/maledevelopment.html" role="_blank">Male development</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_hermcellfate/hermcellfate.html" role="_blank">Hermaphrodite cell fate specification</ulink>, respectively.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
            <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
			<imageobject>
			<imagedata entityref="fig1" align="center" width="4.5in"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase> figure 1</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>The global somatic sex determination pathway</title>
            <para>The sexual fates of all somatic cells are controlled by a regulatory pathway whose
                activity differs between the sexes (<xref linkend="figure2" />). This regulatory pathway is often
                called a “global” sex determination pathway to distinguish it from more specialized
                regulatory pathways that control sexual differentiation of particular tissues and
                lineages. The global pathway also controls dosage compensation, the process that
                equalizes X-linked gene expression in the two sexes (see below). The global pathway
                was originally proposed on the basis of extensive genetic epistasis tests involving
                mutations affecting sex determination; it has been supported by subsequent molecular
                analysis (<link linkend="bib23">Hodgkin, 1987</link><!-- PMID 3327460-->; <link linkend="bib60">Villeneuve and Meyer, 1990</link><!-- PMID 2190446-->). In
                addition to the regulatory interactions shown in <xref linkend="figure2" />, several minor
                interactions have been described, and these are thought to help reinforce the
                activity of the pathway in one sex or the other (<link linkend="bib16">Goodwin and Ellis, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11839294-->). The same core regulatory pathway also controls sex determination in the
                germ line (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_vulvaldev/vulvaldev.html" role="_blank">Vulval development</ulink>). However, because hermaphrodites need to generate both
                oocytes and sperm, additional regulators are required in the germ line to
                temporarily reverse the sex determination decision, as described in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_controloocytematuration/controloocytematuration.html">Oocyte meiotic maturation and fertilization</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_spermatogenesis/spermatogenesis.html">Spermatogenesis</ulink> 
.</para>
            <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
			<imageobject>
			<imagedata entityref="fig2" align="center" width="6.5in"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase> figure 2</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
            <para>The overall regulatory logic of the somatic sex determination scheme is seemingly
                straightforward. In essence, the number of X chromosomes controls a series of
                inhibitory interactions that ultimately sets the activity of the terminal regulator
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> (<emphasis><emphasis role="underline">tra</emphasis>nsformer 1</emphasis>).
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> then directs sexual differentiation throughout the soma
                (<link linkend="bib24">Hodgkin, 1987</link><!-- PMID 3428597-->; <link linkend="bib28">Hodgkin and Brenner, 1977</link><!-- PMID 560330-->; <link linkend="bib29">Hunter and Wood, 1990</link><!-- PMID 2261640-->).</para>
            <para>If its purpose is to regulate <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> activity, why does the
                pathway appear so needlessly baroque? Part of the explanation is that there are
                other functions and features, such as the need to coordinate dosage compensation
                with sex determination (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_dosagecomp/dosagecomp.html" role="_blank">X-chromosome dosage compensation</ulink>). Similarly, the <emphasis>fem</emphasis> genes promote
                spermatogenesis independently of their regulation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis>
                (<link linkend="bib22">Hodgkin, 1986</link><!-- PMID 3770465-->). In addition, the pathway has regulatory interactions
                that enhance the plasticity and fidelity of the sex determination switch. One
                example is the ability of the pathway to reverse the sex determination decision in
                the XX germ line and allow both sperm and oocytes to form from a common stem cell
                pool. Another is the cell non-autonomous regulation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-2" role="_blank">tra-2</ulink></emphasis> by
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis>, described below.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>The balance of X-linked and autosomal signal elements controls <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xol-1" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis>
        </title>
        <para>The sex determination cascade is initiated in the early embryo by the ratio between
            the number of X chromosomes and sets of autosomes (X:A; <link linkend="bib45">Nigon, 1951</link><!-- PMID-->). The X:A
            ratio determines the expression level of the upstream regulator
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xol-1" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis> (<emphasis role="underline">XO</emphasis> <emphasis role="underline">l</emphasis>ethal 1), with a high ratio (XX) repressing
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xol-1" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis> expression and a low ratio (XO) permitting high
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xol-1" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis> expression. The activity of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xol-1" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis> then
            controls the rest of the sex determination pathway (<link linkend="bib42">Miller et al., 1988</link><!-- PMID 3167975-->;
            <link linkend="bib51">Rhind et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 7813020-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=XOL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">XOL-1</ulink> is structurally related to GHMP small molecule
            kinases, but it does not bind ATP and its regulatory activity is not yet understood (<link linkend="bib36">Luz et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12672694-->).</para>
        <para>The X:A ratio regulates the activity of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xol-1" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis> via the combined
            action of a set of “numerator” or X-signal elements on the X chromosome and
            “denominator,” or autosomal, signal elements elsewhere in the genome. Genetic dissection
            of the X chromosome using duplications and deletions revealed that the X-signal is
            polygenic, involving at least four components (<link linkend="bib2">Akerib and Meyer, 1994</link><!-- PMID 7896094-->).
            Further dissection and mutational analysis have identified two X-signal components,
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fox-1" role="_blank">fox-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sex-1" role="_blank">sex-1</ulink></emphasis>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FOX-1;class=protein" role="_blank">FOX-1</ulink> is a putative RNA
            binding protein (<link linkend="bib27">Hodgkin et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 7821230-->; <link linkend="bib44">Nicoll et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9217163-->;
            <link linkend="bib55">Skipper et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 9927456-->) that can post-transcriptionally repress a
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xol-1" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis> reporter when overexpressed (<link linkend="bib44">Nicoll et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9217163-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SEX-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SEX-1</ulink> is related to nuclear hormone receptors and represses
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xol-1" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis> transcription, probably by direct binding to the
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xol-1" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis> promoter (<link linkend="bib5">Carmi et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9823896-->).</para>
<?newpage?>
        <para>The X-signal elements are opposed by autosomal signal elements. Three candidate genes
            were identified in a screen for suppressors of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fox-1" role="_blank">fox-1</ulink></emphasis>
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sex-1" role="_blank">sex-1</ulink></emphasis> lethality. Two of these genes have been cloned and found to
            encode likely transcriptional regulators: <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sea-1" role="_blank">sea-1</ulink></emphasis> encodes a T-box protein, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sea-2" role="_blank">sea-2</ulink></emphasis> a
            novel protein with zinc fingers and a metalloprotease domain (B. Meyer, pers. comm.; <link linkend="bib69">Powell et al., 2005</link>).</para>
        <para>The X:A signal system is exquisitely sensitive: although normally required to
            distinguish between ratios of 0.5 (XO) and 1.0 (XX), it can reliably discriminate a
            ratio of 0.67 from one of 0.75 (<link linkend="bib37">Madl and Herman, 1979</link><!-- PMID 295035-->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Sex determination and dosage compensation are coordinately regulated</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>The SDC proteins connect sex determination and dosage compensation</title>
            <para>The global sex determination pathway can be divided into two segments (<xref linkend="figure2" />).
                The first segment (X:A signal to <emphasis>sdc</emphasis> genes) coordinately controls both sex
                determination and dosage compensation, ensuring that these processes always occur in
                the same mode. The segment from <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis> onward is dedicated to
                sex determination.</para>
            <para>The three SDC (<emphasis role="underline">s</emphasis>ex determination and <emphasis role="underline">d</emphasis>osage <emphasis role="underline">c</emphasis>ompensation defective) proteins link
                the gene-specific regulation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis> that controls sex
                determination with the chromosome-wide process of dosage compensation. The SDC
                proteins are components of a large protein complex that localizes to the X
                chromosomes of hermaphrodites early in embryogenesis and reduces their transcription
                by one-half (reviewed by <link linkend="bib41">Meyer, 2000</link><!-- PMID 10827451-->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_dosagecomp/dosagecomp.html" role="_blank">X-chromosome dosage compensation</ulink>).Components
                of the dosage compensation complex including the SDC proteins also control sex
                determination by binding to the promoter of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis> and
                repressing its transcription in XX animals to one-twentieth that of XO animals (<emphasis>her</emphasis> = <emphasis role="underline">her</emphasis>maphroditization of XO; <link linkend="bib8">Chu et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 11937488-->; <link linkend="bib11">Dawes et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10364546-->; <link linkend="bib59">Trent et al., 1991</link><!-- PMID 1716965-->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>SDC proteins and repression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis>
            </title>
            <para>All three SDC proteins function both in repression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis>
                and in dosage compensation. However, there are clear indications that these
                processes are mechanistically distinct. First, the two complexes have different
                compositions. In particular, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DPY-21;class=protein" role="_blank">DPY-21</ulink> localizes to X but not to
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib64">Yonker and Meyer, 2003</link><!-- PMID 14660541-->). There also are
                differences in how the complexes recognize their targets. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SDC-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SDC-2</ulink> plays a key role in
                X chromosome recognition, whereas <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SDC-3;class=protein" role="_blank">SDC-3</ulink> is more important for
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis> recognition (<link linkend="bib64">Yonker and Meyer, 2003</link><!-- PMID 14660541-->). The
                magnitude of transcriptional repression is much greater for
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis> regulation than for dosage compensation of X-linked genes
                (twenty-fold versus two-fold, respectively; <link linkend="bib11">Dawes et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10364546-->).
                Finally, the two activities of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SDC-3;class=protein" role="_blank">SDC-3</ulink> are genetically separable, with the ATP binding
                motif of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SDC-3;class=protein" role="_blank">SDC-3</ulink> required for regulation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis> and the zinc
                fingers required for dosage compensation (<link linkend="bib32">Klein and Meyer, 1993</link><!-- PMID 8431944-->).</para>
            <para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SDC-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SDC-2</ulink> is expressed only in hermaphrodites, as a result of male-specific repression
                by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=XOL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">XOL-1</ulink>, and this gives the SDC complex sex-specificity (<link linkend="bib11">Dawes et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10364546-->). Several potential SDC binding elements have been identified in
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis>. Two of these contain a 15 bp sequence not found on X;
                binding of SDC complexes to this element may mediate formation of a sex
                determination-specific complex (<link linkend="bib8">Chu et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 11937488-->). Two dominant
                gain-of-function alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis> have been shown to alter
                promoter sequences and result in constitutive <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis> expression
                (<link linkend="bib47">Perry et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 7828816-->). These mutations interfere with binding and
                regulation by the SDC complex (<link linkend="bib8">Chu et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 11937488-->).</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HER-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HER-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-2;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-2</ulink> provide cell non-autonomous control of sexual fate</title>
        <sect2>
            <title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HER-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HER-1</ulink> inactivates <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-2;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-2</ulink></title>
            <para>
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis> controls the segment of the pathway that is dedicated to
                sex determination. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HER-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HER-1</ulink> is a small secreted protein and promotes male development
                in a cell non-autonomous manner, by inhibiting the function of the transmembrane
                protein TRA-2A (<link linkend="bib30">Hunter and Wood, 1992</link><!-- PMID 1741033-->; <link linkend="bib46">Perry et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8436294-->). A model illustrating likely molecular interactions between the
                sex-determining proteins from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HER-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HER-1</ulink> to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> is shown in <xref linkend="figure3" />.</para>
            <mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
			<imageobject>
			<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="3.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase> Types of alternative splicing figure 3</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
            <para>There is compelling evidence for direct <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HER-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HER-1</ulink>/TRA-2A binding: TRA-2A expression is
                necessary and sufficient to confer <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HER-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HER-1</ulink> binding to cultured cells, and the probable
                interaction interfaces of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HER-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HER-1</ulink> and TRA-2A have been identified by a combination of
                genetic and structural studies (<link linkend="bib20">Hamaoka et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15289613-->; <link linkend="bib33">Kuwabara, 1996</link><!-- PMID 8681790-->). Having a cell non-autonomous step in the sex determination pathway
                has been suggested to help avoid errors by coordinating the sexual fates of cells.
                With a largely fixed cell lineage, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is limited in its
                ability to repair errors in cell fate specification. Secreted <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HER-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HER-1</ulink> also allows
            somatic control of germline sexual fate (<link linkend="bib30">Hunter and Wood, 1992</link><!-- PMID 1741033-->).</para>
            <para>
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-2" role="_blank">tra-2</ulink></emphasis> also is regulated by translational repression. This is of
                particular importance in the germ line (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_vulvaldev/vulvaldev.html" role="_blank">Vulval development</ulink>), but also is likely to affect
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-2;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-2</ulink> expression in the soma. Disruption of elements in the 3’ UTR of
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-2" role="_blank">tra-2</ulink></emphasis> can cause weak dominant feminization of the male soma and
                increased translation of reporters (<link linkend="bib13">Doniach, 1986</link><!-- PMID 3770471-->; <link linkend="bib18">Goodwin et al.,1993</link><!-- PMID 8402916-->). A candidate to mediate repression via the
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-2" role="_blank">tra-2</ulink></emphasis> 3’ UTR is the essential gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=laf-1" role="_blank">laf-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib17">Goodwin et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9043090-->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-2;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-2</ulink> inactivates the FEM proteins</title>
            <para>The three FEM proteins (<emphasis>fem</emphasis> = <emphasis role="underline">fem</emphasis>inization) are a diverse group whose biochemistry
                is still largely unclear. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-1</ulink> has ankyrin repeats, but otherwise no obvious
                conserved motifs, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-2;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-2</ulink> is a serine/threonine protein phosphatase, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-3;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-3</ulink> is
                novel (<link linkend="bib1">Ahringer et al., 1992</link><!-- PMID 1376249-->; <link linkend="bib7">Chin-Sang and Spence, 1996</link><!-- PMID 8824590-->; <link linkend="bib48">Pilgrim et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 8534913-->; <link linkend="bib57">Spence et al., 1990</link><!-- PMID 2317869-->). All
                three are required for male development and, based on genetic epistasis tests, the
                appear to act between <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-2" role="_blank">tra-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> to
                control somatic sex (<link linkend="bib22">Hodgkin, 1986</link><!-- PMID 3770465-->). TRA-2A inhibits the FEM proteins
                in hermaphrodites, regulation that is prevented in males by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HER-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HER-1</ulink>. Regulation of the
                <emphasis>fem</emphasis> genes is not transcriptional, as they show similar expression levels in both
                sexes (<link linkend="bib1">Ahringer et al., 1992</link><!-- PMID 1376249-->; <link linkend="bib15">Gaudet et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8862524-->;
                <link linkend="bib48">Pilgrim et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 8534913-->). Instead regulation is likely to involve
                protein/protein interactions: <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> and yeast two-hybrid interactions have been
                demonstrated between TRA-2A and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-3;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-3</ulink> (<link linkend="bib40">Mehra et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10364161-->) and
                between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-3;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-2;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib7">Chin-Sang and Spence, 1996</link><!-- PMID 8824590-->). Consequently, a
                simple model is that association of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HER-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HER-1</ulink> with an extracellular domain of TRA-2A
                blocks the ability of an intracellular domain of TRA-2A to associate with and
                inhibit <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-3;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-2;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-2</ulink>. How these interactions affect FEM protein function, whether
                the three FEM proteins form a complex <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>, and what substrate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-2;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-2</ulink>
                dephosphorylates remain to be determined.</para>
            <para>TRA-2A function may be enhanced by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-3;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-3</ulink>, a calcium-dependent protease that can
                cleave TRA-2A <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> to produce a peptide (TRA-2ic) that is predicted from
                transgenic experiments to have feminizing activity (<link linkend="bib3">Barnes and Hodgkin, 1996</link><!-- PMID 8887539-->; <link linkend="bib56">Sokol and Kuwabara, 2000</link><!-- PMID 10783162-->). Another negative regulator of the
                FEM proteins in hermaphrodites is <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SEL-10;class=protein" role="_blank">SEL-10</ulink>, one of a large family of F-box proteins.
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SEL-10;class=protein" role="_blank">SEL-10</ulink> has weak feminizing activity <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>, coimmunoprecipitates all three FEM
                proteins from transfected cells, and appears to target <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-3;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-3</ulink> for
                proteasomal degradation (<link linkend="bib31">Jager et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15306688-->).</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>High versus low <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> activity determines somatic cell sexual fates</title>
        <sect2>
            <title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> is the nematode GLI protein</title>
            <para>The global sex determination pathway appears to act entirely though the terminal
                regulator <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis>. Active <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> promotes
                hermaphrodite development and prevents male development (<link linkend="bib21">Hodgkin, 1983</link><!-- PMID 6866126-->; <link linkend="bib24">Hodgkin, 1987</link><!-- PMID 3428597-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> expresses two
                mRNAs encoding proteins with zinc fingers (<link linkend="bib66">Zarkower and Hodgkin, 1992</link><!-- PMID 1339311-->). The larger transcript encodes TRA-1A, with five zinc fingers, and the
                smaller RNA encodes TRA-1B, which contains only the amino terminus and first two
                zinc fingers. It is unknown whether both proteins contribute to
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> activity, but TRA-1A binds DNA <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis>, while TRA-1B
                does not (<link linkend="bib67">Zarkower and Hodgkin, 1993</link><!-- PMID 8367286-->).</para>
            <para>The zinc fingers of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> are highly similar to those of the <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> Ci and
                vertebrate GLI proteins, transcription factors regulated by Hedgehog signaling via
                the Patched and Smoothened co-receptors (<link linkend="bib66">Zarkower and Hodgkin, 1992</link><!-- PMID 1339311-->).
                Although <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> lacks obvious Hedgehog or Smoothened
                homologs, it does have a number of Patched-related proteins, including TRA-2A
                (<link linkend="bib34">Kuwabara et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10921907-->). This suggests that part of the global sex
                determination pathway originally derived from a Hedgehog signaling pathway.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> has distinct functions in sex determination and gonadogenesis</title>
            <para>
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis>(null) XX animals are transformed into pseudomales that
                can be fertile, so robust male development is possible in the absence of
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> function. However, these <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis>
                pseudomales frequently have small and disorganized somatic gonads, indicating that
                some <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> activity is required for development of the male
                somatic gonad (<link linkend="bib24">Hodgkin, 1987</link><!-- PMID 3428597-->; <link linkend="bib52">Schedl et al., 1989</link><!-- PMID 2612895-->). The
                gonadal defects stem at least in part from roles in the organization and
                proliferation of the gonadal primordium that are distinct from the sex determination
                function of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis>.</para>
            <para>
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> controls gonadal development in concert with at least two
                other factors. During embryogenesis <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ehn-3" role="_blank">ehn-3</ulink></emphasis> together
                regulate formation of the somatic gonadal primordium (<link linkend="bib38">Mathies et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15294864-->), and after hatching, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fkh-6" role="_blank">fkh-6</ulink></emphasis> redundantly
                control gonadal cell proliferation (<link linkend="bib6">Chang et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14993191-->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Regulation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> activity</title>
            <para>How <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> activity is controlled is still poorly understood.
                Many strong gain-of-function mutations have been isolated (<link linkend="bib24">Hodgkin, 1987</link><!-- PMID 3428597-->). All affect a short protein sequence common to TRA-1A and TRA-1B (the
                “gain-of-function domain”), suggesting that regulation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> is primarily
                post-translational (<link linkend="bib12">de Bono et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 7851791-->). As
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> activity is controlled by the three FEM proteins, an
                attractive model is that a FEM protein inhibits the activity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> via
                interaction with the gain-of-function domain. Regulation may involve the
                localization, modification, or degradation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> (or a combination of these, as
                sex-specific differences in processing and nuclear accumulation of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink>
                protein(s) have been observed; <link linkend="bib53">Segal et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11703944-->; A. Spence, pers. comm.).</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> links global and tissue-specific sexual regulation</title>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> directs sexually dimorphic development at the cellular level, with diverse
            consequences in different cell types. Direct transcriptional regulation by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> in
            somatic cells has thus far been shown for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib62">Yi et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 11003845-->) and
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-1" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib10">Conradt and Horvitz, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10458607-->). Both genes are transcriptionally
            repressed by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> in specific hermaphrodite cell types in order to prevent male
            differentiation. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> represses <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> transcription in the XX intestine, thereby
            preventing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-3;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-3</ulink> from repressing yolk protein transcription in hermaphrodites (<link linkend="bib63">Yi and Zarkower, 1999</link><!-- PMID 9927589-->; <link linkend="bib62">Yi et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 11003845-->).<emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-1" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> is a global
            regulator of programmed cell death (<link linkend="bib9">Conradt and Horvitz, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9604928-->); however a
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> binding site is found nearly 6 kb downstream of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-1" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> coding region.
            Disruption of this site in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-1" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> gain-of-function mutants results in ectopic <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-1" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis>
            transcription in the HSN neurons causes the death of these cells (<link linkend="bib10">Conradt and Horvitz,1999</link><!-- PMID 10458607-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> likely represses the homeobox gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-30" role="_blank">ceh-30</ulink></emphasis> to control
            sex-specific death of the four CEM neurons: <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-30" role="_blank">ceh-30</ulink></emphasis> is required for CEM survival in
            males; and mutations in a conserved <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> consensus binding site near <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-30" role="_blank">ceh-30</ulink></emphasis> cause
            ectopic CEM survival in XX animals (H. Schwartz and H.R. Horvitz, pers. comm.).</para>
        <para>From the limited data available, a picture emerges in which <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> is expressed widely
            but exerts highly selective effects on target gene expression in particular cell types.
            This specificity may arise from short-range transcriptional repression, in which <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink>
            binding to DNA only blocks the activity of <emphasis>cis</emphasis> elements within a limited distance (<link linkend="bib62">Yi et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 11003845-->). By repressing some enhancer elements in a target gene without
            affecting others, a globally-expressed regulator like <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> can control expression of
            each target gene selectively in particular cells or tissues. It has been suggested that
            short-range repression facilitates “sampling” of new target genes by the global
            regulator during evolution and thereby provides superior evolutionary flexibility (<link linkend="bib4">Cai et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8790326-->; <link linkend="bib19">Gray et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 7958860-->; <link linkend="bib65">Zarkower, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11256069-->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Downstream sexual regulators: the interface between sex determination and sexual differentiation</title>
        <para>The critical role of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> in establishing sexual dimorphism and its function as a
            likely transcriptional regulator have been known for some time. Despite this,
            surprisingly little is known of the genes that function directly downstream of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> in
            specific cell lineages, tissues, and organs to generate sexual dimorphism. For example,
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> controls whether the posterior seam cells V5 and V6 generate
            male V rays or hermaphrodite lateral hypodermis (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_maledevelopment/maledevelopment.html" role="_blank">Male development</ulink>), but no <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> target
            has been identified in this lineage. Regulation by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-1" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> accounts for
            only a small proportion of sexual dimorphism; many additional direct targets likely
            await discovery.</para>
        <para>The establishment of sexual dimorphism can be roughly divided into two steps, first
            the sex determination decision, and second the execution of sexual differentiation. In
            general, mutations that abrogate sex determination cause sex reversal, and this is true
            of all the genes in the global pathway. By contrast, mutations in regulators of sexual
            differentiation cause defects in this process, but not sex reversal. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> and its
            targets are at the interface between these processes. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> illustrates that the
            distinction between regulators of sex determination and sexual differentiation can be
            hazy. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> mutant males have a feminized intestine that produces yolk, but the V ray
            lineages in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> male tail are defective rather than feminized (<link linkend="bib54">Shen and Hodgkin, 1988</link><!-- PMID 3046751-->). Another gene at this interface is the gonadal regulator <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fkh-6" role="_blank">fkh-6</ulink></emphasis>,
            which has a sex-determining function in the early male somatic gonad, and a
            differentiation role later in the hermaphrodite gonad (<link linkend="bib6">Chang et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14993191-->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Some aspects of sex determination may be evolutionarily conserved</title>
        <para>Primary sex-determining mechanisms are extremely varied and evolve rapidly (see
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_evolutionsexdetermin/evolutionsexdetermin.htm" role="_blank">The evolution of nematode sex determination</ulink>). The lability of sex determination is clearly demonstrated by the ease
            with which the process can be brought under the control of different genes in the
            pathway. Hodgkin has shown that any of seven autosomal sex determination genes can be
            genetically manipulated to become the primary determinant of sex, and that any of the
            five autosomes can thereby become a sex chromosome (<link linkend="bib25">Hodgkin, 2002</link><!-- PMID 12399387-->). Given
            the facility with which new sex determination pathways can be created in the laboratory,
            they would be expected to be highly diverse in nature. This is the case: none of the
            sex-determining genes in <xref linkend="figure2" /> has been found to have a homolog playing a similar
            role outside the nematode phylum.</para>
        <para>So far the best candidates for conserved sexual regulators are downstream genes
            related to <emphasis>Drosophila doublesex</emphasis>. These are termed DM domain (<emphasis>doublesex</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis>
            related) genes, after the conserved DNA binding motif they share (<link linkend="bib14">Erdman and Burtis, 1993</link><!-- PMID 8440242-->; <link linkend="bib50">Raymond et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9490411-->; <link linkend="bib68">Zhu et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10898790-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> these include <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-23" role="_blank">mab-23</ulink></emphasis>, both of
            which regulate multiple aspects of male differentiation and behavior (<link linkend="bib35">Lints and Emmons, 2002</link><!-- PMID 12231628-->; <link linkend="bib54">Shen and Hodgkin, 1988</link><!-- PMID 3046751-->; <link linkend="bib62">Yi et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 11003845-->). Genes encoding DM domain proteins have been shown to regulate sexual
            development in mammals (<link linkend="bib49">Raymond et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 11040213-->) and fish (<link linkend="bib39">Matsuda et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12037570-->; <link linkend="bib43">Nanda et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12193652-->), and are likely, based on
            sexually dimorphic expression and sex-linkage, to play similar roles in other
            vertebrates with different sex determination mechanisms (<link linkend="bib65">Zarkower, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11256069-->).
            Thus it appears that at least some downstream sexual regulators have an ancient
            involvement in sexual dimorphism that is more stable than that of the upstream primary
            sex determination pathway. While <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-23" role="_blank">mab-23</ulink></emphasis> primarily function in sexual
            differentiation rather than sex determination, comparison with Drosophila and vertebrate
            homologs suggests that the ancestral role of these genes may have been in sex
            determination. As more sexual regulators downstream of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> are identified, other
            conserved factors may be found.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Open questions</title>
        <para>Much progress has been made in understanding the regulation of somatic sex
            determination in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, but new questions have been raised and
            some old ones remain unanswered. Questions needing more experimental attention can be
            divided into four categories:</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Molecular mechanisms of the global pathway</title>
            <para>How the cascade of inhibitory interactions that converts X chromosome dosage into
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> activity functions is known in outline, but not in great detail. Do the X and
                autosomal signal elements antagonize one another directly or indirectly? How does
                the interaction of TRA-2A with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-3;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-3</ulink> inactivate the FEM proteins, and how does <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HER-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HER-1</ulink>
                binding to TRA-2A prevent this inactivation? How do the FEM proteins repress
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> activity? <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-2;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-2</ulink> is a phosphatase, so does regulation of
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> involve sex-differential phosphorylation, and if so what is the kinase? How is
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> processed to generate sex-specific peptides, and what are their activities?</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Other regulators</title>
            <para>Most of known sex determining genes were found in genetic screens for defects in
                sexual differentiation. These screens have probably identified all of the genes
                whose loss of function phenotype is severe sex reversal. However, although many of
                these screens were conducted in sensitized genetic backgrounds, other regulators
                must have been missed, particularly essential genes and those that act redundantly.
                Two lines of evidence make it clear that such genes exist. First, there are
                biochemical activities unaccounted for, such as the putative kinase whose
                phosphorylation is reversed by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-2;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-2</ulink>. Second, there is genetic evidence for
                additional regulators. As an example, mutating <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xol-1" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis> enhances
                the masculinization of XX <emphasis>tra-(null)</emphasis> mutants, suggesting that another regulator(s)
                acts downstream of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xol-1" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis> and in parallel with
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-2" role="_blank">tra-2</ulink></emphasis> to promote <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> activity (<link linkend="bib28">Hodgkin and Brenner, 1977</link><!-- PMID 560330-->; <link linkend="bib42">Miller et al., 1988</link><!-- PMID 3167975-->). Focused
                molecular screens should allow the identification of such regulatory molecules.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>What genes act downstream of TRA-1?</title>
            <para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> activity directs alternative cell fates throughout the soma. This involves
                transcriptional repression of dedicated sexual regulators (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis>) and of more
                general cellular factors (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-1" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis>), and can control the physiology of entire organs
                like the intestine or the fates of individual cells. Is <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-1" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> the more
                typical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> target? Does <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> act exclusively as a transcriptional repressor or
                might it also activate transcription? Much work remains to find genes that act
                downstream of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> in other tissues. This will aid in understanding how sexual
                dimorphism is established in different cell types and how sexual regulation
                interacts with spatial and temporal regulation during development. The improved
                availability of reporter genes marking sexually dimorphic tissues and new techniques
                for global analysis of gene expression and function should accelerate progress.</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>How has the sex determination pathway evolved?</title>
            <para>Evolution of sex determination pathways is covered in detail in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_evolutionsexdetermin/evolutionsexdetermin.html" role="_blank">The evolution of nematode sex determination</ulink>. The
                    <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> sex determination pathway has been proposed to
                have arisen from a “bottom up” accretion of negative regulators during evolution
                (<link linkend="bib61">Wilkins, 1995</link><!-- PMID 7702596-->). Genetic investigations of somatic sex determination
                in other nematodes have begun, and these, along with comparative molecular studies,
                are certain to be informative. As mentioned earlier, the pathway from
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=her-1" role="_blank">her-1</ulink></emphasis> to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> appears to derive from a
                hedgehog signaling pathway which might have been co-opted in one step; comparative
                studies should clarify this question. As more divergent species are studied, it also
                will become clearer which parts of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> pathway are
                ancient and which are more recently recruited. In particular, it will be important
                to test suggestions that DM domain genes like <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-23" role="_blank">mab-23</ulink></emphasis> are descended from
                very ancient metazoan sex-determining genes.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
		<para/>
		&somaticsexdet_Refs;</sect1>
</article>