<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 2. The first four Notch interactions in the AB lineage</title>
        <para>A partial lineage of the AB blastomere is shown in red; for simplicity the vertical
            axis is not scaled accurately with respect to time. A subset of descendants of ABa and
            ABp that express GLP-1 or LIN-12 contact various ligand-expressing cells (blue) and
            activate Notch signaling. Expression of the REF-1 family members occurs about 25 minutes
            after an interaction (bold black lines). For comparison with Figure 5, the left and
            right head precursors are indicated. The bottom panel shows the effects of Notch
            signaling on the various fates of AB descendants. The pattern of cell division and
            differentiation of a cell is considered here as its 'fate'. In wild-type development,
            the eight AB descendants have unique fates that can be represented by their names
            (ABala, ABarp, etc); for simplicity, these different fates/names are represented as
            numbers with the key shown at right. Defects in Notch signaling transform one or more of
            these cells to resemble other cells as shown. In the absence of Notch signaling, all
            eight cells express TBX-37, -38 (magenta) and adopt one of two fates (1a or 1p, where
                a<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003D;</symbol> anterior and p<symbol
            role="symbolfont">&#x003D;</symbol>posterior). For example, all of the 1a cells
            adopt a pattern of development that resembles a wild-type ABala cell. When only the
            first interaction occurs, TBX-37, -38 are repressed in ABp descendants and these cells
            adopt new fates as shown. If embryos undergo both the first and second interaction, ABa
            descendants (boxed) also change their fate as indicated. When all four interactions
            occur (bottom line), all AB descendants have their wild-type fates. </para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>
