<caption align="left">
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 2. Regulation of the mitosis/meiosis decision in the adult germ line</title>
        <para> (A) Top,
            distal end of an adult hermaphrodite gonad, dissected from the animal. Projection of
            confocal z series. Green DTC projection includes entire z-series, red ToPro-3 projection
            includes a subset of sections so nuclear morphology is clearer. Mitotic region,
            transition zone (TZ) and pachytene region (Pach) are marked with brackets. The DTC and
            its processes are visualized using GFP (green), produced under control of the <emphasis>lag-2</emphasis>
            promoter; germline nuclei are visualized with ToPro-3 (red). The distal to proximal axis
            of the germ line extends from the DTC at the distal end to mature gametes at the
            proximal end. (B) Extents of the niche, mitotic region and transition zone in one stage
            of the hermaphrodite adult gonad. The niche (DTC and its processes) extends along the distal-proximal axis (see processes in A). The mitotic region
            extends ~20 cell diameters and is defined by the region in which mitotic nuclei are
            observed when averaged over multiple germlines. The yellow bar graph depicts relative
            number of phosphohistone H3-positive mitotic nuclei at each position in the mitotic
            region. The TZ begins where 60% nuclei have the crescent-shaped morphology typical
            of early meiotic prophase (see red crescents above). The green bar graph shows
            percentage of nuclei in meiotic prophase (leptotene, zygotene or pachytene) at a given
            position along the distal-proximal axis. Red bar indicates approximate boundary of
            premeiotic S-phase (SLC and JK, unpub.). This region is likely similar to the meiotic
            entry region described in Hansen et al. (2004<!-- : PMID15063172 -->). (C) Distribution of mitotic
            and meiotic regulators within distal germ line. Levels of GLP-1 and FBF mitotic
            regulators are high throughout the mitotic region and decrease as germ cells enter
            meiosis (Crittenden et al., 2002<!-- : PMID12050669 -->; Crittenden et al., 1994<!-- : PMID7607080 -->;
            Lamont et al., 2004<!-- : PMID15525531 -->). Conversely, levels of most meiotic regulators
            (GLD-1, GLD-2 and GLD-3) gradually increase in the proximal part of the mitotic region
            and reach high levels as germ cells enter meiotic prophase (Eckmann et al., 2002<!-- :
            PMID12431376 -->; Jones et al., 1996<!-- : PMID8948583 -->; Wang et al., 2002<!-- : PMID12239571 -->). One
            exception is NOS-3, which is distributed uniformly throughout the germ line (Kraemer et
            al., 1999<!-- : PMID10508609 -->). The balance of mitotic and meiotic regulators is likely to
            determine whether a cell remains in mitosis or enters meiosis (for review see Crittenden
            et al., 2003<!-- : PMID14511482 -->). The sizes of the bars representing the regulators are not
            quantitative; for example, levels of GLD-2 and GLD-3 appear to be lower and increase
            less sharply than levels of GLD-1 (Eckmann et al., 2004<!-- : PMID15454534 -->; Eckmann et al.,
            2002<!-- : PMID12431376 -->; Jones and Schedl, 1995<!-- : PMID7601353 -->; Wang et al., 2002<!-- :
            PMID12239571 -->). (D) Summary of the genetic and molecular network controlling
            mitosis/meiosis decision. The diagrammed network is simplified, and additional
            regulators are certain to exist. Briefly, GLP-1 activates <emphasis>fbf-2</emphasis> (along with one or more
            other unidentified targets (X)). FBF-1 and FBF-2 negatively regulate each other, a
            feedback loop critical for specifying size of the mitotic region. FBF-1 and FBF-2 also
            negatively regulate levels of GLD-1 and GLD-3, inhibiting meiosis in the distal region
            of the germ line. See text for details and references. </para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>

