<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 4. Imaging live embryos carrying <emphasis>lacO</emphasis> inserts.</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">A.</emphasis> Preparation of the agarose pad, using 3 microscope slides. The outer two slides are taped to the bench using thick laboratory tape. Additional layers of tape will determine the thickness of the agarose pad. A drop of molten 2% agarose is placed in the center of the middle slide and immediately covered with a perpendicular slide, creating a flat pad. <emphasis role="bold">B.</emphasis> Embryos dissected in an watch glass are transferred to the agarose pad using a mouth pipette. Excess buffer is removed with the pipette and embryos are grouped with an eyelash (bar = 20 &#x00B5;m). After covering the embryos with a coverslip, the space around the pad is filled with injection oil and the coverslip is sealed to the slide using Vaseline/lanoline/paraffin or Vaseline alone. <emphasis role="bold">C.</emphasis> Axial z projection of a stack of optical slices of an embryo expressing GFP-lacI from an integrated large array with <emphasis>lacO</emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GW76;class=Strain" role="_blank">GW76</ulink>, <emphasis>gwIs4[<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000235;class=Gene" role="_blank">baf-1</ulink>::GFP-lacI; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003515;class=Gene" role="_blank">myo-3</ulink>::RFP]X</emphasis>). Two large spots corresponding to the homolog chromosomes are visible in each nucleus (bar = 5 &#x00B5;m). <emphasis role="bold">D.</emphasis> Axial z projection of a stack of optical slices of an embryo expressing GFP-lacI from an integrated large array without <emphasis>lacO</emphasis> and an insertion of <emphasis>lacO</emphasis> repeats created using the technique described in Figure 1 (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GW440;class=Strain" role="_blank">GW440</ulink>, <emphasis>gwIs39[<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000235;class=Gene" role="_blank">baf-1</ulink>::GFP-lacI; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006929;class=Gene" role="_blank">vit-5</ulink>::GFP]III gwSi0[lacO/Cb unc-119@ttTi5605]II</emphasis>)<emphasis>.</emphasis> The GFP-lacI expressing array is not visible as it carries no <emphasis>lacO</emphasis> sites. The single copy insertion forms small spots, although these are highly dynamic and appear larger on a z-projection.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>
