<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'WMStrongfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'WMStrongfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'WMStrongfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'WMStrongfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'WMStrongfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'WMStrongfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'WMStrongfig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'WMStrongfig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'WMStrongfig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'WMStrongfig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY WMStrong_Refs SYSTEM "WMStrongrefs.xml">
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="WMStrong_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title><emphasis>Strongyloides stercoralis</emphasis>: a model for translational research on parasitic nematode biology<footnote>
			<para>Edited by Ralf J. Sommer. WormMethods editor Victor Ambros. Last revised December 21, 2006. Published February 17, 2007. This chapter should be cited as: Lok, J.B. <emphasis>Strongyloides stercoralis</emphasis>: a model for translational research on parasitic nematode biology (February 17, 2007), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.134.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2007 James B. Lok. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
		<author>
			<firstname>James B.</firstname>
			<surname>Lok<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:jlok@vet.upenn.edu">jlok@vet.upenn.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></surname>
			<affiliation><address>Department of Pathobiology, University of Pennsylvania School of Veterinary Medicine, Philadelphia, PA 19104 USA</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Because of their free-living life cycle alternatives,</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Strongyloides</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">and related nematode parasites may represent the best models for translating</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">science to the study of nematode parasitism.</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">S. stercoralis,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">a significant pathogen of humans, can be maintained in laboratory dogs and gerbils. Biosafety precautions necessary for work with</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">S. stercoralis,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">though unfamiliar to many</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">researchers, are straightforward and easily accomplished. Although specialized methods are necessary for large-scale culture of the free-living stages of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">S. stercoralis,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">small-scale cultures for experimental purposes may be undertaken using minor modifications of standard</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">methods. Similarly, the morphological similarities between</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">and the free-living stages of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">S. stercoralis</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">allow investigational methods such as laser cell ablation and DNA transformation by gonadal microinjection to be easily adapted from</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">to</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">S. stercoralis.</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">Comparative studies employing these methods have yielded new insights into the neuronal control of the infective process in parasites and its similarity to regulation of dauer development in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans.</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">Furthermore, we have developed a practical method for transient transformation of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">S. stercoralis</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">with vector constructs having various tissue- and cell-specific expression patterns and have assembled these into a modular vector kit for distribution to the community.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>The breadth and depth of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> science, exemplified by WormBook, represents an under-utilized resource for the study of parasitic nematodes. Conversely, the global health impact of nematode parasitism (<link linkend="bib18">Hotez et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16435908-->) provides a strong but seldom cited rationale for research on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. The recent addition of chapters on parasitic nematodes to WormBook (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_genomesTrichinella/genomesTrichinella.html" role="_blank"><emphasis>Trichinella spiralis</emphasis></ulink>; <emphasis>Strongyloides</emphasis> spp.) represents an effort to attract the attention of parasitologists to this resource and to interest the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> community in the potential applications of their work to an important group of pathogens. Of all the parasitic nematodes, <emphasis>Strongyloides</emphasis> and relatives, by virtue of their free-living life cycle alternatives, appear best suited to the immediate application of methodology from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Free-living larvae, males and females of <emphasis>Strongyloides</emphasis> sp. (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>) and <emphasis>Parastrongyloides</emphasis> sp., resemble <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> in their feeding habits and in many aspects of their overall body plans (see <emphasis>Strongyloides</emphasis> spp.). Like <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, the free-living stages of these parasites may be grown or, in the case of <emphasis>Parastrongyloides trichosuri</emphasis>, propagated on agar plates with bacterial lawns (<link linkend="bib11">Grant et al., 2006a</link><!--: PMID 16500655-->; <link linkend="bib35">Schad, 1989</link><!--: -->; <link linkend="bib42">Viney, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10366829-->). As will be discussed below, our group has exploited anatomical similarities between <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>Strongyloides stercoralis</emphasis> to adapt not only standard culture methods but also techniques for neuronal ablation and gene delivery in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to this parasite. Grant and colleagues have similarly achieved transgenesis and developed other basic components of a genetic system in <emphasis>P. trichosuri</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib11">Grant et al., 2006a</link><!--: PMID 16500655-->; <link linkend="bib12">Grant et al., 2006b</link><!--: PMID 16500659-->; <link linkend="bib30">Newton-Howes et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16469320-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Laboratory hosts for <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis></title>
<sect2 id="sec2_1">
<title>Dogs</title>
<para>All progeny of free-living <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> adults are fated to become iL3, which must infect a host in order to develop further (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). Consequently, worms of this species are capable of undergoing only one generation of development outside the host and continuous laboratory rearing requires maintenance of host animals. <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> is a parasite of primates (including humans) and dogs (<link linkend="bib35">Schad, 1989</link>). We maintain the strain of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> designated UPD (<emphasis role="underline">U</emphasis>niversity of <emphasis role="underline">P</emphasis>ennsylvania, <emphasis role="underline">D</emphasis>og) as a subclinical infection in purpose-bred, mix-breed laboratory dogs. We typically, infect dogs by inoculating them subcutaneously with 3000 infective third-stage larvae (iL3).</para>
<sidebar><note>
<title>Note</title>
<para>Protocols for cultivation of selected life stages, including iL3 for inoculation are covered in <link linkend="sec3">Section 3</link> below. The infection becomes patent, that is, iL3 migrate to the intestine, develop to parasitic females and the progeny of these become apparent as first stage larvae (L1) in the feces, within 10 days of inoculation. Without intervention, immunocompetent dogs control infections of this size and cease passing L1 in their feces within 13 weeks of inoculation. The period of patency may be extended to periods of up to six months by means of daily corticosteroid treatment (0.25 mg methylprednisolone acetate/kg body weight orally) of infected dogs. We hypothesize that at this level, corticosteroid treatment extends patency either by extending the reproductive lifespan of existing adult worms or by allowing repeated, but well-regulated cycles of autoinfective development whereby barren or moribund female worms are replaced by their progeny. The former possibility could occur via suppression of immune-mediated clearance of parasitic females by the host (<link linkend="bib10">Gardner et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16913877-->).</para>
</note></sidebar>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2_2">
<title>Gerbils</title>
<para>Their ability to tolerate chronic infection with larger numbers of adult worms and their higher output of fecal larvae make dogs the most practical hosts for laboratory maintenance of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis>. However, the use of such a species for experiments requiring many replicate host infections or the maintenance of numerous parasite strains may be prohibitively expensive and a source of ethical concern. While attempts to infect rats and mice with <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> have failed, gerbils, <emphasis>Meriones unquiculatus</emphasis>, have been found to be susceptible to both infection and autoinfection (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>, "aL3") by<emphasis></emphasis> this parasite. The factors that promote autoinfection in the natural canine or human hosts, immunological immaturity or corticosteroid treatment, do so in the gerbil as well, making this small mammal a valuable model in which to study host-parasite interactions that govern the autoinfective process (<link linkend="bib32">Nolan et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID 8245532-->; <link linkend="bib24">Kerlin et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7635616-->; <link linkend="bib33">Nolan and Schad, 1996</link><!--: PMID 8878405-->; <link linkend="bib31">Nolan et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10219310-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Biosafety</title>
<sect2 id="sec3_1">
<title><emphasis>Strongyloides stercoralis</emphasis> is a parasite and potential pathogen of humans</title>
<para>The iL3 of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> invade the host percutaneously. Convention holds that they migrate via the microvasculature to the lungs where they break out of the capillary bed, enter the alveoli and then proceed to the intestine via the trachea. Work by Schad and colleagues (<link linkend="bib35">Schad et al., 1989</link><!--: PMID 2529363-->), however, suggests that the majority of larvae may actually migrate via a variety of other somatic tissues. In any case, the larvae then undergo two molts to the parasitic female, which invades crypts of the intestinal mucosa. The primary symptom of uncomplicated human strongyloidiasis is abdominal pain, mimicking that associated with peptic ulcer, and acute infections are marked by the presence of first stage larvae in fresh fecal specimens and by eosinophilia. As indicated above, <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> is unique among the parasitic nematodes in its capacity to undertake autoinfection, and immunosuppressed individuals should refrain from working with active cultures of this parasite.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_2">
<title>Animal husbandry precautions: incubation time of infectious larvae and proper waste disposal</title>
<para>With regard to safety of animal husbandry staff, it is important to reinforce that 1.) <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> iL3 infect percutaneously, 2.) larvae found in feces in the first 24 hours (L1) are not infectious and 3.) 24 hours at normal room temperature are required for L1 passed in the feces to reach the infective stage via the homogonic route (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). Therefore, provided a schedule of daily, thorough cage cleaning is maintained (standard operating procedure in most institutional vivaria), the risk of transmission should be minimal. Staff should wear protective clothing consisting at minimum of disposable gloves, gowns, shoe covers and caps, as well as eye and face protection when cleaning cages. In general, these will not constitute special precautions for maintenance of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis>, but rather standard procedure for laboratory animal husbandry staff at most institutional laboratory animal operations.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_3">
<title>Laboratory precautions and decontamination of implements</title>
<para>As with animal husbandry operations, laboratory safety measures mandated at most institutions are adequate to protect against infection with <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis>. Although the presence of infective larvae may be predicted with some precision based on the age of the culture and the incubation temperature (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>), it must be borne in mind that at least a small proportion of post-parasitic L1 in most <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> strains develop directly to the iL3 within 24-48 hours of deposition (ie. the homogonic route). Since the exact deposition time of fecal samples is usually uncertain, it is therefore good practice to regard all <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> cultures, regardless of age as potentially containing infectious parasites. All disposable culture waste should be accumulated in clearly marked biohazard bags and autoclaved prior to discard. Non-disposable glassware, Baermann funnel components (see <link linkend="sec4_3">Protocol 2</link> below) and other implements contaminated with free-living larvae and adults of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> may be decontaminated with a 20% solution of a commercial surgical scrub such as ChlorhexiDerm (2% Chlorhexidine, DVM Pharmaceuticals, Miami, Florida). Surgical scrub should be added to Baermann funnel effluent waste at a similar concentration to kill free-living larvae and adults prior to disposal. Because of their highly resistant cuticles, iL3 are impervious to Chlorhexidine and other conventional surgical scrubs even after several hours of exposure. Implements and solutions containing iL3 can be chemically decontaminated with Lugol&apos;s Iodine (10 mg/ml KI + 10 mg/ml I<subscript>2</subscript> in distilled water).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title><emphasis>In vitro</emphasis> cultivation of free-living stages</title>
<sect2 id="sec4_1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>The challenge in designing preparative culture methods for free-living larvae and adults of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> is to simulate the complex nutritional milieu of moist, fecally contaminated soil while preventing anaerobia. The charcoal coproculture method described below (see <link linkend="sec4_2">Protocol 1</link>) accomplishes this and, assuming adequate output of fecal larvae by the host, provides excellent yields of worms. Methods for isolation of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> and related parasites from such a chemically and microbiologically complex environment (e.g., the Baermann funnel technique, <link linkend="sec4_3">Protocol 2</link>) generally exploit the natural migratory behaviors of the worms, as do some methods for further purification (the agarose migration technique, <link linkend="sec4_5">Protocol 3</link>). Otherwise, by virtue of their similarity to other soil-dwelling nematodes, many standard cultures methods may be adapted from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> methodology for small-scale analytical culture.</para>
<?newpage?>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="100%">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1. Incubation protocols for derivation of selected life stages of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">S. stercoralis</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">from charcoal coproculture.</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colname="c1" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c2" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c3" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c4" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry morerows="1">Developmental stage</entry>
<entry morerows="1"><link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link> reference<superscript>&#x0002A;&#x0002A;</superscript></entry>
<entry align="center" namest="c3" nameend="c4">Incubation protocol</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Temperature (&#x000B0;C)</entry>
<entry>Incubation time</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>Postparasitic L1</entry>
<entry>1</entry>
<entry align="center" namest="col3" nameend="col4">Available immediately in freshly deposited feces</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Directly developing (homogonic) iL3</entry>
<entry>2</entry>
<entry>22</entry>
<entry>24 hr</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry morerows="1">Free-living adults</entry>
<entry morerows="1">3</entry>
<entry>20</entry>
<entry>72 hr</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>22</entry>
<entry>48 hr</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Postfree-living L1<superscript>&#x0002A;</superscript></entry>
<entry>4</entry>
<entry>23.5</entry>
<entry>48 hr</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>iL3</entry>
<entry>5</entry>
<entry>22</entry>
<entry>3-5 days</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="c1" nameend="c4" align="left">&#x0002A; Old free-living adults will also be present in these cultures of postfree-living L1. The L1 may be manually selected from Baermann effluent using flame constricted Pasteur pipets and a dissecting microscope.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="c1" nameend="c4" align="left">&#x0002A;&#x0002A;<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link> reference numbers indicate where specified life stages occur in the <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> life cycle in <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link> (see encircled numerical labels on key life stages).</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_2">
<title>Protocol 1. Charcoal coproculture</title>
<sect3 id="sec4_2_1">
<title>Equipment</title>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Low temperature incubator(s).</emphasis> One or more incubators capable of regulating temperature in the range of 4-37&#x000B0;C are essential for cultivating the free-living stages of <emphasis>S. stercoralis.</emphasis> A single unit set for 26&#x000B0;C can be made to suffice for many purposes. However, we find it advantageous to have three incubators set at 20&#x000B0;, 22&#x000B0; and 25&#x000B0; to allow maximum flexibility in planning experiments and incubating selected stages at optimum temperatures.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Fume hood.</emphasis> Feces of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis>-infected dogs present no hazards of exposure to infective larvae via the contact aerosol inhalant routes during the culture procedure outlined below. However, the aesthetic drawbacks of working with fresh canine feces on an open laboratory bench are easy to imagine. Happily, once this material is dispersed on activated charcoal as called for in this protocol, it is virtually odor-free. However, prior to this step, odors may be offensive. As a measure against this, we carry out the culture preparation procedure (<link linkend="sec4_2_3">4.2.3</link>, steps 2&#x02013;6) in a fume hood. A small biohazard bag for discard of waste materials, such as soiled sample bags and tongue depressors used for fecal collection, should be kept in the fume hood and changed frequently.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">A standard dissecting microscope</emphasis></para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec4_2_2">
<title>Materials</title>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Disposable nitrile gloves</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Wooden tongue depressors</emphasis> to collect fecal samples.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Self-closing plastic sample bags</emphasis> to contain fecal samples.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Small Tupperware box</emphasis> to transport bagged samples from the vivarium.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Plastic Petri dishes</emphasis>, disposable 100 mm</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Filter paper circles</emphasis>, Whatman #1 (or equivalent), 100 mm diameter.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Absorbent paper bench liner</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Plastic beaker, Nalgene</emphasis>, 1 liter capacity.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Biohazard bag (12<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> X 24<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02033;</symbol>) with stand</emphasis></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Plastic containers with lids</emphasis> to contain coprocultures in incubators.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Activated bone charcoal</emphasis>, (5 X 8 mesh). This should be autoclaved and washed thoroughly with tap water prior to use. Washing can be carried out by transferring about 1 kg of the material to a suitably sized Styrofoam shipping container with one or more small holes in a bottom corner. Place the box with charcoal in the sink and fill with tap water. Allow the tap water to drain and repeat. The washed charcoal should be allowed to drain overnight and may then be stored covered in this container next to (or inside) the fume hood.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Deionized (DI) water</emphasis> in a plastic squeeze bottle.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Large funnel(s)</emphasis>, 150 mm diameter, glass or Nalgene plastic.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Tubing</emphasis>, rubber or Tygon plastic, with diameter gauged to give a watertight fit over stem of large funnel (#13).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Pinch clamps</emphasis>, thumbscrew operated.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec4_2_3">
<title>Coproculture procedure</title>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>As with laboratory safety precautions (see <link linkend="sec3_3">Section 3.3</link>), minimum standards for protective clothing required for entry into well regulated institutional vivaria will be adequate for safe handling of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> infected dogs and their feces.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Obtain fresh feces from an infected dog. Feces, which should be formed and free of urine contamination, can be scooped from the cage bottom using a wooden tongue depressor and placed in a self-sealing plastic sample collection bag. To attain some uniformity in the age of fecal parasite larvae, it is best to fix a standard time of day to do fecal collections. We typically do this between 09:00 and 09:30 hrs, prior to scheduled cage cleaning by lab animal husbandry personnel.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Place sample bag with feces in a small Tupperware container for transport from the vivarium to the laboratory. Handle this box with a gloved hand.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mix 1 part feces with 3 parts activated charcoal and 1 part DI water in a 1-liter plastic beaker. Estimate relative volumes feces and charcoal by eye.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mix thoroughly with a tongue depressor.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Add more water if necessary. Charcoal grains should appear moist, and uniformly coated with fecal slurry, but there should not be excess water apparent in the mixture.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Line several 100 mm Petri dishes with Whatman #1 filter paper circles (see <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). Moisten these to the point of glistening with DI water.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Transfer fecal charcoal mixture to each dish and cover (see <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). Dishes should be full, but the mixture should not touch the lid. Do not seal the plates.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="3in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject></listitem>
<listitem><para>Incubate at predetermined temperature (22-27&#x000B0;C, depending on experimental procedures) at ~75% R.H. This humidity may be achieved by placing dishes on a Styrofoam flat floating in approximately 0.5 in. of water in a Tupperware crisper box.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Some common incubation protocols and their results are given in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>.</para>
<sidebar><note>
<title>Note</title>
<para>Feces from infected gerbils may be collected by temporarily transferring the animals to cages in which normal bedding has been replaced by a liner of moist cardboard surmounted by a wire mesh platform suspended approximately 1 cm. above the substratum. Fecal pellets fall through the wire mesh onto the most cardboard, which prevents them from desiccating. We typically place gerbils in the late afternoon and transfer them back to conventional cages early the following morning. Fecal pellets from several animals may be pooled and dispersed on activated charcoal and cultured as described for canine feces. Alternatively, single or small numbers of fecal pellets, as from individual animals, may be cultured in watch glasses as described (<link linkend="bib44">Viney et al., 1992</link><!--: PMID 1469259-->).</para>
</note></sidebar></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_3">
<title>Protocol 2. Recovery of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> from charcoal coprocultures: the Baermann funnel technique</title>
<para>The Baermann funnel is commonly used to isolate small parasitic nematodes from solid materials such as feces, soil or animal tissue. It exploits the tendency of these worms to migrate from a solid into a surrounding liquid medium when stimulated by slightly elevated temperature and then to settle to the substratum (<link linkend="bib6">Bowman, 1995</link>). By using an ordinary laboratory funnel to contain the incubating sample, and taking some simple filtration measures, it is possible to collect and concentrate large numbers of worms in small volumes of medium, relatively free of fecal debris.</para>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>Assemble the Baermann funnel apparatus as shown in <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>. We find that Tygon plastic food delivery tubing (0.5 inch inside diameter, Fisher Scientific Cat. No. 14-169-21D) because it is transparent, has the advantage of allowing visual detection of substantial numbers of worms accumulating at the bottom of the apparatus, giving some indication of parasite yield prior to harvest. The disadvantage of Tygon tubing of this size is that due to its thick walls, a very tight closure using a thumbscrew operated clamp is required to achieve a watertight seal. The lid from a 150 mm disposable plastic Petri dish fits well over the top of the funnel. When properly cleaned between procedures, all of these components may be reused many times.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Line the sample basket, basically a sieve consisting of a Lucite ring with coarse nylon mesh (bridal netting, available at fabric stores) attached with cement, with two layers of laboratory tissue (see <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). A pair of Kimwipes oriented at 90&#x000B0; angles works well for this purpose. A somewhat cruder, but no less effective sample basket can be made by cutting the bottoms from two half pint-sized plastic food containers and nesting one tightly inside the other with a single layer of bridal netting between.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Select one or two charcoal coprocultures of the desired age based on <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Use a tongue depressor to place the contents of the plate(s) including the filter paper liners on top of the Kimwipes lining the sample basket.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Carefully place the sample basket with culture contents into the funnel.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Close the tubing clamp tightly and then gently pour tap water at 43&#x000B0;C down the side of the funnel until the level rises just above the culture contents. Use the tongue depressor to gently submerge the edges of the tissue liner into the water. Note: The roughly 600&#x02013;800 ml of tap water needed may be warmed to 43&#x000B0;C in a microwave oven or achieved by mixing hot and cold water at the tap.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="3.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject></listitem>
<listitem><para>Cover the funnel with the Petri dish lid and incubate for 1-3 hours. As a safety measure in the event of leakage, we place a one-liter plastic beaker underneath each funnel. To avoid hypoxic stress to the isolated parasites we harvest and plate the proceeds of Baermann funnels at one-hour intervals.</para>
<sidebar><note>
<title>Note</title>
<para>Different life stages of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> migrate in the Baermann funnel at different rates. Free-living adults and iL3 migrate relatively rapidly, and substantial yields may be obtained at the first hourly harvest, and virtually all viable individuals will have collected in the funnel stem within two hours. First stage larvae migrate less rapidly, and maximal yields will require three hours&apos; incubation.</para></note></sidebar></listitem>
<listitem><para>Harvest the worms accumulated in the funnel stem by carefully loosening the thumbscrew of the tubing clamp and releasing 15-20 ml of fluid into a 50 ml conical centrifuge tube. If desired, the yield may be determined by transferring 20&#x003BC;l aliquots of the collected worm suspension onto a microscope slide, counting under the dissecting microscope. The total number of parasites is then calculated based on the volume of the suspension, which can be approximated from the graduations on the centrifuge tube). Note that <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> settle rapidly, and the worms must be re-suspended prior to taking each aliquot.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Allow the worms to sediment at 1 x g for approximately 15 min; collect with a long Pasteur pipet, and transfer to an appropriate receptacle. For worms to be used in active cultures, transfer the sedimented with approximately 100&#x003BC;l of fluid to a standard NGM agar plate spread with <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP50;class=Strain" role="_blank">OP50</ulink> (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html" role="_blank">Maintenance of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>; <link linkend="bib25">Lewis and Fleming, 1995</link><!--: PMID 8531730-->), and place the plate on the bench with its lid ajar for drying. Drying in a laminar flow hood accelerates this process and decreases exposure to airborne contaminants.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_4">
<title>Small-scale cultures for analysis</title>
<para>For applications requiring observation and analysis of smaller populations of worms, such as screening of phenotypes or manual selection of genetic transformants, the free-living stages of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> may be cultured on standard NGM/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP50;class=Strain" role="_blank">OP50</ulink> plates (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html" role="_blank">Maintenance of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>; <link linkend="bib25">Lewis and Fleming, 1995</link><!--: PMID 8531730-->). Since the worms used to inoculate such cultures will be derived from the septic environment of a coproculture, significant carryover of fecal bacteria onto the NGM/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP50;class=Strain" role="_blank">OP50</ulink> plate is likely. Contamination due to bacteria and fungi external to the worms may be minimized, but not eliminated by either of two approaches: allowing the worms to migrate through a semi-solid matrix of low gelling temperature agar (see <link linkend="sec4_5">Protocol 3</link>) or subjecting them to density gradient centrifugation (see <link linkend="sec4_6">Protocol 4</link>). Since the worms carry fecal bacteria within their guts, neither of these procedures will result in a sterile preparation. To date we have been unscuccessful at adapting the standard alkaline sodium hypochlorite technique used for axenization of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> eggs (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html" role="_blank">Maintenance of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>; <link linkend="bib25">Lewis and Fleming, 1995</link><!--: PMID 8531730-->) to yield viable <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> eggs in quantity.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_5">
<title>Protocol 3. Surface decontamination of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> by migration through low melting point agarose</title>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>Prepare 10 ml of 3% low melting point agarose (Sigma Alderich Cat. No. A9414) in BU saline (<link linkend="bib16">Hawdon and Schad, 1991</link>). Boil in the microwave oven for 30-40 sec on high power.</para>
<para>BU saline (1 liter):</para>
<simplelist columns="2" type="horiz">
<member>50 mM Na<subscript>2</subscript>HPO<subscript>4</subscript></member><member>7.098 g</member>
<member>22 mM KH<subscript>2</subscript>PO<subscript>4</subscript></member><member>2.99 g</member>
<member>70 mM NaCl</member><member>4.09 g</member>
<member>H<subscript>2</subscript>O</member><member>to 1 liter</member>
</simplelist></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mix molten agarose thoroughly and place in a 37&#x000B0;C water bath until temperature equilibrates.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Similarly, place a concentrated suspension of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> to be purified (e.g., the sediment from a Baermann funnel isolation reduced to 2-3 ml volume) as well as a 20 ml aliquot of BU saline into the 37&#x000B0;C water bath to equilibrate.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Thoroughly mix 1 volume of low melting point agarose at 37&#x000B0;C with 2 volumes of concentrated parasite suspension to give a 1:3 dilution to a final concentration of 1% low melting point agarose. Note: since low melting point agarose solidifies rapidly at temperatures below 37&#x000B0;C, we typically perform this operation with tubes in the water bath.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Place a 100 mm Petri dish(s) on ice, and carefully pipet 5 ml of parasite suspension in 1% agarose into the center of the plate. Try to form bead of agarose that does not contact the sides of the plate. To facilitate this step, a level cooling platform may be made by embedding an inverted aluminum block insert from a laboratory dry bath in crushed ice.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Allow the dish with agar bead to rest on ice for a few minutes until completely solidified.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Add 10&#x02013;20 ml of warmed BU saline to the plate with solidified agar. Cover the plate and incubate at 37&#x000B0;C for 30 min. Viable worms should migrate from the agar matrix into the surrounding medium during this period.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Without disturbing the solid agar bead, pipet the liquid medium from the incubated plate and transfer to a 15 ml conical centrifuge tube. Worms may be allowed to sediment by gravity (approx. 15 min) or by centrifugation at 500 rpm for 5 min.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_6">
<title>Protocol 4. Surface decontamination of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> by density gradient centrifugation</title>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>Wash worms two times in M9 buffer</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>During final wash spin, add 10 ml of 40% Percoll solution to a 15 ml conical centrifuge tube.</para>
<para>40% Percoll solution 100 ml:</para>
<simplelist columns="2" type="horiz">
<member>Percoll</member><member>40 ml</member>
<member>HEPES</member><member>0.596 g (25mM)</member>
<member>Penicillin/Streptomycin stock soln.*</member><member>1 ml</member>
<member>H<subscript>2</subscript>O</member><member>To 100 ml</member>
</simplelist>
<para>*10,000 U/ml Penicillin, 10 mg/ml Streptomycin</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Remove supernatant from washed worm pellet and re-suspend worms in the residual volume.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Use a Pasteur pipet to carefully layer the suspended pellet onto the Percoll solution.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Spin at 1000 rpm for 2 min. Repeat spin as necessary to pellet the worms. Because of their ability to swim upwards, iL3 may require more than one spin.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Remove Percoll supernatant by aspiration.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Subject worm pellet to two washes with M9 buffer.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Transfer worms in final wash pellet to a clean <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP50;class=Strain" role="_blank">OP50</ulink> plate.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Transgenesis</title>
<sect2 id="sec5_1">
<title>Gonadal microinjection of DNA constructs</title>
<para>The size, transparency and body plan of a free-living <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> female is so similar to that of a <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> hermaphrodite that published techniques for delivery of DNA constructs into <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> by gonadal microinjection (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transformationmicroinjection/transformationmicroinjection.html" role="_blank">Transformation and microinjection</ulink>; <link linkend="bib28">Mello and Fire, 1995</link><!--: PMID 8531738-->) may be used for this parasite virtually without modification (<link linkend="bib26">Li et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16500658-->; <link linkend="bib27">Lok and Massey, 2002</link><!--: PMID 11814580-->). Persons experienced with gonadal microinjection of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> will succeed almost immediately with <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> but will notice two relatively minor differences in the two worms. First, the reproductive tracts of free-living <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> females and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> hermaphrodites are highly similar, both being in the form of a double recurved tube with the vulva placed at mid-body. However, as pictured in <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>, the syncytial ovary of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis>, corresponding to the usual point of injection in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, is generally narrower and less transparent than that of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, and individual oocyte nuclei are less visible by DIC microscopy. Second, due perhaps to relative fragility of its cuticle or to a higher internal hydrostatic pressure, <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> free-living females are somewhat more susceptible than <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to injury by injection of an excessive fluid volume or by large or improperly placed needles. The most frequent manifestation of this is prolapse of the gonad from the injection wound. This problem may be overcome by using needles with an outside tip diameter no greater than 5&#x003BC;m and by keeping the injection pressure under 20 pounds per square inch.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="3.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 4</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5_2">
<title>Vector constructs: necessity of endogenous 5<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> and 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> regulatory elements for transgene expression in <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis></title>
<para>Early attempts to transform <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> involved a series of constructs in which various <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> promoters were fused to the coding sequence of <emphasis>gfp</emphasis> in standard <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> vectors from the vector kit maintained previously by A. Fire and colleagues (Stanford University). These constructs incorporated either of two commonly used <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> UTRs, that of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-54;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis> or of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-858;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-858</ulink></emphasis>. Invariably, transgene constructs incorporating <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> UTRs were expressed in apparently unregulated fashion in degenerating embryos of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> and never in normally developing F1 larvae (<link linkend="bib26">Li et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16500658-->; <link linkend="bib27">Lok and Massey, 2002</link><!--: PMID 11814580-->). Regulated, cell- and tissue-specific transgene expression was not achieved until both 5<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> and 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> regulatory sequences derived from the parasite were incorporated. For example, as with all such constructs, <emphasis>gfp</emphasis> expression under the control of the <emphasis>S. stercoralis era-1</emphasis> promoter in a standard <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> vector background (pPD 95.81) is always of the unregulated type described above. In contrast to this, substitution of the endogenous <emphasis>Ss era-1</emphasis> 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> UTR for the <emphasis>C. elegans <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-54;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis> 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> UTR in the original vector is sufficient to bring about tissue-specific expression in normally developing F1 larvae (<link linkend="bib26">Li et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16500658-->). Sequence comparison reveals that the endogenous <emphasis>Ss era-1</emphasis> 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> UTR, which gives regulated expression, contains three canonical polyadenylation signals whereas the previously used <emphasis>C. elegans <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-54;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis> element, which gives unregulated expression, contains only one (<link linkend="bib26">Li et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16500658-->). This signal alone may be insufficient to properly terminate message transcription in <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis>. The <emphasis>Ss era-1</emphasis> 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> UTR is also sufficient to give regulated expression of gene constructs incorporating other <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> promoters (see <link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>). In combination with this element, the promoter from the cellular actin gene <emphasis>Ss <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=act-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">act-2</ulink></emphasis> gives expression primarily in body wall muscle of F1 larvae while that of the G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> protein-encoding gene <emphasis>Ss <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpa-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpa-3</ulink></emphasis> gives a pattern of expression in sensory neurons remarkably similar to that of its <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog (<link linkend="bib22">Jansen et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 0010192394-->). Our group has developed a "toolkit" of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> vectors for distribution, which are designed to accept promoters in all reading frames upstream of the <emphasis>gfp</emphasis>S65C coding sequence with artificial introns and the <emphasis>Ss era-1</emphasis> 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> UTR. This toolkit is available from the author upon request.</para>
<table id="table2" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="100%">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 2. Tissue- and cell-specific expression of three promoter:gfp fusion constructs incorporating the</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Ss era-1</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> UTR in F1 transformant larvae of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">S. stercoralis</emphasis>.</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colname="c1" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c2" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c3" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c4" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c5" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Vector</entry>
<entry>Promoter</entry>
<entry>Reporter</entry>
<entry>3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> UTR</entry>
<entry>Expression pattern</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>pPV230.13</entry>
<entry><emphasis>Ss era-1</emphasis></entry>
<entry morerows="2"><emphasis>gfp</emphasis>S65C</entry>
<entry morerows="2"><emphasis>Ss era-1</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Intestinal cells</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>pAJ08</entry>
<entry><emphasis>Ss <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=act-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">act-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>Body wall muscle</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>pAJ09</entry>
<entry><emphasis>Ss <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpa-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpa-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>8 amphidial, 2 phasmidial neurons</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5_3">
<title>Cultivation of F1 transformants and use of markers for screening</title>
<para>For experiments involving smaller numbers of worms, we typically cultivate microinjected free-living female worms along with 1-2 males per female, and their F1 progeny on standard NGM agar plates spread with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP50;class=Strain" role="_blank">OP50</ulink> bacteria. We have been able to rear isolated P0 transformant females (plus males) and their broods in this manner (<link linkend="bib26">Li et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16500658-->) as well as pools of up to 30 transformant females and an equal number of males. Carryover of fecal bacteria to the NGM/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP50;class=Strain" role="_blank">OP50</ulink> plates may be problematic and can be minimized by washing free-living adults from Baermann isolations with two changes of M9 buffer.</para>
<para>For larger cohorts of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P0;class=Cell" role="_blank">P0</ulink> transformants (100-200 individuals), as would be required for host passage of transgenics, we temporarily pool females as they are microinjected, along with a roughly equal number of males, on NGM/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP50;class=Strain" role="_blank">OP50</ulink> plates. At the end of a day&apos;s injection session, microinjected females and males are washed from the plate with a small volume of M9 buffer and transferred as a pool to a charcoal coproculture dish (see <link linkend="sec4_2_3">section 4.2.3</link>) made with feces from a non-infected dog. These plates are incubated at 22&#x000B0;C for 5-6 days to allow development to the iL3, which are collected by the Baermann funnel protocol (see <link linkend="sec4_3">section 4.3</link>).</para>
<para>Behavioral or selectable transformation markers have not been developed as yet for <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis>. However, <emphasis>gfp</emphasis> expression under the control of strong promoters such as that of <emphasis>Ss <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=act-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">act-2</ulink></emphasis> constitutes a workable visual marker for transformation. <emphasis>Ss act-2p::gfp</emphasis> transformants are easily hand-selected under a stereomicroscope equipped with epifluorescence.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5_4">
<title>Establishment of transgenic lines through host passage</title>
<para>Although reliable protocols for derivation of stable transgenic lines of <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> are not yet in hand, we have used experimental infections in gerbils to accomplish the following required steps in this process. First, we have shown that relatively small cohorts of transgenic <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> (i.e., inocula containing 100-200 F1 transformant iL3) can establish patent infections in gerbils and that construct DNA can be maintained in transgenic populations through two host passages with intervening free-living generations in culture to the F5 generation (<link linkend="bib26">Li et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16500658-->). This initial finding was made with a non-expressed construct, the <emphasis>C. elegans-</emphasis>based pTG96_2, which contains the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sur-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">sur-5</ulink></emphasis> promoter fused to <emphasis>gfp</emphasis> and the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-54;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis> 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> UTR (<link linkend="bib14">Gu et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 0009671465-->), and so host passages had to be carried out without selection. More recent attempts to effect host passage of F1 larvae showing regulated expression of the <emphasis>Strongyloides</emphasis>-based <emphasis>Ss <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=act-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">act-2</ulink></emphasis>p::gfp construct, pAJ08, have yielded <emphasis>gfp</emphasis>-expressing parasitic females. However no <emphasis>gfp</emphasis>-expressing individuals have been observed among the progeny of these transgenic parasitic females and, thus, we have not yet succeeded in establishing a stable <emphasis>gfp</emphasis>-expressing line.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5_5">
<title>Biolistic DNA transfer</title>
<para>The tendency of gonadal microinjection to result in the incorporation of transgenes into multi-copy episomal arrays has led to some interest in biolistic DNA transfer as an alternate method of gene delivery facilitating the isolation of stable lines of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> with low-copy chromosomal integrations or homologous gene replacements. Microparticle bombardment has also been used for transient transfection of the adult filariae such as <emphasis>Litomosoides carinii</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib21">Jackstadt et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10551368-->) and <emphasis>Brugia malayi</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib17">Higazi et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12054699-->). One of the major impediments to the use of biolistics for heritable transgenesis in parasitic nematodes is the low frequency of germline transformation by this method relative to the number of adult or L4 parasites that may be practicably obtained. The most efficient systems for biolistic transformation of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> allow derivation of one stable transformant line per 20,000 individuals bombarded, and typical bombardments involve 10<superscript>4</superscript>-10<superscript>5</superscript> animals (<link linkend="bib34">Praitis et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11238406-->). The ease of large-scale <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> culture and the availability of powerful, selectable co-transformation markers such as the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-119;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-119</ulink></emphasis> mutant rescue make it relatively straightforward to amass the numbers of worms required for bombardment and to select integrated lines (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transformationmicroinjection/transformationmicroinjection.html" role="_blank">Transformation and microinjection</ulink>). It has been possible for us to prepare cohorts of 5-7 x 10<superscript>4</superscript> free-living <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> adults using the fecal output of two infected dogs and scaled up versions of the charcoal coproculture and Baermann isolation techniques described above (see <link linkend="sec4_2">Protocols 1</link> and <link linkend="sec4_3">2</link>). Initial problems with overgrowth of these large cultures by fecal bacteria can be overcome using the percoll gradient method (see <link linkend="sec4_6">Protocol 4</link>) to decontaminate the worms. However, using the PDS/1000 He bombardment apparatus we have been unable, thus far, to detect F1 transformants expressing the <emphasis>Ss <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=act-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">act-2</ulink></emphasis>p::gfp construct, pAJ08 (<link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>), which has proven so effective in producing F1 transformants by microinjection. A selectable transformation marker, possibly one encoding resistance to an anthelmintic drug, would greatly facilitate the detection of transformants in large populations of bombarded <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis>, and our future efforts in this area will concentrate on this approach.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Neuronal ablation</title>
<sect2 id="sec6_1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>Microsurgical ablation of cells and observation of resulting developmental and behavioral deficits is a standard approach to the study of cell function in whole organisms. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>&apos; transparent cuticle and the fact that few of its cells are strictly required for survival make microlaser ablation, particularly of neurons, an important part of the methodological repertoire for this model organism (<link linkend="bib4">Bargmann and Avery, 1995</link><!--: PMID 8531727-->). The power of this method was recently demonstrated in the elucidation of a complete &#x0201C;.....behavioral circuit for navigation in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, from sensory input to motor output...&#x0201D; (<link linkend="bib13">Gray et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15689400-->). As has been the case for microinjection of transgene DNA, we have been able to exploit morphological similarities between <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> to adapt established techniques for laser cell killing from the model organism to the parasite and have used this method to investigate the neuronal control of various behaviors and developmental events associated with the infective process (<link linkend="bib3">Ashton et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17067579-->). The method for cell ablation in <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> detailed in <link linkend="sec6_2">Protocol 5</link> below is a modification of that reported for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib4">Bargmann and Avery, 1995</link><!--: PMID 8531727-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6_2">
<title>Protocol 5. Cell ablation by laser microsurgery</title>
<sect3 id="sec6_2_1">
<title>Mounting <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> for light microscopy</title>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>Prepare 20 ml of 1.5% low gelling temperature (low melting point) agarose (Type 1-A, Sigma Aldrich Chemical Co., St. Louis, Missouri) in BU saline (see Section 4.5, <link linkend="sec4_5">Protocol 3</link>) and divide into 2 ml. aliquots. These may be stored in the refrigerator in sterile snap-cap tubes.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Melt one aliquot of 1.5 low melting point agarose; add 6&#x003BC;l of the anesthetic 1-phenoxy 2-propanol (Janssen Chemica, Geel, Belgium), and vortex.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Use molten agarose with anesthetic to prepare mounting pads on microscope slides, using one layer of laboratory tape to gauge pad thickness, as described (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_intromethodscellbiology/intromethodscellbiology.html" role="_blank">Methods in cell biology</ulink>; <link linkend="bib4">Bargmann and Avery, 1995</link><!--: PMID 8531727-->)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Use a finely drawn capillary tube to transfer post-parasitic first-stage larvae, 5-8 per slide, to the anesthetic pad. These larvae are should be freshly isolated from feces or charcoal coproculture as described in <link linkend="sec4_2">4.2</link>. The 1-2&#x003BC;l of fluid transferred with the larvae will allow the worms to undulate a few times before coming to rest on the pad, thereby orienting themselves laterally.</para>
<sidebar><note>
<title>Note</title>
<para>We use 1-phenoxy 2-propanol as an anesthetic because we have found that the standard one for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, 25 mM sodium azide, does not immobilize <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> sufficiently for close observation, imaging or cell ablation. We have recently found that 10-20 mM levamisole is also an effective anesthetic for <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis>. However we have some concern that parasites exposed to this drug appear somewhat flattened when mounted on pads, possibly reflecting loss of tone in body wall muscles.</para>
</note></sidebar></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec6_2_2">
<title>Laser cell ablation</title>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>View anesthetized larvae at 1000X magnification by differential interference contrast microscopy and identify the cell bodies, which should be clearly visible at this magnification (see <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>), by comparison to a published map of the cell bodies of the L1. (<link linkend="bib2">Ashton et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9714195-->).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 5</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject></listitem>
<listitem><para>Ablate the target cell in the upper focal plane using 50-60 pulses of the laser. Amphidial neurons are paired and bilateral. If the worms are oriented laterally, it should be possible to refocus the microscope and laser directly downward through the organism to the cell body of the underlying member of the neuron pair for ablation.</para>
<sidebar><note>
<title>Note</title>
<para>Following the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> protocol of Bargmann and Avery (1996) we use a Coumarin 440 dye laser (Fryer &amp; Co., Chicago, Illinois) pumped with a nitrogen laser (Laser Sciences, Inc., Newton Massachusetts). Outputs of the nitrogen and dye lasers are 115&#x003BC;J and 2&#x003BC;J of energy respectively. A 0.4% neutral density filter above the oil immersion objective in the light path reduces the laser energy to 0.5 &#x003BC;J.</para>
</note></sidebar></listitem>
<listitem><para>Following ablation, apply a lethal laser burst to kill any unoperated larvae. This will prevent their being confused with successfully operated worms later in the experiment.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Carefully transfer operated larvae from the anesthetic pad to a dish containing 1.5 ml of PBS for recovery. Once the operated worms resume normal motility, transfer them via micropipet to the center well of a 15 X 60 mm organ culture dish containing 1 ml of 1% NGM agar to which a small patch of canine fecal solids (approximately 1 mm diameter) has been applied with the tip of a wooden applicator stick.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Depending on the phenotype of interest, worms may be observed immediately or cultured to the appropriate stage. Our group&apos;s interest is primarily in neuronal control of switching between homogonic and heterogonic developmental alternatives and of resumption of development by iL3, so we typically screen larvae for phenotypes following incubation for 24-30 hr at 20&#x000B0; C.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>Future prospects</title>
<sect2 id="sec7_1">
<title>Transgenesis</title>
<para>The recent successes with transgenesis in strongyloidoid parasites (<link linkend="bib12">Grant et al., 2006b</link><!--: PMID 16500659-->; <link linkend="bib26">Li et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16500658-->) are highly encouraging. However, in the cases of both <emphasis>Strongyloides</emphasis> and <emphasis>Parastrongyloides</emphasis>, some key components of a practical transgenesis system have yet to be identified. We have succeeded in designing a number of reporter constructs <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> based upon cell- and tissue-specific promoters linked to the <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> reporters <emphasis>gfp</emphasis> and <emphasis>mrfp</emphasis>. However, it remains for us to establish any of these in a stable transformant line through host passage, and much of our current effort is directed toward this goal. By contrast, stable transgenic lines of <emphasis>P. trichosuri</emphasis> expressing constructs incorporating the (<symbol role="symbolfont">&beta;</symbol>-GAL reporter system have been established (<link linkend="bib12">Grant et al., 2006b</link><!--: PMID 16500659-->), but, to date, constructs that will express <emphasis>gfp</emphasis> or other <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> reporters have not been reported for this parasite.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec7_2">
<title>Targeted gene silencing</title>
<para>The utility of RNA interference (RNAi) as a method of investigating gene function in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is well substantiated (<link linkend="bib8">Fire et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 0009486653-->; <link linkend="bib23">Johnson et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15994029-->; <link linkend="bib39">Tabara et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 0009841401-->; <link linkend="bib40">Tavernarakis et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10655066-->; <link linkend="bib41">Timmons et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11223248-->). Robust RNAi effects following natural uptake or electroporation of dsRNA have been observed in the filariae (<link linkend="bib1">Aboobaker and Blaxter, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12798505-->; <link linkend="bib9">Ford et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16186127-->; <link linkend="bib15">Hashmi et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14630920-->) and the trichostrongyles (<link linkend="bib19">Hussein et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12076773-->; <link linkend="bib20">Issa et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16023650-->), parasites occupying Clades III and V, respectively, in the contemporary nematode phylogeny (<link linkend="bib5">Blaxter et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9510248-->). By contrast, despite concerted efforts, none of the laboratories investigating <emphasis>Strongyloides</emphasis> or <emphasis>Parastrongyloides</emphasis>, members of nematode Clade IV, have been able to demonstrate clear RNAi effects in these parasites following application of dsRNA in various configurations via the common routes of administration. Our own efforts have shown a significant knock down of<emphasis></emphasis> mRNA encoding the <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> homolog of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-54;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis> in the progeny of free-living females microinjected with homologous dsRNA. However, whereas <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-54;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-54</ulink></emphasis> shows a strong paralyzed RNAi phenotype in <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> no such phenotype has been seen in <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis>. Among planned approaches to address this problem in the future are combinatorial experiments in which we will attempt to enhance RNAi effects in <emphasis>S. stercoralis</emphasis> by knocking down mRNAs encoding putative orthologs of molecules such as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LIN-53;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-53</ulink>, which modulate RNAi effects in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, simultaneously with targets of interest.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec7_3">
<title>Forward genetics</title>
<para>The extensive body of work by Viney and co-workers on <emphasis>S. ratti</emphasis> demonstrates that limited forward genetic approaches may be feasible with the strongyloidoid parasites. For example, they have shown that clonal populations, varying in key developmental traits, may be selected and maintained through host passage, that genetic exchange occurs during mating in the free-living generation (<link linkend="bib45">Viney et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID 8108454-->) and that free living populations may be chemically mutagenized, screened for phenotypes of interest and selected for relevant mutations (<link linkend="bib43">Viney et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12464413-->). The ability of <emphasis>P. trichosuri</emphasis> to undergo multiple free-living generations in culture make it an attractive subject with which to build upon these advancements for further development of a forward genetic system in a parasitic nematode (<link linkend="bib11">Grant et al., 2006a</link><!--: PMID 16500655-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<?newpage?>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>Afterword</title>
<para>It is hoped that in reading this chapter and the one on the biology of <emphasis>Strongyloides</emphasis> spp. (Viney and Lok, 2007), <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> researchers will be struck by the many similarities between these parasites and their model organism and by the ease with which standard <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> techniques may be adapted to <emphasis>Strongyloides</emphasis> spp. Nevertheless, some aspects of the methodology outlined here, particularly those dealing with biosafety and maintenance of infected animal hosts, may seem daunting. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community should be re-assured that once an infection is established in laboratory animals, and a straightforward set of handling protocols is in place, all aspects of this methodology are eminently practical and feasible. As the specialty of laboratory animal medicine expands, institutional vivaria are increasingly staffed by attending veterinarians who can provide assistance with technical aspects of maintaining parasite cultures in dogs and rodents. Furthermore, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> researchers are frequently located in biomedical institutions that also include parasitologists. In these cases especially, productive collaborations may be formed that facilitate both the technical aspects of the research and the application of basic science.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec9">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<para>The approaches detailed in this chapter were developed through fruitful collaborations and exchange of ideas with Gerhard Schad, Tom Nolan Ariel Junio and Meera Sundaram at Penn, Mark Viney at the University of Bristol and Warwick Grant at AgResearch, Ltd., New Zealand. The generosity of all these individuals in sharing ideas, materials and methods is gratefully acknowledged. Work in the author&apos;s laboratory was supported by grants from NIH (AI50688, AI22662 and RR02512) and the Ellison Medical Foundation (ID-IA-0037-02).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>References</title>
&WMStrong_Refs;
<para/>
</sect1>
</article>