<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'neurotransGprotein_fig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'neurotransGprotein_fig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'neurotransGprotein_fig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'neurotransGprotein_fig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'neurotransGprotein_fig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY movie1 SYSTEM 'neurotransGprotein_movie1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'neurotransGprotein_fig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'neurotransGprotein_fig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'neurotransGprotein_fig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'neurotransGprotein_fig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'neurotransGprotein_fig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY movie1legend SYSTEM 'neurotransGprotein_movie1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY neurotransGprotein_ref SYSTEM 'neurotransGprotein_ref.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'httxsp://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="neurotransGprotein">
<articleinfo>
<title>Neurotransmitter signaling through heterotrimeric G proteins: insights from studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis><footnote><para>Edited by Iva Greenwald Last revised February 4, 2016. Published in its final form December 11, 2018. This chapter should be cited as: Koelle M.R. Neurotransmitter signaling through heterotrimeric G proteins: insights from studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. (December 11, 2018), <emphasis role="italic">WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.75.2, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2016 Michael R. Koelle. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para></footnote></title>
<author><othername>Michael R. Koelle<superscript><emphasis role="italic">&sect;</emphasis></superscript><remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Email: <ulink url="mailto:michael.koelle@yale.edu">michael.koelle@yale.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></othername>
<affiliation><orgname>Department of Molecular Biophysics &amp; Biochemistry, Yale University, New Haven CT 06520 USA</orgname></affiliation>
</author></articleinfo>
<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para>Neurotransmitters signal via G protein coupled receptors (GPCRs) to modulate activity of neurons and muscles. <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has &sim;150 G protein coupled neuropeptide receptor homologs and 28 additional GPCRs for small-molecule neurotransmitters. Genetic studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> demonstrate that neurotransmitters diffuse far from their release sites to activate GPCRs on distant cells. Individual receptor types are expressed on limited numbers of cells and thus can provide very specific regulation of an individual neural circuit and behavior. G protein coupled neurotransmitter receptors signal principally via the three types of heterotrimeric G proteins defined by the G alpha subunits G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript>. Each of these G alpha proteins is found in all neurons plus some muscles. G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling inhibit and activate neurotransmitter release, respectively. G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling, like G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling, promotes neurotransmitter release. Many details of the signaling mechanisms downstream of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> have been delineated and are consistent with those of their mammalian orthologs. The details of the signaling mechanism downstream of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> remain a mystery. Forward genetic screens in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> have identified new molecular components of neural G protein signaling mechanisms, including Regulators of G protein Signaling (RGS proteins) that inhibit signaling, a new G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> effector (the Trio RhoGEF domain), and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> protein that is required for neuronal G&alpha; signaling. A model is presented in which G proteins sum up the variety of neuromodulator signals that impinge on a neuron to calculate its appropriate output level.</para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>The nervous system functions through the use of neurotransmitters that act as chemical signals between cells. Small-molecule neurotransmitters such as acetylcholine, glutamate, and GABA (gamma aminobutyric acid) are released from vesicles clustered at synapses. Neuropeptides (secreted proteins of &lt;50 amino acids) are released at synaptic and non-synaptic sites from a different class of vesicles, known as dense-core vesicles for their appearance in the electron microscope (<link linkend="bib153">Merighi et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21385606-->). Certain small-molecule neurotransmitters such as serotonin can be released from either class of vesicle. All these types of neurotransmitters act on neurons and muscles to generate dynamic patterns of activity that constitute thoughts and behaviors. A principal objective in neuroscience is to understand the molecular mechanisms by which neurons and muscles respond to neurotransmitters. This objective is important to advance our basic science understanding of the brain, but also is of great medical significance since many pharmaceuticals used to treat psychiatric disorders act by mimicking, antagonizing, or altering the levels of naturally-occurring neurotransmitters (<link linkend="bib46">Conn and Roth, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18216778-->), and drugs of abuse also act by altering neurotransmitter signaling (<link linkend="bib109">Joffe et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 24999377-->).</para>
<sect2 id="sec1.1">
<title>Neurotransmitters signal by gating ion channels and by activating G protein coupled receptors</title>
<para>Neurotransmitters signal via two distinct classes of receptors, known within the neuroscience field as ionotropic and metabotropic receptors. Ionotropic receptors are neurotransmitter-gated ion channels, and most small-molecule neurotransmitters each have a number of such receptors (<link linkend="bib141">Lemoine et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22988962-->). Binding of neurotransmitter to an ionotropic receptor favors channel opening, and communication between neurons using ionotropic receptors can occur in less than a millisecond (<link linkend="bib206">Sabatini and Regehr, 1996</link><!--:PMID 8906792-->). Metabotropic receptors are known outside the neuroscience field as G protein coupled receptors (GPCRs) because they activate intracellular signaling proteins called heterotrimeric G proteins. All small-molecule neurotransmitters have G protein coupled receptors, as do most neuropeptides (<link linkend="bib83">Hall, 2004</link>; <!--:PMID 15125891--> <link linkend="bib12">Beaulieu and Gainetdinov, 2011</link><!--:PMID 21303898-->; <link linkend="bib190">Pytliak et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22530579-->; <link linkend="bib100">Hoyer and Bartfai, 2012</link><!--:PMID 23161624-->; <link linkend="bib251">Vaidya et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 22530579-->; <link linkend="bib132">Kruse et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 24903776-->). An individual small-molecule neurotransmitter might have up to a dozen different GPCRs. There are over 100 neuropeptide genes in both humans and <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans,</emphasis> and each organism also has about an equal number of GPCRs that are likely to be neuropeptide receptors, as they are similar to the few G protein coupled neuropeptide receptors that have been characterized so far (<link linkend="bib142">Li and Kim, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18819171-->; <link linkend="bib143">Li and Kim, 2010</link><!--:PMID 21189676-->; <link linkend="bib68">Frooninckx et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23267347-->; <link linkend="bib100">Hoyer and Bartfai, 2012</link><!--:PMID 23161624-->). Binding of a neurotransmitter to a GPCR, as opposed to an ionotropic receptor, leads to slower and longer lasting effects. For example, GCPR signaling can involve biochemical amplification of a signal (e.g., production of a pool of second messenger) that is much slower than the rapid voltage changes induced by opening ion channels, and GPCR signaling can result in changes to the transcriptional program and structure of a neuron that last days or longer (<link linkend="bib114">Kandel, 2004</link><!--:PMID 16134023-->). Whereas ionotropic receptors mediate signaling underlying such prosaic neural functions as the knee-jerk response, GPCRs mediate signaling underlying more poetical functions of the brain, such as feelings of pleasure and love that result from dopamine and oxytocin (<link linkend="bib147">Love, 2014</link><!--:PMID 23850525-->), the psychedelic effects of hallucinogens (<link linkend="bib65">Fantegrossi et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 17977517-->), and the regulation of mood by serotonin (<link linkend="bib58">Donaldson et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23385115-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec1.2">
<title><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> as a model system for studies of neural signaling</title>
<para>This review focuses on insights into the molecular mechanisms and biological functions of neurotransmitter signaling through GPCRs that arise from studies in the model organism <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. But why study neurotransmitter signaling in the worm? Signaling through ionotropic receptors has already been studied in a sophisticated manner in other species using electrophysiological techniques to analyze ion channel activity. Such electrophysiological studies have often used model organisms such as slug, squid, leech, or crab that have large neurons easily accessible to electrodes. GPCRs activate intracellular signaling pathways that can have indirect effects on ion channel activity, and electrophysiological studies in the same model organisms have given important insights into how GPCR signaling modulates the function of neural circuits (<link linkend="bib7">Bailey and Kandel, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18394474-->; <link linkend="bib148">Marder, 2012</link><!--:PMID 23040802-->). However, methods for studying intracellular signaling pathways have been most highly developed outside of the neuroscience field, with the greatest successes coming from applying a combination of biochemistry and genetics, techniques not easily applied in the model organisms suited to electrophysiology. A remarkable body of biochemical studies of signaling by heterotrimeric G proteins, mostly in non-neuronal mammalian cells, has been in progress for decades and has resulted in many Nobel prizes (<link linkend="bib47">Cori and Cori, 1947</link>; <link linkend="bib239">Sutherland, 1971</link>; <link linkend="bib131">Krebs, 1992</link>; <link linkend="bib67">Fischer 1992</link>; <link linkend="bib73">Gilman 1994</link>; <link linkend="bib201">Rodbell 1994</link>; <link linkend="bib126">Kobilka, 2013</link><!--:PMID 23650120-->; <link linkend="bib139">Lefkowitz 2013</link><!--:PMID 23650015-->). Prior to the studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> described in this review, neural G protein signaling had not been seriously studied using genetic approaches. Thus, despite the excellence of the body of biochemical work on G protein signaling, there remained significant gaps in understanding the molecular mechanisms of this type of signaling in neurons, and also in achieving a big-picture understanding of how and why such signaling is used to control the activity of neural circuits.</para>
<para>As described in this review, the molecular mechanisms of neural G protein signaling are strongly conserved between humans and <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, and <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> provides two advantages that complement the past electrophysiological and biochemical work on neural G protein signaling. First, the power of forward genetics in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has allowed new neural signaling proteins to be discovered. Second, the simplicity of the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> nervous system, combined with the use of genetics, has allowed biological functions to be assigned to signaling by specific neurotransmitters acting through specific GPCRs on individual identified neurons. Enough such biological functions of neural G protein signaling have now been described that the long-elusive big-picture understanding of the whole purpose of this mode of neurotransmission is beginning to emerge.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec1.3">
<title>The heterotrimeric G protein activity cycle</title>
<para>Here I outline the activity cycle for a generic heterotrimeric G protein as a prelude to diving more deeply into how specific GPCRs, G proteins, and their downstream signaling pathways regulate neural function in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. The G protein activity cycle proceeds through five states labeled in <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>. Most steps in the cycle were discovered and characterized through biochemical studies of mammalian proteins, but the RGS and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> proteins that catalyze the transitions between states 4 and 5 were discovered through studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> and subsequently characterized in mammals.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase><link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link></phrase>
</textobject>&fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<sect3 id="sec1.3.1">
<title>State 1, the inactive state</title>
<para>GPCRs are integral membrane proteins with seven transmembrane helices. Heterotrimeric G proteins have &alpha;, &beta;, and &gamma; subunits and are peripheral membrane proteins tethered to the inner leaflet of the plasma membrane by lipid modifications (<link linkend="bib91">Hepler and Gilman, 1992</link><!--:PMID 1455506-->; <link linkend="bib260">Wedegaertner et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 7822269-->). The G&alpha; subunit changes conformation depending on whether it is bound to GDP, GTP, or no guanine nucleotide, and these conformational changes allow G&alpha; to alter its association with other proteins (<link linkend="bib167">Noel et al., 1993</link><!--:PMID 8259210-->; <link linkend="bib13">Coleman et al., 1994</link><!--:PMID 8073283-->; <link linkend="bib137">Lambright et al., 1994</link><!--:PMID 8208289-->; <link linkend="bib256">Wall et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 8521505-->). In its GDP-bound inactive state, G&alpha; is typically bound to G&beta;&gamma; to form an inactive G protein heterotrimer.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec1.3.2">
<title>State 2, activated GPCR promotes release of GDP by the G&alpha;</title>
<para>Neurotransmitter binding induces conformational shifts in GPCRs that have recently been delineated by X-ray crystallographic studies (<link linkend="bib118">Katritch et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23140243-->). GPCRs and G proteins are able to diffuse laterally due to the fluid nature of biological membranes, and a neurotransmitter-bound, activated receptor can thus collide with an inactive G protein heterotrimer. This interaction induces a large conformational change in G&alpha; that allows the release of bound GDP (<link linkend="bib70">Fung et al., 1981</link><!--:PMID 6264430-->; <link linkend="bib18">Brandt and Ross, 1986</link><!--:PMID 2868003-->; <link linkend="bib192">Rasmussen et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21772288-->). The active GPCR and nucleotide-free G protein heterotrimer form a stable complex that dissociates in the next step of the G protein cycle.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec1.3.3">
<title>State 3, GTP binding induces dissociation of GPCR, G&alpha;, and G&beta;&gamma;</title>
<para>The open nucleotide-binding site on G&alpha; can bind GTP, which causes G&alpha; to undergo another conformational change that causes G&alpha;-GTP to dissociate from both the receptor and G&beta;&gamma; (<link linkend="bib167">Noel et al., 1993</link><!--:PMID 8259210-->; <link linkend="bib13">Coleman et al., 1994</link><!--:PMID 8073283-->; <link linkend="bib137">Lambright et al., 1994</link><!--:PMID 8208289-->; <link linkend="bib256">Wall et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 8521505-->). The release of GDP and subsequent GTP binding by G&alpha; is referred to as &ldquo;nucleotide exchange&rdquo;. The receptor, which remains bound to neurotransmitter, can diffuse laterally in the membrane and proceed to promote nucleotide exchange on additional G proteins. Thus the active receptor can function as an enzyme to catalytically promote conversion of inactive G&alpha;&beta;&gamma;-GDP to the active signaling species G&alpha;-GTP and G&beta;&gamma; (<link linkend="bib205">Ross, 2014</link><!--:PMID 25279250-->).</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec1.3.4">
<title>State 4, G&alpha;-GTP and G&beta;&gamma; signal by forming stable complexes with effectors</title>
<para>The separated G&alpha;-GTP and G&beta;&gamma; complexes are able to stably bind to and regulate activity of other proteins to promote responses in the cell, and these other proteins are collectively termed G protein &ldquo;effectors&rdquo;. Effectors have been identified for G&beta;&gamma; (<link linkend="bib193">Reuveny et al., 1994</link><!--:PMID 8022483-->; <link linkend="bib92">Herlitze et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8637576-->) and for the G&alpha; isoforms G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> (<link linkend="bib234">Sunahara et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8725398-->), G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> (<link linkend="bib113a">Kadamur and Ross, 2013</link><!--:PMID 23140367-->; <link linkend="bib203">Rohas et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17606614-->; <link linkend="bib264">Williams et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17942708-->), G&alpha;<subscript>12</subscript> (<link linkend="bib219">Siehler, 2009</link><!--:PMID 19226283-->), and G&alpha;<subscript>i</subscript> (<link linkend="bib243">Taussig et al., 1994</link><!--: 8119955-->). Most G protein effectors are transmembrane protein complexes. Some G protein effectors are enzymes that catalyze the production of second messengers, small molecules that can diffuse in the cell and evoke responses. G&alpha; proteins bind their effectors via the same &ldquo;switch&rdquo; regions they use to bind G&beta;&gamma;. G&alpha; must be in its GTP-bound conformation to bind and activate effectors, but must be in its GDP-bound conformation to bind G&beta;&gamma;. Thus G&alpha; serves as a molecular switch that alternates between an active GTP-bound state and an inactive GDP-bound state. G&beta;&gamma; can only activate its effectors once it has dissociated from G&alpha;.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec1.3.5">
<title>State 5, inactivation of G&alpha; via GTP hydrolysis, and reactivation via receptor-independent nucleotide exchange</title>
<para>G&alpha; subunits of heterotrimeric G proteins have a slow but significant intrinsic GTPase activity, such that purified G&alpha; protein can hydrolyze bound GTP to GDP with a half time on the order of a few minutes. A key contribution of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> and yeast genetics was the discovery of a class of &ldquo;regulator of G protein signaling&rdquo; (RGS) proteins (<link linkend="bib127">Koelle and Horvitz, 1996</link><!--:PMID 8548815-->; <link linkend="bib57">Dohlman et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8756677-->) that serve as GTPase activators for G&alpha; proteins, speeding up the hydrolysis reaction by orders of magnitude (<link linkend="bib16">Berman et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8910288-->; <link linkend="bib244">Tesmer et al., 1997</link><!--:PMID 9108480-->). Physiologically, G&alpha; signaling is typically inactivated with the help of an RGS protein (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>).</para>
<para>A second key contribution of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genetics was the discovery of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink>, a soluble protein that promotes G protein signaling (<link linkend="bib156">Miller et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 11102364-->), sometimes with the help of other proteins containing the G protein regulatory (GPR) motif that binds G&alpha; proteins (<link linkend="bib45">Colombo et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12750478-->; <link linkend="bib78">Gotta et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12814548-->; <link linkend="bib225">Srinivasan et al., 2003</link><!--: PMD 12730122-->; <link linkend="bib98">Hofler and Koelle, 2011</link><!--:PMID 21832186-->). Genetic studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> show that GPR proteins and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> promote G protein activity, and the biochemical activities of these proteins <emphasis role="italic">in vitro</emphasis> suggest that they may do so by reactivating G&alpha;-GDP as illustrated in <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>. However, studies in mammalian cells show that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink>, in addition to catalyzing nucleotide exchange <emphasis role="italic">in vitro</emphasis>, also acts in living cells as a chaperone to promote folding and stability of G&alpha; proteins (<link linkend="bib71">Gabay et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22114146-->; <link linkend="bib26">Chan P. et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23431197-->). The <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genetic data are consistent with the alternative model that GPR and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> proteins are simply required for G&alpha; folding and stability.</para>
<para>The G protein activity cycle is completed when G&alpha;-GDP re-associates with G&beta;&gamma; to re-form the inactive G&alpha;&beta;&gamma; heterotrimer. G&beta;&gamma; is sequestered in the heterotrimer so that it can no longer associate with its effectors.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Neurotransmitters and receptors that signal through heterotrimeric G proteins</title>
<para>In this section, I describe analysis of the surprisingly large set of neurotransmitters and neural G protein coupled receptors present in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. Each neurotransmitter and each receptor is expressed in a very specific and limited set of neurons, and as a result each affects a very specific and limited set of behaviors. An important result from <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> is that a neurotransmitter can signal via a GPCR expressed on cells that are not postsynaptic to the neurons that release that neurotransmitter. Thus neurotransmitters travel through tissue to signal at sites distant from their site of release. The pattern of neurotransmitter signaling via GPCRs is thus not determined by the synaptic wiring of the nervous system, but rather by the specific expression patterns of the neurotransmitters and their GPCR receptors. The widespread nature of extrasynaptic neurotransmitter signaling forces us to expand our notion of a neural circuit to a unit consisting of neurons that function together but that may lack direct anatomical connections.</para>
<sect2 id="sec2.1">
<title>GPCRs for small-molecule neurotransmitters</title>
<para>Most major small-molecule neurotransmitters used in humans are also found in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> (exceptions are norepinephrine, histamine, and possibly glycine and ATP). <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> and <link linkend="table2">Table 2</link> summarize studies of a set of 28 <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> GPCRs for small-molecule neurotransmitters. This includes four serotonin receptors, four dopamine receptors, three octopamine receptors, three tyramine receptors, three acetylcholine receptors, two GABA receptors that function together as an obligate dimer, three apparent glutamate receptors, and six additional predicted receptors with sequence similarity to small molecule neurotransmitter GPCRs that have yet to have ligands assigned to them or to be studied genetically. Many of these 28 GPCRs are produced in multiple isoforms via alternative splicing of their RNA transcripts</para>
<sect3 id="sec2.1.1">
<title>Identification of ligands for individual GPCRs</title>
<para>Putative small-molecule neurotransmitter GPCRs were first identified in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> as homologs of mammalian neurotransmitter receptors (e.g., <link linkend="bib129">Komuniecki et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15279946-->). Such analyses can make predictions for the ligand that might activate a GPCR homolog, but these are weak predictions. For example, the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> receptors <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32299;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17158;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-3</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31653;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-6</ulink> were originally assigned their names due to similarity with serotonin receptors, but later proved experimentally to be receptors for other biogenic amine neurotransmitters (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). Thus, assigning a ligand to a GPCR requires experimental evidence. Three lines of such experimental evidence are described below, and <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> lists which of these lines of evidence are available for each of 22 <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> receptors.</para>
<para>The first line of experimental evidence is listed in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> as &ldquo;binding studies&rdquo;. Here, a GPCR is expressed in heterologous cells inducing a binding activity in their membranes for a radiolabeled ligand. Since characterizing binding by many different radioligands is inconvenient, typically a single radioligand with binding activity is identified (e.g., <superscript>3</superscript>H-LSD, which binds with high affinity to most biogenic amine receptors), and then the ability of many unlabeled neurotransmitters and pharmaceuticals to compete off the radioligand is measured as a &ldquo;K<subscript>i</subscript>&rdquo;. Such studies measure the relative binding affinity of different ligands, but do not determine if an individual ligand is an agonist (activator) or antagonist (inhibitor) for the receptor. Based on such binding data, a GPCR is considered likely to be a receptor for the neurotransmitter that appears to bind it with highest affinity.</para>
<para>The second line of experimental evidence listed in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> is &ldquo;heterologous cell signaling&rdquo;. Here, a GPCR is expressed in heterologous cultured cells, typically mammalian cells or <emphasis role="italic">Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes, potential ligands are applied in the medium, and activation of downstream signaling is measured (e.g., through use of fluorescent Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> indicators, electrophysiological recording of G protein regulated ion channels, etc.). This method allows the concentration of a ligand that gives half-maximal response (EC<subscript>50</subscript>) to be measured, and can determine if a ligand is an agonist or antagonist. Further, it provides evidence for the type of G&alpha; protein activated by the receptor (see Section 2.2.2.). Based on such heterologous cell signaling studies, a GPCR is considered likely to be a receptor for the neurotransmitter that activates it with the lowest EC<subscript>50</subscript>.</para>
<para>The third line of experimental evidence listed in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> is genetic studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. In many cases, a mutant for a GPCR renders worms insensitive to the effects of a specific neurotransmitter, either applied exogenously or released endogenously via optogenetic stimulation. Another type of genetic study demonstrates that a GPCR mutant shows behavioral defects similar to those of a mutant lacking a particular neurotransmitter. Such genetic studies provide evidence that GPCR functions <emphasis role="italic">in vivo</emphasis> as a receptor for a specific neurotransmitter.</para>
<para><link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> shows that for the 22 GPCRs listed as assigned a ligand, the number of experimental lines of evidence for that assignment varies from zero to three, and the quality of each piece of evidence can also vary widely. Clearly, the more experimental evidence that is available, the more confident a ligand assignment will be.</para>
<para>Both <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> and mammals have multiple GPCRs for individual neurotransmitters. A large number of pharmaceuticals have been developed that activate or antagonize specific mammalian receptor isoforms. It is tempting to try to use <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> as a model system to investigate the functions of specific neurotransmitter receptor isoforms to better understand the actions of these important drugs. However, when the sequences of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neurotransmitter receptors are lined up with those of mammalian receptors, individual <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> receptors cannot be unambiguously assigned as orthologs of specific mammalian receptors. For example, the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> serotonin receptors are more similar to mammalian serotonin receptors than they are to mammalian receptors for other neurotransmitters, but an additional <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> receptor (named <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32299;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-2</ulink>) is also most similar to mammalian serotonin receptors in sequence and turned out be a tyramine receptor (<link linkend="bib196">Rex et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15569254-->). By sequence analysis, the bona fide <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> serotonin receptors do not unambiguously match up with individual mammalian serotonin receptor isoforms. Furthermore, when <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> serotonin receptors are expressed in cultured cells or <emphasis role="italic">Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes, their profiles of binding and activation by drugs do not match up to the pharmacology of specific mammalian serotonin receptor isoforms (<link linkend="bib129">Komuniecki et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15279946-->). Thus, while <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> generally provides an excellent model for studying small-molecule neurotransmitter signaling through G proteins, there are limits to the level of conservation of receptors between humans and worms.</para>
<para>An important issue in assigning ligands to GPCRs is the potential that a single GPCR might physiologically mediate signaling by more than one type of neurotransmitter. The heterologous cell signaling studies cited in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> show that certain receptors have significant affinities for more than one biogenic amine neurotransmitter. For example, the dopamine receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39181;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-3</ulink> is activated in heterologous cell signaling studies by dopamine with an EC<subscript>50</subscript> of 27 nm, but also by tyramine with an EC<subscript>50</subscript> of 500 nm (<link linkend="bib230">Sugiura et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16001968-->). Binding studies show significant affinities for more than one biogenic amine by the receptors <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33616;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35994;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib237">Suo et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 11814642-->), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35478;class=Protein" role="_blank">OCTR-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib265">Wragg et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18057198-->), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32299;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib194">Rex and Komuniecki, 2002</link><!--:PMID 12354282-->), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE38313;class=Protein" role="_blank">TYRA-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib195">Rex et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15953361-->), and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31203;class=Protein" role="_blank">TYRA-3</ulink> (<link linkend="bib265">Wragg et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18057198-->). Since the synaptic concentrations of released neurotransmitters are thought to go above one millimolar (<link linkend="bib8a">Barberis et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21734864-->), the high nanomolar or micromolar binding affinities of certain receptors for a secondary neurotransmitter could be biologically meaningful. Studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> could resolve this issue. Given the complete wiring diagram in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, along with the known identifies of neurons that release specific neurotransmitters and that express specific GPCRs, there is the potential to identify synapses at which a GPCR is exposed to a high concentration of one of its lower-affinity ligands. Genetic analysis could then determine if this results in physiologically significant signaling.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec2.1.2">
<title>Identification of G proteins activated by individual GPCRs</title>
<para>Sequence comparison of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> GPCRs to homologous mammalian GPCRs can be used to predict to which G&alpha; protein a particular <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> GPCR might couple (e.g., <link linkend="bib265">Wragg et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18057198-->). However, a more definitive assignment requires experimental evidence. Two lines of such experimental evidence are described below, and <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> lists the lines of evidence for G&alpha; protein coupling available for each of 22 <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> receptors.</para>
<para>The first line of experimental evidence is listed in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> as &ldquo;heterologous cell&rdquo; studies. Here, a GPCR is expressed in heterologous cultured cells for ligand activation studies, as described above in <link linkend="sec2.1.1">Section 2.1.1</link>. In addition to identifying an activating ligand, these studies can determine what type of G&alpha; protein is activated by the GPCR in heterologous cells. For example, activation of Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> release generally indicates G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling, activation of cAMP production generally indicates G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> activation, and inhibition of cAMP production and/or sensitivity to pertussis toxin generally indicates G&alpha;<subscript>i/o</subscript> activation.</para>
<para>The second line of experimental evidence listed in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> comes from genetic studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. Here, a <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> GPCR mutant can be used to demonstrate that a receptor acts in a particular cell type to support a particular behavior, and genetic studies can similarly show that a particular G&alpha; protein is also required in the same cell type for the same behavior.</para>
<para><link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> shows that 20 of 22 GPCRs assigned to a ligand are also assigned coupling to a specific G&alpha; protein, with the number of experimental lines of evidence for that G&alpha; assignment varying from zero to two. G&alpha; assignments from heterologous cell studies generally agree with assignments from <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genetics in cases where both lines of evidence are available, bolstering confidence in assignments from the many cases with only one line of evidence. An interesting case is that of the dopamine receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35994;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-2</ulink>, which was assigned to G&alpha;<subscript>i/o</subscript> in heterologous cell studies, and for which <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genetics suggests that three different G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>-related G&alpha; proteins may mediate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35994;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-2</ulink> signaling in worms (<link linkend="bib238">Suo et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12887685-->; <link linkend="bib235">Suo et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19609300-->; <link linkend="bib48">Correa et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23166505-->; <link linkend="bib173">Pandey and Harbinder, 2012</link><!--:PMID 22280843-->; <link linkend="bib154">Mersha et al. 2013</link><!--:PMID 23607404-->).</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2.2">
<title>Cataloging GPCRs for neuropeptides</title>
<para>At present at least 119 <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genes encoding over 250 neuropeptides have been cataloged (<link linkend="bib142">Li and Kim, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18819171-->; <link linkend="bib143">Li and Kim, 2010</link><!--:PMID 21189676-->). Identifying the receptors for all these neuropeptides is a major challenge. Of the >1,000 putative GPCRs encoded in the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genome, most are chemosensory receptors, and a much smaller subset are likely to be neuropeptide receptors. For tables itemizing these receptors, I refer readers to several recent reviews that have cataloged the likely <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neuropeptide receptors by looking for GPCRs most similar to known neuropeptide receptors (<link linkend="bib5">Altun, 2011</link>; <link linkend="bib68">Frooninckx et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23267347-->; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_neuronalgenome/neuronalgenome.html">The neuronal genome of <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis></ulink>). These cataloging efforts generally predict about 150 genes encoding neuropeptide receptors, with individual genes often producing a number of differentially spliced isoforms.</para>
<para>Only a relatively small number of putative neuropeptide receptors have been assigned as receptors for specific neuropeptide(s)&mdash;one recent count put the number of such &ldquo;deorphanized&rdquo; neuropeptide receptors at 23 (<link linkend="bib68">Frooninckx et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23267347-->). The quality of the data varies for each receptor, but a definitive assignment of a peptide to a receptor should include data showing the peptide binds the receptor with high affinity and specificity, as well as <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genetic data demonstrating that the peptide functions via the receptor to regulate a specific behavior. An example of such a definitive assignment is work showing that the sensory BAG neurons release two different peptides encoded by the <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001460;class=Gene" role="_blank">flp-17</ulink></emphasis> gene which then act via the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04219;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-6</ulink> receptor on the HSN motor neuron to inhibit egg-laying behavior (<link linkend="bib199">Ringstad and Horvitz, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18806786-->).</para>
<para>Can <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neuropeptides or neuropeptide receptors be matched up with mammalian orthologs? In the case of the neuropeptides, the sequences are so short that there just is not enough information content in them to make such an analysis possible. In the case of the receptors, their information-rich sequences do allow such an analysis. Mammalian neuropeptide receptors can be broken down into several subfamilies based on sequence relationships, and many worm receptors can similarly be fitted into the same families (<link linkend="bib5">Altun, 2011</link>; <link linkend="bib68">Frooninckx et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23267347-->; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_neuronalgenome/neuronalgenome.html">The neuronal genome of <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis></ulink>). Most <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> putative neuropeptide receptors cannot be definitively assigned as orthologs of specific mammalian receptors simply based on sequence analysis. However, based on sequence similarity as well as additional functional data, some worm receptors have been described as models for specific mammalian receptors. Thus <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06941;class=Protein" role="_blank">NPR-1</ulink> is similar to the mammalian neuropeptide Y receptor (<link linkend="bib50">de Bono and Bargmann, 1998</link><!--:PMID 9741632-->), <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30860;class=Protein" role="_blank">PDFR-1</ulink> is similar to the <emphasis role="italic">Drosophila</emphasis> pigment dispersing factor receptor and mammalian vasoactive peptide and calcitonin receptors (<link linkend="bib108">Janssen et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18390545-->), and <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE38997;class=Protein" role="_blank">NPR-17</ulink> is similar to mammalian opioid receptors (<link linkend="bib37">Cheong et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 25898004-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2.3">
<title>Neural GPCRs are each expressed in very restricted sets of cells</title>
<para>An important result from analysis of G protein coupled neurotransmitter receptors in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> is that each receptor tends to be expressed on a small number of specific neurons, allowing that receptor to mediate very specific effects on behavior. <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> hermaphrodites have just 302 neurons, which, due to symmetries and repeated structures in the anatomy, can be classified into 118 types. Each neuron can be identified by its unique position and morphology within the animal. Further, all the synaptic connections of each neuron with other neurons and muscles have been mapped, making <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> the only animal for which a complete neural wiring diagram is available (<link linkend="bib261">White et al., 1986</link><!--:PMID 22462104-->). Because of these features, identifying all the specific neurons that express a neurotransmitter and its receptor is uniquely possible in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, and this information, once obtained, can be interpreted using the wiring diagram to obtain unique insights into neural signaling. In this section I begin a discussion of this area of investigation.</para>
<para>The expression patterns of a significant subset of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neural GPCRs have been studied. These experiments generally involve creating transgenic worms in which the promoter and other regulatory sequences for a GPCR gene are used to drive expression of the green fluorescent protein (GFP), and specific cells expressing GFP are identified by fluorescence microscopy. Data for the expressions patterns of 22 GPCR receptors for small-molecule neurotransmitters are summarized in <link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>, and expression patterns for 27 of the &sim;150 putative neuropeptide receptors are also available (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_neuronalgenome/neuronalgenome.html">The neuronal genome of <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis></ulink>). The quality and completeness of the work varies greatly for each receptor. In some cases, only relatively short promoter regions were used to construct the GFP reporter transgenes, raising questions as to whether the results obtained fully represent the expression patterns of the endogenous GPCR genes. In other cases, only a cursory analysis of the fluorescently labeled cells is presented, with little or no attempt to identify the GFP-expressing cells.</para>
<para>Despite these caveats, an important generalization can be made about the expression patterns of neural GPCRs: an individual neurotransmitter receptor type tends to be expressed in a limited set of specific cells. This can be illustrated with examples from receptors for which relatively high-quality expression data are available and which typify the results obtained with other receptors. A GFP reporter for the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04219;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-6</ulink> neuropeptide receptor was expressed in just three types of neurons (HSN, SDQ, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVA;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVA</ulink>) and one type of glial cell (GLR) (<link linkend="bib199">Ringstad and Horvitz, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18806786-->). A GFP reporter for the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06941;class=Protein" role="_blank">NPR-1</ulink> neuropeptide receptor was expressed in approximately 20 neuron cell types (<link linkend="bib41">Coates and de Bono, 2002</link><!--:PMID 12410311-->). A reporter for the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37317;class=Protein" role="_blank">NPR-4</ulink> neuropeptide receptor was expressed in five neuron types, the intestine, and the rectal gland cell, while a reporter for the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36962;class=Protein" role="_blank">NPR-5</ulink> neuropeptide receptor was expressed 13 neuron types and in all body wall muscles (<link linkend="bib42">Cohen et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19356718-->). Expression patterns of G protein coupled receptors for small-molecule neurotransmitters (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>) show similar characteristics to those seen in the above examples of neuropeptide receptors&mdash;each receptor is typically expressed in a limited number of neuron types plus sometimes additional non-neuronal cell types. For example, a reporter for the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE38313;class=Protein" role="_blank">TYRA-2</ulink> tyramine receptor is expressed in about 14 neuron types (<link linkend="bib195">Rex et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15953361-->). Reporters for the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32299;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-2</ulink> tyramine receptor are expressed in a total of 24 neuron types, plus body wall muscles, pharyngeal muscles, and the excretory gland (<link linkend="bib250">Tsalik et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14568548-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2.4">
<title>Neurotransmitters signal extrasynaptically through GPCRs</title>
<para>The predominant model of neural signaling has been that synapses, specialized physical connections between neurons, are the sites of neurotransmitter signaling between neurons. A presynaptic neuron releases neurotransmitter from vesicles clustered at a presynaptic terminus, flooding the narrow synaptic cleft with neurotransmitter, which binds to neurotransmitter receptors clustered on the postsynaptic membrane. The idea that synapses are central to understanding neural function inspired the landmark achievement of mapping all the synaptic connections in the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> nervous system (<link linkend="bib261">White et al., 1986</link><!--:PMID 22462104-->), and is behind current efforts, for example within the BRAIN initiative, to map synaptic connections within more complex nervous systems (<link linkend="bib111">Jorgenson et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 25823863-->).</para>
<para>While ionotropic neurotransmitter signaling may typically be restricted to synapses, studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> provide ample evidence that neurotransmitter signaling through G protein coupled receptors may be predominantly extrasynaptic. The concept of extrasynaptic neurotransmission (also called volume transmission) originated in 1986 based on studies of mammalian brain (<link linkend="bib2">Agnati et al., 1986</link><!--:PMID 3022556-->). Since then, many studies in mammalian brain demonstrated the release of neurotransmitters from extrasynaptic sites, the ability of neurotransmitters to diffuse through the extracellular space, and the localization of G protein coupled neurotransmitter receptors to extrasynaptic sites (<link linkend="bib3">Agnati et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 20347870-->). Indeed, given the submicromolar affinities of many GPCRs for their neurotransmitter ligands (see <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> for examples), it would make little sense for such receptors to function at synapses where neurotransmitter concentrations can rise to the millimolar level (<link linkend="bib8a">Barberis et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21734864-->) and may never be reduced to low enough concentrations to allow high-affinity receptors to become unliganded. Despite this evidence, it has been difficult to provide genetic evidence demonstrating the functional significance of extrasynaptic signaling in mammalian brain. In contrast, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> is ideally suited to such work. In this system, it is possible to use rigorous genetic experiments to define the specific neurons that release a neurotransmitter to induce a particular behavioral response, and to also define the specific neurons that express the G protein coupled receptor that functionally receives the neurotransmitter signal to execute the response. Remarkably, results of such analyses show over and over again that the neurotransmitter releasing neuron and the receptor-expressing receiving neuron are not synaptically connected. Ironically, the complete synaptic wiring diagram of the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> nervous system has thus been the key tool for demonstrating that synapses are often not needed to mediate neurotransmitter signaling via G protein coupled receptors. Here I summarize the evidence for extrasynaptic neurotransmitter signaling in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
<sect3 id="sec2.4.1">
<title>Neurotransmitters are released from extrasynaptic sites</title>
<para>Neuropeptides and some small-molecule neurotransmitters are released from dense-core vesicles, which are distinct from the small-clear vesicles clustered at presynaptic termini. In <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neurons that make synapses dense-core vesicles are excluded from the synaptic active zones where synaptic vesicles are released, although many are localized nearby (Hammarlund et al., 2008 <!--:PMID 18250196-->). Furthermore, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, like the human brain, has specialized neuroendocrine cells that synthesize and release neurotransmitters but that do not form synaptic connections with any other cells. The uv1 neuroendocrine cells release tyramine and neuropeptides to inhibit egg-laying behavior (<link linkend="bib113">Jose et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17057248-->), and the NSM neuroendocrine cells release serotonin to regulate locomotion (<link linkend="bib209">Sawin et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 10896158-->; <link linkend="bib81">G&uuml;rel et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23023001-->). The extrasynaptic neurotransmitter release sites of NSM have been studied in some detail (<link linkend="bib166">Nelson and Col&oacute;n-Ramos, 2012</link><!--:PMID 23345213-->). The documented functions of neurotransmitter release from uv1 and NSM provide one set of evidence that neurotransmitters do signal extrasynaptically. Some additional cells in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> do not form any synapses, yet express neuropeptide genes, so any functions of peptides secreted from these cells must also be extrasynaptic. Cells in this category include the CAN cell, intestinal cells, muscle cells, and hypodermal cells (<link linkend="bib261">White et al., 1986</link><!--:PMID 22462104-->; <link linkend="bib142">Li and Kim, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18819171-->; <link linkend="bib143">Li and Kim, 2010</link><!--:PMID 21189676-->).</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec2.4.2">
<title>Neurotransmitters can signal through GPCR receptors on cells not postsynaptic to their release sites</title>
<para>The specific <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neurons that synthesize and release individual small molecule neurotransmitters or neuropeptides have been mapped in considerable detail (see WormBook chapter <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_gaba/gaba.html">GABA</ulink>; <link linkend="bib191">Rand, 2007</link>; <link linkend="bib32">Chase and Koelle, 2007</link>; <link linkend="bib142">Li and Kim, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18819171-->; <link linkend="bib143">Li and Kim, 2010</link><!--:PMID 21189676-->; <link linkend="bib104">Jafari et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21677178-->; <link linkend="bib215">Serrano-Saiz et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 24243022-->; <link linkend="bib181">Periera et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 26705699-->). Thus when the expression pattern of a G protein coupled receptor for a specific neurotransmitter is determined, we can use the synaptic wiring diagram of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> to see if the cells that produce that neurotransmitter are presynaptic to the cells that express its receptor. In many cases, the answer is no.</para>
<para>G protein coupled receptors for small-molecule neurotransmitters are expressed on cells not postsynaptic to neurons that release the corresponding neurotransmitter. This was first noted for the dopamine receptors <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33616;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39181;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-3</ulink>, which are expressed, among other places, on ventral cord motor neurons (<link linkend="bib31">Chase et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15378064-->). Dopamine is released from exactly three types of neurons in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, and none of these neurons make synapses onto the ventral cord motor neurons. Genetic studies show that dopamine regulates locomotion via the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33616;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39181;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-3</ulink> receptors, and the locomotion defects of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001052;class=Gene" role="_blank">dop-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020506;class=Gene" role="_blank">dop-3</ulink></emphasis> mutants can be rescued be re-expressing the receptors specifically in ventral cord motor neurons (<link linkend="bib31">Chase et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15378064-->). These experiments rigorously demonstrate that dopamine receptors are not only found on cells distant from dopamine release sites, but that they also function to mediate dopamine signaling in these distant cells.</para>
<para>Since those initial studies of dopamine signaling, similar experiments have demonstrated extrasynaptic signaling by other small-molecule neurotransmitters. One striking case is that of the neurotransmitter tyramine, which is released from only the neuroendocrine uv1 cells (which make no synapses) and from the RIM interneuron, which makes synapses only onto four other types of neurons and onto neck muscles (<link linkend="bib261">White et al., 1986</link><!--:PMID 22462104-->). When <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> is touched on the head, tyramine released from RIM mediates a complex escape response. One aspect of this response is mediated by tyramine signaling at synapses from RIM onto neck muscles using an ionotropic receptor (<link linkend="bib186">Pirri et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19477154-->). However, another aspect of the escape response is mediated by tyramine signaling from RIM through a G protein coupled receptor. This GPCR, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32299;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-2</ulink>, is expressed on GABAergic motor neurons, which are not post-synaptic to RIM, and defects in the escape response seen in <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004777;class=Gene" role="_blank">ser-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants are rescued by cell-specific re-expression of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004777;class=Gene" role="_blank">ser-2</ulink></emphasis> in GABAergic motor neurons, demonstrating that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32299;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-2</ulink> acts in these neurons to mediate extrasynaptic signaling by tyramine that originates from RIM (<link linkend="bib60">Donnelly et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23565061-->).</para>
<para>There have now been similar genetic demonstrations that neuropeptides signal onto cells not postsynaptic to the neurons that release them. For example, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17594;class=Protein" role="_blank">FLP-17</ulink> neuropeptides are released from BAG sensory neurons and signal via the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04219;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-6</ulink> neuropeptide receptor on the HSN motor neurons, which are not postsynaptic to BAG, to inhibit egg laying (<link linkend="bib199">Ringstad and Horvitz, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18806786-->). The <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> defecation motor program is coordinated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24660;class=Protein" role="_blank">NLP-40</ulink> peptides released from intestinal cells, which being non-neuronal make no synapses, and these <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24660;class=Protein" role="_blank">NLP-40</ulink> peptides signal onto GABAergic motor neurons via the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31607;class=Protein" role="_blank">AEX-2</ulink> peptide receptor (<link linkend="bib258">Wang et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23583549-->). Beyond these rigorous genetic demonstrations that specific peptides signal extrasynaptically via particular neuropeptide receptors, there are additional data showing that some neuropeptide receptors are expressed on cells that do not receive any synapses, so that any signaling they mediate on these cells must be extrasynaptic. These receptor-expressing cells include intestinal, hypodermal, and glial cells (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_neuronalgenome/neuronalgenome.html">The neuronal genome of <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis></ulink>).</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2.5">
<title>The genetics of G protein coupled neurotransmitter receptors</title>
<para>Null mutants or RNAi knockdowns for many <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> G protein coupled neurotransmitter receptors have been analyzed, and the main finding is that phenotypic defects are very hard to detect in them. Most of the time no defects are observed, and the few mutant phenotypes that have been described for neural GPCRs are typically not gross behavioral defects obvious upon inspection of individual animals, but rather narrow behavioral defects detectable only when populations of worms are put through specific phenotypic assays.</para>
<para>An initial effort at identifying neural GPCR phenotypes used RNAi to knock down expression of 60 G protein coupled neurotransmitter receptors (<link linkend="bib121">Keating et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14521838-->) and simply looked for uncoordinated movement or defects in reproduction. Knockdown of seven of the receptors had detectable effects on the frequency and/or amplitude of body bends, while knockdown of five receptors had some effect on the production of progeny. Later large-scale RNAi screens for genes that affect acetylcholine release/signaling identified hits in five GPCR genes, of which three were validated using genetic knockout mutations (<link linkend="bib217">Sieburth et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16049479-->; <link linkend="bib252">Vashlishan et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18466746-->). It is difficult to interpret some of these RNAi results: not all the defects seen with RNAi were reproduced with genetic mutations, the RNAi results did not always reproduce in different labs, and the phenotypes that were observed have not been characterized in much detail. Negative results from RNAi for GPCRs are also difficult to interpret since gene expression in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neurons is not always efficiently knocked down by RNAi, even in mutant backgrounds that enhance neuronal RNAi (<link linkend="bib188">Poole et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21698137-->).</para> 
<para>Mutations in genes encoding GPCRs have almost never been generated in forward genetic screens, despite the large number of GPCR genes in the worm genome. Since Brenner&rsquo;s first screen for uncoordinated mutants (<link linkend="bib19">Brenner, 1974</link><!--:PMID 4366476-->), <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> mutants for thousands of genes have been generated in genetic screens, including a large number with defects in neural structure and/or function. Included in this trove are many mutants for heterotrimeric G proteins and other signaling proteins that act downstream of neural GPCRs (<link linkend="bib183">Perez-Mansilla and Nurrish, 2009</link><!--:PMID 19615533-->), making the absence of neural GPCR mutants even more conspicuous.</para>
<para>Considering the few neural GPCR mutants that have arisen in forward genetic screens is instructive. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04219;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-6</ulink> neuropeptide receptor was identified by a rare gain-of-function mutation that inhibits egg laying (by increasing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04219;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-6</ulink> signaling), yet knockout mutations of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04219;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-6</ulink> do not produce detectable egg-laying defects (<link linkend="bib199">Ringstad and Horvitz, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18806786-->). Loss-of-function mutations in G protein coupled serotonin and dopamine receptors have arisen in forward genetic screens, but in these cases the phenotype screened for was resistance to the paralysis induced by applying these neurotransmitters to worms at high concentrations (<link linkend="bib31">Chase et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15378064-->; <link linkend="bib81">G&uuml;rel et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23023001-->). These mutants do not have obvious behavioral defects when animals are not bathed in a neurotransmitter, although defects have been detected when populations of mutant animals are put through very specific behavioral assays known to depend on serotonin or dopamine. There is perhaps only a single example of a neural GPCR for which loss-of-function mutants have been recovered from a forward genetic screen and for which the mutant phenotype is easily observable in single animals: mutants lacking <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31607;class=Protein" role="_blank">AEX-2</ulink>, the receptor for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24660;class=Protein" role="_blank">NLP-40</ulink> neuropeptides, are defective in the expulsion step of defecation (Mahoney et al., 2008 <!--:PMID 18852466-->; <link linkend="bib258">Wang et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23583549-->).</para>
<para><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> mutants for many G protein coupled neurotransmitter receptors are available as a result of large-scale efforts to produce gene knockouts for all <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genes (<link linkend="bib21"><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> deletion mutant consortium, 2012</link><!--:PMID 23173093-->). However, phenotypic defects have been described for only a small subset of these GPCR mutants. The cases in which phenotypic defects have been detected have generally come when either the neurotransmitter that activates the GPCR was known, so that specialized assays for behaviors dependent on that neurotransmitter could be assayed for defects, or in cases in which the expression pattern of the GPCR was known, so that specialized assays for behaviors dependent on neuron(s) that express the receptor could be tested for defects. An example that illustrates both strategies comes from the work of <link linkend="bib87">Harris et al. (2009)</link><!--:PMID 19193891-->, which analyzed how <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> backs away from the odor of dilute octanol, a response known to depend on both the neurotransmitter serotonin and on a neural circuit containing specific sensory neurons and interneurons. This information was used to focus in on two G protein coupled serotonin receptors, one expressed in the interneurons, another in the sensory neurons, and further experiments showed that knockouts and knock downs of these receptors resulted in specific behavioral defects in response to octanol. The two serotonin receptors studied by <link linkend="bib87">Harris et al. (2009)</link><!--:PMID 19193891--> are part of the set of 22 receptors for small molecule neurotransmitters listed in <link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>, which are the most intensively studied GPCRs in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans.</emphasis> As shown in <link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>, at this point mutant defects have been described for 20 of these receptors. The situation is less encouraging in the case of neuropeptide receptors, with mutant phenotypic defects described for only a few out of this large set of &sim;150 receptors.</para>
<para>Considering the totality of available genetic studies of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> G protein coupled neurotransmitter receptors, it appears that the knockout phenotypes for these proteins are generally so narrow that they will not be easily detected. Because individual receptors are expressed in only a few types of neurons, it is reasonable to expect that just the very specific behaviors affected by those neurons will be affected, and that specialized behavioral assays will be required to detect these defects. Another possible reason that GPCR mutant phenotypic defects are rarely detected could be that the large family of GPCRs contains many functionally redundant receptors, such that knocking out one receptor will not give obvious defects unless its redundant partners are also knocked out simultaneously. Several examples support the idea that neurotransmitter receptors can function redundantly. Two serotonin receptors appear to be co-expressed on the vulval muscles and both appear to promote activity of these muscles (<link linkend="bib85">Hapiak et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19001289-->). Serotonin released from the NSM neurosecretory cells inhibits locomotion, and two different serotonin receptors expressed on largely non-overlapping sets of neurons redundantly mediate this effect (<link linkend="bib81">G&uuml;rel et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23023001-->). Neuropeptides encoded by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33736;class=Protein" role="_blank">FLP-18</ulink> modulate locomotion, and three different receptors, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06941;class=Protein" role="_blank">NPR-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37317;class=Protein" role="_blank">NPR-4</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36962;class=Protein" role="_blank">NPR-5</ulink>, expressed in different sets of cells, redundantly mediate these effects of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33736;class=Protein" role="_blank">FLP-18</ulink> (<link linkend="bib227">Stawicki et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23658528-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33736;class=Protein" role="_blank">FLP-18</ulink> signaling is quite complex, because other behavioral effects of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33736;class=Protein" role="_blank">FLP-18</ulink> peptides are mediated non-redundantly by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06941;class=Protein" role="_blank">NPR-1</ulink>, and for these effects <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33736;class=Protein" role="_blank">FLP-18</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30733;class=Protein" role="_blank">FLP-21</ulink> neuropeptides both seem to activate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06941;class=Protein" role="_blank">NPR-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib39">Choi et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23764289-->). If such complex functional relationships between neurotransmitters and receptors are widespread, this will make assigning functions to receptors using knockout mutations very challenging.</para>
<para>A tool that may prove generally useful in genetically characterizing redundant or subtle GPCR functions is transgenic overexpression of GPCRs. One example comes from studies of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04219;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-6</ulink> neuropeptide receptor. Loss-of-function mutants for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04219;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-6</ulink> do not result in obvious defects under standard lab growth conditions. However, using a transgene carrying many copies of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001175;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-6</ulink></emphasis> genomic DNA to presumably overexpress the receptor does result in an obvious egg-laying defective phenotype, apparently due to increased activation of the overexpressed <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04219;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-6</ulink> receptor by the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04902;class=Protein" role="_blank">FLP-10</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17594;class=Protein" role="_blank">FLP-17</ulink> neuropeptides (<link linkend="bib199">Ringstad and Horvitz, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18806786-->). Another example comes from studies of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE38997;class=Protein" role="_blank">NPR-17</ulink> neuropeptide receptor. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE38997;class=Protein" role="_blank">NPR-17</ulink> mediates an effect of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE10752;class=Protein" role="_blank">NLP-3</ulink> peptides to modulate how <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> backs away from aversive stimuli, and a transgene carrying many copies of the <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015559;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-17</ulink></emphasis> gene causes a gain-of-function phenotype opposite that of an <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003741;class=Gene" role="_blank">nlp-3</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015559;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-17</ulink></emphasis> knockout, and that depends on the presence of a wild-type <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE10752;class=Protein" role="_blank">NLP-3</ulink>, suggesting that the overexpressed <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE38997;class=Protein" role="_blank">NPR-17</ulink> receptor causes increased <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE38997;class=Protein" role="_blank">NPR-17</ulink> signaling (<link linkend="bib89">Harris et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 20534837-->). If transgenically overexpressing a GPCR is generally able to induce gain-of-function phenotypes, this could be a valuable approach for identifying subtle or redundant functions of GPCRs.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2.6">
<title>Heterodimerization of G protein coupled neurotransmitter receptors</title>
<para>A major area of current research on mammalian GPCRs concerns the homo- and hetero-oligomerization of these receptors (<link linkend="bib76">Gonz&aacute;lez-Maeso, 2011</link><!--:PMID 21619615-->). It appears that in many cases, two different types of GPCRs can exist and function <emphasis role="italic">in vivo</emphasis> as a heterodimeric complex, and that a heteromeric receptor can have very different signaling properties than homomers of its subunits, including the ability to bind to different ligands. While GPCR heteromerization has so far been studied mainly using biochemical and biophysical methods, genetic analysis has much to contribute to understanding the physiological significance of this phenomenon. Heteromerization also potentially vastly complicates the challenge of understanding GPCR function: if <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has &sim;150 G protein coupled neurotransmitter receptor genes, how many types of heteromeric GPCRs might actually be the functional units <emphasis role="italic">in vivo</emphasis>?</para>
<para>There have so far been only a few efforts to analyze GPCR heteromer function in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. One example is that of the G protein coupled receptor for the neurotransmitter GABA. In mammals this GABA<subscript>B</subscript> receptor is an obligate heteromer between the GABA<subscript>B1</subscript> and GABA<subscript>B2</subscript> subunits (<link linkend="bib120">Kaupmann et al., 1998</link><!--:PMID 9872317-->). <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has orthologs of each subunit, known as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43326;class=Protein" role="_blank">GBB-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43384;class=Protein" role="_blank">GBB-2</ulink>, respectively. Knockouts of either <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43326;class=Protein" role="_blank">GBB-1</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43384;class=Protein" role="_blank">GBB-2</ulink> can block all G protein coupled responses to GABA in worms (<link linkend="bib212">Schultheis et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21613582-->), and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43326;class=Protein" role="_blank">GBB-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43384;class=Protein" role="_blank">GBB-2</ulink> act together to alter responses to the drug aldicarb (<link linkend="bib55">Dittman and Kaplan 2008</link><!--:PMID 18614679-->; <link linkend="bib252">Vashlishan et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18466746-->), consistent with the idea that the GABA<subscript>B</subscript> receptor is an obligatory heterodimer in worms just as it is in mammals. A second example comes from studies of signaling onto sensory neurons, not by a neurotransmitter, but by the mixture of small molecules known as ascarosides that collectively make up the worm dauer pheromone. The functional receptor for the specific ascaroside isoform ascr#2 appears to be a heteromer of the GPCRs <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02524;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-37</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24056;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-38</ulink> (<link linkend="bib174">Park et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22665789-->). ascr#2 binds directly to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02524;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-37</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02524;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-37</ulink> is essential for response to ascr#2 but is not involved in the response to other ascaroside isoforms. Genetic studies show that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24056;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-38</ulink> assists but is not essential for response to ascr#2, and similarly assists response to other ascaroside isoforms that do not signal through <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE02524;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-37</ulink>, suggesting <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24056;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-38</ulink> may heteromize with and assist signaling by a several different GPCRs that bind directly to different ascaroside isoforms. These studies demonstrate the potential of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genetic studies to sort out the intricacies of how GPCR subunits function together as heteromeric receptors <emphasis role="italic">in vivo</emphasis>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2.7">
<title>Deorphanizing neural G protein coupled neurotransmitter receptors</title>
<para>One of the principal issues in studying neural GPCRs is identifying the specific neurotransmitters that activate them. At this point, 22 of 28 GPCRs encoded in the worm genome that seem likely to be receptors for small-molecule neurotransmitters have been matched with their activating ligands (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>), but about 85% of the &sim;150 putative neuropeptide receptors remain &ldquo;orphans&rdquo;, that is receptors with unknown activators (<link linkend="bib68">Frooninckx et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23267347-->).</para>
<para>The general strategy to deorphanize neuropeptide receptors is to express them in heterologous cells, to apply synthetic versions of each neuropeptide encoded in the genome, and to test which specific peptides can activate receptor signaling. There are a number of cell types and signaling assays that have been used successfully for this purpose (<link linkend="bib155">Mertens et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15335287-->). This strategy has been applied to a number of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neuropeptide receptors, for example, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04219;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-6</ulink> (<link linkend="bib199">Ringstad and Horvitz, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18806786-->) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06941;class=Protein" role="_blank">NPR-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib202">Rogers et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14555955--> <link linkend="bib133">Kubiak et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12821653-->). The reverse strategy has also been used, screening through a set of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neuropeptide receptors to identify those that can be activated by a particular neuropeptide of interest (<link linkend="bib42">Cohen et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19356718-->). The results of receptor deorphanization experiments are complex: often a single receptor can be activated by multiple different peptides, the same peptides can activate multiple different receptors, the results can vary depending on the cell type and assay system used, and the EC<subscript>50</subscript> values measuring the potencies with which peptides activate receptors vary from the nanomolar to micromolar ranges (<link linkend="bib185">Peymen et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 24982652-->).</para>
<para><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> provides the opportunity to analyze mutants for the receptors and peptides putatively matched by such deorphanizing experiments to determine if they actually function together <emphasis role="italic">in vivo</emphasis>. Genetic approaches can also be used to match peptides and their receptors, for example, screening RNAi knockdowns of many neuropeptide genes to find those that phenocopy a particular orphan receptor mutant (<link linkend="bib42">Cohen et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19356718-->). Such genetic studies have generated results that are similar in complexity to those from using signaling assays in cultured cells for receptor deorphanization. Thus it appears that <emphasis role="italic">in vivo</emphasis> individual receptors can be activated by multiple peptides and individual peptides can act through multiple receptors (<link linkend="bib39">Choi et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23764289-->; <link linkend="bib227">Stawicki et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23658528-->).</para>
<para>The gold standard in matching neuropeptides with receptors is to combine studies of receptor activation by purified peptides in cultured cells with genetic studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. For the most part, it has been possible to achieve consistent results between the two approaches, generating strong confidence in the results, although there have been occasional puzzling exceptions (<link linkend="bib37">Cheong et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 25898004-->). Overall, the data matching neuropeptides to their cognate receptors remains sparse and we have a long way to go to fully match up these signaling molecules.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2.8">
<title>Studies of receptor desensitization in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis></title>
<para>In order for signaling by an activated GPCR to terminate, the receptor must eventually be inactivated. One mechanism for terminating receptor activity is to clear neurotransmitter from the extracellular space so that it no longer remains bound to the receptor. There are enzymes that degrade neurotransmitters and transporters that take them back up into cells that function for this purpose (<link linkend="bib270">Zimmerman and Soreq, 2006</link><!--:PMID 16802134-->; <link linkend="bib117">Kanner and Zomot, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18393466-->). Another mechanism for terminating signaling involves G protein coupled receptor kinases (GRKs) that specifically recognize and phosphorylate active GPCRs, and arrestin proteins that bind phosphorylated receptors. Phosphorylation and arrestin binding can block the ability of receptors to activate G proteins and also cause cells to internalize receptors from the cell surface, down-regulating signaling (<link linkend="bib128">Kohout and Lefkowitz, 2003</link><!--:PMID 12488531-->). These mechanisms, referred to as receptor desensitization, have been extensively studied in mammalian cells. Studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> of GRK and arrestin homologs have identified specific functions of these proteins in sensory neurons (<link linkend="bib69">Fukuto et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15157420-->; <link linkend="bib172">Palmitessa et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15878875-->, <link linkend="bib182">Pereira and van der Kooy, 2012</link><!--:PMID 22745502-->; <link linkend="bib220">Singh and Aballay, 2012</link><!--:PMID 22875856-->), but have so far failed to show any striking effects of GRK or arrestin on neurotransmitter signaling in the rest of the nervous system.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2.9">
<title>The overall landscape of neurotransmitter signaling through GPCRs</title>
<para>It is interesting to extrapolate from the existing data on <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> G protein coupled neurotransmitter receptors to consider what the overall landscape of neural signaling through GPCRs may look like. If we imagine that the &sim;175 neural GPCRs in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> are each expressed on average in 10 of the 118 neural cell types, then a typical neuron would express about 15 GPCRs, about two of which might be small-molecule neurotransmitter receptors, with the remainder being neuropeptide receptors. This typical neuron would then face the task of simultaneously sensing the levels of &sim;15 neurotransmitters in its extracellular space and executing appropriate responses to the dynamic mix of these signals it receives over time. All the GPCRs in this typical neuron may signal through about three types of G&alpha; proteins, which do not act separately but rather collaborate to modulate neurotransmitter release from the neuron (see <link linkend="sec3">Section 3</link>). Thinking about neurotransmitter signaling through GPCRs this way, it does not make sense to consider the action of a single neurotransmitter at a time, which is the way that we currently investigate neural signaling. Rather, it may be more appropriate to investigate how a single neuron computes appropriate responses to the entire mix of neurotransmitters in its environment. A prerequisite to such an investigation would be to know all the GPCRs that are present on that neuron, and we currently do not have that information for even a single <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neuron.</para>
<para>Perhaps the most striking result from analysis of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neural GPCRs is that neurotransmitters signal extrasynaptically through these receptors. Thus neurons that have no physical connections can signal each other and work together to control specific behaviors. The predominant model for understanding nervous system function has been that the functional ensembles of neurons that control thoughts and behaviors are circuits defined by the synaptic connections between the neurons in the ensemble. We have had the synaptic wiring diagram for the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> nervous system for almost 30 years (<link linkend="bib261">White et al., 1986</link><!--:PMID 22462104-->) and it has proven insufficient to allow us to understand the neural control of behaviors in this organism. Now that we understand the widespread nature of extrasynaptic neurotransmitter signaling, we need to expand our understanding of a neural circuit to be a functional ensemble of neurons that signal each other but that may lack direct anatomical connections. The patterns of signaling via GPCRs are not determined by the synaptic wiring of the nervous system, but rather by the specific expression patterns of neurotransmitters and their GPCR receptors. Thus to help understand neural circuit function, we need to supplement the existing synaptic wiring diagram with an additional diagram in which the specific cells that express each neurotransmitter and its cognate receptor(s) are defined. This goal, while ambitious, is potentially achievable in the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> system, perhaps aided by new cell-specific RNAseq technologies (<link linkend="bib224">Spencer et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 25372608-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>The mechanism of signaling by neural heterotrimeric G proteins</title>
<para>In this section, I focus on genetic studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> of signaling by the neural G proteins G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> that mediate signaling by G protein coupled neurotransmitter receptors. The G proteins themselves and their downstream signaling pathways are strongly conserved comparing mammalian brain and <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. Genetic studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> show that all three types of G&alpha; proteins signal to regulate neurotransmitter release. <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genetic screens have been used to discover new signaling molecules that regulate neural G protein signaling, including Regulators of G protein Signaling (RGS proteins) that help terminate signaling, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> protein that is required for signaling, and a new G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> effector (Trio&rsquo;s RhoGEF domain). The <emphasis role="italic">in vivo</emphasis> studies of neural signaling in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> suggest a model in which the heterotrimeric G proteins present in a neuron act to integrate signaling through the multiple GPCRs present on the neuron to produce its appropriate output level.</para>
<sect2 id="sec3.1">
<title>Heterotrimeric G proteins that mediate neurotransmitter signaling</title>
<para>I will focus here on the G protein subunits that mediate neurotransmitter signaling, and refer readers to an earlier review for a table listing all G&alpha;, G&beta;, and G&gamma; subunits in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, and for discussion of the large family of specialized <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> G&alpha; proteins found in sensory neurons that mediate chemosensation (see WormBook chapter <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_heterotrimericGproteins/heterotrimericGproteins.html">Heterotrimeric G proteins in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis></ulink> <!--:PMID 18050432-->).</para>
<para>In <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, as in mammals, there are multiple G protein &alpha;, &beta;, and &gamma; subunits that can potentially combine to form a larger number of heterotrimeric combinations. In mammals there are few functional differences between the various &beta; and &gamma; subunits (<link linkend="bib122">Khan et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23406670-->). In <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> only one &beta; subunit homolog is actually used in G protein heterotrimers (<link linkend="bib272">Zwaal et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8752216-->; <link linkend="bib33">Chase et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11250150-->; <link linkend="bib200">Robatzek et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11250160-->; <link linkend="bib254">van der Linden et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11333232-->), and only one &gamma; subunit is expressed outside the chemosensory neurons (<link linkend="bib107">Jansen et al. 2002</link><!--:PMID 11867526-->). Thus in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, as in mammals, functional diversity among G protein heterotrimers rests primarily on which &alpha; subunit is used. Mammals have multiple members of each of four families of &alpha; subunits, while <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has just one member for each of these four &alpha; families (<link linkend="bib106">Jansen et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10192394-->). The four conserved <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> &alpha; subunits, with their corresponding mammalian orthologs and percent sequence identities to them, are: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink> (G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, &gt;80%), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49743;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-30</ulink> (G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, &gt;80%), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47896;class=Protein" role="_blank">GSA-1</ulink> (G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript>, 66%), and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE20692;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-12</ulink> (G&alpha;<subscript>12</subscript>, 52%). These worm G&alpha; proteins are each more similar to their mammalian orthologs than they are to each other. Below I will use the mammalian names to refer to the worm G&alpha; proteins, for example using G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> to refer to its <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink>. The worm G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> proteins are each widely expressed in most or all neurons, plus some muscle and other cells (<link linkend="bib152">Mendel et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 7886455-->; <link linkend="bib213">S&eacute;galat et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 7886454-->; <link linkend="bib175">Park et al., 1997</link><!--:PMID 9272860-->; <link linkend="bib130">Korswagen et al., 1997</link><!--:PMID 9203577-->; <link linkend="bib136">Lackner et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10571228-->; <link linkend="bib10">Bastiani et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14704167-->). G&alpha;<subscript>12</subscript>, in contrast, is expressed in only a small subset of neurons plus some muscle and hypodermal cells (<link linkend="bib253">van der Linden et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12646136-->; <link linkend="bib267">Yau et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14657363-->).</para>
<para>I note as an aside that while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink> appears to be the G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> ortholog in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, there are also two more distantly related G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> homologs that have some functional redundancy with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49147;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink> is co-expressed with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink> in some neurons (<link linkend="bib106">Jansen et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10192394-->) and in early embryonic cells, where these two G&alpha; proteins function redundantly to control mitotic spindle positioning during asymmetric cell divisions (reviewed in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv.2/asymcelldiv.2.html">Polarity establishment, asymmetric division and segregation of fate determinants in early <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> embryos</ulink> <!--:PMID 25548889-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06296;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-7</ulink> is another G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>-related protein that shows expression in many neurons (<link linkend="bib106">Jansen et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10192394-->). The functions of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06296;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-7</ulink> have not been carefully investigated, but in one study <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06296;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-7</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink> were shown to function redundantly to mediate dopamine signaling in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> male copulatory neurons and muscles (<link linkend="bib48">Correa et al., 2012</link>; <!--:PMID 23166505-->).</para>
<para>Studies of mammalian GPCRs demonstrate that any one receptor may activate G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript>, or G&alpha;<subscript>12</subscript>, but will generally not couple to more than one of these G&alpha; types (<link linkend="bib163">Moreira, 2014</link><!--:PMID 24016604-->). Currently it is not possible to predict from the sequence of a GPCR which G&alpha; protein it will activate, so this must be determined experimentally (see <link linkend="sec2.1.2">Section 2.1.2</link>).</para>
<para><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> G&alpha;<subscript>12</subscript>, like mammalian G&alpha;<subscript>12</subscript>, can activate its effector protein RGS-RhoGEF protein (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39724;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHGF-1</ulink> in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>) to in turn activate the small GTPase Rho, and genetic work in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> shows this can regulate a pathway involving diacylglycerol and protein kinase C to increase neurotransmitter release (<link linkend="bib253">van der Linden et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12646136-->; <link linkend="bib267">Yau et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14657363-->; <link linkend="bib94">Hiley et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 17139250-->). However, these results all arise from studies of worms expressing constitutively active mutants of G&alpha;<subscript>12</subscript>, and no defects have yet been observed in worms carrying loss of function mutations in G&alpha;<subscript>12</subscript> or its effector <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39724;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHGF-1</ulink>. Thus the normal physiological functions of the G&alpha;<subscript>12</subscript> pathway in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> remain to be elucidated. I will not further consider G&alpha;<subscript>12</subscript> signaling here, but see <link linkend="bib183">Perez-Mansilla and Nurrish (2009)</link><!--:PMID 19615533-->) for a detailed review of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> G&alpha;<subscript>12</subscript> signaling.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3.2">
<title>Introduction to the genetics of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript></title>
<para>Before delving into the details of the signaling pathways for the three major neural G proteins, I begin with an overview of what these pathways do and a description of the genetic approaches in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> that have been used to study them.</para>
<sect3 id="sec3.2.1">
<title>A simplified overview: G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling regulate neurotransmitter release</title>
<para>The simplified take-home message from genetic analysis of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neurons is that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling inhibits neurotransmitter release, while G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling activate neurotransmitter release or promote synaptic activity (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling appear to affect the localization of specific molecules at presynaptic release sites that regulate the neurotransmitter release machinery itself (<link linkend="bib136">Lackner et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10571228-->; <link linkend="bib168">Nurrish et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10677040-->; <link linkend="bib25">Chan et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22588719-->), while it remains less clear how G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling promotes neurotransmitter release (<link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->). A single neuron expresses many GPCRs (see <link linkend="sec2">Section 2</link>), so at any one time all three pathways may be active simultaneously, and indeed there may be receptors for different neurotransmitters activating a single type of G&alpha; protein simultaneously. Thus G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> sum up signaling by the several GPCRs active on a neuron, and their three downstream signaling pathways function together to compute an appropriate efficiency for the neurotransmitter release machinery in the neuron.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase><link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link></phrase>
</textobject>&fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para><link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link> is a gross simplification. The neurotransmitter release machinery is complex, with distinct pools of small-clear vesicles present at presynaptic termini, as well as dense-core vesicles at non-synaptic sites, and release can occur tonically or after being evoked by depolarization. G&alpha; signaling may differentially affect the various types of vesicle release (<link linkend="bib102">Hu et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 25609620-->). Further, G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling are known from electrophysiological studies to affect activity of specific ion channels, and from studies in other experimental systems to affect gene expression and synaptic structure. These G proteins are expressed not only in neurons but also in other cell types (e.g., muscles). So, clearly signaling by G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> must have effects other than on the neurotransmitter release machinery. Despite this, studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> have focused on the effects of G protein signaling on synaptic neurotransmitter release because genetic experiments demonstrate that they actually affect behavior.</para>
<para>There are multiple lines of evidence that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling affect neurotransmitter release in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, with the most extensive evidence coming from studies of acetylcholine release by ventral chord motor neurons that control locomotion behavior. The four major lines of evidence are: 1) mutations in the G proteins and/or their signaling pathways alter locomotion behavior; 2) mutations in the G proteins and/or their signaling pathways alter response to aldicarb, an inhibitor of the acetylcholinesterase enzyme that clears released acetylcholine from synapses; 3) mutations in the G proteins and/or their signaling pathways alter the localization of GFP-tagged presynaptic proteins at cholinergic synapses; and 4) mutations in the G proteins and/or their signaling pathways cause changes in acetylcholine release that can be measured with electrophysiological methods. The specific studies detailing these lines of evidence for G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> are described and cited below in the remainder of <link linkend="sec3">Section 3</link>. As these details will show, all four lines of experimental evidence have established the effects of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling on acetylcholine release in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, while the effects of G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling on acetylcholine release from <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> ventral cord motor neurons rest on just the first two lines of evidence. However additional lines of evidence for the effects of G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling on neurotransmitter release come from studies of other cell types and species. For example studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ALA;class=Cell" role="_blank">ALA</ulink> neurons show that the G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling pathway affects dense-core vesicle release (<link linkend="bib269">Zhou et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18031683-->), and electrophysiological studies in mammalian and <emphasis role="italic">Drosophila</emphasis> neurons have also established effects of G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling on release of small clear neurotransmitter vesicles (<link linkend="bib249">Trudeau et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8893035-->; <link linkend="bib35">Chen and Regehr, 1997</link><!--:PMID 9348337-->; <link linkend="bib135">Kuromi and Kidokoro, 2000</link><!--:PMID 10939337-->).</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3.2.2">
<title>Isolation of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling mutants</title>
<para>Studies of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neural G protein signaling have been carried out in parallel through both forward and reverse genetics. In the reverse genetic approach, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> homologs of mammalian signaling proteins are knocked out by gene-targeting technologies. Thus, for example, the entire sets of G protein subunit genes and RGS genes have been knocked out and analyzed (<link linkend="bib106">Jansen et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10192394-->; <link linkend="bib93">Hess et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15479638-->). The special power of the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> system, however, is its capacity for large-scale forward genetic screens in which the genome is randomly mutagenized and vast numbers of animals are screened for specific phenotypes associated with neural G protein signaling defects. The initial screens for mutants with general neural G protein signaling defects took advantage of the fact that heterotrimeric G proteins regulate neurotransmitter release from the egg-laying motor neurons and from the cholinergic motor neurons that control locomotion. Thus these screens looked for mutants that fail to lay eggs (<link linkend="bib248">Trent et al., 1983</link><!--:PMID 11813735-->; <link linkend="bib53">Desai and Horvitz, 1989</link><!--:PMID 2721931-->), that lay eggs too frequently (<link linkend="bib8">Bany et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12954868-->), that alter acetylcholine release (<link linkend="bib157">Miller et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8901627-->; <link linkend="bib158">Miller et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10571227-->; <link linkend="bib156">Miller et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 10985349-->; <link linkend="bib217">Sieburth et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16049479-->; <link linkend="bib252">Vashlishan et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18466746-->), that carry suppressors of previously-isolated G protein signaling mutations (<link linkend="bib158">Miller et al., 1999</link>; <!--:PMID 10571227--> <link linkend="bib210">Schade et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489510-->; <link linkend="bib30">Charlie et al., 2006b</link><!--:PMID 16624912-->; <link linkend="bib264">Williams et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17942708-->), or that have hyperactive locomotion (<link linkend="bib210">Schade et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489510-->). Additional screens were for mutants that fail to respond to specific neurotransmitters that signal through GPCRs, including dopamine (<link linkend="bib31">Chase et al., 2004</link>: ) and serotonin (<link linkend="bib81">G&uuml;rel et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23023001-->).</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3.2.3">
<title>Phenotypes of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling mutants</title>
<para>All genetic studies of neural G protein signaling in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> involve assaying mutant phenotypes that arise from G protein signaling defects. Here I describe some of the mutant phenotypes used for this work.</para>
<para>G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> null and partial loss-of-function mutants have a &ldquo;<ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/phenotype/WBPhenotype:0000642#0--10" role="_blank">hyperactive</ulink>&rdquo; phenotype (<link linkend="bib152">Mendel et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 7886455-->; <link linkend="bib213">S&eacute;galat et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 7886454-->), which, as described below, appears to arise from increased neurotransmitter release from neurons throughout the animal. This phenotype can easily be recognized by observing animals growing on a standard laboratory petri dish (<link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link>) and includes body bends that are deeper and more frequent than in the wild type. This defect arises at least in part from increased release of acetylcholine from the ventral cord motor neurons that control locomotion (<link linkend="bib252">Vashlishan et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18466746-->). The hyperactive phenotype also includes an increased frequency of egg-laying behavior, such that animals lay almost all their eggs as soon as they are produced, so that whereas a wild-type animal might carry &sim;12 unlaid eggs on average, a hyperactive mutant might carry only one or two (<link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link>). This defect arises at least in part from increased neurotransmitter release from the HSN motor neurons that stimulate egg laying (<link linkend="bib242">Tanis et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18202365-->). Specific serotonin and dopamine receptors signal through G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> to inhibit locomotion, such that treating worms with sufficiently high concentrations of dopamine or serotonin paralyzes wild-type worms, but hyperactive G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> mutants are resistant to paralysis by serotonin or dopamine (<link linkend="bib213">S&eacute;galat et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 7886454-->; <link linkend="bib31">Chase et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15378064-->; <link linkend="bib81">G&uuml;rel et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23023001-->). As might be expected, since G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> is expressed in many neurons and non-neuronal cells, G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> mutants have a number of additional phenotypic defects, including defects in mitotic spindle movements in early embryonic cells (<link linkend="bib156">Miller and Rand, 2000</link><!--:PMID 11102364-->; <link linkend="bib77">Gotta and Ahringer, 2001</link><!--:PMID 11231580-->) and defects in meiotic maturation of germ cells (<link linkend="bib79">Govindan et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16824915-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="movie1" xreflabel="Movie 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="movie1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>movie 1</phrase>
</textobject> &movie1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> null mutants undergo developmental arrest as young larvae (<link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->), but partial loss-of-function mutants develop to adulthood and show a &ldquo;sluggish&rdquo; phenotype that appears to arise from decreased neurotransmitter release (<link linkend="bib136">Lackner et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10571228-->; <link linkend="bib158">Miller et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10571227-->) from neurons throughout the animal (<link linkend="bib10">Bastiani et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14704167-->). Sluggish animals have less frequent and shallower body bends than in the wild type, and strong loss-of-function or null G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> mutants are virtually paralyzed (<link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link>) (<link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->; <link linkend="bib264">Williams et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17942708-->). This defect results at least in part from decreased acetylcholine release from ventral cord motor neurons (<link linkend="bib136">Lackner et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10571228-->; <link linkend="bib102">Hu et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 25609620-->). Sluggish animals rarely engage in egg-laying behavior, such that adult animals can become bloated with up to &sim;50 unlaid eggs (<link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link>), and this defect arises at least in part from decreased neurotransmitter release from the HSN motor neurons (<link linkend="bib242">Tanis et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18202365-->).</para>
<para>The G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> loss-of-function phenotypes are in many respects precisely the opposite of each other. This interpretation is reinforced by the fact that mutations and transgenes that increase G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling cause a sluggish phenotype essentially indistinguishable from that seen in G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> loss-of-function mutants (<link linkend="bib152">Mendel et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 7886455-->; <link linkend="bib213">S&eacute;galat et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 7886454-->; <link linkend="bib127">Koelle and Horvitz, 1996</link><!--:PMID8548815-->), while transgenes and mutations that increase G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling cause a hyperactive phenotype virtually indistinguishable from that seen in G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> loss-of-function mutants (<link linkend="bib10">Bastiani et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14704167-->; <link linkend="bib82">Hajdu-Cronin et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10421631-->; <link linkend="bib210">Schade et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489510-->; <link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->; <link linkend="bib29">Charlie et al., 2006a</link><!--:PMID 16272411-->; <link linkend="bib264">Williams et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17942708-->; <link linkend="bib149">Matsuki et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16418272-->).</para>
<para>G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> null mutations are lethal (<link linkend="bib130">Korswagen et al., 1997</link><!--:PMID 9203577-->), but mutations that decrease G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling cause a sluggish, near-paralyzed locomotion phenotype similar to that of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> loss-of-function mutants (<link linkend="bib162">Moorman and Plasterk, 2002</link><!--:PMID 12019229-->; <link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->). Mutations and transgenes that increase G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling induce a smoothly sinusoidal hyperactive phenotype, distinctly different from the deep body bends seen in G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> loss-of-function or G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> gain-of-function mutants (<link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->; <link linkend="bib210">Schade et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489510-->; <link linkend="bib29">Charlie et al., 2006a</link><!--:PMID 16272411-->).</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3.2.4">
<title>The neuromuscular junction and the egg-laying synapse are often used to study neural G protein signaling in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis></title>
<para>While G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling affect many <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> behaviors, locomotion and egg-laying behaviors are two readouts of neural G protein signaling that have been frequently used to carry out genetic studies of the mechanism of neural G protein signaling due to the unique advantages of each.</para>
<para>Egg-laying behavior depends on release of serotonin and other neurotransmitters from the HSN motor neuron. G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> have opposing effects on HSN neurotransmitter release (<link linkend="bib242">Tanis et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18202365-->), and mutations in their signaling pathways result in easily scored and quantitated defects in egg laying (<link linkend="bib31">Chase and Koelle, 2004</link><!--:PMID 15313573-->). Thus it has been possible to carry out genetic screens for mutants that are defective or hyperactive for egg-laying behavior to isolate mutants with defects in G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling (<link linkend="bib248">Trent et al., 1983</link><!--:PMID 11813735-->; <link linkend="bib53">Desai and Horvitz, 1989</link><!--:PMID 2721931-->; <link linkend="bib8">Bany et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12954868-->). Such mutants were used to originally discover and subsequently characterize the Regulators of G protein Signaling (RGS proteins) that inhibit most neural G protein signaling in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> and in mammals (<link linkend="bib127">Koelle and Horvitz, 1996</link><!--:PMID 8548815-->; <link linkend="bib82">Hajdu-Cronin et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10421631-->). The neural circuit that controls egg laying is particularly simple and well-characterized, and tools to express transgenes in any cell of the circuit, to monitor activity of the circuit in freely-behaving animals with the fluorescent Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> indicator GCaMP, and to optogenetically manipulate the circuit have all been developed (<link linkend="bib211">Schafer, 2006</link>; <!--:PMID 17094742--> <link linkend="bib62">Emtage et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23152612-->; <link linkend="bib44">Collins and Koelle, 2013</link><!--:PMID 23303953-->).</para>
<para><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> locomotion behavior involves release of acetylcholine from ventral cord motor neurons onto body wall muscles, and G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> all affect acetylcholine release at this neuromuscular junction. The drug aldicarb paralyzes worms by preventing acetylcholine released at this neuromuscular junction from being degraded, and a powerful genetic screen for mutants resistant to aldicarb paralysis has been used to isolate mutants with decreased acetylcholine release that lie in the G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling pathways (<link linkend="bib157">Miller et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8901627-->; <link linkend="bib158">Miller et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10571227-->; <link linkend="bib156">Miller et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 10985349-->). Screens for suppressors of aldicarb-resistant mutants and screens for mutants with hyperactive locomotion were used to isolate mutants with increased signaling in the G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> pathways (<link linkend="bib158">Miller et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10571227-->; <link linkend="bib210">Schade et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489510-->; <link linkend="bib30">Charlie et al., 2006b</link><!--:PMID 16624912-->). Mutations that affect acetylcholine release were used to discover the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> protein that promotes signaling by heterotrimeric G proteins in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> and in mammals (<link linkend="bib156">Miller et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 11102364-->). The cholinergic neuromuscular junctions in the ventral cord have been used for important experiments visualizing the effects of G protein signaling mutations on the localization of synaptic vesicle release proteins (<link linkend="bib136">Lackner et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10571228-->; <link linkend="bib168">Nurrish et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10677040-->; <link linkend="bib25">Chan et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22588719-->). These neuromuscular junctions are also the most accessible synapses for electrophysiological studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, and have allowed studies of the fine details of G protein signaling mutations on neurotransmitter release (<link linkend="bib102">Hu et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 25609620-->).</para>
<para>While mutations in the G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling pathways have powerful effects on egg-laying behavior by affecting neurotransmitter release from the HSN neurons and on locomotion by affecting acetylcholine release from ventral cord motor neurons, it has been hard to identify the GPCRs that activate the G proteins in these neurons. This difficulty is in line with the understanding, described in <link linkend="sec2">Section 2</link>, that an individual neuron appears to express many different GPCRs so that mutations in a single GPCR are expected to have very weak effects compared to mutations in a G protein. In the HSN neuron, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04219;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-6</ulink> neuropeptide receptor signals through G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> to inhibit egg laying, but this effect is only obvious in gain-of-function <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04219;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-6</ulink> mutants, whereas <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04219;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-6</ulink> null mutants do not have detectable defects. In the ventral cord motor neurons, the neuropeptide receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE38443;class=Protein" role="_blank">CKR-2</ulink> and the G protein coupled acetylcholine receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35800;class=Protein" role="_blank">GAR-3</ulink> both appear to signal through G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> to increase acetylcholine release (<link linkend="bib101">Hu et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21745640-->; <link linkend="bib26">Chan J.P. et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23986249-->), while a different G protein coupled acetylcholine receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30134;class=Protein" role="_blank">GAR-2</ulink>, the heterodimeric G protein coupled GABA<subscript>B</subscript> receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43326;class=Protein" role="_blank">GBB-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43384;class=Protein" role="_blank">GBB-2</ulink>, and the dopamine receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39181;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-3</ulink> all appear to signal through G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> to decrease acetylcholine release (<link linkend="bib31">Chase et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15378064-->; <link linkend="bib55">Dittman and Kaplan, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18614679-->). Mutations in these ventral cord motor neuron GPCRs have detectable effects on locomotion (<link linkend="bib31">Chase et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15378064-->; <link linkend="bib55">Dittman and Kaplan, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18614679-->; <link linkend="bib101">Hu et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21745640-->; <link linkend="bib26">Chan J.P. et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23986249-->), but knocking out a single one of these GPCRs, as expected, has much weaker effects than does knocking out its downstream G protein (<link linkend="bib152">Mendel et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 7886455-->; <link linkend="bib213">S&eacute;galat et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 7886454-->; <link linkend="bib20">Brundage et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8630258-->).</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3.3">
<title>The mechanism of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling</title>
<para>In mammalian cells, active G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>-GTP is classically known to signal by directly binding to and activating its effector, the transmembrane enzyme phospholipase C&beta; (PLC&beta;), which hydrolyzes the membrane lipid phosphatidylinositol 4,5 bisphosphate (PIP<subscript>2</subscript>) to generate the soluble molecule inositol 1,4,5 trisphosphate (IP<subscript>3</subscript>) and the membrane lipid diacylglycerol (DAG). IP<subscript>3</subscript> can go on to increase intracellular Ca<superscript>2+</superscript>, which along with DAG can bind and activate protein kinase C (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>; reviewed by <link linkend="bib207">S&aacute;nchez-Fern&aacute;ndez et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 24440667-->). Prior to studies of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, the only confirmed direct G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> effector was PLC&beta;. Genetic analysis of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> (previously reviewed by <link linkend="bib183">Perez-Mansilla and Nurrish, 2009</link><!--:PMID 19615533-->) supported the idea that PLC&beta; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36909;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-8</ulink> in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>) is a physiologically important effector (<link linkend="bib136">Lackner et al., 1999</link>, <link linkend="bib158">Miller et al., 1999</link>; <link linkend="bib10">Bastiani et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14704167-->). However, these same studies also suggested that there had to be additional G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> effector(s) since the phenotypes of PLC&beta; null mutants were much less severe than those of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> null mutants.</para>
<para>The missing G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> effector was identified as the Trio RhoGEF through genetic screens for suppressors of the slow growth and hyperactive locomotion phenotypes caused by excessive G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> pathway activity (<link linkend="bib264">Williams et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17942708-->). Analysis using loss- and gain-of-function mutants in various double-mutant combinations showed that for control of growth, locomotion, and egg laying, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signals through both PLC&beta; and Trio RhoGEF. Knocking out either effector alone only partially blocks G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling, while knocking out both appears to completely block G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling (<link linkend="bib264">Williams et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17942708-->). Trio RhoGEF proved to be as or more important than the classical PLC&beta; effector pathway for multiple effects of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling, including effects on growth, locomotion, and egg laying. Concomitant with the discovery of Trio RhoGEF as a G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> effector in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, biochemical and structural studies demonstrated that mammalian G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> binds and activates the orthologous mammalian RhoGEF proteins (<link linkend="bib147a">Lutz et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18096806-->; <link linkend="bib203">Rojas et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17606614-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase><link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link></phrase>
</textobject>&fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Two mechanisms for signaling downstream of the Trio RhoGEF effector of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> have been identified based on <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genetics (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). First, while PLC&beta; enzyme activity directly produces DAG, Trio RhoGEF can also increase DAG levels by an indirect mechanism. Trio RhoGEF activates the RhoA protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25369;class=Protein" role="_blank">RHO-1</ulink>, allowing it to directly bind and inhibit the diacylglycerol kinase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE08039;class=Protein" role="_blank">DGK-1</ulink>, blocking the first step in metabolic clearance of DAG, its phosphorylation to produce phosphatidic acid (PA) (<link linkend="bib151">McMullan et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16391233-->). Thus both effectors for G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> collaborate to increase DAG levels. Although Rho activity in mammals is principally known to regulate other processes, such as actin cytoskeleton dynamics and transcription, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genetics demonstrates that in its role mediating neurotransmitter signaling downstream of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, a major physiologically significant role of Rho seems to be increasing DAG levels.</para>
<para>A second downstream mediator of the effects of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>/RhoGEF/RhoA signaling is the sphingosine kinase SphK (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47276;class=Protein" role="_blank">SPHK-1</ulink> in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>). SphK catalyzes the phosphorylation of the membrane lipid sphingosine (Sph) to sphingosine-1-phosphate (Sph1P), a signaling lipid that among other functions promotes neurotransmitter release (<link linkend="bib169">Okada et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 18694820-->). In ventral cord cholinergic neurons, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling via the Trio RhoGEF <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE19465;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-73</ulink> causes an increase in the perisynaptic localization of SphK, and this in turn appears to increase acetylcholine release (<link linkend="bib25">Chan et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22588719-->). In a separate study, it was found that G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling recruits SphK to synapses via calcium influx using a mechanism involving the calcium binding protein CIB (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44485;class=Protein" role="_blank">CALM-1</ulink> in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>) (<link linkend="bib25">Chan et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22588719-->). The ability of SphK to increase neurotransmitter release depends on both its localization to perisynaptic regions and its ability to generate sphingosine 1-phosphate (<link linkend="bib25">Chan et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22588719-->). At this point, the details of the mechanism by which Trio RhoGEF leads to recruitment of SphK to perisynaptic regions, and specifically the relationship between the calcium and Trio RhoGEF effects on Sphk localization, remain to be determined.</para>
<para>How does the second messenger DAG produced by G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling lead to the ultimate effect of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling, an increase in neurotransmitter release? Two DAG- binding proteins appear to mediate independent effects. One of these, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34623;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-13</ulink>, is a protein essential for synaptic vesicle priming that facilitates neurotransmitter release by binding to the SNARE protein complexes that mediate vesicle fusion (<link linkend="bib105">James and Martin, 2013</link><!--:PMID 24363652-->). Binding of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34623;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-13</ulink> to DAG in the membrane may help recruit it to synaptic membranes. The evidence for G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> acting through <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34623;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-13</ulink> includes the observations that in ventral cord motor neurons, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> activation of acetylcholine release depends on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34623;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-13</ulink>, and that G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> activation or addition of DAG analogs induces overexpressed UNC-13S::GFP to relocalize from a diffuse pattern in axons to punctate structures at synapses (<link linkend="bib136">Lackner et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10571228-->). These effects can be abrogated by a mutation that blocks the ability of overexpressed UNC-13S::GFP to bind DAG. Recent electrophysiological studies provide perhaps the strongest evidence that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34623;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-13</ulink> functions in G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling to promote acetylcholine release from ventral cord motor neurons, with both the long and short isoforms of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34623;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-13</ulink> differentially affecting tonic and evoked release (<link linkend="bib102">Hu et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 25609620-->). Nevertheless, the extent to which <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34623;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-13</ulink> mediates the behavioral effects of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling has remained unclear. The recent development of methods for precise genome engineering using CRISPR/Cas9 provide an opportunity to mutate the DAG binding site of native <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34623;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-13</ulink> and potentially resolve this issue.</para>
<para>A second DAG binding protein that mediates effects of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling in ventral cord motor neurons is protein kinase C (PKC) (<link linkend="bib218">Sieburth et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17128266-->). PKC appears to affect release of neuropeptide-containing dense-core vesicles, although the targets via which PKC does this remain unknown. PKC does not appear to directly affect release of acetylcholine from small-clear synaptic vesicles. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34623;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-13</ulink> appears to affect small-clear vesicles, and there are differences of opinion as to whether it directly affects dense-core vesicles release (<link linkend="bib218">Sieburth et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17128266-->; <link linkend="bib223">Speese et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17553987-->). Thus the current model is that G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling produces DAG to act via two different DAG-binding proteins, PKC and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34623;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-13</ulink>, that together activate release of dense-core and synaptic vesicles (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>).</para>
<para>A key observation about the role of DAG in G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling is that treating G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> mutant worms with the DAG analogs known as phorbol esters rescues the paralysis of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> null and strong reduction-of-function mutants to wild-type levels of coordinated locomotion (<link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link>; <!--:PMID 15489511--> <link linkend="bib264">Williams et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17942708-->). The effectiveness of such non-localized phorbol ester treatment suggests that DAG is a &ldquo;licensing factor&rdquo; that promotes neurotransmitter release, i.e., that DAG need not be produced focally at synapses. Further, the fact that G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> mutants can be rescued by phorbol ester treatment demonstrates that developmental defects do not contribute to the strong paralysis of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> strong loss-of-function or null mutants.</para>
<para>How does the other second messenger produced by G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling, sphingosine 1-phosphate, increase neurotransmitter release? An initial study suggested the effect of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> on neurotransmitter release via SphK appeared to be entirely independent and parallel to the ability of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling to increase neurotransmitter release via increasing DAG levels (<link linkend="bib25">Chan et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22588719-->). However, a subsequent study suggested SphK is essential for G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling to relocalize UNC-13S::GFP to synapses (<link linkend="bib25">Chan and Sieburth, 2012</link><!--:PMID 22588719-->), and UNC-13S::GFP relocalization also appears to depend on DAG (<link linkend="bib136">Lackner et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10571228-->). So, more work remains to clarify the relationship of DAG and SphK signaling downstream of G&alpha; in regulating neurotransmitter release.</para>
<para>Two upstream regulators of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> were identified through <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genetic analysis. The Regulator of G protein signaling (RGS) protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30491;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-16</ulink> behaves as a specific inhibitor of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling (<link linkend="bib82">Hajdu-Cronin et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10421631-->). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> protein promotes G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling (<link linkend="bib156">Miller et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 11102364-->). I will elaborate on studies of RGS proteins and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> in <link linkend="sec3.6">Section 3.6</link> and <link linkend="sec3.7">Section 3.7</link>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3.4">
<title>The mechanism of G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling</title>
<para>The G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling pathway (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>) has been intensively studied for decades in mammalian cells using biochemical approaches (<link linkend="bib74">Godinho et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 25859216-->). G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> activated by GPCRs binds and activates its effector, the transmembrane enzyme adenylyl cyclase, which generates the second messenger cyclic AMP (cAMP). cAMP binds the regulatory subunits of protein kinase A (PKA), causing them to dissociate from and thus activate the catalytic subunit, which can then phosphorylate various target proteins. Signaling is terminated in part through the action of the enzyme phosphodiesterase to hydrolyze cAMP. G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> is unique among G&alpha; isoforms in that no RGS protein is known to act on G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> to help it hydrolyze GTP, so the slow intrinsic GTPase activity of G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> is apparently used to terminate G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> activity.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase><link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link></phrase>
</textobject>&fig4legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Genetic studies show that the same pathway delineated by biochemical studies in mammals also operates in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> motor neurons (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>; <link linkend="bib210">Schade et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489510-->). Initial studies showed that transgenic overexpression of constitutively-active G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> kills neurons through a cAMP-dependent mechanism, as the killing could be suppressed with mutations in the adenylyl cyclase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00955;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACY-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib130">Korswagen et al., 1997</link><!--:PMID 9203577-->; <link linkend="bib15">Berger et al., 1998</link><!--:PMID 9526004-->; <link linkend="bib162">Moorman and Plasterk, 2002</link><!--:PMID 12019229-->). G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> null mutants are lethal (<link linkend="bib130">Korswagen et al., 1997</link><!--:PMID 9203577-->), but mutants with increased G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling are viable, and have provided important tools for genetic analysis of G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling. Mutations that increase G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling have been identified in G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> itself (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47896;class=Protein" role="_blank">GSA-1</ulink> in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>), adenylyl cyclase (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00955;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACY-1</ulink>), protein kinase A (loss of the regulatory subunit <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04821;class=Protein" role="_blank">KIN-2</ulink> causes constitutive activity of the catalytic subunit <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31762;class=Protein" role="_blank">KIN-1</ulink>), and in phosphodiesterase (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33440;class=Protein" role="_blank">PDE-4</ulink>) (<link linkend="bib210">Schade et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489510-->; <link linkend="bib30">Charlie et al., 2006b</link><!--:PMID 16624912-->). Increased G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling results in smoothly hyperactive sinusoidal locomotion, which is distinct from the hyperactive locomotion with abnormally deep body bends induced by loss of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling or increased G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling (<link linkend="bib210">Schade et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489510-->). Epistasis analysis using G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling pathway mutants supports the idea that G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> functions in a pathway analogous to the mammalian G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling pathway that had been characterized biochemically (<link linkend="bib210">Schade et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489510-->; <link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->).</para>
<para>G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> pathway activity requires the guanine nucleotide exchange factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink>, (<link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->), although it remains unclear if this is due to the function of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> as chaperone or due to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> acting as a non-receptor nucleotide exchange protein.</para>
<para>The ultimate effect of G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling in neurons appears to be to promote neurotransmitter release. <link linkend="bib210">Schade et al. (2015)</link><!--:PMID 15489510--> showed that activating G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling in both neurons and muscles using gain-of-function mutations appears to induce acetylcholine release from motor neurons, although <link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al. (2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->) showed that loss of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000068;class=Gene" role="_blank">acy-1</ulink></emphasis> just in neurons did not seem to affect neurotransmitter release. Separate studies in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ALA;class=Cell" role="_blank">ALA</ulink> neurons show that PKA activation can induce dense-core vesicle release (<link linkend="bib269">Zhou et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18031683-->), so G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling may be able to activate neurotransmitter release via both synaptic and dense-core vesicles. The downstream targets of phosphorylation by PKA that increase vesicle release remain unknown.</para>
<para>G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling may operate in muscles, in addition to neurons, to control <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> behavior. Null mutants for the adenylyl cyclase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00955;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACY-1</ulink> show two separable defects: larval arrest and near-paralysis. In an <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000068;class=Gene" role="_blank">acy-1</ulink></emphasis> null mutant, re-expression of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000068;class=Gene" role="_blank">acy-1</ulink></emphasis> in either muscles or neurons can rescue the larval arrest, but neither is sufficient to rescue paralysis, indicating that <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000068;class=Gene" role="_blank">acy-1</ulink></emphasis> may be required in both neurons and muscles for proper locomotion (<link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->). Rescue experiments also indicate that G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling is required for adult neural function, but is not required for neural development, since induced expression of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000068;class=Gene" role="_blank">acy-1</ulink></emphasis> in paralyzed animals lacking neural <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000068;class=Gene" role="_blank">acy-1</ulink></emphasis> can restore locomotion behavior in these animals (<link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->).</para>
<para>Genetic studies initiated to study G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling have led to a broader genetic analysis of the <emphasis role="italic">in vivo</emphasis> functions of cAMP in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. While the adenylyl cyclase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00955;class=Protein" role="_blank">ACY-1</ulink> mediates all known effects of G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling (<link linkend="bib210">Schade et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489510-->), there are other adenylyl cyclase isoforms in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> that appear to generate a G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript>-independent pool of cAMP that also affect locomotion and larval growth (<link linkend="bib30">Charlie et al., 2006b</link><!--:PMID 1461419-->). cAMP is an important negative regulator of sleep-like states throughout the animal kingdom (<link linkend="bib271">Zimmerman et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18538867-->), and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> pathway activating mutants are being used to study sleep-like states in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib14">Belfer et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23633751-->). <link linkend="bib72">Ghosh-Roy et al., (2010)</link><!--:PMID 20203177--> has also used G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> pathway mutants to study the role of cAMP in axon regeneration.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3.5">
<title>The mechanism of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling</title>
<para>The mechanism of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>) is poorly understood and remains an area ripe for further investigation using the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> system. Biochemical studies in mammals have shown that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> is expressed throughout the nervous system and is by orders of magnitude the most abundant G&alpha; protein in neurons, constituting &sim;1.5% of membrane protein in the brain (<link linkend="bib229">Sternweis and Robishaw, 1984</link><!--:PMID 6438083-->). Despite efforts to identify G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> binding proteins that might function as effectors for G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> or its paralogs (<link linkend="bib36">Chen et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10480904-->; <link linkend="bib240">Takesono et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10559191-->; <link linkend="bib49">Cuppen et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 18629017-->), no such protein has been validated as a bona fide effector of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>. Activation of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> releases G&beta;&gamma; subunits, allowing them to activate specific K<superscript>+</superscript> channels and inhibit specific Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> channels, resulting in inhibition of neural activity (<link linkend="bib193">Reuveny et al., 1994</link><!--:PMID 8022483-->; <link linkend="bib92">Herlitze et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8637576-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase><link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link></phrase>
</textobject>&fig5legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The ultimate effect of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neurons is to inhibit neurotransmitter release, and this has been studied in detail in ventral cord motor neurons, where G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling inhibits acetylcholine release (<link linkend="bib168">Nurrish et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10677040-->; <link linkend="bib158">Miller et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10571227-->; <link linkend="bib29">Charlie et al., 2006a</link><!--:PMID 16272411-->; <link linkend="bib252">Vashlishan et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18466746-->), and in HSN neurons, where G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling inhibits release of serotonin and other neurotransmitters that stimulate egg laying (<link linkend="bib242">Tanis et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18202365-->). G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling have the opposite effects on locomotion, egg laying, and a variety of other behaviors (<link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link>), suggesting that in general, while G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling promotes neurotransmitter release (see <link linkend="sec3.2">Section 3.2</link>), G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> has an opposing effect of inhibiting neurotransmitter release.</para>
<para>Activation of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling in ventral cord motor neurons appears to increase the localization of the synaptic vesicle priming protein UNC-13S to presynaptic termini, as seen by visualizing a fusion of UNC-13S to the green fluorescent protein (<link linkend="bib136">Lackner et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 105712-->). A G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> loss-of-function mutation also causes an increase in localization of this UNC-13S::GFP protein to presynaptic termini (<link linkend="bib168">Nurrish et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10677-->). This result suggests that that G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> oppose each other at a mechanistic level. The effects of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> on UNC-13S::GFP localization both depend on the diacylglycerol (DAG) binding site of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34623;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-13</ulink> (<link linkend="bib136">Lackner et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 105712-->; <link linkend="bib168">Nurrish et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10677-->). Thus it is assumed that the increase in DAG levels produced by G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling cause the observed changes in UNC-13S::GFP localization. G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling could affect <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34623;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-13</ulink>::GFP and inhibit neurotransmitter release by decreasing DAG levels (<link linkend="bib168">Nurrish et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10677-->). However, no biochemical experiments have demonstrated any effect of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> on DAG or on the enzymes that generate or degrade DAG (<link linkend="bib112">Jose and Koelle, 2005</link><!--:PMID 15563467-->; <link linkend="bib183">Perez-Mansilla and Nurrish, 2009</link><!--:PMID 19615533-->).</para>
<para>While genetic studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> have not clarified the downstream mechanism of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling, they have identified novel upstream regulators of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>. The RGS protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46003;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-10</ulink> is expressed in all neurons, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46003;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-10</ulink> null mutants show sluggish locomotion and egg-laying defects due to increased G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling (<link linkend="bib127">Koelle and Horvitz, 1996</link><!--:PMID 8548815-->). There are other RGS proteins (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27794;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41393;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29404;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-7</ulink>) that additionally inhibit G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> in specific cell types or under specific circumstances (see <link linkend="sec3.7">Section 3.7</link>). G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling is promoted by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink>, working in combination with a GPR-domain containing protein (<link linkend="sec3.6">Section 3.6</link>). As in the case of RIC-8&rsquo;s effect on G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling (<link linkend="sec3.3">Section 3.3</link>), it is unclear whether RIC-8&rsquo;s effect on G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling reflects its nucleotide exchange activity, its G&alpha; chaperone function (<link linkend="bib71">Gabay et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22114146-->; <link linkend="bib26">Chan P. et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23431197-->), or both.</para>
<sect3 id="sec3.5.1">
<title>Does G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> have an effector?</title>
<para>One view is that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> has no effector, and that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling occurs simply by release of G&beta;&gamma; subunits that would then be entirely responsible for further downstream signaling by regulating K<superscript>+</superscript> and Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> channels. The plausibility of such a scheme is bolstered by careful genetic studies of heterotrimeric G protein signaling in yeast, in which mating pheromone signaling through a heterotrimeric G protein is indeed carried out by activation of a G&alpha; protein whose principal function is simply to release G&beta;&gamma; so that G&beta;&gamma; can induce further signaling events (<link linkend="bib56">Dohlman and Thorner, 2001</link><!--:PMID 11395421-->).</para>
<para>Genetic studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> strongly suggest that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling does not proceed purely through G&beta;&gamma; effectors, and that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> must also signal directly through its own yet-to-be-discovered effectors. The only study of G&beta;&gamma; effectors in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> showed that when the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04219;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-6</ulink> neuropeptide receptor activates G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> in the HSN neurons, the resulting inhibition of egg laying requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47227;class=Protein" role="_blank">IRK-1</ulink>, a homolog of mammalian G&beta;&gamma;-activated K<superscript>+</superscript> channels, and that no other such K<superscript>+</superscript> channel is required (<link linkend="bib62">Emtage et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23152612-->). However, this same study also demonstrated that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47227;class=Protein" role="_blank">IRK-1</ulink> does not mediate inhibition of egg laying when other methods are used to activate G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, suggesting that other effectors besides K<superscript>+</superscript> channels must mediate G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling. This study leaves open the possibility that these other effectors could be additional G&beta;&gamma; effectors such as Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> channels. However, other genetic results argue in favor of effectors for G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> itself.</para>
<para>First, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> release the identical G&beta;&gamma; subunits, as there is only one G&beta;&gamma; isoform generally expressed in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neurons, yet activation of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, acting in the same neurons, have exactly opposite effects on neurotransmitter release and behavior (<link linkend="bib136">Lackner et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10571228-->; <link linkend="bib168">Nurrish et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10677040-->; <link linkend="bib242">Tanis et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18202365-->). To argue that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling principally results from released G&beta;&gamma; inhibiting neural activity, one needs to explain how G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling does not give the same result. This discrepancy might result from the far greater abundance of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, or by supposing that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> reside in different membrane microdomains, but so far there is no actual data to support either idea.</para>
<para>Second, the genetics of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> does not match the genetics of G&beta;&gamma;-mediated pheromone signaling pathway in yeast. In the yeast pheromone signaling pathway, a null mutant for the G&alpha; subunit results in constitutive signaling, as G&alpha; is no longer present to sequester G&beta;&gamma; and inhibit its ability to signal (<link linkend="bib262">Whiteway et al., 1989</link><!--:PMID 2536595-->). Conversely, transgenic overexpression of yeast G&alpha; inhibits pheromone signaling, apparently by increasing the pool of G&alpha; available to associate with and inhibit G&beta;&gamma; (<link linkend="bib43">Cole et al., 1990</link><!--:PMID 2105453-->). The analogous experiments in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> with G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> give precisely the opposite results. G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> null mutations appear to result in a loss of signaling, not constitutive signaling (<link linkend="bib152">Mendel et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 7886455-->; <link linkend="bib213">S&eacute;galat et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 7886454-->), and overexpression of wild-type G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> appears to result in constitutive signaling, not loss of signaling (<link linkend="bib152">Mendel et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 7886455-->). These results are exactly analogous to those obtained from genetic studies of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib20">Brundage et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8630258-->), a case in which it is clear that downstream signaling is due to G&alpha; effectors, not G&beta;&gamma; effectors.</para>
<para>Could it be that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signals by directly binding to and inhibiting adenylyl cyclase? Adenylyl cyclase is the effector directly activated by G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> (see <link linkend="sec3.3">Section 3.3</link>.), and it can also be directly bound and inhibited by members of the G&alpha;<subscript>i/o</subscript> family of G&alpha; proteins, at least in cultured cells. Indeed, G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> overexpressed in cultured cells has been shown to inhibit one isoform of adenylyl cyclase (<link linkend="bib165">N&auml;sman et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12472880-->). While this hypothesis is intriguing, there is currently no genetic evidence that inhibition of adenylyl cyclase is a physiologically relevant mechanism for G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling. If G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaled by inhibiting adenylyl cyclase, we might expect that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling would show precisely opposite effects in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genetic experiments. However, this is not the case (see <link linkend="sec3.3">Section 3.3</link>), and G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling rather shows far more precise opposition to the effects of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling.</para>
<para>Could it be that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signals by directly binding to and regulating one of the components of the G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling pathway, thus neatly solving the problem of identifying the G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> effector and explaining how G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling opposes G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling (<link linkend="sec3.5">Section 3.5</link>)? Two specific G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling pathway proteins (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>) have been proposed as G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> effectors: DGK and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30491;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-16</ulink>. First, all genetic studies are consistent with the possibility that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> could signal by activating diacylglycerol kinase (DGK), the enzyme that terminates G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling by destroying the G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> second messenger diacylglycerol. However, all efforts to demonstrate a biochemical effect of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> on DGK activity have proven negative (<link linkend="bib112">Jose and Koelle, 2005</link><!--:PMID 15563467-->; <link linkend="bib183">Perez-Mansilla and Nurrish, 2009</link><!--:PMID 19615533-->). The second hypothesis is that the effector for G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> could be the G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>-specific RGS protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30491;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-16</ulink>. An elegant model based on both genetic analysis and structural features of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30491;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-16</ulink> protein complex proposes that inactive G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> sequesters <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30491;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-16</ulink>, and activation of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> releases <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30491;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-16</ulink> to inhibit G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> (<link linkend="bib200">Robatzek et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11250160-->). However, no biochemical studies of either the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> proteins nor their mammalian equivalents has produced any support for this model.</para>
<para>If G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> indeed signals directly through its own effectors, why have these effectors not yet been identified? Known effectors for other G proteins are often multi-subunit membrane protein complexes, and the cDNA expression library screening methods that have been employed in attempts to identify G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> effectors (<link linkend="bib36">Chen et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10480904-->; <link linkend="bib240">Takesono et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10559191-->; <link linkend="bib49">Cuppen et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 18629017-->) are not well suited for finding such proteins. Genetic screens in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> for G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling proteins would have failed to identify G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> effectors if there are multiple redundant effectors, such that mutating a single effector gene causes little reduction in G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling. In addition, if a G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> effector is essential for viability or reproduction, mutating such an effector would not produce animals that could be detected and recovered in a genetic screen. Because there are perfectly reasonable explanations why a G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> effector may have eluded discovery, the absence of such a discovery at this point should not be taken as evidence that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> effectors do not exist.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3.6">
<title>The relationship between G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling</title>
<para>G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling all operate at the same time in the same neurons, and <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link> presents a model showing them acting in parallel to each other until they intersect downstream by ultimately all regulating neurotransmitter release. However, genetic epistasis experiments have been used to examine the relationship between the three G protein signaling pathways, and other relationships between the G protein signaling pathways are also consistent with these genetic results.</para>
<para>Double mutants for G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> resemble G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> single mutants, and this and results from other double-mutant combinations are consistent with the interpretation that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling acts to inhibit G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling (<link linkend="bib82">Hajdu-Cronin et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10421631-->; <link linkend="bib158">Miller et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10571227-->; <link linkend="bib29">Charlie et al., 2006a</link><!--:PMID 16272411-->). More specifically, this means that G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling could inhibit the G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> pathway at any level, upstream of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, at the level of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, or at any level downstream of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>. Only molecular experiments will ultimately be able to distinguish between these possibilities.</para>
<para>The relationship between G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling has been investigated by combining mutations that increase signaling in one pathway with mutations that block signaling in the other pathway (<link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->; <link linkend="bib29">Charlie et al., 2006a</link><!--:PMID 16272411-->). This was done in both directions (i.e., a G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> pathway gain-of-function mutation combined with a G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> null mutation, and also a G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> gain-of-function mutation combined with a G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> pathway null mutation). The results of these experiments do not yield a simple epistatic relationship between the two signaling pathways, but do yield several important insights. First, the G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> pathway is virtually completely dependent on the G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> pathway to exert its effects on locomotion (<link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->). Second, the G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> pathway can still promote locomotion in the absence of a functional G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> pathway, but the resulting locomotion is uncoordinated (<link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->). Third, phorbol esters (analogs of the DAG ultimately produced by the G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> pathway) can also promote uncoordinated locomotion in the absence of a functional G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> pathway, suggesting G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling regulates locomotion downstream of DAG production (<link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->). Fourth, the G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> pathways have distinct effects in driving locomotion, one line of evidence for which is that loss of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling appears to strongly reduce acetylcholine release from motor neurons while loss of G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling does not (<link linkend="bib29">Charlie et al., 2006a</link><!--:PMID 16272411-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3.7">
<title>Receptor-independent activation of heterotrimeric G proteins</title>
<para>An important contribution of the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> system was the discovery of the receptor-independent G&alpha; chaperone and activator <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink>, which was first identified in a genetic screen for mutants with reduced acetylcholine release from ventral cord motor neurons (<link linkend="bib157">Miller et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8901627-->). Genetic studies showed that reduction of function mutations in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> and G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> have similar phenotypes and were consistent with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> acting upstream of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> to promote G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling (<link linkend="bib156">Miller et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 11102364-->). Subsequent genetic studies demonstrated that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> also appears to promote G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling (<link linkend="bib197">Reynolds et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15489511-->) and G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling (<link linkend="bib156">Miller and Rand, 2000</link><!--:PMID 11102364-->; <link linkend="bib98">Hofler and Koelle, 2011</link><!--:PMID 21832186-->).</para>
<para>Biochemical studies of mammalian <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> have identified two mechanisms by which <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> can promote G&alpha; signaling. First, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> can act as a nucleotide exchange factor to convert inactive G&alpha;-GDP to active G&alpha;-GTP (<link linkend="bib241">Tall et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12509430-->; <link linkend="bib27">Chan et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21467038-->). Unlike GPCRs, which are transmembrane proteins that act as nucleotide exchange factors to activate G&alpha;&beta;&gamma; heterotrimers, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> is a soluble protein and will not act on the heterotrimer, but rather can only activate free G&alpha;-GDP. This leads to the model depicted in <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link> in which a G&alpha;&beta;&gamma; heterotrimer would need to initially be activated by a GPCR to generate G&alpha;-GTP, but after GTP hydrolysis the inactive G&alpha;-GDP produced might be reactivated by the nucleotide exchange activity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink>, thus prolonging signaling.</para>
<para>The second mechanism by which <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> can activate G&alpha; signaling is by simply stabilizing G&alpha; proteins. Knocking out <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> in mammalian cells causes dramatic reductions in the levels of G&alpha; proteins (<link linkend="bib71">Gabay et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22114146-->). Biochemical studies show <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> acts as a chaperone to help fold nascent G&alpha; proteins (<link linkend="bib26">Chan P. et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23431197-->). It has not yet been determined if <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> mutations in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> similarly cause reductions of G&alpha; protein levels. The genetics of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> are consistent with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> promoting G&alpha; signaling either by simply stabilizing G&alpha; proteins, by acting as a nucleotide exchange factor, or by both mechanisms.</para>
<para>Another type of receptor-independent activator for G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> are proteins containing a short motif that binds specifically to G&alpha; proteins of the G&alpha;<subscript>i/o</subscript> subfamily and that is known either as the GPR (G protein regulatory) or GoLoco motif (<link linkend="bib216">Siderovski et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10470031-->; <link linkend="bib184">Peterson et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 10969064-->). <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has three such proteins. The two very similar and functionally redundant <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00107;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> proteins act in early embryonic cells with G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> to regulate spindle positioning during asymmetric cell divisions (<link linkend="bib45">Colombo et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12750478-->; <link linkend="bib78">Gotta et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12814548-->; <link linkend="bib225">Srinivasan et al., 2003</link><!--: PMD 12730122-->). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04472;class=Protein" role="_blank">AGS-3</ulink> protein acts with G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> to regulate function of adult neurons (<link linkend="bib98">Hofler and Koelle, 2011</link><!--:PMID 21832186-->). Biochemical studies of mammalian GPR/GoLoco proteins emphasize the fact that when these proteins bind G&alpha;-GDP, they inhibit nucleotide exchange, which would suggest that they prevent formation of active G&alpha;-GTP and thus inhibit signaling (<link linkend="bib216">Siderovski et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10470031-->; <link linkend="bib184">Peterson et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 10969064-->). However, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genetic studies clearly demonstrate that precisely the opposite is true, since <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24910;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/2 promote G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> activity in embryonic cell divisions and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04472;class=Protein" role="_blank">AGS-3</ulink> also promotes G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling in adult neurons (<link linkend="bib45">Colombo et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12750478-->; <link linkend="bib78">Gotta et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12814548-->; <link linkend="bib225">Srinivasan et al., 2003</link><!--: PMD 12730122-->; <link linkend="bib98">Hofler and Koelle, 2011</link><!--:PMID 21832186-->). The apparent conflict between these results can be resolved by the findings that all known functions of the GPR/GoLoco proteins in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> also require <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink>, along with the biochemical result that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> can act as a nucleotide exchange factor on the complex between G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>-GDP and a GPR/GoLoco protein to produce active G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>-GTP (<link linkend="bib246">Thomas et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18541531-->). Thus an attractive model is that when active G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>-GTP hydrolyzes GTP to become G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>-GDP, the function of the GPR/GoLoco protein is to bind G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>-GDP, preventing it from reassociating with G&beta;&gamma;, which would have terminated signaling, and rather to present G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>-GDP to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> for nucleotide exchange to convert it back to active G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>-GTP (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). The net result would be to prolong signaling that had been initiated earlier by a GPCR.</para>
<para>The <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> GPR/GoLoco protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04472;class=Protein" role="_blank">AGS-3</ulink> is of particular interest as it has a close mammalian brain ortholog, AGS3, and a role in mediating behavioral response to food deprivation. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04472;class=Protein" role="_blank">AGS-3</ulink> is expressed in most or all <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> neurons and is required for several different behavioral changes that normally occur in response to short-term food deprivation (<link linkend="bib98">Hofler and Koelle, 2011</link><!--:PMID 21832186-->). Biochemical studies show that over the first few hours of food deprivation, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04472;class=Protein" role="_blank">AGS-3</ulink> protein from <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> lysates changes from a detergent-insoluble form to a detergent-solubilizable form, indicating that a physical change in the protein occurs. These results lead to a model in which food deprivation leads to a physical change in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04472;class=Protein" role="_blank">AGS-3</ulink>, allowing it to activate G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling to induce behavioral changes appropriate for the food-deprived state of the animal. It will be fascinating to see if this role of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04472;class=Protein" role="_blank">AGS-3</ulink> in mediating response to food deprivation is conserved in mammals (<link linkend="bib99">Hofler and Koelle, 2012</link><!--:PMID 24058824-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3.8">
<title>Regulators of G protein signaling inhibit G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling</title>
<para>Another important contribution of the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> system was the discovery and characterization of the family of Regulator of G protein Signaling (RGS) proteins. The first RGS protein, Sst2p, was identified in yeast (<link linkend="bib54">Dietzel and Kurjan, 1987</link><!--:PMID 2830483-->), but it was not clear that it had any homologs in higher eukaryotes. Genetic studies identified the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> RGS protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46003;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-10</ulink> as an inhibitor of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling, and comparison of Sst2p and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46003;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-10</ulink> allowed the discovery of an &ldquo;RGS domain&rdquo; conserved between the two and that is also found in a large family of proteins in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> and mammals (<link linkend="bib127">Koelle and Horvitz, 1996</link><!--:PMID 8548815-->). Biochemical studies showed that the RGS domain binds directly to G&alpha; proteins, and by stabilizing the transition state for GTP hydrolysis, inactivates signaling by driving the conversion of active G&alpha;-GTP to the inactive species G&alpha;-GDP (<link linkend="bib16">Berman et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8910288-->; <link linkend="bib244">Tesmer et al., 1997</link><!--:PMID 9108480-->). GTPase activators were previously known for the small ras-like G proteins, which have structural similarity to the GTPase domain of G&alpha; proteins but lack a catalytic arginine residue that G&alpha; proteins use for GTP hydrolysis. Thus small G proteins are unable to convert GTP to GDP at a meaningful rate without first binding a GTPase activating protein that inserts an arginine residue into their active site (<link linkend="bib144">Li and Zhang, 2004</link><!--:PMID 15236956-->). In contrast, G&alpha; subunits of heterotrimeric G proteins were initially thought to not require help from any GTPase activating proteins to convert to their inactive GDP-bound state, since they have an intrinsic GTPase activity orders of magnitude faster than that of small GTPases. However, genetic studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> show that <emphasis role="italic">in vivo</emphasis>, the G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> proteins require RGS proteins to appropriately terminate signaling (<link linkend="bib127">Koelle and Horvitz, 1996</link><!--:PMID 8548815-->; <link linkend="bib82">Hajdu-Cronin et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10421631-->). In contrast, neither genetic studies in worms nor biochemical studies of mammalian proteins have identified a GTPase activator for G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript>. Thus G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> may indeed simply use its slow intrinsic GTPase activity to terminate signaling.</para>
<para>The two most intensively studied RGS proteins in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> are <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46003;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-10</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30491;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-16</ulink>, which serve as specific inhibitors of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling, respectively (<link linkend="bib127">Koelle and Horvitz, 1996</link><!--:PMID 8548815-->; <link linkend="bib82">Hajdu-Cronin et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10421631-->). They are members of the R7 family of RGS proteins, of which there are four members in mammals that are expressed in the brain (<link linkend="bib6">Anderson et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19521673-->). <emphasis role="italic">In vitro</emphasis>, these mammalian R7 proteins all preferentially inactivate G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> rather than G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, and it is unclear if any of them might actually be G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> specific <emphasis role="italic">in vivo</emphasis>, like <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30491;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-16</ulink>. Analysis of chimeras between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46003;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-10</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30491;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-16</ulink> shows that the G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> versus G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> specificity of these proteins lies in an N-terminal domain that remains of unknown biochemical function (<link linkend="bib179">Patikoglou and Koelle, 2002</link><!--:PMID 12354761-->). The <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> R7 RGS proteins, like their mammalian homologs, contain a G&gamma;-like domain that is constitutively bound to a G&beta;-like protein known as G&beta;<subscript>5</subscript> in mammals and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17845;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPB-2</ulink> in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib33">Chase et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11250150-->; <link linkend="bib200">Robatzek et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11250160-->; <link linkend="bib254">van der Linden et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11333232-->). Thus the R7 RGS/G&beta; complex in many respects resembles a G&beta;&gamma; complex, but there is as yet no understanding of what this means or how it might be used. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30491;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-16</ulink>, like the mammalian R7 RGS proteins, is anchored to the plasma membrane via a lipid-modified membrane anchoring subunit (<link linkend="bib189">Porter and Koelle, 2009</link><!--:PMID 19923320-->). There is no known membrane anchor for EGL-10.</para>
<para>There are at least 13 RGS proteins in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, and the genes for all have been knocked out and studied (reviewed by <link linkend="bib189">Porter and Koelle, 2009</link><!--:PMID 20374712-->). While the R7 family RGS proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46003;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-10</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30491;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-16</ulink> are widely expressed, and mutants cause severe disruption of G protein signaling and behavior, the other RGS proteins appear to have much more specific functions. For example, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29201;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-3</ulink> is expressed only in a subset of sensory neurons, where it dampens signaling in response to strong stimuli, increasing the dynamic range for sensing these stimuli (<link linkend="bib66">Ferkey et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17196529-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27794;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41393;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-2</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29404;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-7</ulink> are all inhibitors of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, but have much more limited functions than does the main G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> inhibitor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46003;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-10</ulink>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29404;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-7</ulink> is expressed in early embryos where it regulates the function of G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> in controlling asymmetric cell divisions (<link linkend="bib93">Hess et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15479638-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27794;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41393;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-2</ulink> are very similar to each other and are functionally redundant (<link linkend="bib59">Dong et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 10950865-->). Knocking out both disrupts a specific behavioral response that occurs when starved animals are re-fed. Knockouts for a number of additional RGS genes so far have shown no detectable defects, suggesting that these RGS genes, like <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27794;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41393;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGS-2</ulink>, may have redundant and/or very specific functions that will be difficult to define.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3.9">
<title>Reconciling studies of neural G&alpha; signaling in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> with those in more complex model organisms</title>
<para>The studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> reviewed above show that the molecular details of the G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> signaling pathways, to the extent they are known, are the same in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> versus the other invertebrate and vertebrate systems in which they have been studied, until we get down to the very most downstream outputs of these signaling pathways. The <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> work has been focused largely on the effects of the G proteins in ventral cord motor neurons on locomotion behavior and in the HSN neurons on egg-laying behavior. Using these two behaviors as readouts, the relevant outputs of signaling that have been identified are changes in the efficiency of the neurotransmitter release machinery. All the proteins involved in these changes are highly conserved across evolution, and functional studies in mammalian neurons support the idea that the very same mechanisms are used in mammalian brain to allow G protein signaling to modulate neurotransmitter release (<link linkend="bib198">Rhee et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 11792326-->; <link linkend="bib263">Wierda et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17442248-->).</para>
<para>Studies of neural G protein signaling in more complex model organisms have focused on readouts of signaling very different from those used in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. When electrophysiological measurements have been used to measure signaling outcomes, the focus has been on the regulation of specific ion channels by G&beta;&gamma; subunits (<link linkend="bib193">Reuveny et al., 1994</link><!--:PMID 8022483-->; <link linkend="bib92">Herlitze et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID 8637576-->), and indeed some of the effects of neural G protein signaling in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> are mediated by such ion channels (<link linkend="bib62">Emtage et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23152612-->). When effects on long-term memories have been the readout of signaling, the focus has been on the lasting effects of neural G protein signaling on synaptic structure or on transcription (<link linkend="bib114">Kandel, 2004</link><!--:PMID 16134023-->). It is not yet fully clear whether neural G protein signaling in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> results in these sorts of lasting changes. We do know that G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling in worms, as in mammals, results in activation of the Rho GTPase, whose best-studied function is as a regulator of the actin cytoskeleton, but it remains to be seen if G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling through Rho leads to functionally significant and lasting structural changes in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> synapses. In <emphasis role="italic">Aplysia</emphasis> and mammals, G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling produces cAMP that activates the transcription factor CREB to induce changes in transcription that may underlie long-term memories (<link linkend="bib123">Kida et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 11889468-->; <link linkend="bib114">Kandel, 2012</link><!--:PMID 22583753-->), although the relevance of CREB is less clear in <emphasis role="italic">Drosophila</emphasis> memory (<link linkend="bib180">Perazzona et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15470148-->). <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> also has a CREB homolog that was shown to be essential for worms to form a long-term memory of a food-odorant association (<link linkend="bib119">Kauffman et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 20502519-->) and that mediates G protein regulation of gene expression (<link linkend="bib236">Suo et al,. 2006</link><!--:PMID 17021164-->). Thus it seems likely that the mechanisms of neural G protein signaling are deeply conserved across evolution, but that the different types of behavioral readouts used to study such signaling in different model organisms tends to focus attention on different downstream effects of the signaling pathways on neural function.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Concluding remarks and future directions</title>
<para>Finally, I return to the simplified model presented in <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link> to illustrate an overview of what has been learned from studies of neurotransmitter signaling through heterotrimeric G proteins in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>. As described in <link linkend="sec2">Section 2</link>, a typical neuron expresses many GPCRs, and these receptors sense the levels of neurotransmitters that are released, not just from presynaptic partners to our typical neuron, but also from distant neurons and are thus acting extrasynaptically. Each neurotransmitter and its receptor are expressed in very specific and small sets of neurons, and the extrasynaptic communication between these cells is a crucial type of functional connection that goes beyond the physical synaptic connections between neurons and that is essential for understanding neural circuits. As described in <link linkend="sec3">Section 3</link>, three different G&alpha; proteins, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>, G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript>, and G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, integrate signaling by the many GPCRs that may be active on a neuron at any one time. The major outcomes of neural G protein signaling studied in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> are the opposing effects that G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> have to activate and inhibit the synaptic vesicle release machinery, respectively. G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> signaling collaborates with the G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> pathway to promote synaptic output. Other outcomes of G&alpha; activation, such as regulation of K<superscript>+</superscript> and Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> channels, or effects on neural structure or transcription, also seem to occur but are not responsible for the most obvious effects of the G proteins on <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> behavior. The neurotransmitters, receptors, G proteins, downstream signaling molecules, and mechanisms used in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> are all conserved in mammals. The contribution of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> studies has been to focus attention on the ubiquity of extrasynaptic signaling through GPCRs, the effects of neural G proteins on the neurotransmitter release machinery, and on new signaling molecules such as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink>, TrioRhoGEF, and RGS proteins that were discovered in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> using the power of forward genetic screens.</para>
<para>Opportunities for future progress using <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> include the chance to grapple with the huge family of GPCRs that activate neural G proteins. Perhaps the entire set of GPCRs expressed on some model neurons, such as the ventral cord motor neurons or the HSN egg-laying neurons, can be defined and used to study how these receptors act together to regulate activity of these neurons. More work remains to define the mechanisms by which the three major neural G proteins affect neurotransmitter release, and at what level they intersect. In particular, the effector for G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript>, if it exists, still remains to be identified. Finally, it remains to be seen whether <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> can be used to successfully study the types of changes in synaptic structure and transcription that occur downstream of G proteins in neurons of more complex organisms.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>I thank Judy Pepper and Jacob Brewer for preparing the video shown as <link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link>, Robert Fernandez for providing research for <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> and <link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>, and Seongseop Kim, Robert Fernandez, and Andrew Olson for critically reading the manuscript. Work in the Koelle lab is supported by grants R01NS036918 and R01NS086932 from the NIH.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Table 1 and Table 2</title>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1. G protein coupling and pharmacological profiles of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> G protein coupled small molecule neurotransmitter receptors</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5"/>
<colspec colnum="6" colname="col6"/>
<colspec colnum="7" colname="col7"/>
<thead>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Serotonin receptors</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Experimental evidence for ligand assignment</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References binding studies</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Agonists (EC<subscript>50</subscript>) in heterologous cells</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References heterologous cell studies</emphasis></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28481;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Binding studies, heterologous cell signaling, mutant resistant to serotonin</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> in heterologous cells</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib84">Hamdan et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10098838--></entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib84">Hamdan et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10098838--></entry>
<entry align="left">Serotonin (0.72 and 0.8 &mu;M), lisuride (partial, 0.2 and 2.4 &mu;M), DOI (partial, &gt;100 &mu;M). No activity with dopamine or octopamine.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib84">Hamdan et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10098838--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29370;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-4</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Binding studies, heterologous cell signaling, mutant resistant to serotonin</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>i/o</subscript> in heterologous cells</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib170">Olde and McCombie, 1997</link><!--:PMID 9061615--></entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib170">Olde and McCombie, 1997</link><!--:PMID 9061615--></entry>
<entry align="left">Serotonin (~0.1 &mu;M), tyramine</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib170">Olde and McCombie, 1997</link><!--:PMID 9061615-->; <link linkend="bib184a">Petrascheck et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18033297--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42717;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-5</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Mutant resistant to serotonin</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> predicted from sequence analysis</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib87">Harris et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19193891--></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17391;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-7</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Binding studies, heterologous cell signaling, mutant resistant to serotonin</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> in heterologous cells, G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> in <ulink url="https://wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003638#01--10" role="_blank">MC</ulink> neurons, G&alpha;<subscript>12</subscript> in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M4;class=Clone" role="_blank">M4</ulink> neuron</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib96">Hobson et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12969249-->; <link linkend="bib97">Hobson et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16204223-->; <link linkend="bib221">Song and Avery, 2012</link><!--:PMID 22323705--></entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib96">Hobson et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12969249-->; <link linkend="bib97">Hobson et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16204223--></entry>
<entry align="left">Serotonin (30 nM), tryptamine (4.7 &mu;M)</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib96">Hobson et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12969249-->; <link linkend="bib97">Hobson et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16204223--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Dopamine receptors</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Experimental evidence for ligand assignment</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References binding studies</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Agonists (EC<subscript>50</subscript>) in heterologous cells</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References heterologous cell studies</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33616;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Binding studies, mutation affects dopamine response</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> in ventral cord motor neurons and <ulink url="https://wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005237#01--10" role="_blank">touch response</ulink> neurons</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib34">Chase et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15378064-->; <link linkend="bib125">Kindt et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17698017--></entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib237">Suo et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 11814642--></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35994;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-2</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Binding studies, mutant resistant to dopamine, heterologous cell signaling</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>i/o</subscript> in heterologous cells, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink> in <ulink url="https://wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005361#01--10" role="_blank">SIA</ulink> neurons, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE38990;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-14</ulink> in yeast interaction assay and <ulink url="https://wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005415#01--10">ADE</ulink> neurons. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05311;class=Protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE06296;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPA-7</ulink> in male mating.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib238">Suo et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12887685-->; <link linkend="bib235">Suo et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19609300-->; <link linkend="bib48">Correa et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23166505-->; <link linkend="bib173">Pandey and Harbinder, 2012</link><!--:PMID 22280843-->; <link linkend="bib154">Mersha et al, 2013</link><!--:PMID 23607404--></entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib238">Suo et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12887685--></entry>
<entry align="left">dopamine (75 nM)</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib238">Suo et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12887685--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39181;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-3</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Mutant resistant to dopamine, heterologous cell signaling</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> in ventral cord motor neurons, G&alpha;<subscript>i/o</subscript> in heterologous cells</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib34">Chase et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15378064-->; <link linkend="bib230">Sugiura et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16001968--></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left">dopamine (27 nM), tyramine (500 nM ), octopamine (250 &mu;M)</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib230">Sugiura et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16001968--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39139;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-4</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Mutant resistant to dopamine, heterologous cell signaling</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> in heterologous cells</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib230">Sugiura et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16001968--></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left">dopamine (9.3 &mu;M), &gt;1 mM for dopamine, octopamine, tyramine and serotonin</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib230">Sugiura et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16001968--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Octopamine receptors</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Experimental evidence for ligand assignment</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References binding studies</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Agonists (EC<subscript>50</subscript>) in heterologous cells</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References heterologous cell studies</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35478;class=Protein" role="_blank">OCTR-1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Binding studies, heterologous cell signaling, mutant resistant to octopamine</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> in <ulink url="https://wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005665#01--10" role="_blank">ASH</ulink> neurons, G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> in heterologous cells</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib89">Harris et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 20534837--></entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib265">Wragg et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18057198--></entry>
<entry align="left">octopamine (0.39 &mu;M in <emphasis role="italic">Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes, but binding studies suggest higher affinity)</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib160">Mills et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22124329--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17158;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-3</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Mutant resistant to octopamine, heterologous cell signaling</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> in <ulink url="https://wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005665#01--10" role="_blank">ASH</ulink> neurons, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> in heterologous cells</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib236">Suo et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 17021164--></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left">octopamine (24 nM in mammalian cells; 0.33 &mu;M in <emphasis role="italic">Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes), tyramine (26 &mu;M in mammalian cells)</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib184a">Petrascheck et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18033297-->; <link linkend="bib160">Mills et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22124329--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31653;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-6</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Mutant resistant to octopamine</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>s</subscript> in <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005661#01--10" role="_blank">ADL</ulink> neurons</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib160">Mills et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22124329-->;</entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left">octopamine (2 &mu;M in <emphasis role="italic">Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes) > tyramine. No response to dopamine or serotonin.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib160">Mills et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22124329-->;</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Tyramine receptors</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Experimental evidence for ligand assignment</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References binding studies</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Agonists (EC<subscript>50</subscript>) in heterologous cells</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References heterologous cell studies</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32299;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-2</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">heterologous cell signaling, mutant resistant to tyramine</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>i/o</subscript> in heterologous cells, G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> in VD neurons</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib194">Rex and Komuniecki, 2002</link><!--:PMID 12354282-->; <link linkend="bib60">Donelly et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23565061--></entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib194">Rex and Komuniecki, 2002</link><!--:PMID 12354282--></entry>
<entry align="left">Tyramine 360 nM, 403 nM)</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib194">Rex and Komuniecki, 2002</link><!--:PMID 12354282-->; <link linkend="bib196">Rex et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15569254--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE38313;class=Protein" role="_blank">TYRA-2</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Binding studies, heterologous cell signaling</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>i/o</subscript> in heterologous cells</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib195">Rex et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15953361--></entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib195">Rex et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15953361--></entry>
<entry align="left">Tyramine (50 nM), octopamine and dopamine had little/no effect</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib195">Rex et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15953361--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31203;class=Protein" role="_blank">TYRA-3</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Binding studies, mutant resistant to tyramine</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> in heterologous cells</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib86">Hapiak et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23986246--></entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib265">Wragg et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18057198--></entry>
<entry align="left">tyramine (70.8 nM)</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib86">Hapiak et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23986246--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Acetylcholine receptors</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Experimental evidence for ligand assignment</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References binding studies</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Agonists (EC<subscript>50</subscript>) in heterologous cells</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References heterologous cell studies</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29667;class=Protein" role="_blank">GAR-1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">heterologous cell signaling</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>i</subscript> in <emphasis role="italic">Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib178">Park et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 10679207--></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left">Acetylcholine (~100 nM), carbachol, no effect of oxotremorine</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib178">Park et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 10679207--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30134;class=Protein" role="_blank">GAR-2</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">heterologous cell signailng</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>i/o</subscript> in <emphasis role="italic">Xenopus</emphasis> oocytes, G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> in ventral chord cholinergic neurons</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib138">Lee et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 11032868-->; <link linkend="bib55">Dittman and Kaplan, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18614679--></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left">acetylcholine (~35 nM), carbachol, no effect of oxotremorine</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib138">Lee et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 11032868-->; <link linkend="bib231">Suh et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11700045--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35800;class=Protein" role="_blank">GAR-3</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">heterologous cell signaling, mutant resistant to acetylcholine agonist arecoline</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> and G&alpha;<subscript>i/o</subscript> in heterologous cells, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> in pharyngeal muscles, G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> in male spicule protraction</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib161">Min et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 10854271-->; <link linkend="bib177">Park et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12927813-->; <link linkend="bib228">Steger and Avery 2004</link><!--:PMID 15238517-->; <link linkend="bib176">Park et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16631594-->; <link linkend="bib146">Liu et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17287516--></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left">carbachol (13.0 and 11.5 &mu;M), oxotremorine</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib103">Hwang et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10635059-->; <link linkend="bib161">Min et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 10854271-->; <link linkend="bib177">Park et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12927813--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">GABA receptors</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Experimental evidence for ligand assignment</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References binding studies</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Agonists (EC<subscript>50</subscript>) in heterologous cells</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References heterologous cell studies</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43326;class=Protein" role="_blank">GBB-1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Mutant insensitive to optogenetically released GABA</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> in cholinergic motor neurons</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib55">Dittman and Kaplan, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18614679--></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43384;class=Protein" role="_blank">GBB-2</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Mutant insensitive to optogenet-ically released GABA</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>o</subscript> in cholinergic motor neurons</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib55">Dittman and Kaplan, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18614679--></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Glutamate receptor homologs</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Experimental evidence for ligand assignment</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References binding studies</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Agonists (EC<subscript>50</subscript>) in heterologous cells</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References heterologous cell studies</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40729;class=Protein" role="_blank">MGL-1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Mutant resistant to mGluR agonists <emphasis role="italic">trans</emphasis>-ACPD and LCCG-I</entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42117;class=Protein" role="_blank">MGL-2</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">heterologous cell signaling</entry>
<entry align="left">G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> in heterologous cells</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib245">Tharmalingam et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22652059--></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left">glutamate (8.61 &mu;M), quisqualate (169 &mu;M), DHPG (partial agonist),</entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49187;class=Protein" role="_blank">MGL-3</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">None&mdash;inferred to be a glutamate receptor from sequence homology</entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Poorly-studied putative small-molecule GPCRs</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Experimental evidence for ligand assignment</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References G protein coupling</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References binding studies</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Agonists (EC<subscript>50</subscript>) in heterologous cells</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References heterologous cell studies</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T02E9.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">T02E9.3</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C24A8.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">C24A8.1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00044004;class=Gene" role="_blank">C24A8.6</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00018073;class=Gene" role="_blank">F35H10.10</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00010329;class=Gene" role="_blank">F59D12.1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">T21B4.4</entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<table id="table2" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 2. Genetically-established functions and expression patterns of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> G protein coupled small molecule neurotransmitter receptors</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5"/>
<thead>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Serotonin receptors</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Functions revealed in mutants</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References mutant phenotype</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Expression pattern</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References expression pattern</emphasis></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28481;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Exogenous serotonin-stimulated egg laying, feeding, and slowing of locomotion, &alpha;-methyl-5-HT stimulated egg laying, male ventral tail curling, food-induced slowing, food modulation of aversive response, heat shock response, longevity</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib22">Carnell et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16291940-->; <link linkend="bib51">Dempsey et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15654117-->; <link linkend="bib266">Xiao et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16890216-->; <link linkend="bib52">Dernovici et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17443782-->; <link linkend="bib164">Murakami and Murakami, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17559503-->; <link linkend="bib226">Srinivasan et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18522834-->; <link linkend="bib88">Harris et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21814562--></entry>
<entry align="left">Pharyngeal muscle (<ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003740#01--10" role="_blank">pm3</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003739#01--10" role="_blank">pm4</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003737#01--10" role="_blank">pm5</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003724#01--10" role="_blank">pm6</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003721#01--10" role="_blank">pm7</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0004302#01--10" role="_blank">pm8</ulink>), <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005244#01--10" role="_blank">CEP</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006842#01--10" role="_blank">RMG</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006843#01--10" role="_blank">RMH</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006841#01--10" role="_blank">RMF</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005400#01--10" role="_blank">RMD</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006833#01--10" role="_blank">RIA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006834#01--10" role="_blank">RIC</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005346#01--10" role="_blank">URY</ulink>, additional head neurons, vulval muscle and epithelial cells, tail neurons (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PVT;class=Cell" role="_blank">PVT</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006976#01--10" role="_blank">PVQ</ulink>, possibly <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVC;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVC</ulink>) ventral nerve cord, excretory cell, uterine cells, ray sensory neurons in male</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib38">Cho et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 11167007-->; <link linkend="bib250">Tsalik et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14568548-->; <link linkend="bib22">Carnell et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16291940-->; <link linkend="bib51">Dempsey et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15654117-->; <link linkend="bib266">Xiao et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16890216-->; <link linkend="bib52">Dernovici et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17443782--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29370;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-4</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Egg laying induced by imipramine but not by fluoxetine or serotonin, inhibition of locomotion by serotonin, effects of ethanol on gustatory plasticity and locomotion, thermotaxis memory behavior</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib38">Cho et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 11167007-->; <link linkend="bib51">Dempsey et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15654117-->; <link linkend="bib164">Murakami and Murakami, 2007</link><!--:PMID 17559503-->; <link linkend="bib259">Wang et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21889959-->; <link linkend="bib81">G&uuml;rel et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23023001-->; <link linkend="bib145">Li et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 24223727--></entry>
<entry align="left"><ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003666#01--10" role="_blank">NSM</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005834#01--10" role="_blank">RIB</ulink> or <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006813#01--10" role="_blank">AIB</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RIS;class=Cell" role="_blank">RIS</ulink>, pharyngeal neuron, pair of sublateral interneurons or motorneurons, retrovesicular ganglion, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PVT;class=Cell" role="_blank">PVT</ulink> tail neuron, vm2 vulval muscles, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0004823#01--10 " role="_blank">DVA</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVC;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVC</ulink> tail interneuron</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib250">Tsalik et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14568548-->; <link linkend="bib81">G&uuml;rel et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23023001--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42717;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-5</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Exogenous serotonin-stimulated egg laying, food and serotonin-dependent increase in sensitivity of <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005665#01--10" role="_blank">ASH</ulink> neurons to octanol and decrease in sensitivity to Cu<superscript>2+</superscript>. Reduced sensitivity to serotonin and fluoxetine induced paralysis.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib85">Hapiak et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19001289-->; <link linkend="bib134">Kullyev et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 20739712-->; <link linkend="bib88">Harris et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21814562-->; <link linkend="bib80">Guo et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 25585042--></entry>
<entry align="left">Neurons including <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005671#01--10" role="_blank">AWB</ulink> and <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005665#01--10" role="_blank">ASH</ulink>, body wall muscles, vulval muscles</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib85">Hapiak et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19001289--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17391;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-7</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Exogenous serotonin-stimulated egg laying, pharyngeal pumping, and food intake. Regulation of pharyngeal pumping. Egg laying. Hypoxia regulation of gustatory and effects of ethanol on gustatory plasticity, thermotaxis memory behavior</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib97">Hobson et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16204223-->; <link linkend="bib61">Donohoe et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19447297-->; <link linkend="bib85">Hapiak et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19001289-->; <link linkend="bib187">Pocock and Hobert, 2010</link><!--:PMID 20400959-->; <link linkend="bib259">Wang et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21889959-->; <link linkend="bib221">Song and Avery, 2012</link><!--:PMID 22323705-->; <link linkend="bib222">Song et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23390589-->; <link linkend="bib145">Li et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 24223727-->; <link linkend="bib75">Gomez-Amaro et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 25903497-->; <link linkend="bib140">Leiser et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 26586189--></entry>
<entry align="left">Pharyngeal neurons MC, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M4;class=Clone" role="_blank">M4</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003645#01--10" role="_blank">I2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=I3;class=Cell" role="_blank">I3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M5;class=Clone" role="_blank">M5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M3;class=Cell" role="_blank">M3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=I4;class=Cell" role="_blank">I4</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=I6;class=Cell" role="_blank">I6</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M2;class=Clone" role="_blank">M2</ulink>, vulval muscles</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib97">Hobson et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16204223--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Dopamine receptors</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Functions revealed in mutants</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References mutant phenotype</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Expression pattern</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References expression pattern</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33616;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Antagonizes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39181;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-3</ulink> to control locomotion, a behavioral decision-making paradigm, and acetylcholine release. Regulates swim-to-crawl transition, fat reservoirs, local food search behavior. Delays habituation to mechanical stimulation. Promotes nicotine approach behavior.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib34">Chase et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15378064-->; <link linkend="bib208">Sanyal et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 14739932-->; <link linkend="bib125">Kindt et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17698017-->; <link linkend="bib4">Allen et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21515580-->; <link linkend="bib255">Vidal-Gadea et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21969584-->; <link linkend="bib214">Sellings et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23351035-->; <link linkend="bib9">Barros et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 24465759-->; <link linkend="bib17">Bhattacharya et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 25167143-->; <link linkend="bib257">Wang et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 25536037--></entry>
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVA;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005490#01--10" role="_blank">PLM</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0008446#01--10" role="_blank">PHC</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006851#01--10" role="_blank">ALN</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005406#01--10" role="_blank">ALM</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVM;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVM</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PLN;class=Cell" role="_blank">PLN</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006976#01--10" role="_blank">PVQ</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006817#01--10" role="_blank">AUA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005834#01--10" role="_blank">RIB</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005835#01--10" role="_blank">RIM</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RIS;class=Cell" role="_blank">RIS</ulink>, unidentified head neurons, head muscles, labial and amphid sheath/socket cells, excretory gland cells, cholinergic ventral cord motor neurons</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib250">Tsalik et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14568548-->; <link linkend="bib208">Sanyal et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 14739932-->; <link linkend="bib34">Chase et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15378064-->; <link linkend="bib17">Bhattacharya et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 25167143--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35994;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-2</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Antagonizes octopamine signaling, inhibits CRE-mediated gene expression in SIA. Mediates swimming-induced paralysis. Inhibits unproductive male mating behavior. Promotes nicotine approach behavior. Regulates touch habituation and chemosensory associative learning. Affects a decision-making paradigm.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib235">Suo et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19609300-->; <link linkend="bib24">Carvelli et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 20410438-->; <link linkend="bib48">Correa et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23166505-->; <link linkend="bib214">Sellings et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23351035-->; <link linkend="bib154">Mersha et al. 2013</link><!--:PMID 23607404-->; <link linkend="bib257">Wang et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 25536037-->; <link linkend="bib47a">Correa et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 26156999--></entry>
<entry align="left">All dopaminergic neurons of hermaphrodite (<ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005244#01--10" role="_blank">CEP</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005415#01--10" role="_blank">ADE</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PDE;class=Cell" role="_blank">PDE</ulink>) and probably of male (<ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006856#01--10" role="_blank">R5A</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006857#01--10" role="_blank">R7A</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=R9A;class=Cell" role="_blank">R9A</ulink>). <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006833#01--10" role="_blank">RIA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005361#01--10" role="_blank">SIA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005359#01--10" role="_blank">SIB</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RID;class=Cell" role="_blank">RID</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PDA;class=Cell" role="_blank">PDA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0004762#01--10" role="_blank">HOA</ulink>.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib238">Suo et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12887685-->; <link linkend="bib250">Tsalik et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14568548-->; <link linkend="bib235">Suo et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19609300-->; <link linkend="bib47a">Correa et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 26156999--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39181;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-3</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Antagonizes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33616;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-1</ulink> to control locomotion, a behavioral decision-making paradigm, and acetylcholine release. Mediates swimming induced paralysis. Inhibits unproductive male mating behavior. Antagonizes octopamine signaling and inhibits CRE-mediated gene expression in <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005361#01--10" role="_blank">SIA</ulink>. Regulates avoidance of octanol and 2-nonanone.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib34">Chase et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15378064-->; <link linkend="bib150">McDonald et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18094261-->; <link linkend="bib235">Suo et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19609300-->; <link linkend="bib63">Ezak and Ferkey, 2010</link><!--:PMID 20209143-->; <link linkend="bib24">Carvelli et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 20410438-->; <link linkend="bib124">Kimura et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 21123582-->; <link linkend="bib171">Omura et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22719914-->; <link linkend="bib48">Correa et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23166505-->; <link linkend="bib257">Wang et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 25536037--></entry>
<entry align="left">Ventral cord GABAergic and cholinergic neurons, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005668#01--10" role="_blank">ASK</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PVD;class=Cell" role="_blank">PVD</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005361#01--10" role="_blank">SIA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006834#01--10" role="_blank">RIC</ulink>, head neurons, tail neurons, body wall muscles, male tail cells</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib34">Chase et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15378064-->; <link linkend="bib235">Suo et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19609300-->; <link linkend="bib63">Ezak and Ferkey, 2010</link><!--:PMID 20209143-->; <link linkend="bib48">Correa et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 23166505-->;</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39139;class=Protein" role="_blank">DOP-4</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Mediates swimming induced paralysis, swim/crawl transition, food enhancement of <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005665#01--10" role="_blank">ASH</ulink> response to repellents, alcohol-induced disinhibition of crawling.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib24">Carvelli et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 20410438-->; <link linkend="bib64">Ezcurra et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21304491-->; <link linkend="bib247">Topper et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 24681782-->; <link linkend="bib255">Vidal-Gadea et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21969584--></entry>
<entry align="left"><ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003649#01--10">I1</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003645#01--10">I2</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005664#01--10">ASG</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVL;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVL</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006827#01--10">CAN</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PQR;class=Cell" role="_blank">PQR</ulink>, vulva, intestine, rectal glands, rectal epithelial cells, male ray 8, additional head neurons, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005665#01--10" role="_blank">ASH</ulink> (inferred indirectly).</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib230">Sugiura et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16001968-->; <link linkend="bib64">Ezcurra et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21304491--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Octopamine receptors</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Functions revealed in mutants</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References mutant phenotype</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Expression pattern</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References expression pattern</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35478;class=Protein" role="_blank">OCTR-1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Mediates effect of exogenous octopamine on response to octanol. Controls innate immunity by regulating the unfolded protein response.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib265">Wragg et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18057198-->; <link linkend="bib89">Harris et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 20534837-->; <link linkend="bib232">Sun et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21474712-->; <link linkend="bib160">Mills et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22124329-->; <link linkend="bib232">Sun et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22791024--></entry>
<entry align="left"><ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005666#01--10">ASI</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005665#01--10" role="_blank">ASH</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005413#01--10">AIY</ulink>, <ulink url="https://wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005415#01--10">ADE</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005244#01--10">CEP</ulink>, spermatheca, uterine toroid cells, head and tail neurons</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib265">Wragg et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18057198--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17158;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-3</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Mediates octopamine- and starvation-induced expression of a CREB-dependent reporter gene in <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005361#01--10" role="_blank">SIA</ulink> neurons. Antagonizes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35478;class=Protein" role="_blank">OCTR-1</ulink> in the control of octanol response by exogenous octopamine. Mediates inhibition of <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005666#01--10" role="_blank">ASI</ulink> sensory neuron by <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005665#01--10" role="_blank">ASH</ulink> sensory neuron via a circuit involving octopamine released from <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006834#01--10" role="_blank">RIC</ulink>.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib236">Suo et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 17021164-->; <link linkend="bib160">Mills et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22124329-->; <link linkend="bib80">Guo et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 25585042--></entry>
<entry align="left"><ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005665#01--10" role="_blank">ASH</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005664#01--10
">ASG</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005666#01--10" role="_blank">ASI</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005361#01--10" role="_blank">SIA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0007807#01--10">PHA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0007808#01--10">PHB</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006976#01--10">PVQ</ulink>,	neurons in the head and tail, head muscles, intestine, phasmid socket cells, spermatheca</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib236">Suo et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 17021164-->; <link linkend="bib160">Mills et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22124329-->; <link linkend="bib80">Guo et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 25585042--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31653;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-6</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Mediates octopamine- and starvation-induced expression of a CREB-dependent reporter gene in <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005361#01--10" role="_blank">SIA</ulink> neurons. Mediates exogenous serotonin-stimulated fat reduction. Mediates exogenous octopamine mediated inhibition of response to 100% octanol.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib226">Srinivasan et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18522834-->; <link linkend="bib160">Mills et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22124329-->; <link linkend="bib268">Yoshida et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 24446241--></entry>
<entry align="left"><ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005361#01--10" role="_blank">SIA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006834#01--10" role="_blank">RIC</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005671#01--10" role="_blank">AWB</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005661#01--10" role="_blank">ADL</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005666#01--10" role="_blank">ASI</ulink>, head neurons, tail neurons, posterior ventral cord neurons, intestine</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib226">Srinivasan et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18522834-->; <link linkend="bib268">Yoshida et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 24446241--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Tyramine receptors</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Functions revealed in mutants</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References mutant phenotype</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Expression pattern</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References expression pattern</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32299;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-2</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Mediates paralysis and suppression of pharyngeal pumping by exogenous tyramine. Suppresses head movements during backing. Facilitates execution of omega turns.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib196">Rex et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15569254-->; <link linkend="bib60">Donelly et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23565061--></entry>
<entry align="left">Neurons: <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005413#01--10" role="_blank">AIY</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006821#01--10" role="_blank">AVH</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006817#01--10" role="_blank">AUA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006834#01--10" role="_blank">RIC</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005396#01--10" role="_blank">SAB</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RID;class=Cell" role="_blank">RID</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006833#01--10" role="_blank">RIA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006844#01--10" role="_blank">SDQ</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006827#01--10" role="_blank">CAN</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DA9;class=Cell" role="_blank">DA9</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0008031#01--10" role="_blank">LUA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006851#01--10" role="_blank">ALN</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005840#01--10" role="_blank">PVC</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003666#01--10" role="_blank">NSM</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005836#01--10" role="_blank">AIZ</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVA;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006826#01--10" role="_blank">BDU</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005361#01--10" role="_blank">SIA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005399#01--10" role="_blank">RME</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PVT;class=Cell" role="_blank">PVT</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006847#01--10" role="_blank">OLL</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PVD;class=Cell" role="_blank">PVD</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/VD" role="_blank">VD</ulink>. Excretory gland cells. Muscles: <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003744#01--10" role="_blank">pm1</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003724#01--10" role="_blank">pm6</ulink>, head muscles, male posterior body wall muscles and diagonal muscles. Possibly male <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005310#01--10" role="_blank">CP</ulink> neurons. Uterine toroid cells <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00274923;class=Variation" role="_blank">ut1</ulink> and <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006786#01--10" role="_blank">ut2</ulink>.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib250">Tsalik et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14568548-->; <link linkend="bib196">Rex et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15569254-->; <link linkend="bib60">Donelly et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23565061--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE38313;class=Protein" role="_blank">TYRA-2</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MCL;class=Cell" role="_blank">MCL</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003666#01--10" role="_blank">NSM</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005663#01--10" role="_blank">ASE</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005664#01--10" role="_blank">ASG</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005665#01--10" role="_blank">ASH</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005666#01--10" role="_blank">ASI</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PVD;class=Cell" role="_blank">PVD</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006827#01--10" role="_blank">CAN</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005406#01--10" role="_blank">ALM</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib195">Rex et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15953361--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31203;class=Protein" role="_blank">TYRA-3</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Mediates effect of exogenous tyramine on response to octanol; affects decision to leave bacterial lawn. Antagonizes the effect of serotonin to sensitize aversive responses.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib265">Wragg et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18057198-->; <link linkend="bib14a">Bendesky et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21412235-->; <link linkend="bib86">Hapiak et a., 2013</link>; <!--:PMID 23986246--></entry>
<entry align="left"><ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005415#01--10" role="_blank">ADE</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005244#01--10" role="_blank">CEP</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005668#01--10" role="_blank">ASK</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005661#01--10" role="_blank">ADL</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006814#01--10" role="_blank">AIM</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006817#01--10" role="_blank">AUA</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006825#01--10" role="_blank">BAG</ulink>, DEP, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006848#01--10" role="_blank">OLQ</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SDQL;class=Cell" role="_blank">SDQL</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005662#01--10" role="_blank">AFD</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005672#01--10" role="_blank">AWC</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006834#01--10" role="_blank">RIC</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005666#01--10" role="_blank">ASI</ulink>, spermatheca, distal tip cell, vulval muscles, additional head and tail neurons</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib23">Carre-Pierrat et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 17082916-->; Unpublished results cited in <link linkend="bib265">Wragg et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 18057198-->; <link linkend="bib14a">Bendesky et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21412235--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Acetyl-choline receptors</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Functions revealed in mutants</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References mutant phenotype</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Expression pattern</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References expression pattern</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29667;class=Protein" role="_blank">GAR-1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left">head neurons, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PVM;class=Cell" role="_blank">PVM</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib138">Lee et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 11032868--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30134;class=Protein" role="_blank">GAR-2</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Mediates inhibition of egg laying. Mediates feedback inhibition of cholinergic ventral cord motor neurons to regulate locomotion.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib8">Bany et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12954868-->; <link linkend="bib55">Dittman and Kaplan, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18614679--></entry>
<entry align="left">head neurons, ventral cord GABAergic and cholinergic, neurons, cell near vulva</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib138">Lee et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 11032868-->; <link linkend="bib55">Dittman and Kaplan, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18614679--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35800;class=Protein" role="_blank">GAR-3</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Regulates multiple calcium-dependent processes in pharyngeal muscle. Sensitizes nicotinic signaling in male spicule neurons and muscles to facilitate mating. Regulates head movements by compartmentalizing axon activity in the <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006833#01--10" role="_blank">RIA</ulink> interneuron. Promotes acetylcholine release from cholinergic motor neurons.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib228">Steger and Avery, 2004</link>; <!--:PMID 15238517--> <link linkend="bib146">Liu et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17287516-->; <link linkend="bib90">Hendricks et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22722842-->; <link linkend="bib26">Chan J.P. et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23986249--></entry>
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=I3;class=Cell" role="_blank">I3</ulink>, pharyngeal muscle, body wall muscles, anal depressor muscle, cholinergic ventral cord neurons, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005303#01--10" role="_blank">VD</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005270#01--10">DD</ulink>, male diagonal muscles, male ray 8 neuron, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006861#01--10" role="_blank">SPC</ulink>, <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006859#01--10" role="_blank">PCB</ulink>, and <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0007806#01--10" role="_blank">PCA</ulink> neurons and the spicule protractor muscles</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib228">Steger and Avery, 2004</link>; <!--:PMID 15238517-->; <link linkend="bib146">Liu et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17287516-->; <link linkend="bib26">Chan J.P. et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23986249--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">GABA receptors</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Functions revealed in mutants</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References mutant phenotype</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Expression pattern</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References expression pattern</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43326;class=Protein" role="_blank">GBB-1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">With <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43384;class=Protein" role="_blank">GBB-2</ulink>, decreases acetylcholine release from ventral cord motor neurons to regulate locomotion. Affects lifespan.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib55">Dittman and Kaplan, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18614679-->; <link linkend="bib212">Schultheis et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21613582-->; <link linkend="bib40">Chun et al., 2015</link><!--:PMID 26537867--></entry>
<entry align="left">Expression in ventral cord cholinergic neurons in inferred indirectly.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib55">Dittman and Kaplan, 2008</link><!--:PMID 18614679-->; <link linkend="bib212">Schultheis et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21613582--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43384;class=Protein" role="_blank">GBB-2</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">With <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43326;class=Protein" role="_blank">GBB-1</ulink>, decreases acetylcholine release from ventral cord motor neurons to regulate locomotion.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib55">Dittman and Kaplan 2008</link><!--:PMID 18614679-->; <link linkend="bib212">Schultheis et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21613582--></entry>
<entry align="left">Expression in ventral cord cholinergic neurons in inferred indirectly.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib55">Dittman and Kaplan 2008</link><!--:PMID 18614679-->; <link linkend="bib212">Schultheis et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21613582--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Glutamate receptor homologs</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Functions revealed in mutants</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References mutant phenotype</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Expression pattern</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">References expression pattern</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40729;class=Protein" role="_blank">MGL-1</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Regulates starvation response, perhaps by directly sensing amino acids from food. Pharmacological activation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40729;class=Protein" role="_blank">MGL-1</ulink> inhibits pharyngeal pumping. Mediates reduction in pharyngeal pumping when animals are removed from food.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib116">Kang and Avery, 2009</link><!--:PMID 19136622-->; <link linkend="bib54a">Dillon et al,. 2015</link><!--:PMID 25869139--></entry>
<entry align="left">Expression in <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005413#01--10" role="_blank">AIY</ulink> and <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006813#01--10" role="_blank">AIB</ulink> is inferred indirectly. Head neurons, tail neurons, pharyngeal neurons including <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003666#01--10" role="_blank">NSM</ulink>.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib116">Kang and Avery, 2009</link><!--:PMID 19136622-->; <link linkend="bib54a">Dillon et al,. 2015</link><!--:PMID 25869139--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42117;class=Protein" role="_blank">MGL-2</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left">Regulates starvation response, perhaps by directly sensing amino acids from food.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib116">Kang and Avery, 2009</link><!--:PMID 19136622--></entry>
<entry align="left">Expression in <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0005413#01--10" role="_blank">AIY</ulink> and <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0006813#01--10" role="_blank">AIB</ulink> is inferred indirectly. Head neurons, tail neurons, pharyngeal neurons including <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003666#01--10" role="_blank">NSM</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=I5;class=Cell" role="_blank">I5</ulink>, intestine, pharyngeal-intestinal valve, pharyngeal muscle.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib116">Kang and Avery, 2009</link><!--:PMID 19136622-->; <link linkend="bib54a">Dillon et al,. 2015</link><!--:PMID 25869139--></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49187;class=Protein" role="_blank">MGL-3</ulink></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left"></entry>
<entry align="left">Head neurons, pharyngeal neurons including <ulink url="https://www.wormbase.org/species/all/anatomy_term/WBbt:0003666#01--10" role="_blank">NSM</ulink>.</entry>
<entry align="left"><link linkend="bib54a">Dillon et al., 2015</link><!-- MPID 25869139--></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>References</title>
<para/>
&neurotransGprotein_ref;
</sect1>
</article>
