<caption>
<formalpara>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Figure 3. Mechanism of G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling.</emphasis></title>
<para>G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> is induced to bind GTP to generate its active form by GPCRs, and induced to hydrolyze GTP to generate its inactive form by the RGS protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30491;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-16</ulink>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33952;class=Protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> promotes G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling by acting as a chaperone to stabilize G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> protein and/or by acting as a non-receptor activator to promote GTP binding by G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>. These proteins are drawn at both left and right to facilitate showing the two G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> effector pathways at center. Left pathway: G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>-GTP activates Trio RhoGEF, which in turn activates sphingosine kinase (SphK) to generate the lipid second messenger sphingosine 1-phosphate (Sph1P). Trio RhoGEF also increases levels of another lipid second messenger diacylglycerol (DAG) by activating RhoA to prevent diacylglycerol kinase (DGK) from converting DAG to phosphatidic acid (PA). Right pathway: G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>-GTP activates phospholipase C&beta; (PLC&beta;) to generate the second messengers DAG and (not shown) IP<subscript>3</subscript>. Sph1P and DAG each help <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34623;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-13</ulink> to relocalize to synaptic membranes and to promote synaptic vesicle release. DAG also activates protein kinase C (PKC) to promote dense-core vesicle release. Solid grey arrows (or bars), activation (or inhibition) via direct physical interactions. Dashed arrows or bars, indirect or poorly understood effects. Light green, proteins that promote G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling; red, proteins that inhibit G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript> signaling.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>