<caption>
	<formalpara>
		<title>Figure 6. Recombinant inbred lines and near isogenic lines</title>
		<para>A. A set of <emphasis>n</emphasis> Recombinant Inbred Lines (RIL) is produced by picking <emphasis>n</emphasis> individuals in the F2 generation of a cross between two wild isolates, and letting them self for 10&#x02013;15 generations until the resulting strains are isogenic. RIL have been built between the reference strain N2 and a number of other wild isolates, including Bergerac (<link linkend="bib39">Johnson and Wood, 1982</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib23">Ebert et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8307318-->; <link linkend="bib64">van Swinderen et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9223344-->), CB4856 (S. Wicks and R. Plasterk; M. Hammarlund &amp; E. Jorgensen, pers. comm.), DR1350 (<link linkend="bib67">Viney et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12950280-->), CB4857 (<link linkend="bib8">Bonnaud et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID-->), etc. B. Frequency distribution of male ray 3 position (black bars) and ray 3-4 fusion (red bars) among Recombinant Inbred Lines of the <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> AF16 and HK104 strains (<link linkend="bib5">Baird et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15634358-->). The phenotypes of the parental lines are indicated by arrows. The phenotypic variation is due to variation at several loci, with transgressive segregation. In addition, the only partial correlation of the two phenotypes between the different lines (not shown) show that they can evolve independently. C. A Near Isogenic Line is obtained by moving a chromosomal segment from one genetic background to another by repeated crosses, which can be assisted by flanking markers. For example, a Plugging <emphasis>plg-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e2001;class=Variation" role="_blank">e2001</ulink>)III</emphasis> strain in the N2 background was built in this manner (<link linkend="bib35">Hodgkin and Doniach, 1997</link><!--; PMID 9136008-->).</para>
	</formalpara>
</caption>
