<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'Otipulaefig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'Otipulaefig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'Otipulaefig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'Otipulaefig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'Otipulaefig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'Otipulaefig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY Otipulae_Refs SYSTEM 'Otipulaerefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="Otipulae_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title><emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis><footnote>
			<para>Edited by Jonathan Hodgkin. Last revised June 30, 2006. Published August 16, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: F&#x000E9;lix, M.-A. <emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> (August 16, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.119.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 Marie-Anne F&#x000E9;lix. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
<author>
	<firstname>Marie-Anne</firstname>
	<surname>F&#x000E9;lix<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed.</para></footnote></remark>
	</surname>
	<affiliation><address>Institut Jacques Monod, CNRS &#x02013; Universit&#x000E9;s Paris, 75251 Paris cedex 05, France</address></affiliation>
</author>
</articleinfo>
<abstract>
	<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
	<para><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Oscheius tipulae</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">is a common soil nematode of the same family as</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">(Rhabditidae), which presents the same hermaphroditic mode of reproduction and is easily cultured in the same conditions.</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Oscheius tipulae</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">has been used as a developmental genetic model system to study vulva formation. Compared to</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">it has a simpler vulval cell lineage, a reduced competence group and a different mechanism of vulval cell fate patterning. The spectrum of vulval phenotypes obtained in genetic screens differs from that found in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans.</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">Its easy isolation from soil and the availability of numerous wild isolates of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">O. tipulae</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">from all over the world facilitate population genetic and microevolutionary studies, especially of the evolution of cell lineage. The</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Oscheius</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">genus also presents many species with interesting evolutionary changes in mode of reproduction, gonad development, body size, etc.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<?newpage?>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Phylogenetic relationships</title>
<sect2 id="sec1_1">
<title>Phylogenetic position of the <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> genus</title>
<para><emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> is a nematode of the same family as <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (Rhabditidae), commonly found in soil. Its relationship to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is more distant than that of members of the <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> genus, yet it is more closely related to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> than <emphasis>Pristionchus pacificus</emphasis> and <emphasis>Brugia malayi</emphasis> are (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). Compared to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> shares a common ancestor with the insect parasite <emphasis>Heterorhabditis</emphasis> and the vertebrate parasites Strongylida (<link linkend="bib3">Blaxter et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID-->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_phylogrhabditids/phylorhab.html" role="_blank">The phylogenetic relationships of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and other rhabditids</ulink>).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="6.5in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec1_2">
<title>The <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> genus</title>
<para>The <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> genus comprises two main subclades (<emphasis>Dolichura</emphasis> and <emphasis>Insectivora</emphasis> groups; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_phylogrhabditids/phylorhab.html" role="_blank">The phylogenetic relationships of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and other rhabditids</ulink>; <link linkend="bib26">Sudhaus, 1976</link>; <link linkend="bib28">Sudhaus and Hooper, 1994</link>; Figure 1). One distinctive character between these two clades appears to be the smaller size of the animals in the <emphasis>Dolichura</emphasis> clade (that includes <emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis>) (<link linkend="bib16">Flemming et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10805788-->) (M.-A. F., unpublished). The <emphasis>Dolichura</emphasis> group comprises <emphasis>Oscheius guentheri</emphasis>, which is a species with a reduced posterior-gonadal arm (<link linkend="bib28">Sudhaus and Hooper, 1994</link>), plus two subgroups, of which two representative species are <emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> and <emphasis>O. dolichura</emphasis>, respectively (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_phylogrhabditids/phylorhab.html" role="_blank">The phylogenetic relationships of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and other rhabditids</ulink>). Historically, <emphasis>Oscheius dolichura</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib22">Schneider, 1866</link>) was one of the first nematode species (before <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>) described to have an androdioceous mode of reproduction (<link linkend="bib21">Maupas, 1900</link>; see English translation: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/papers/1900-maupas/index.html">http://www.wormbase.org/papers/1900-maupas/index.html</ulink>).</para>
<para><emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> was first described by Lam and Webster (<link linkend="bib18">Lam and Webster, 1971</link>). The species was brought to persisting live culture (strain SB128) and redescribed by <link linkend="bib27">Sudhaus (1993)</link>. It was called <emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis> because these researchers found it associated with the larvae of the insect <emphasis>Tipula paludosa</emphasis> (a dipteran). The CEW1 strain was found by C.E. Winter in soil in S&#x000E3;o Paulo, Brazil around 1992 (<link linkend="bib29">Winter, 1992</link>). Because of taxonomic confusions, the CEW1 strain has been variably named <emphasis>Dolichorhabditis</emphasis> sp. or <emphasis>D. brevesophaga</emphasis> or <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> sp. 1 before it was decided to be an isolate of <emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib10">Dichtel-Danjoy and F&#x000E9;lix, 2004</link><!--; PMID 14697357-->), which is the valid name.</para>
<para><emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis> and its two closely related species, provisionally called <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> spp. 2 and 3 (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>), are hard to distinguish morphologically, but can be distinguished through mating experiments and molecular features (<link linkend="bib15">F&#x000E9;lix et al., 2001</link>).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<?newpage?>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Natural populations</title>
<sect2 id="sec2_1">
<title>Ecology</title>
<para><emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> is one of the most common nematode species in soil of different (non-desert) parts of the world. It is both widespread and abundant in soil samples. It is mostly (or exclusively) found in the dauer stage (like <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>), raising the question of whether it proliferates in soil. It was originally isolated from <emphasis>Tipula</emphasis> larvae, but this may not be a particularly specific association. <emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis> is more heat-resistant in the lab than <emphasis>O.</emphasis> spp. 2 and 3 (<link linkend="bib15">F&#x000E9;lix et al., 2001</link>) and has been found in tropical as well as temperate regions.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2_2">
<title>Isolation and wild genetic resources</title>
<para><emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> is easy to isolate (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_nematodeisolation/nematodeisolation.html" role="_blank">Isolation of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and related nematodes</ulink>). Species of the <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> genus are characterized in particular by their long rectum (see Figure 5 in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_nematodeisolation/nematodeisolation.html" role="_blank">Isolation of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and related nematodes</ulink>).</para>
<para>Available wild isolates can be found at the CGC (<ulink url="http://elegans.swmed.edu/CGC/">http://elegans.swmed.edu/CGC/</ulink>), the NYU Rhabditidae collection (<ulink url="http://www.nyu.edu/projects/fitch/WSRN/">http://www.nyu.edu/projects/fitch/WSRN/</ulink>) or in the F&#x000E9;lix lab collection (<ulink url="http://www2.ijm.jussieu.fr/worms">http://www2.ijm.jussieu.fr/worms</ulink>).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2_3">
<title>Population genetics</title>
<para>AFLP (Amplified Fragment Length Polymorphism) analysis on 53 wild isolates from all over the world suggest a genetic diversity at least three-fold higher than that measured with the same method in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib2">Barri&#x000E8;re and F&#x000E9;lix, 2005</link><!--; PMID 16005289-->), with no genetic differentiation between continents, yet a clear structure at a smaller scale between three local populations sampled in France (100 km scale), and a relatively high local diversity (D. Ba&#x000EF;lle and M.-A. F., unpublished).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Basic biology in the laboratory</title>
<para><emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> has the same mode of reproduction as <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (self-fertile hermaphrodites and facultative males), and can be cultured and frozen in the same conditions. The lifecycle of the reference strain CEW1 lasts approximately 3 days at 25&#x000B0;C, 4 days at 23&#x000B0;C and 5&#x02013;6 days at 20&#x000B0;C. <emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> develops through four juvenile stages and an alternative dauer stage like <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. The animals are smaller and slower than <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Eggs are laid at the one-cell stage. Adult hermaphrodites rarely bag upon starvation. The larvae are clear in Nomarski optics. The gonad is syncytial with a central medial region where injected material can diffuse (rachis).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Genetics</title>
<sect2 id="sec4_1">
<title>Basic forward genetic methods</title>
<para><emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> reproduces through XX hermaphrodites and XO males like <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
<para>The X chromosome non-disjunction rate of the reference strain CEW1 is lower than that of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> N2 and males are not easy to induce by heat-shock. However, other <emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis> strains such as PS959 have a higher proportion of males. Males reproduce less well at 25&#x000B0;C and above than at lower temperatures; therefore, crossing plates are better maintained at 23&#x000B0;C (or below).</para>
<para>Mutagenesis and genetic analysis are basically performed as in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib4">Brenner, 1974</link><!--; PMID 4366476-->). Because the germ line divides later than that of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, mutagenesis is best performed on young adults (rather than L4-stage animals). The concentration of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> used for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (50 mM) is not as efficient nor as lethal as in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>; therefore, mutageneses were performed using an <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> concentration of 100&#x02013;150 mM, or using TMP-UV irradiation.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_2">
<title>Available mutants</title>
<para>Screens for visible mutants and for mutants with a defective vulva (see below, <link linkend="sec6">Section 6</link>.) have been performed. 79 visible markers were isolated: 24 with a Dumpy or Small phenotype, 5 Rollers, 2 Longs, 1 Constipated and 47 Uncs (twitchers, kinkers, sluggish worms, coilers including one dominant allele; <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). Slightly surprisingly, 35 out of 74 mutants are X-linked (especially 26/43 Uncs compared to 3/23 Dpys, M.-L. Dichtel and M.-A. F., unpublished). Mutants with a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Him;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Him</ulink> phenotype (recessive or dominant) were also isolated, as well as one mutant with a partially penetrant left-right inversion of the body (<emphasis>cov-7</emphasis>; <link linkend="bib7">Delattre and F&#x000E9;lix, 2001c</link><!--; PMID 11401398-->; <link linkend="bib20">Louvet-Vall&#x000E9;e et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12586702-->).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="5in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The apparent haploid number of chromosomes observed by DAPI staining of the germ line is six, as in <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis> G. Maro, M.-L. Dichtel and M.-A. F&#x000E9;lix defined (by genetic complementation or linkage data; unpublished) 6 <emphasis>dpy</emphasis> loci, 7 <emphasis>unc</emphasis> loci and 2 <emphasis>lon</emphasis> loci. The <emphasis>unc</emphasis>, <emphasis>dpy</emphasis>, and <emphasis>lon</emphasis> loci are provisionally designated by a letter to avoid confusion with <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> loci. Rough linkage data gave six linkage groups, which may or may not cover the six chromosomes:</para>
<simplelist>
<member><emphasis role="underline">5 autosomal linkage groups:</emphasis></member>
<member>A. <emphasis>unc-a(sy486)</emphasis> (Twitcher), <emphasis>unc-c(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mf43;class=Variation" role="_blank">mf43</ulink>)</emphasis>, <emphasis>unc-d(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sy457;class=Variation" role="_blank">sy457</ulink>)</emphasis>, <emphasis>unc-e(mf42)</emphasis>, <emphasis>dpy-a(mf1)</emphasis>, <emphasis>dpy-e(sy517)</emphasis>, <emphasis>iov-1(mf86)</emphasis> (not ordered)</member>
<member>B. <emphasis>dpy-c(sy471), lon-a(sy475)</emphasis></member>
<member>C. <emphasis>unc-b(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mf29;class=Variation" role="_blank">mf29</ulink>)</emphasis></member>
<member>D. <emphasis>dpy-f(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sy518;class=Variation" role="_blank">sy518</ulink>)</emphasis></member>
<member>E. <emphasis>con-a(sy462)</emphasis></member>
</simplelist>
<?newpage?>
<simplelist>
<member><emphasis role="underline">X-linked:</emphasis></member>
<member><emphasis>unc-f(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sy474;class=Variation" role="_blank">sy474</ulink>)</emphasis>, <emphasis>unc-g(sy485)</emphasis>, <emphasis>rol-a(sy472)</emphasis>, <emphasis>lon-b(sy502)</emphasis> (not ordered)</member>
</simplelist>
<para>A few mutants are at CGC. Others can be found at <ulink url="http://www2.ijm.jussieu.fr/worms">http://www2.ijm.jussieu.fr/worms</ulink>. The gene nomenclature is temporary, since these loci are not homologs to the corresponding <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes. Once their molecular identity is determined, the correct nomenclature is, for example, <emphasis>Oti-lin-39</emphasis> for the <emphasis>Oscheius tipulae <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-39;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> ortholog.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_3">
<title>Reverse genetics</title>
<para>Injection of morpholinos results in a partial inactivation of the corresponding gene product, for example <emphasis>Oti-lin-39</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib20">Louvet-Vall&#x000E9;e et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12586702-->) or <emphasis>Oti-let-60</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib10">Dichtel-Danjoy and F&#x000E9;lix, 2004</link><!--; PMID 14697357-->). However, as in many non-<emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> nematodes, RNA interference does not appear to work efficiently: injection of double-stranded RNA for various genes has not produced any phenotype.</para>
<para>DNA-mediated transformation has been unsuccessful so far, but recent studies in <emphasis>Strongyloides stercoralis</emphasis> suggest that using a 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol>UTR from the species may be crucial for transgene expression (<link linkend="bib19">Li et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16500658-->). This remains to be tested in <emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis>. Plasmids injected into the mother&apos;s female germ line have been detected by PCR in the F1 progeny (M.-L. Dichtel, unpublished).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Genome and molecular biology resources</title>
<para>From rough estimates based on hybridization of a genomic library, the genome size of <emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> appears similar to that of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (M. Delattre, unpublished). Its GC content was determined to be close to 43&#x00025; (<link linkend="bib1">Ahn and Winter, 2005</link>). Codon biases of highly expressed genes such as vitellogenins appear slightly different from those in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib30">Winter et al., 1996</link>). Transcription in operons also occurs in <emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis> as in <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> with SL1 and SL2 trans-splicing; these SL sequences are similar yet slightly different from those of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib11">Evans et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9275196-->).</para>
<para>Libraries from <emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> CEW1 include a cDNA library in <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003BB;</symbol>ZAP II described in <link linkend="bib12">F&#x000E9;lix et al. (2000)</link> and a genomic library in <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003BB;</symbol>FIX II described in <link linkend="bib20">Louvet-Vall&#x000E9;e et al. (2003<!--; PMID 12586702-->)</link> (available on request: <ulink url="mailto:felix@ijm.jussieu.fr">felix@ijm.jussieu.fr</ulink>).</para>
<para><emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> taxon number in sequence databases is 141969; because of changes in the species&#x02019; name that have been associated with particular strains in the literature (see <link linkend="sec1_2">Section 1.2</link>), some of the sequences may not appear in a direct search for &#x0201C;<emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis>&#x0201D; in databases. In addition, a few dozen ESTs have been sequenced (M.-A. F. and P.W. Sternberg, unpublished).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Developmental biology</title>
<sect2 id="sec6_1">
<title>Gonad development</title>
<para>Gonad development and morphology of <emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis> are overall similar to those of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, except that germ line divisions are delayed. However, <emphasis>O. guentheri</emphasis> presents an interesting case of variable partial reduction of the posterior gonadal arm, which appears to result from a lesser activity of the posterior distal tip cell in its roles in arm migration and germ line proliferation (<link linkend="bib13">F&#x000E9;lix and Sternberg, 1996</link><!--; PMID 8681794-->).</para>
<para>Anchor cell determination is stochastic and unbiased in <emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis> as in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, but biased towards <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4.aaa;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4.aaa</ulink> becoming the anchor cell in <emphasis>Oscheius guentheri</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib13">F&#x000E9;lix and Sternberg, 1996</link><!--; PMID 8681794-->; <link linkend="bib28">Sudhaus and Hooper, 1994</link>).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6_2">
<title>Vulva development</title>
<para><emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> has been mostly studied for its vulva development (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_evoldevnematode/evoldevnematode.html" role="_blank">see Evolution of development in nematodes related to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). Several features make it a particularly interesting comparison to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Its vulval cell lineage is different, and simpler than that of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. In particular, it is much easier to distinguish the 1&#x000B0; and 2&#x000B0; precursor cell fates by the number of division rounds they undergo (three and two, respectively) (<link linkend="bib25">Sommer and Sternberg, 1995</link><!--; PMID 7851663-->; <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). The vulval competence group is composed of P(4-8).p: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P3.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P3.p</ulink> is not competent (unlike in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>). The adult vulva is formed of six superposed rings, instead of seven in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib20">Louvet-Vall&#x000E9;e et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12586702-->). Most strikingly, anchor cell ablations demonstrate that the anchor cell is required after <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P6.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P6.p</ulink> division for its daughters to acquire a 1&#x000B0; fate: if the anchor cell is ablated in the mid-L3 stage, P(5-7).p all adopt a 2&#x000B0; lineage pattern. The same spatial pattern of fates is thus induced by different mechanisms in <emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib14">F&#x000E9;lix and Sternberg, 1997</link><!--; PMID 9006085-->), and recent results suggest that the two-step induction mechanism found in <emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis> is ancestral (Kiontke et al., in preparation).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="6.5in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<para><emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis> has been used for extensive genetic screens for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Egl;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Egl</ulink> (Egg-laying defective) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Pvl;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Pvl</ulink> (Protruding vulva) mutants (<link linkend="bib9">Dichtel-Danjoy and F&#x000E9;lix, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15109782-->; <link linkend="bib23">Sommer, 2000</link>). Those with abnormal vulva development were divided in three categories corresponding to successive steps in vulval development:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="dash">
<listitem><para>Vulva competence group formation and centering : Cov mutants (for Competence/centering Of the Vulva), including a deletion in <emphasis>Oti-lin-39</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib20">Louvet-Vall&#x000E9;e et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12586702-->);</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Vulval fate induction: Iov (for Induction Of the Vulva; <link linkend="bib10">Dichtel-Danjoy and F&#x000E9;lix, 2004</link><!--; PMID 14697357-->);</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Division of vulval precursor cells, without affecting their vulval fates: Dov (for Division Of the Vulva; <link linkend="bib8">Dichtel et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11139501-->).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Interestingly, the spectrum of phenotypes obtained in vulva mutant screens in <emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis> strongly differs from that obtained in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. For example, the Dov mutations have no equivalent in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, or are at least not found at the same rate. In contrast, Hypoinduced phenotypes have proven difficult to isolate in <emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis>. Also, the 1&#x000B0;/2&#x000B0; fate pattern of Hyperinduced mutants differ between the two species. This comparison of parallel mutagenesis screens on a homologous developmental system shows that the spectrum of phenotypes that can be reached by random mutagenesis evolves (<link linkend="bib9">Dichtel-Danjoy and F&#x000E9;lix, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15109782-->).</para>
<para>A particularly interesting phenotype of <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> species is the number of division rounds of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P4.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P4.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.p</ulink>: zero in <emphasis>Oscheius guentheri</emphasis>, one in <emphasis>O. dolichura</emphasis> and <emphasis>O. dolichuroides</emphasis> (as in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>), but usually two in <emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis>, spp. 2 and 3. However, whereas <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P4.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P4.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P8.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P8.p</ulink> divide twice in the CEW1 reference strain of <emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis>, this trait is highly polymorphic within an isogenic strain or between wild isolates of <emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib5">Delattre and F&#x000E9;lix, 2001a</link><!--; PMID 11369226-->; <link linkend="bib6">Delattre and F&#x000E9;lix, 2001b</link><!--; PMID 11536293-->). From the analysis of recombinant inbred lines between the two isolates CEW1 and PS959, the difference between them (two versus one division round) is caused by variations at several segregating loci (<link linkend="bib5">Delattre and F&#x000E9;lix, 2001a</link><!--; PMID 11369226-->). P(4,8).p division is a trait that is easily mimicked by mutation in CEW1, as shown by the isolation of several mutants with one or zero division round of these cells (<link linkend="bib8">Dichtel et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11139501-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Acknowledgement</title>
<para>I thank M.-L. Dichtel-Danjoy, M. Delattre, S. Louvet-Vall&#x000E9;e, G. Maro and D. Ba&#x000EF;lle for published and unpublished work on Oscheius and K. Kiontke and anonymous reviewers for comments.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>References</title>
&Otipulae_Refs;
<para/>
</sect1>
</article>