<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 4. Asymmetric localization of polarity mediators and cell fate determinants in the early embryo</title>
        <para>P granules: black discs; cytoplasmic POS-1, MEX-1, and cytoplasmic and nuclear PIE-1: blue; nuclear PAL-1: hatched; MEX-5 and MEX-3: peach; plasma membrane localized GLP-1: black; membrane localized APX-1: green; membrane localized MES-1: red. Although shown discreetly localized for simplicity, the cytoplasmic proteins are present at low levels in the opposite domain before division, and in the sister cell after division. In addition, MEX-5, MEX-3, MEX-1, POS-1 and PIE-1 are also present on P granules. (A) MEX-5, MEX -3, MEX-1, PIE-1, POS-1 and P granules are uniformly present in the cytoplasm just after fertilization, but become asymmetrically localized during the one-cell stage. (B) The anterior and posterior determinants are differentially segregated to AB and P<subscript>1</subscript> as a result of the first asymmetric division. GLP-1 protein first appears in AB at the two-cell stage, and PIE-1 protein enters the nucleus in addition to being cytoplasmic. As the cell cycle proceeds (not shown), posterior determinants become restricted to the posterior half of P<subscript>1</subscript>, while MEX-5 appears in the anterior half of P<subscript>1</subscript>. (C) In the four-cell embryo, GLP-1 is expressed on membranes of both AB cells, but only ABp is in contact with the P<subscript>2</subscript> cell expressing APX-1. MES-1 is enriched at the cell contact between P<subscript>2</subscript> and EMS; MES-1/SRC-1 signaling in conjunction with Wnt signaling polarizes the EMS cell, such that it will divide asymmetrically. As the cell cycle proceeds, posterior determinants within P<subscript>2</subscript> become asymmetrically localized as in previous P cells. MEX-5 disappears from the AB cells, but is still present in the anterior daughters of each P division. (D) In the eight-cell embryo, P granules and PIE-1 are now restricted to the P<subscript>3</subscript> cell. P<subscript>3</subscript> will undergo asymmetric division to produce the D cell and P<subscript>4,</subscript> to which P granules and PIE-1 are segregated. Nuclear PAL-1 is present in all posterior nuclei; however, it influences the fate of the C and D cells only, as its effects are repressed by PIE-1 in the P lineage and SKN-1 protein (not shown) in EMS and its descendents.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>
