<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 5. Polarity and spindle positioning in two to six-cell stage embryos</title>
            <para>Centrosomes: black discs; microtubules: black lines; nuclei: gray circles; cortical PAR-3/PAR-6/PKC-3: red; cortical PAR-2 and PAR-1: blue; cortical GPR-1/2: green; cortical LET-99: gold. (A) Early two-cell stage. As a result of asymmetric spindle elongation during anaphase, the first division was unequal and generated a larger anterior blastomere AB and a smaller posterior blastomere P<subscript>1</subscript>. PAR-2 and PAR-1 are initially present around the entire cortex of P<subscript>1</subscript>. GPR-1/2 and LET-99 are not shown: in the early two-cell embryo, they are initially enriched in patterns similar to that seen at the end of first division. (B) After the centrosomes migrate on to a transverse plane, the P<subscript>1</subscript> nucleus rotates 90<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> during late prophase to align the centrosomes on the AP axis. By this time, asymmetric PAR domains have been reestablished, and a band of cortical LET-99 becomes detectable; cortical GPR-1/2 are uniform at this stage. For simplicity, LET-99 is shown as a band, but lower levels are present throughout the remaining cortex of both P<subscript>1</subscript> and AB. During mitosis (not shown), higher levels of GPR-1/2 are present at the posterior cortex in P<subscript>1</subscript>, and asymmetric spindle elongation occurs. (C) At third cleavage the AB cells divide along the left/right plane; the spindles shift slightly anteriorly during telophase, such that the left daughters assume a more anterior position. The EMS nucleus rotates 90<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> to align on the AP axis, while the P<subscript>2</subscript> nucleus rotates 45<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>; both movements are directed towards the cell contact region between EMS and P<subscript>2</subscript>, where GPR-1/2 levels are highest. Cortical LET-99 is present as a lateral band in P<subscript>2</subscript> and is absent from the EMS-P<subscript>2</subscript> cell contact.</para>
        </formalpara>
</caption>
