<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % local.notation.class '| MOV'>
<!NOTATION MOV SYSTEM 'MOV'>
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'acdfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'acdfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'acdfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'acdfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'acdfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'acdfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'acdfig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'acdfig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'acdfig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'acdfig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY mov1 SYSTEM 'acdmov1.mov' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov1fig SYSTEM 'acdmov1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY mov1legend SYSTEM 'acdmov1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY mov2fig SYSTEM 'acdmov2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY mov2 SYSTEM 'acdmov2.mov' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov2legend SYSTEM 'acdmov2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY mov3fig SYSTEM 'acdmov3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY mov3 SYSTEM 'acdmov3.mov' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov3legend SYSTEM 'acdmov3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY Acd_Refs SYSTEM 'acdrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="Acd_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        
        <!-- Changes in PDF style sheet
        <xsl:attribute-set name="subscript.properties">
                  <xsl:attribute name="font-size">85%</xsl:attribute>
                  </xsl:attribute-set>
        <xsl:attribute-set name="normal.para.spacing">
                  <xsl:attribute name="space-before.optimum">1.2em</xsl:attribute>
                  <xsl:attribute name="space-before.minimum">1em</xsl:attribute>
                  <xsl:attribute name="space-before.maximum">1.4em</xsl:attribute>
                  <xsl:attribute name="text-indent">24pt</xsl:attribute> 
            </xsl:attribute-set> -->
		<title>Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo<footnote><para>Edited by Geraldine Seydoux and James R. Priess. Last revised October 13, 2005. Published October 15, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: G&#x000F6;nczy, P. and Rose, L.S. Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo (October 15, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.30.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 Pierre G&#x000F6;nczy and Lesilee S. Rose. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
</footnote></title>

        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 4/24/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory> 
-->
 <author>
            <firstname>Pierre</firstname><surname>G&#x000F6;nczy<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:Pierre.Gonczy@isrec.unil.ch">Pierre.Gonczy@isrec.unil.ch</ulink> or <ulink url="mailto:lsrose@ucdavis.edu">lsrose@ucdavis.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></surname>
			<affiliation>
				<address>Swiss Institute for Experimental Cancer Research, (ISREC), CH-1066 Epalinges/Lausanne, Switzerland</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<author>
			<firstname>Lesilee S.</firstname>
			<surname>Rose<remark><superscript>&#x000A7;</superscript></remark></surname>
			<affiliation>
				<address>Section of Molecular and Cellular Biology, University of California, Davis, CA USA 95616</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	
	<abstract>
		<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Asymmetric cell divisions play an important role in generating diversity during metazoan development. In the early</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">embryo, a series of asymmetric divisions are crucial for establishing the three principal axes of the body plan (AP, DV, LR) and for segregating determinants that specify cell fates. In this review, we focus on events in the one-cell embryo that result in the establishment of the AP axis and the first asymmetric division. We first describe how the sperm-derived centrosome initiates movements of the cortical actomyosin network that result in the polarized distribution of PAR proteins. We then briefly discuss how components acting downstream of the PAR proteins mediate unequal segregation of cell fate determinants to the anterior blastomere <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> and the posterior blastomere <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink>. We also review how a heterotrimeric G protein pathway generates cortically based pulling forces acting on astral microtubules, thus mediating centrosome and spindle positioning in response to AP polarity cues. In addition, we briefly highlight events involved in establishing the DV and LR axes. The DV axis is established at the four-cell stage, following specific cell-cell interactions that occur between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink>, the two daughters of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink>, as well as between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink>, a daughter of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink>. The LR axis is established shortly thereafter by the division pattern of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABa;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABa</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink>. We conclude by mentioning how findings made in early</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">embryos are relevant to understanding asymmetric cell division and pattern formation across metazoan evolution.</emphasis></para>
	</abstract>
	
	<sect1>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>Asymmetric divisions are crucial for generating diversity during development because they yield daughter cells that differ in fate. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos, five asymmetric divisions produce six founder cells: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C;class=Cell" role="_blank">C</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=D;class=Cell" role="_blank">D</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P4;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>4</subscript></ulink> (<xref linkend="figure1"/>; see also <xref linkend="movie1"/> and <xref linkend="movie2"/>). The first asymmetric division parts the zygote into the larger anterior blastomere <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> and the smaller posterior blastomere <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink>. In turn, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink> undergoes an asymmetric division that yields <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink>. Further asymmetric division of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> into <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink>, of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink> into <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C;class=Cell" role="_blank">C</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P3;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>3</subscript></ulink>, and then of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P3;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>3</subscript></ulink> into <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=D;class=Cell" role="_blank">D</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P4;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>4</subscript></ulink>, completes the generation of six founder cells whose descendants each produce a specific subset of cell types (<link linkend="bib89">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6684600 -->).</para>
        <para>During these early cleavage divisions, the three principal axes of the body plan are established. First, the anterior-posterior (AP) axis is set up in the one-cell stage, with the sperm-derived centrosome breaking the symmetry of the oocyte and initiating a sequence of events relying on maternally-contributed proteins. Second, the dorso-ventral (DV) axis becomes apparent at the transition between the two- and four-cell stage, with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> defining the ventral side of the embryo. Third, the left-right (LR) axis is detectable at the transition between the four- and six-cell stage, with the location of two granddaughters of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABal;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABal</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABpl;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABpl</ulink>) defining the left side of the embryo. Because the position of the mitotic spindle in animal cells determines the relative size and spatial relationship of daughter cells (reviewed in <link linkend="bib68">Rappaport, 1971</link><!-- PMID 4400359 -->), proper spindle positioning during these early cleavage divisions is crucial for correct segregation of cell fate determinants and cell division patterns.</para> 
		<para>In this brief review, we discuss the principal mechanisms governing asymmetric division and axis formation during early <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryogenesis. Due to space constraints, we refer the reader to other publications for a more detailed coverage of the underlying data.</para>
        <mediaobject id="movie1" xreflabel="Movie 1">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="mov1fig" width="4in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
			<textobject><phrase>Generation of founder cells in the early embryo</phrase></textobject>
            &mov1legend;
       </mediaobject>
        
        <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="3.5in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
			<textobject><phrase>Generation of founder cells in the early embryo</phrase></textobject>
            &fig1legend;
       </mediaobject>

        <mediaobject id="movie2" xreflabel="Movie 2">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="mov2fig" width="4in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
			<textobject><phrase>Generation of founder cells in the early embryo</phrase></textobject>
            &mov2legend;
       </mediaobject>
       </sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>The one-cell stage embryo: establishment of the anterior-posterior axis</title>
		<sect2>
			<title>Breaking the symmetry</title>
			<para>In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, formation of the AP axis is initiated after fertilization, which takes place when a mature oocyte traverses the spermatheca and encounters a sperm cell. The newly fertilized zygote then moves into the uterus where the remainder of early embryogenesis takes place. In wild-type animals, sperm usually enters the egg opposite from the side of the oocyte nucleus. In addition to DNA, the sperm donates a pair of centrioles that assembles pericentriolar material (PCM) to form a centrosome that nucleates microtubules. Importantly, experiments in which the sperm entry site was altered established that a sperm component confers posterior character to the zygote (<link linkend="bib26">Goldstein and Hird, 1996</link><!-- PMID 8625834 -->).</para>
			<para>What is the nature of this symmetry-breaking cue? The cue does not appear to be the sperm entry site or paternally-contributed DNA (<link linkend="bib26">Goldstein and Hird, 1996</link><!-- PMID 8625834 -->; <link linkend="bib76">Sadler and Shakes, 2000</link><!-- PMID 10603352 -->). Early results indicated that the sperm-associated microtubule aster might correspond to the cue. Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spd-2" role="_blank">spd-2</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spd-5" role="_blank">spd-5</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=air-1" role="_blank">air-1</ulink></emphasis> that prevent PCM assembly and hence formation of astral microtubules also prevent polarity establishment (<link linkend="bib36">Hamill et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12431374 -->; <link linkend="bib64">O'Connell et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10885746 -->; <link linkend="bib97">Wallenfang and Seydoux, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11081513 -->). However, these results could not distinguish whether the cue depends on the PCM or on the microtubules it nucleates. The finding that embryos blocked in meiosis exhibit a polarity reversal correlating with the position of ectopic microtubule arrays suggested a prominent role for microtubules (<link linkend="bib97">Wallenfang and Seydoux, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11081513 -->). However, more recent evidence indicates that the centrosome per se is key. Laser-mediated ablation of the centrosome prevents polarity establishment (<link linkend="bib16">Cowan and Hyman, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15343338 -->), whereas elimination of all detectable microtubules following RNAi-mediated inactivation of tubulin genes does not (<link linkend="bib16">Cowan and Hyman, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15343338 -->; <link linkend="bib86">Sonneville and G&#x000F6;nczy, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15215208 -->). Therefore, unless extremely attenuated microtubules provide the cue, these experiments demonstrate that the centrosome or a specific protein contained within it breaks the symmetry of the zygote.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>A dynamic actomyosin network</title>
			<para>Physical association of the centrosome with the posterior cortex appears crucial for initiating the sequence of events that result in polarization of the embryo along the AP axis. Consistent with this view, proper AP polarity is not established in embryos in which this close association does not occur due to impairment of fatty acid synthesis or APC (Anaphase Promoting Complex) function (<link linkend="bib69">Rappleye et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14527340 -->; <link linkend="bib70">Rappleye et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 11832245 -->). In wild-type animals, the entire cortex undergoes surface contractions after fertilization (<xref linkend="figure2"/>A), and these movements cease in a local manner after the centrosome becomes juxtaposed to the presumptive posterior cortex (<link linkend="bib10">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15186741 -->; <link linkend="bib16">Cowan and Hyman, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15343338 -->; <link linkend="bib17">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12588843 -->; <link linkend="bib62">Munro et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15363415 -->). The smoother cortical area expands gradually towards the anterior until approximately 50% egg-length, concomitant with a flow of cortical material and neighboring yolk granules (<xref linkend="figure2"/>B; <link linkend="bib40">Hird and White, 1993</link><!-- PMID 8509454 -->). This anterior-directed cortical movement is compensated by posterior-directed flow of cytoplasmic material (<link linkend="bib40">Hird and White, 1993</link><!-- PMID 8509454 -->).</para>
       <para>Whereas it has been long recognized that actin is required for AP polarity (<link linkend="bib88">Strome and Wood, 1983</link><!-- PMID 6684994 -->), recent observations further clarified the relationship between the centrosome and the actin cytoskeleton. Imaging of the non-muscle myosin II heavy chain <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMY-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> fused to GFP revealed the presence of a dynamic meshwork of filaments connecting denser foci (<link linkend="bib62">Munro et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15363415 -->; see also <xref linkend="movie3"/>). Whereas this cortical network is initially distributed in a uniform manner (<xref linkend="figure2"/>A), GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMY-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> foci cease to form in the posterior following association of the sperm aster with the cortex. By contrast, existing foci move in an anterior-directed manner, indicating a contraction of the entire network (<xref linkend="figure2"/>B). Furthermore, the distribution of F-actin, as well as that of the E-cadherin <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HMR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HMR-1</ulink> and the <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-catenin <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HMP-2;class=protein" role="_blank">HMP-2</ulink>, demonstrates that the behavior observed with GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMY-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> reflects that of the entire cortical actomyosin network (<link linkend="bib62">Munro et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15363415 -->).</para>
      <literallayout></literallayout>
       <mediaobject id="movie3" xreflabel="Movie 3">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="mov3fig" width="5.5in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
			<textobject><phrase>Generation of founder cells in the early embryo</phrase></textobject>
            &mov3legend;
       </mediaobject> 
        </sect2> 
		<sect2>
			<title>PAR proteins and polarity establishment</title>
			<para>Contraction of the actomyosin network is crucial for establishing asymmetric distribution of PAR proteins in one-cell stage embryos (<xref linkend="figure2"/>, <xref linkend="figure3"/>). The six <emphasis>par</emphasis> genes (for <emphasis>par</emphasis>titioning defective) were identified in screens for maternal-effect mutations that result in defective AP polarity in the one-cell stage, as evidenced by the generation of daughter cells with altered fate, size, spindle orientation and cell cycle progression (<link linkend="bib49">Kemphues et al., 1988</link><!-- PMID 3345562 -->; reviewed in <link linkend="bib50">Kemphues and Strome, 1997</link><!-- PMID not available -->; <link linkend="bib74">Rose and Kemphues, 1998b</link><!-- PMID 9928490 -->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> are PDZ-containing proteins that form a complex with the atypical protein kinase C, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PKC-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink>. The distribution of this complex is restricted to the anterior cortex by the end of prophase. At that time, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink>, a Ring-finger protein, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink>, a Ser/Thr kinase, localize in a reciprocal manner to the posterior cortex. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-4;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-4</ulink>, another Ser/Thr kinase, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-5;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-5</ulink>, a 14-3-3 protein, are present in a uniform manner throughout the cortex, as well as in the cytoplasm. Systematic examination of PAR protein distributions in fixed embryos lacking the function of one of the other<emphasis> par</emphasis> genes led to the view that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-5" role="_blank">par-5</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-2" role="_blank">par-2</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-3" role="_blank">par-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-6" role="_blank">par-6</ulink></emphasis> act upstream of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-1" role="_blank">par-1</ulink></emphasis>, whereas <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-4" role="_blank">par-4</ulink></emphasis> may function in a separate pathway (reviewed in <link linkend="bib50">Kemphues and Strome, 1997</link><!-- PMID not available -->; <link linkend="bib74">Rose and Kemphues, 1998b</link><!-- PMID 9928490 -->).</para>
            <para>More recently, live imaging studies have led to a richer description of these relationships and of the dynamics of PAR protein distribution during AP polarity establishment. Imaging of GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> indicates that whereas the anterior PAR complex (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PKC-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink>) is present throughout the cortex shortly after fertilization, it recedes from the posterior soon after centrosome juxtaposition with the cortex, to eventually reach approximately 50% egg-length (<link linkend="bib17">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12588843 -->). Conversely, GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> becomes enriched on the posterior cortex in the vicinity of the centrosome shortly after onset of cortical smoothing and then extends anteriorly to approximately 50% egg-length (<link linkend="bib17">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12588843 -->). Cortical flows of GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> occur concomitantly with movements of GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMY-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> and both are severely diminished when contraction of the actomyosin network is compromised by depletion of the regulatory myosin light chain <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mlc-4" role="_blank">mlc-4</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib62">Munro et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15363415 -->). Similarly, anterior expansion of GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> does not occur in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nmy-2" role="_blank">nmy-2</ulink>(RNAi)</emphasis> embryos (<link linkend="bib17">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12588843 -->). Interestingly, fluorescence recovery after photobleaching (FRAP) shows that both GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> and GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> dynamically associate with the cell cortex during this cortical flow, indicating that they somehow recognize specific features of the receding and advancing cortices, respectively (<link linkend="bib10">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15186741 -->).</para> 
           
            <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="3in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
			<textobject><phrase>AP polarity and spindle positioning in one-cell stage embryos</phrase></textobject>
            &fig2legend;
       </mediaobject>
            <para>Whereas contraction of the actomyosin network plays a crucial role in establishing distinct domains of GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> and GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink>, <emphasis>par</emphasis> genes are required to generate robust cortical flows. Although cortical flows are similar to wild-type animals in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-1" role="_blank">par-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos, they are essentially abolished in embryos lacking <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-3" role="_blank">par-3</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-6" role="_blank">par-6</ulink></emphasis> function (<link linkend="bib10">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15186741 -->). Flows are likewise absent in embryos lacking <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEX-5;class=protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEX-6;class=protein" role="_blank">MEX-6</ulink> (<link linkend="bib10">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15186741 -->), two partially redundant CCCH finger proteins that also play a role in setting up AP polarity (<link linkend="bib17">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12588843 -->; <link linkend="bib82">Schubert et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10882103 -->). Furthermore, the movement of GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMY-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> foci away from the posterior is greatly attenuated in embryos lacking one of the anterior PAR complex components (<link linkend="bib62">Munro et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15363415 -->). Interestingly, flows are also abolished in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-4" role="_blank">par-4</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos (<link linkend="bib10">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15186741 -->), in which <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> distribution are normal initially (<link linkend="bib9">Boyd et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8898221 -->; <link linkend="bib22">Etemad-Moghadam et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 8521491 -->; <link linkend="bib42">Hung and Kemphues, 1999</link><!-- PMID 9834192 -->), indicating an apparent uncoupling between the presence of flows and proper distribution of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink>. However, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> do expand towards the posterior by the end of the one-cell stage in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-4" role="_blank">par-4</ulink></emphasis> embryos (<link linkend="bib42">Hung and Kemphues, 1999</link><!-- PMID 9834192 -->). Cortical flows also appear compromised in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-5" role="_blank">par-5</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos (<link linkend="bib10">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15186741 -->); in this case, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> can overlap, indicating a unique role for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-5" role="_blank">par-5</ulink></emphasis> in maintaining distinct anterior and posterior cortical domains (<link linkend="bib60">Morton et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 11784094 -->). In embryos lacking <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-2" role="_blank">par-2</ulink></emphasis> function, rates of cortical flow and of GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMY-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> movements are normal initially (<link linkend="bib10">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15186741 -->; <link linkend="bib62">Munro et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15363415 -->). Probably as a consequence, retraction of GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> from the embryo posterior during this establishment phase occurs normally in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-2" role="_blank">par-2</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos (<link linkend="bib17">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12588843 -->).</para>
            <literallayout></literallayout>
	<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="3.75in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
			<textobject><phrase>Sequential relationships between AP polarity components in one-cell stage embryos</phrase></textobject>
            &fig3legend;
       </mediaobject>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Maintenance of polarity</title>
			<para>The above phase of polarity establishment is followed by a distinct maintenance phase that begins just after meeting of the male and female pronuclei. During this second phase, laser-mediated ablation of the centrosome does not abolish AP polarity &#x02014; although small alterations in the extent of the GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> cortical domain are observed (<link linkend="bib16">Cowan and Hyman, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15343338 -->). Moreover, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-2" role="_blank">par-2</ulink></emphasis> is required during this phase to maintain GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> restricted to the anterior cortex. In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-2" role="_blank">par-2</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos, cortical GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> abnormally returns towards the posterior to occupy the entire circumference of the embryo (<link linkend="bib17">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12588843 -->). This may be due to the abnormal posterior-directed cortical movements of GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMY-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> that occur concomitantly and which may prevent maintenance of PAR asymmetries (<link linkend="bib62">Munro et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15363415 -->).</para> 
			<para>Another component important for the maintenance of AP polarity is the small G protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CDC-42;class=protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> (<link linkend="bib29">Gotta et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11412997 -->; <link linkend="bib47">Kay and Hunter, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11412996 -->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cdc-42" role="_blank">cdc-42</ulink>(RNAi)</emphasis> embryos, polarity appears to be correctly established, because initially <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> localizes to the anterior cortex and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> to the posterior cortex. However, these asymmetries are not maintained. Although <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CDC-42;class=protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> distribution has not been reported, the protein physically interacts with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> in a yeast two-hybrid assay (<link linkend="bib29">Gotta et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11412997 -->), as is the case in other organisms. Because Cdc42 is a universal regulator of the actin cytoskeleton, an attractive possibility is that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CDC-42;class=protein" role="_blank">CDC-42</ulink> may somehow modulate the actomyosin network during the maintenance phase to prevent posterior flow of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMY-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink>.</para>
		</sect2>
<?newpage?>		
		<sect2>
			<title>Polarity mediators and segregation of cell fate determinants</title>
			<para>After AP polarity has been established and maintained, several components act downstream of the PAR proteins to mediate unequal segregation of cell fate determinants during early embryogenesis (<xref linkend="figure3"/>, <xref linkend="figure4"/>). Whereas such polarity mediators and cell fate determinants will be mentioned briefly here, other chapters in this collection are devoted to a more detailed discussion of their nature and mechanism of action.</para> 
            <para>Polarity mediators include the CCCH-finger proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEX-1;class=protein" role="_blank">MEX-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib34">Guedes and Priess, 1997</link><!-- PMID 9043088 -->; <link linkend="bib55">Mello et al., 1992</link><!-- PMID 1623520 -->), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEX-5;class=protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEX-5;class=protein" role="_blank">6</ulink> (<link linkend="bib82">Schubert et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10882103 -->) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=POS-1;class=protein" role="_blank">POS-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib91">Tabara et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 9834181 -->), as well as the putative RNA binding proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEX-3;class=protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink> (<link linkend="bib20">Draper et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8861905 -->) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPN-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SPN-4</ulink> (<link linkend="bib27">Gomes et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11684665 -->). Inactivation of polarity mediators does not abolish AP polarity, but prevents correct segregation of cell fate determinants. Although clear in principle, the distinction between polarity proteins and polarity mediators can be difficult to make in practice. For instance, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEX-5;class=protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEX-5;class=protein" role="_blank">6</ulink> help restrict <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PKC-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink> to the anterior during polarity establishment (<link linkend="bib17">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12588843 -->), but are also regulated by PAR proteins as loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> prevents <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEX-5;class=protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEX-5;class=protein" role="_blank">6</ulink> asymmetric distribution (<link linkend="bib17">Cuenca et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12588843 -->; <link linkend="bib82">Schubert et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10882103 -->). Therefore, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEX-5;class=protein" role="_blank">MEX-5</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEX-5;class=protein" role="_blank">6</ulink> can be considered both as polarity proteins and as polarity mediators.</para> 
			<para>Three principal mechanisms ensure unequal segregation of cell fate determinants during early embryogenesis in response to AP polarity: directed transport, localized degradation and translational control (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_specgermline/specgermline.html" role="_blank">Specification of the germ line</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transctrlmaternalRNAs/transctrlmaternalRNAs.html" role="_blank">Translational control of maternal RNAs</ulink>). The segregation of P granules (<xref linkend="figure3"/>; <xref linkend="figure4"/>), large ribonucleoprotein complexes destined to the germ line, provides a good example for protein transport: present uniformly in the cytoplasm at fertilization, P granules move towards the posterior of the one-cell embryo concomitantly with cytoplasmic flows (<link linkend="bib39">Hird et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8620857 -->; <link linkend="bib88">Strome and Wood, 1983</link><!-- PMID 6684994 -->). In addition, localized degradation contributes to clearing of P granules from the anterior. Similarly, localized degradation of the CCCH-finger protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PIE-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib57">Mello et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8751440 -->), a regulator of germ line fate, exemplifies the second type of mechanism. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PIE-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> is restricted to germ line precursors (<xref linkend="figure3"/>; <xref linkend="figure4"/>) in part because protein remaining in somatic blastomeres is degraded by a CUL-2-based E3 ligase (<link linkend="bib18">DeRenzo et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12894212 -->; <link linkend="bib71">Reese et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10983990 -->). Translational control of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink>, a determinant necessary for the fate of posterior blastomeres (<link linkend="bib99">Waring and Kenyon, 1990</link><!-- PMID 2295086 -->), provides an example of the last principal mechanism. Whereas <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pal-1" role="_blank">pal-1</ulink></emphasis> mRNA is present throughout the early embryo, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink> protein becomes detectable only starting at the four cell stage and strictly in posterior blastomeres (<link linkend="bib43">Hunter and Kenyon, 1996</link><!-- PMID 8861906 -->; <xref linkend="figure4"/>C). The repression of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink> in the anterior is mediated by the KH domain protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEX-3;class=protein" role="_blank">MEX-3</ulink>, whose activity is restricted to the anterior by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib41">Huang et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 11830574 -->).</para>
   </sect2> 
	</sect1>
	<sect1> 
		<title>The one-cell stage embryo: spindle positioning</title> 
		<sect2>
			<title>Cortical forces position centrosomes</title>
			<para>Following polarity establishment, proper spindle positioning is critical for ensuring that cell fate determinants are correctly segregated to daughter cells during asymmetric division. In one-cell stage embryos, spindle positioning follows from two processes: placement of centrosomes along the AP axis during prophase, and asymmetric spindle movements along the AP axis during mitosis (<xref linkend="figure2"/>C-D; <link linkend="bib2">Albertson, 1984</link><!-- PMID 6692980 -->; <link linkend="bib63">Nigon et al., 1960</link><!-- PMID not available -->). Importantly, both processes are dependent upon the PAR proteins, which thus coordinate segregation of cell fate determinants with spindle positioning (<link linkend="bib11">Cheng et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 7713417 -->; <link linkend="bib32">Grill et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11214323 -->; <link linkend="bib49">Kemphues et al., 1988</link><!-- PMID 3345562 -->; <link linkend="bib95">Tsou et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12642612 -->).</para>
			<para>After migration of the female pronucleus towards the male pronucleus and its associated centrosomes at the embryo's posterior, the centrosomes and pronuclei move as a unit towards the embryo's center during prophase (centration). The unit also rotates by 90<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x000B0;</symbol> such that the centrosomes become aligned with the AP axis (rotation), typically before nuclear envelope breakdown (<link linkend="bib2">Albertson, 1984</link><!-- PMID 6692980 -->; <link linkend="bib45">Hyman and White, 1987</link><!-- PMID 3680373 -->). During metaphase, the entire spindle moves slightly towards the posterior (<link linkend="bib52">Labb&#x000E9; et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15492042 -->; <link linkend="bib65">Oegema et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11402065 -->), whereas the spindle elongates asymmetrically at anaphase (<link linkend="bib2">Albertson, 1984</link><!-- PMID 6692980 -->; <link linkend="bib32">Grill et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11214323 -->; <link linkend="bib63">Nigon et al., 1960</link><!--  PMID not available -->); the posterior spindle pole moves farther towards the cortex than the anterior one, thus dictating unequal cleavage. During anaphase, the posterior spindle pole also exhibits vigorous transverse oscillations while the anterior spindle pole remains relatively stationary. In addition, the posterior spindle pole assumes a disc shape during telophase.</para>
          
            <mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="2.5in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
			<textobject><phrase>Asymmetric localization of polarity mediators and cell fate determinants in the early embryo</phrase></textobject>
            &fig4legend;
       </mediaobject>
<para>&#x000A0;</para>
         <para>Spatially-confined laser ablation studies suggest that the forces driving centrosome and spindle positioning are cortically-based. Ablations of the central spindle or fragmentation of a centrosome result in movements of the liberated spindle pole or of centrosome fragments toward the cortex, revealing the extent and direction of net astral forces acting on each spindle pole or centrosome (<link linkend="bib32">Grill et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11214323 -->; <link linkend="bib33">Grill et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12881570 -->; <link linkend="bib52">Labb&#x000E9; et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15492042 -->). During rotation, forces acting on the anterior centrosome are stronger and thus pull the centrosomes and associated pronuclei towards the anterior (<xref linkend="figure2"/>C; <link linkend="bib52">Labb&#x000E9; et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15492042 -->). After rotation is complete, forces acting on the posterior centrosome strengthen, but the anterior centrosome is tethered to the anterior cortex and thus a central position of the spindle is maintained (<link linkend="bib52">Labb&#x000E9; et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15492042 -->). During metaphase and anaphase, the tether is released (<link linkend="bib52">Labb&#x000E9; et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15492042 -->) and posterior forces increase, causing the rapid posterior movement and oscillations of the posterior spindle pole (<xref linkend="figure2"/>D; <link linkend="bib32">Grill et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11214323 -->).</para>
		</sect2> 
		<sect2>
			<title>A G protein pathway transduces polarity cues to a force generation machinery</title>
            <para>A heterotrimeric G protein signaling pathway acts downstream of the PAR proteins to transduce polarity cues into appropriate force generation. Two redundant G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> subunits, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GOA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPA-16;class=protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink>, are required for rotation and asymmetric spindle movements (<link linkend="bib30">Gotta and Ahringer, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11231580 -->; <link linkend="bib95">Tsou et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14534135 -->). Spindle severing and centrosome fragmentation experiments show that these proteins are required for the majority of force generation during anaphase (<link linkend="bib14">Colombo et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12750478 -->; <link linkend="bib33">Grill et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12881570 -->). The GoLoco-motif proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> are similarly required for force generation (<link linkend="bib14">Colombo et al., 2003</link> ; <link linkend="bib33">Grill et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12881570 -->) and are related to PINS, which functions during asymmetric cell division in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib77">Schaefer et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10753746 -->; <link linkend="bib103">Yu et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10693757 -->). The phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gpr-1" role="_blank">gpr-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gpr-2" role="_blank">gpr-2</ulink>(RNAi)</emphasis> is identical to that of simultaneously inactivating <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=goa-1" role="_blank">goa-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gpa-16" role="_blank">gpa-16</ulink></emphasis>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> act as guanine nucleotide dissociation inhibitors towards <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GOA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib1">Afshar et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15479639 -->; <link linkend="bib31">Gotta et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12814548 -->). Thus, it has been suggested that G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>-GDP might be the active signaling species for force generation (<link linkend="bib14">Colombo et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12750478 -->). Although loss of G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol><symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B3;</symbol> also produces spindle positioning defects in one-cell embryos (<link linkend="bib30">Gotta and Ahringer, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11231580 -->; <link linkend="bib104">Zwaal et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8752216 -->), they are suppressed by loss of G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> activity (<link linkend="bib30">Gotta and Ahringer, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11231580 -->; <link linkend="bib95">Tsou et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14534135 -->). This suggests that G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol><symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B3;</symbol> does not play a positive role in spindle positioning in one-cell stage embryos, but rather acts as a negative regulator of G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>, probably by sequestering it in the inactive heterotrimer.</para>
            <para>How does G protein activity lead to asymmetric force generation on spindle poles? <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GOA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPA-16;class=protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink> are uniformly distributed at the cortex and around the asters (<link linkend="bib1">Afshar et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15479639 -->; <link linkend="bib30">Gotta and Ahringer, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11231580 -->; <link linkend="bib59">Miller and Rand, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11102364 -->; M.F. Tsou and L. Rose, as well as K. Colombo, K. Afshar and P. G&#x000F6;nczy, unpublished observations), as is <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-5;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink>, a coiled-coil protein required for asymmetric spindle positioning and for cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> distribution (<link linkend="bib87">Srinivasan et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12730122 -->). In contrast, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> are enriched at the posterior of the embryo from metaphase through cytokinesis in a PAR-dependent manner, and could thus provide asymmetry of G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> signaling during that time (<link linkend="bib14">Colombo et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12750478 -->; <link linkend="bib31">Gotta et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12814548 -->; <link linkend="bib95">Tsou et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14534135 -->).</para>
            <para>In addition to AP polarity cues, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> asymmetry requires <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-99" role="_blank">let-99</ulink></emphasis> function (<link linkend="bib95">Tsou et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14534135 -->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-99;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> is a DEP domain protein needed for proper nuclear rotation and anaphase spindle movements and it is asymmetrically localized in a posterior cortical band in response to PAR proteins (<link linkend="bib94">Tsou et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12223405 -->; <link linkend="bib95">Tsou et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14534135 -->; <xref linkend="figure2"/>C). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-99" role="_blank">let-99</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> localization is uniform during anaphase, and appears stronger at the cortex in early stages. Thus, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-99;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> appears to inhibit <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> localization to the cortex. In addition, comparison of single and double mutant phenotypes supports the hypothesis that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-99;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> antagonizes G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> activity (<link linkend="bib95">Tsou et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14534135 -->). These findings have led to the model that during prophase, when the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-99;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> band appears but <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> localization is still uniform, force generation is inhibited in the lateral posterior cortex. This would result in stronger forces pulling from both the entire anterior cortex and a small region of the posterior cortex, thus inducing rotation (<xref linkend="figure2"/>C). Because the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-99;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> band is posteriorly positioned, this model is consistent with the laser ablation studies showing that the net anterior forces are higher than posterior forces during prophase. During anaphase, higher levels of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> at the posterior could produce higher G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> activity and thus greater pulling force towards the posterior (<xref linkend="figure2"/>D). Exactly how <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-99;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> modulates G protein activity at the molecular level is an interesting question for future studies.</para>
            <para>The cell autonomous nature of spindle positioning in the P lineage is consistent with the idea that G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> function as part of a receptor-independent G protein pathway (reviewed in <link linkend="bib37">Hampoelz and Knoblich, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15537535 -->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_heterotrimericGproteins/heterotrimericGproteins.html" role="_blank">Heterotrimeric G-proteins in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). However, details of the activation mechanism remain to be determined. In particular, how the heterotrimer gets dissociated in the absence of an activated receptor, and the nucleotide state of the G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> species that activates downstream effectors, are not known. Evidence that a nucleotide cycle is critical for G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> signaling comes from the analysis of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RIC-8;class=protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RGS-7;class=protein" role="_blank">RGS-7</ulink>, which are both required for normal anaphase spindle positioning (<link linkend="bib1">Afshar et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15479639 -->; <link linkend="bib15">Couwembergs et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15498497 -->; <link linkend="bib38">Hess et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15479638 -->; <link linkend="bib59">Miller and Rand, 2000</link><!-- PMID -->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RIC-8;class=protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> has guanine nucleotide exchange activity (GEF) on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GOA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib1">Afshar et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15479639 -->; <link linkend="bib38">Hess et al., 2004</link>), while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RGS-7;class=protein" role="_blank">RGS-7</ulink> can activate GOA-1's GTPase activity (<link linkend="bib38">Hess et al., 2004</link>). Severing experiments show that like G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RIC-8;class=protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> is required for force generation on both spindle poles (<link linkend="bib1">Afshar et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15479639 -->). Thus, G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>-GTP might appear to be the active signaling species for force generation. However, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RIC-8;class=protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> is required for binding of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GOA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GOA-1</ulink>, but not the reverse (<link linkend="bib1">Afshar et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15479639 -->), and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ric-8" role="_blank">ric-8</ulink></emphasis> is also needed for efficient cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> localization (<link linkend="bib1">Afshar et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15479639 -->; <link linkend="bib1">Couwembergs et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15498497 -->). Thus, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RIC-8;class=protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> appears to act upstream of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink>. These data raise the possibility that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RIC-8;class=protein" role="_blank">RIC-8</ulink> somehow promotes generation of G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>-GTP freed from G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol><symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B3;</symbol>. Subsequent hydrolysis to G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>-GDP, followed by binding to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> could then form the active species (<link linkend="bib1">Afshar et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15479639 -->). Loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RGS-7;class=protein" role="_blank">RGS-7</ulink> results in low forces on the anterior spindle pole only (<link linkend="bib38">Hess et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15479638 -->), lending further support to the possibility that G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>-GDP is the active species, at the least on the anterior side.</para>
 </sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Potential downstream targets of the pathway</title>
			<para>What are the downstream targets of the G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> signaling pathway that generate the forces acting on astral microtubules during spindle positioning? Given the complexity of G protein pathways and microtubule dynamics, multiple downstream targets are anticipated. Centration and rotation depend on long astral microtubules and the molecular motor dynein and its associated subunits (<link linkend="bib12">Cockell et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15331665 -->; <link linkend="bib28">G&#x000F6;nczy et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10508861 -->; <link linkend="bib54">Matthews et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9606208 -->; <link linkend="bib80">Schmidt et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID 15616192 -->; <link linkend="bib85">Skop and White, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9778526 -->; <link linkend="bib101">Yoder and Han, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11598181 -->). Dynein is localized on the spindle, in the cytoplasm and weakly at the cortex (<link linkend="bib28">G&#x000F6;nczy et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10508861 -->). Because dynein is a minus end directed microtubule motor, it is thought that cortically-anchored dynein pulls on astral microtubules to generate forces for centration and rotation. A weak reduction in dynein also prevents formation of the disk shape aster (<link linkend="bib83">Severson and Bowerman, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12695495 -->), raising the possibility that dynein plays a role during anaphase. However, inactivation of the dynein heavy chain, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dhc-1" role="_blank">dhc-1</ulink></emphasis>, using temperature-sensitive mutant alleles does not prevent anaphase spindle positioning, even though other dynein-dependent processes, including centration/rotation can be affected using these alleles (<link linkend="bib80">Schmidt et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID 15616192 -->). Thus, it would appear that dynein is not a major contributor to force generation during anaphase. Alternatively, because these temperature-sensitive alleles are not null, and because more microtubules contact the cell cortex during anaphase than during centration/rotation, perhaps there is sufficient residual dynein activity under these conditions to mediate anaphase movements. Overall, dynein and its associated subunits remain plausible candidates for regulation by G protein signaling, as are other microtubule associated proteins. Furthermore, microtubules could be a direct target of this regulation, a possibility suggested by the observation that bovine brain G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> modulates microtubule dynamics <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib75">Roychowdhury et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10224115 -->). Studies of cortical microtubule-residency time in one-cell stage <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos have revealed that the anterior has less dynamic microtubules than the posterior during metaphase and anaphase, and this difference is PAR-dependent (<link linkend="bib51">Labb&#x000E9; et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12725727 -->). However, residency time is much less affected by loss of G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> signaling than would be anticipated from the laser ablation experiments (<link linkend="bib51">Labb&#x000E9; et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12725727 -->), and thus how residency time relates to force generation remains to be clarified.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>The two-cell stage embryo: formation of the dorsal/ventral axis</title>
			<para>The daughters of the first asymmetric division display different developmental fates and division patterns. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cell undergoes a symmetric division in which the spindle is oriented on an axis perpendicular to the AP axis (<xref linkend="figure5"/>B). This orientation is controlled by the PAR proteins, as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> prevents placement of the spindle onto the AP axis (<link linkend="bib11">Cheng et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 7713417 -->; <link linkend="bib95">Tsou et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12642612 -->). In contrast, as in the one-cell stage (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P0;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>0</subscript></ulink>), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink> undergoes an asymmetric division with its spindle oriented on the AP axis, following a 90<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> rotation of the centrosomes and associated nucleus prior to mitosis (<xref linkend="figure5"/>B; <link linkend="bib45">Hyman and White, 1987</link><!-- PMID 3680373 -->). Asymmetric division of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink> depends on the PAR proteins. Although <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> are initially present around the entire cortex in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink> (<xref linkend="figure5"/>A), an anterior <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> domain forms during prophase, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink> recede to the posterior cortex, as do P granules (<xref linkend="figure5"/>B; <link linkend="bib9">Boyd et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8898221 -->; <link linkend="bib22">Etemad-Moghadam et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 8521491 -->; <link linkend="bib35">Guo and Kemphues, 1995</link><!-- PMID 7758115 -->; <link linkend="bib39">Hird et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8620857 -->). This suggests that polarity is actively reestablished in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink>, a view substantiated by mutants such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ooc-5" role="_blank">ooc-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ooc-3" role="_blank">ooc-3</ulink></emphasis> in which PAR localization is largely normal in the one-cell, but not in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink> (<link linkend="bib3">Basham and Rose, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10545235 -->; <link linkend="bib67">Pichler et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10769231 -->). GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> localization in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink> is coincident with a flow of cortical GFP-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MY-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> similar to that seen in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P0;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>0</subscript></ulink> (<link linkend="bib62">Munro et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15363415 -->), but the cue for this flow has not been identified. Thus, the events that polarize <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink> are similar, but not identical, to those in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P0;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>0</subscript></ulink>.</para>
			<para>The movements that determine spindle position in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink> are also similar to those described for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P0;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>0</subscript></ulink> (<xref linkend="figure5"/>B). Moreover, G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-99;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> and dynein are all required for nuclear rotation in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink> (<link linkend="bib14">Colombo et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12750478 -->; <link linkend="bib30">Gotta and Ahringer, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11231580 -->; <link linkend="bib31">Gotta et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12814548 -->; <link linkend="bib73">Rose and Kemphues, 1998a</link><!-- PMID 9477332 -->; <link linkend="bib80">Schmidt et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID 15616192 -->; <link linkend="bib87">Srinivasan et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12730122 -->) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-99;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> is localized in a band pattern (<link linkend="bib94">Tsou et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12223405 -->), presumably in response to PAR cues. Embryos with impaired G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol><symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B3;</symbol> function have abnormal centrosome positioning and late rotation in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink> (<link linkend="bib30">Gotta and Ahringer, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11231580 -->) but it remains to be determined if these defects are due to excess G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> signaling, as for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P0;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>0</subscript></ulink>, or whether G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol><symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B3;</symbol> plays a direct role in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink> spindle positioning. Anaphase spindle positioning has not been analyzed extensively in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink>, but may follow the same rules as in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P0;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>0</subscript></ulink> given that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> are enriched at the posterior cortex here as well (<link linkend="bib14">Colombo et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12750478 -->; <link linkend="bib31">Gotta et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12814548 -->; <link linkend="bib95">Tsou et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14534135 -->).</para>
            <para>There are several other genes required for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink> nuclear rotation, but their precise roles remain to be determined. For example, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spn-4" role="_blank">spn-4</ulink></emphasis> was originally described based on centrosome positioning defects at the two-cell stage (<link linkend="bib27">Gomes et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11684665 -->). However, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPN-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SPN-4</ulink> is now known to be involved in translation regulation (<link linkend="bib41">Huang et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 11830574 -->; <link linkend="bib66">Ogura et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12702662 -->) and thus defective spindle orientation may be due to defects in translation of some of the aforementioned factors. An interesting aspect of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spn-4" role="_blank">spn-4</ulink></emphasis> phenotype is that PAR domains in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P1;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>1</subscript></ulink> are initially normal, but then realign with the transverse spindle later in the cell cycle; this suggests the existence of a mechanism that reinforces alignment of the spindle with cell polarity (<link linkend="bib27">Gomes et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11684665 -->).</para>
            
            <mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="3in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
			<textobject><phrase>Polarity and spindle positioning in two to six-cell stage embryos</phrase>
			</textobject>
            &fig5legend;
            </mediaobject>
			<para>After asymmetric division of the two-cell embryo, localized cell fate determinants lead to unique fates for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink>, with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> defining the ventral portion of the embryo (<xref linkend="figure4"/>C). Further, the second division spindle positions, combined with the constraints of the eggshell, lead to a stereotypical arrangement of cell contacts in the four-cell embryo <xref linkend="figure5"/>C) that play a critical role in cell signaling that distinguishes dorsal from ventral. Only the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> daughters express the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLP-1</ulink> receptor (<link linkend="bib23">Evans et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 8168128 -->), while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink> expresses the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=APX-1;class=protein" role="_blank">APX-1</ulink> ligand (<xref linkend="figure4"/>C; <link linkend="bib58">Mickey et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8674418 -->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transctrlmaternalRNAs/transctrlmaternalRNAs.html" role="_blank">Translational control of maternal RNAs</ulink>). Thus <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLP-1</ulink> signaling is asymmetrically activated in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> through contact with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink>, which induces dorsal fates in ABp's descendents (<link linkend="bib53">Mango et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 7925031 -->; <link linkend="bib56">Mello et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 8156602 -->; <link linkend="bib61">Moskowitz et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID 7720570 -->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_notchembryo/notchembryo.html" role="_blank">Notch signaling in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_lin12Notch/lin12notch.html" role="_blank">LIN-12/Notch signaling in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). At the same time, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink> signals to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> via both a Wnt signaling pathway (<link linkend="bib72">Rocheleau et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9288750 -->; <link linkend="bib92">Thorpe et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9288749 -->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_wntsignaling/wntsignaling.html" role="_blank">Wnt signaling</ulink>) and a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SRC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SRC-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MES-1;class=protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink> signaling pathway (<link linkend="bib4">Bei et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12110172 -->) which polarize <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> and permit its later asymmetric division (<xref linkend="figure4"/>C, D).</para>
	</sect1>
<?newpage?>
	<sect1>
        <title>The four-cell stage embryo: formation of the left/right axis</title>
        <para>At third cleavage, the left/right (LR) axis is determined by the divisions of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABa;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABa</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink>, whereas asymmetric divisions of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> further refine cell fates. Although the spindles of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABa;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABa</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> set up orthogonal with respect to the AP and DV axes, the spindles skew towards the anterior during telophase. The lefthand daughters are thus more anterior in position and have different cell-cell contacts than their righthand counterparts (<xref linkend="figure4"/>C; <link linkend="bib89">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6684600 -->; <link linkend="bib100">Wood, 1991</link><!-- PMID 1992354 -->). Subsequent signaling between the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink> descendents, again utilizing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLP-1</ulink>, produces distinct lineages on the left and right sides (<link linkend="bib44">Hutter and Schnabel, 1995</link><!-- PMID 7588074 -->). This leads to the invariant left/right handedness of the adult (<link linkend="bib5">Bergmann et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9842711 -->). The only component known to play a major role in left/right handedness is the G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPA-16;class=protein" role="_blank">GPA-16</ulink> (<link linkend="bib6">Bergmann et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14534142 -->). Temperature sensitive <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gpa-16" role="_blank">gpa-16</ulink></emphasis> mutants raised at intermediate temperature have variable <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABa;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABa</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> spindle positions. In some cases, the telophase shift in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABa;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABa</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> is reversed, which correlates with the production of adult worms with reversed handedness. It remains to be determined if G protein signaling is part of the cue for left/right handedness, or whether the G protein pathway is responding to an asymmetry established earlier during development.</para>
        <para>After the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABa;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABa</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABp</ulink> cells divide, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> divides asymmetrically to produce <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink>, the precursor of all intestinal tissue, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink>, a major muscle precursor (<link linkend="bib89">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6684600 -->). The Wnt and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SRC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SRC-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MES-1;class=protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink> signaling pathways function to polarize <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> such that the daughter born next to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink> attains <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink> fate (<xref linkend="figure4"/>C, D; <link linkend="bib4">Bei et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12110172 -->; <link linkend="bib25">Goldstein, 1992</link><!-- PMID 1589023 -->; <link linkend="bib72">Rocheleau et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9288750 -->; <link linkend="bib92">Thorpe et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9288749 -->); both signaling pathways also function in orientation of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> spindle towards <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink> (<xref linkend="figure5"/>C; <link linkend="bib25">Goldstein, 1992</link><!-- PMID 1589023 -->; <link linkend="bib79">Schlesinger et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10444600 -->). Many components of the canonical Wnt signaling pathway play a role in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=E;class=Cell" role="_blank">E</ulink> cell specification. Only some of them are also used for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> spindle positioning. Interestingly however, several of these are shared with the "non-canonical" Wnt signaling pathway that establishes planar cell polarity in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib72">Rocheleau et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9288750 -->; <link linkend="bib79">Schlesinger et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10444600 -->; <link linkend="bib92">Thorpe et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9288749 -->; <link linkend="bib98">Walston et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15572126 -->). The downstream targets in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> that function specifically in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> spindle positioning remain to be identified. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SRC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SRC-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MES-1;class=protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink> pathway for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> spindle positioning acts at least in part through G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> signaling and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-99;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> are enriched at the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink> cell contact region (<xref linkend="figure5"/>C), along with their cortical partner <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-5;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink> (<link linkend="bib31">Gotta et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12814548 -->; <link linkend="bib87">Srinivasan et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12730122 -->; <link linkend="bib95">Tsou et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14534135 -->). This localization depends on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MES-1;class=protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink> but not Wnt signaling. Further, temperature sensitive <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gpa-16" role="_blank">gpa-16</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos showed a partially penetrant defect in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> spindle orientation when shifted to the restrictive temperature after a normal second division (<link linkend="bib95">Tsou et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14534135-->). In contrast to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-99;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> is absent from the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink> cell contact, but is uniformly localized to the remaining cortex. This pattern is also dependent on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MES-1;class=protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink> signaling, and temperature shifts of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-99" role="_blank">let-99</ulink>ts</emphasis> embryos during second division result in uniform <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> and failure of rotation in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> at the four-cell stage (<link linkend="bib95">Tsou et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14534135 -->). Thus, a similar G protein module may be used for spindle alignment in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink>, but the role of other G protein signaling components, as well as the downstream targets that execute this alignment, remain to be elucidated.</para>
        <para>After <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> division is complete, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink> undergoes asymmetric division to produce <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C;class=Cell" role="_blank">C</ulink>, a muscle and hypodermis precursor and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P3;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>3</subscript></ulink>, which divides asymmetrically to produce <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=D;class=Cell" role="_blank">D</ulink>, a muscle precursor and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P4;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>4</subscript></ulink>, the germ-line precursor (<xref linkend="figure1"/>D; <xref linkend="figure4"/>D; <link linkend="bib89">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6684600 -->; reviewed in <link linkend="bib81">Schnabel and Priess, 1997</link><!-- PMID not available -->). PAR domains are established in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>2</subscript></ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/cell/cell.cgi?name=P2;class=Cell" role="_blank">P<subscript>3</subscript></ulink>, but their position, as well as the orientation of the asymmetric divisions, are reversed with respect to the earlier divisions (<xref linkend="figure5"/>C; <link linkend="bib78">Schierenberg, 1987</link><!-- PMID 3596018 -->). Reversal of polarity is also dependent on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MES-1;class=protein" role="_blank">MES-1</ulink> function (<link linkend="bib7">Berkowitz and Strome, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11003841 -->; reviewed in <link linkend="bib50">Kemphues and Strome, 1997</link><!-- PMID -->)</para>
        <para>As a result of the asymmetric divisions and cell interactions described above, numerous cell fate determinants become differentially localized to specific cells or subsets of cells in the early embryo (<xref linkend="figure4"/>). These determinants then interact to instruct each of the founder cells to carry out a specific pattern of cell division and developmental program which will ultimately result in the making of an embryo ready to hatch.</para>
        </sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Evolutionarily conserved themes</title>
			<para>Many of the findings made in the early <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo and that were briefly reviewed above have had important bearing on understanding related biological processes in other organisms. Thus, the PAR proteins play a central role in cell polarity across metazoan evolution (reviewed in <link linkend="bib48">Kemphues, 2000</link><!-- PMID 10830161 -->). For instance, <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> Bazooka encodes a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> homologue that forms a complex with DmPar6 and an atypical protein kinase C; this complex is located on the apical side of epithelial cells and neuroblasts and is required for their proper polarity (reviewed in <link linkend="bib19">Doe, 2001</link><!-- PMID 11146637 -->). A complex containing Par3/Par6/aPKC is also present in apically located tight junctions of polarized mammalian epithelial cells (<link linkend="bib46">Izumi et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9763423 -->). Moreover, overexpression of a dominant negative mutant of aPKC results in defective surface polarity of mammalian MDCK epithelial cells (<link linkend="bib90">Suzuki et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11257119 -->). Similarly, <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> DmPar-1 is required notably for maintaining polarity in the follicular epithelium during oogenesis (<link linkend="bib84">Shulman et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10830165 -->; <link linkend="bib93">Tomancak et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10878812 -->), whereas its mammalian counterpart promotes formation of tight junctions in MDCK cells (<link linkend="bib8">Bohm et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9259552 -->; <link linkend="bib13">Cohen et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14981097 -->). Taken together, these observations indicate that the function of the PAR proteins has been significantly conserved across metazoan evolution.</para> 
			<para>The use of PAR proteins to regulate G protein signaling also appears to be conserved (reviewed in <link linkend="bib37">Hampoelz and Knoblich, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15537535 -->). In <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> neuroblasts and sensory organ precursors, Bazooka directs asymmetric distribution of G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol><subscript>i</subscript> and PINS (a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> homologue) to one side of the cell, and both G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol><subscript>i</subscript> and PINS are required for proper spindle positioning. Despite the common use of the PAR and G proteins in asymmetric division in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>, there are clear differences as well between the two systems. For instance, whereas G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol><symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B3;</symbol> function in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> merely serves to dampen G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> activity, as discussed above, it appears to be essential for generating spindle asymmetry in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> neuroblasts (<link linkend="bib24">Fuse et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12781133 -->; <link linkend="bib102">Yu et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12925708 -->). In addition, there is no clear orthologue of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-99;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-99</ulink> in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>, although potential orthologues are found in the mouse and human genomes (L.Rose, unpublished). Interestingly, the requirement for G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> proteins in ensuring spindle positioning extends to mammals. Indeed, LGN, a mammalian homologue of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GPR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GPR-2</ulink> and PINS, is recruited to the cortex through association with G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol><subscript>i</subscript> (<link linkend="bib21">Du and Macara, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15537540 -->). LGN also associates with the microtubule-binding protein NuMA, which may thus be brought to the cell cortex to act as an effector of spindle positioning (<link linkend="bib21">Du and Macara, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15537540 -->). Whereas the effectors that govern spindle positioning remain to be identified in both <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>, these findings illustrate that work in multiple systems will lead to a greater understanding of the regulation of spindle positioning by cellular polarity across metazoan evolution.</para>
            <para>As discussed above, the mechanisms of cellular polarity and asymmetric division that determine the AP axis in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have clear parallels in other organisms. Likewise, the specification of the other axes of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo, as well as that of particular cell fates, utilize highly conserved signaling modules, including the Wnt and Notch signaling pathways (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_wntsignaling/wntsignaling.html" role="_blank">Wnt signaling</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_notchembryo/notchembryo.html" role="_blank">Notch signaling in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_lin12Notch/lin12notch.html" role="_blank">LIN-12/Notch signaling in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). Thus, just as the study of the early <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo provided key insight into developmental processes, studies in other systems inform the work in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to give a broader picture of the mechanisms that control development.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Acknowledgements</title>
			<para>We are grateful to Katayoun Afshar, Kenneth Kemphues, Eric Mortensen and Daniel Starr for critical reading of the manuscript. We thank Ed Munro for providing us with <xref linkend="movie3"/>. Research in the G&#x000F6;nczy laboratory is supported by the Swiss National Science Foundation (3100A0-102087) and Oncosuisse (OCS-01495-02-2004), that in the Rose laboratory by the NIH (R01GM068744-01A1) and previously by the American Cancer Society (RPG-00-076-1-ddc).</para>
	</sect1>
    <sect1>
    <title>References</title>
    <para/>
    &Acd_Refs;
    </sect1>
</article>