<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 8. SL1-type operons.</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">A.</emphasis> In this type of operon, 3&apos; cleavage may occur by SL1 trans-splicing at least sometimes, resulting in a downstream mature SL1 trans-spliced mRNA and an upstream precursor that apparently can be polyadenylated at the site of trans-splicing&ndash;catalyzed cleavage. The transcriptome data has 40 SL1 reads and no SL2 reads (<link linkend="bib1">Allen et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21177958-->). The green bars show extents of a few ESTs, where the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00044008;class=Gene" role="_blank">gip-2</ulink></emphasis> EST ends precisely at the site where the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C45G3.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">C45G3.5</ulink> ESTs begin. The sequence of the genome at this site is shown below. The polyA addition signal, the variant sequence AGUAAA in this case, is underlined, as is the trans-splice site. <emphasis role="bold">B.</emphasis> An SL1-type operon with no monocistronic mRNA for the upstream gene. In this two-gene operon, 3&apos; end formation occurs only at the 3&apos; end of the cluster. There is no CstF-64 peak at the 3&apos; end of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00011563;class=Gene" role="_blank">jmjd-4</ulink> in a ChIP-seq experiment, whereas there is a strong peak at the 3&apos; end of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T07C4.12;class=Gene" role="_blank"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00044891;class=Gene" role="_blank">T07C4.12</ulink></ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson12628">A. Garrido-Lecca</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson71">T. Blumenthal</ulink>, unpublished). Although there is no 3&apos; end formation within the operon, there is SL1 trans-splicing that results in production of mature <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T07C4.12;class=Gene" role="_blank"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00044891;class=Gene" role="_blank">T07C4.12</ulink></ulink> mRNA, as indicated by 188 SL1 transcriptome reads at this site (<link linkend="bib1">Allen et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21177958-->). The upstream gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00011563;class=Gene" role="_blank">jmjd-4</ulink></emphasis>, must be expressed from the dicistronic mRNA where the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T07C4.12;class=Gene" role="_blank"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00044891;class=Gene" role="_blank">T07C4.12</ulink></ulink> encoding exons are out of frame. The sequence shown at the bottom is of some of the intercistronic DNA. The trans-splice site is underlined.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>