<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'intermetabfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'intermetabfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'intermetabfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'intermetabfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'intermetabfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'intermetabfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY intermetab_Refs SYSTEM 'intermetabrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="intermetab_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<title>Intermediary metabolism<footnote>
			<para>Edited by Patricia Kuwabara. Last revised August 12, 2008. Published February 16, 2009. This chapter should be cited as: Braeckman et al. Intermediary metabolism (February 16, 2009), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.146.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2008 Bart P. Braeckman et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
		<author>
			<othername>Bart P. Braeckman, Koen Houthoofd, Jacques R. Vanfleteren<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: &#x0002B;&#x0002B;32.9.264.5212; Fax: &#x0002B;&#x0002B;32.9.264.8793. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:Jacques.Vanfleteren@UGent.be">Jacques.Vanfleteren@UGent.be</ulink></para></footnote></remark></othername>
			<affiliation><address>Biology Department, Ghent University, K.L.Ledeganckstraat 35, B-9000 Ghent, Belgium</address></affiliation>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
<?newpage?>
	<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">has orthologs for most of the key enzymes involved in eukaryotic intermediary metabolism, suggesting that the major metabolic pathways are probably present in this species. We discuss how metabolic patterns and activity change as the worm traverses development and ages, or responds to unfavorable external factors, such as temperature extremes or shortages in food or oxygen. Dauer diapause is marked by an enhanced resistance to oxidative stress and a shift toward microaerobic and anaplerotic metabolic pathways and hypometabolism, as indicated by the increased importance of the malate dismutation and glyoxylate pathways and the repression of citric acid cycle activity. These alterations promote prolonged survival of the dauer larva; some of these changes also accompany the extended lifespan of insulin/IGF-1 and several mitochondrial mutants. We also present a brief overview of the nutritional requirements, energy storage and waste products generated by</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans.</emphasis></emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>Metabolism comprises the entire set of chemical reactions that occur in a living organism that allow it to reproduce, develop, maintain its structure and respond to the environment. These chemical reactions form an intricate network of pathways and cycles in which the flow of reaction products (metabolites) is determined by many regulatory mechanisms. Traditionally, metabolism is subdivided into catabolism, the breaking down of complex molecules, and anabolism, processes related to the synthesis of complex organic substances.</para>
<para>According to the definition provided above, metabolism includes every cellular process, ranging from DNA replication to transcription and translation to enzyme function, and also involves the chemistry of small molecules in the cell. In this chapter, we will focus on intermediary metabolism, which describes all reactions concerned with the storage and generation of metabolic energy required for the biosynthesis of low-molecular weight compounds and energy storage compounds (<link linkend="bib102">Mathews and Van Holde, 1996</link>). In the intermediary metabolism pathway, the structure of each enzyme plays a crucial role in determining the specific properties of each reaction.</para>
<para>In the early seventies, Brenner introduced <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> as a multicellular genetic model, mainly because this organism has very few somatic cells, which made it possible for investigators to reconstruct the cell lineage and to map the wiring of the nervous system (<link linkend="bib22">Brenner, 1974</link><!--: PMID 4366476-->). Since then, it has become one of the most powerful tools for studying the genetics of metazoan development, neurobiology, aging and many other biological processes. This worm, however, is less amenable to classical biochemical study. It is sometimes difficult to obtain large quantities of synchronized individuals; eggshells and cuticles are tough barriers and it is virtually impossible to collect pure tissue in biochemically relevant quantities (<link linkend="bib101">Mains and McGhee, 1999</link>). Nevertheless, many metabolic studies of free-living and parasitic nematodes (<link linkend="bib13">Bolla, 1980</link>) have allowed us to gain deeper insights into the complex biochemical events that underpin the life of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
<para>The intermediary metabolic network is well conserved among eukaryotes and the major metabolic pathways found in heterotrophic organisms are also present in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib164">Vastrik et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17367534-->). In the first section of this chapter, we will elaborate on the characteristics of these general pathways in our <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> model. We will subsequently focus on the vital compounds that cannot be synthesized by <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and hence need to be extracted from the environment. Vitamins, essential amino acids and other related compounds will be discussed in the section about nutritional requirements. At the end of this chapter, a short overview will also be given describing the different metabolic waste products and the storage and production of metabolic energy in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
<para>At many intersections within the metabolic network, the flow of metabolites can be diverted to a specific direction according to the need of the organism at that particular moment. These metabolic shifts can occur instantly, e.g. as a response to changing environments, or more slowly over the course of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> life cycle. In <link linkend="sec6">Section 6</link>, we will explain some of the typical metabolic alterations that take place from embryogenesis to the last larval stage, including the specialized dauer stage. We will also focus on the metabolic changes that accompany the worm aging process, and the large fluctuations in biotic and abiotic environmental factors that might be encountered by the soil dwelling <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Finally, we will discuss the metabolic patterns that arise due to changes in temperature, food restriction, oxygen deprivation or osmotic stress.</para>
</sect1>
<?newpage?>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Major intermediary metabolic pathways in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
<sect2 id="sec2_1">
<title>Metabolic studies in related species</title>
<para>Recent estimates for the last common ancestor to vertebrates and nematodes range from 800 million to over one billion years ago (<link linkend="bib59">Hedges and Kumar, 2003</link><!--: PMID 11580860-->; <link linkend="bib58">Hedges, 2002</link><!--: PMID 12415314-->; <link linkend="bib156">Ureta-Vidal et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12671656-->; <link linkend="bib11">Blaxter, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9851921-->). Since that time, nematodes have developed a bewildering variety of life histories including parasitism of animals and plants and the ability to live in harsh environments. Conceivably, conserved eukaryotic metabolic pathways are more likely to be found in free-living bacterivorous nematodes such as <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, which live under mostly temperate conditions. During the 1960s and -70s there was much interest in comparative biochemistry and a great deal of work was done on the metabolism of nematodes, albeit predominantly focusing on parasitic forms (<link linkend="bib13">Bolla, 1980</link>; <link linkend="bib6">Atkinson, 1980</link>). The other free-living species studied most intensively included the Pangrolaimidae<emphasis> Panagrellus redivivus</emphasis> and <emphasis>Turbatrix aceti</emphasis>, and a Rhabditidae, <emphasis>Caenorhabditis briggsae</emphasis>.<emphasis> C. elegans</emphasis> and<emphasis> C. briggsae</emphasis> are sibling species, which display only a few subtle morphological differences. Their genomes have been completely sequenced and approximately 62% of the predicted <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> genes are one-to-one orthologs of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib148">Stein et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14624247-->). Thus there is little doubt that biochemical reactions identified in <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> also occur in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and vice versa.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2_2">
<title>Conservation of metabolic pathways</title>
<para>Databases such as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org" role="_blank">Wormbase</ulink><!-- (http://www.wormbase.org)-->, <ulink url="http://www.reactome.org" role="_blank">Reactome</ulink><!-- (http://www.reactome.org)--> and <ulink url="http://www.genome.ad.jp/kegg/pathway.html" role="_blank">KEGG</ulink><!-- (www.genome.ad.jp/kegg/pathway.html)--> show that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> orthologs have been found for most of the enzymes involved in the main pathways of intermediary metabolism. Of course, this only provides information about the metabolic machinery present in the animal; the activities of these biochemical pathways can only be determined by gene expression and enzyme studies and by quantifying metabolites. The number of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> orthologs that are currently identified is indicated on the diagram representing the major metabolic pathways, which will be discussed later in this chapter (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>).</para>
<para>Under aerobic conditions (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>), <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> will metabolize energy through the standard metabolic pathways. In glycolysis, a series of enzymatic reactions will convert sugars (typically glucose) to pyruvate. During this process, small amounts of ATP are generated and electron carriers are loaded with electrons (NAD<superscript>&#x0002B;</superscript> is reduced to NADH &#x0002B; H<superscript>&#x0002B;</superscript>). Consequently, pyruvate is translocated to the mitochondria, decarboxylated and converted into acetyl-CoA. In this process the first completely oxidized carbon is released as CO<subscript>2</subscript>. Acetyl-CoA then enters the tricarboxylic acid (TCA) cycle by condensing with oxaloacetate to form citrate. A series of oxidation reactions then ensue with the result that two carbons are expelled as CO<subscript>2</subscript>, (G/A)TP is produced and the electron carriers (NAD<superscript>&#x0002B;</superscript> and FAD<superscript>&#x0002B;</superscript>) are reduced. Finally, the cycle is completed when oxaloacetate is formed. The electron carriers that were reduced during glycolysis and the TCA cycle deliver their electrons to O<subscript>2</subscript> (with the formation of water) through a series of electron transport chain redox proteins located in the inner mitochondrial membrane. During electron transfer, some of these redox proteins shuttle protons from the mitochondrial matrix to the intramembrane space of the mitochondria, thereby creating an electrochemical gradient. The potential energy in this gradient is finally used by ATP-synthase (another protein complex in the inner mitochondrial membrane) to drive ATP synthesis.</para>
<para>Lipids and amino acids can also be used as energy sources, but they enter the main pathways at different points. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has a functional methylmalonyl-CoA epimerase (racemase) that is involved in propionyl-CoA metabolism for the degradation of branched amino acids and odd-chain fatty acids (<link linkend="bib82">K&#x000FC;hnl et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15752362-->). Fatty acid moieties of lipids are broken down by <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation into acetyl-CoA (which in turn can enter the TCA cycle). <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation occurs in the mitochondrial matrix and also yields reduced electron carriers. Peroxisomal <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation of long-chain fatty acids is not linked directly to energy metabolism because the reduced electron carrier is directly oxidized by molecular oxygen (yielding hydrogen peroxide). Amino acids can be broken down via distinct pathways and their carbon skeletons can be metabolized in the TCA cycle.</para>
<para>Besides these well-known pathways of intermediary metabolism, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> can use alternative pathways under distinct developmental or environmental conditions, as will be discussed in more detail in the following sections.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Nutritional requirements</title>
<sect2 id="sec3_1">
<title>Chemically defined media</title>
<para>The search for a chemically defined medium that would support sustained population growth of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> led to the formulation of a mixture, designated EM1, which was based on the amino acid ratios found in <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib140">Sayre et al., 1963</link><!--: PMID 13976451-->). This medium was later modified by <link linkend="bib24">Buecher et al. (1966</link><!--: PMID 5933957-->) and called <emphasis>Caenorhabditis briggsae</emphasis> Maintenance Medium (CbMM). This medium contained a total of 53 components consisting of minerals, glucose, amino acids, vitamins, growth factors and precursors for nucleic acid synthesis (adjusted to pH 5.9 with KOH). <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> Maintenance Medium (CeMM) has the same basal composition, but contains either more glucose or potassium acetate for energy (<link linkend="bib95">Lu and Goetsch, 1993</link>; <link linkend="bib149">Szewczyk et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14580264-->). This basal medium, which can be replaced by 3&#x00025; soy peptone and 3&#x00025; yeast extract, must be further supplemented with sterol and a heme source.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="6.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_2">
<title>Sterols</title>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and all other nematodes studied to date lack the capacity to synthesize sterols <emphasis>de novo</emphasis> from acetate (<link linkend="bib130">Rothstein, 1968</link><!--: PMID 5758374-->; <link linkend="bib27">Cole and Dutky, 1969</link>). This requirement can be met by providing exogenous cholesterol, <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-sitosterol, 7-dehydrocholesterol, ergosterol, or stigmasterol (<link linkend="bib61">Hieb and Rothstein, 1968</link><!--: PMID 4869093-->; <link linkend="bib149">Szewczyk et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14580264-->). Indeed, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> can use various dietary sterols, including plant sterols (<link linkend="bib26">Chitwood and Lusby, 1991</link><!--: PMID 1779708-->). <emphasis>P. redivivus</emphasis> and <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species have the capacity to synthesize lanosterol from squalene 2,3-oxide; the major metabolic block in the pathway of <emphasis>de novo</emphasis> sterol biosynthesis likely occurs between farnesol (and any other steps before farnesol) and squalene (<link linkend="bib172">Willett and Downey, 1974</link><!--: PMID 4822732-->; <link linkend="bib99">Lu et al., 1977</link>). More recently, <link linkend="bib90">Lee et al. (2005</link><!--: PMID 15707967-->) constructed a <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> strain expressing human dehydrocholesterol reductase, which enabled the worms to convert exogenous 7-dehydrocholesterol into cholesterol. This transgenic strain was slightly longer-lived and stress-resistant, but showed reduced fecundity.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_3">
<title>Heme</title>
<para>Sterol-supplemented chemically defined medium will not sustain nematode population growth unless a heme source is added. Hemin chloride can be used, but various heme proteins have proven more effective (<link linkend="bib62">Hieb et al., 1970</link><!--: PMID 5417058-->; <link linkend="bib160">Vanfleteren, 1974</link><!--: PMID 4819421-->). Hemoglobin or myoglobin is most often added (<link linkend="bib43">F&#x000F6;ll et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10631804-->; <link linkend="bib111">Murfitt et al., 1976</link><!--: PMID 131020-->; <link linkend="bib67">Houthoofd et al., 2002a</link><!--: PMID 12559406-->; <link linkend="bib66">Houthoofd et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12954481-->); cytochrome <emphasis>c</emphasis> can be used to prepare a medium that is free of precipitate (<link linkend="bib149">Szewczyk et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14580264-->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> lacks orthologs of all 7 enzymes (&#x003B4;-aminolevulinic acid dehydratase, porphobilinogen deaminase, uroporphyrinogen III synthase, uroporphyrinogen decarboxylase, coproporphyrinogen oxidase, protoporphyrinogen oxidase and ferrochelatase), which are needed to synthesize heme from &#x003B4;-aminolevulinic acid (<link linkend="bib126">Rao et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15767563-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_4">
<title>Vitamins</title>
<para>A requirement for several vitamins has been shown: thiamin, riboflavin, folic acid, niacinamide, pantothenic acid, pyridoxine (<link linkend="bib33">Dougherty et al., 1959</link>; <link linkend="bib113">Nicholas et al., 1962</link>; <link linkend="bib34">Dougherty and Hansen, 1957</link>; <link linkend="bib96">Lu et al., 1974</link><!--: PMID 4812872-->), biotin (<link linkend="bib114">Nicholas and Jantunen, 1963</link>) and vitamin B<subscript>12</subscript> (<link linkend="bib97">Lu et al., 1976</link><!--: PMID 1265054-->). The following essential amino acids are required to sustain population growth of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>: arginine, histidine, lysine, tryptophan, phenylalanine, methionine, threonine, leucine, isoleucine and valine (<link linkend="bib161">Vanfleteren, 1980</link>), although the animals can synthesize limited quantities from labeled precursors (<link linkend="bib112">Nicholas et al., 1960</link>; <link linkend="bib137">Rothstein and Tomlinson, 1961</link><!--: PMID 13743912-->; <link linkend="bib137a">1962</link><!--: PMID 13975395-->; <link linkend="bib128">Rothstein, 1963</link><!--: PMID 14113511-->; <link linkend="bib129">1965</link><!--: PMID 14327568-->). By contrast, alanine, aspartic acid, cysteine, glutamic acid, glutamine, glycine, serine, and tyrosine are not essential nutrients (<link linkend="bib161">Vanfleteren, 1980</link>).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_5">
<title>Energy sources</title>
<para>In addition to long-chain fatty acids, ethanol, n-propanol and acetate also promote population growth of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> in chemically defined medium (<link linkend="bib98">Lu et al., 1978</link><!--: PMID 674219-->). These compounds are utilized as energy sources by <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>, since comparable results were obtained when they were replaced with various carbohydrate supplements. <link linkend="bib95">Lu and Goetsch (1993)</link> found that glucose and glycogen, followed by trehalose, fructose and sucrose can be utilized as energy sources. <link linkend="bib30">Cooper and Van Gundy (1971)</link> reported that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is capable of aerobic, but not anaerobic, catabolism of ethanol. Di- and tricarboxylic acids can probably be transported from the extracellular environment into the gut cells and used as a fuel source in the TCA cycle (<link linkend="bib40">Fei et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14678010-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Metabolic waste products</title>
<sect2 id="sec4_1">
<title>Nitrogen excretion</title>
<para>Ammonia is the main excretory product of nitrogen metabolism, but nitrogen is also excreted in the form of amino acids (<link linkend="bib128">Rothstein, 1963</link><!--: PMID 14113511-->; <link linkend="bib129">1965</link><!--: PMID 14327568-->). <link linkend="bib129">Rothstein (1965</link><!--: PMID 14327568-->) identified several amino acids as excretion products of axenic populations of <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> after they had been cultured on various radioactive precursors; the concentration of excreted amino acids was greater than the concentration retained in the tissues. <link linkend="bib175">Wright (1975a</link><!--: PMID 240608-->; <link linkend="bib176">1975b</link><!--: PMID 1175353-->) found evidence for a functional urea cycle of low activity, and excretion of urea in <emphasis>P. redivivus</emphasis>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_2">
<title>Carbon excretion</title>
<para>In vertebrates, carbon atoms of carbohydrates, lipids and amino acids are usually completely oxidized to CO<subscript>2</subscript> under aerobic conditions. Carbon dioxide is also a major waste product in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> but, like many other invertebrates and micro-organisms, the worm can also excrete other types of carbon waste. <link linkend="bib131">Rothstein (1969</link><!--: PMID 5356614-->) and <link linkend="bib92">Liu and Rothstein (1976</link><!--: PMID 179754-->) found that <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> excretes substantial amounts of glycerol as a major radioactive product when incubated with 2-<superscript>14</superscript>C-acetate in complete nutritional medium, but in unsupplemented buffer solution little or no glycerol was produced. The advantage of glycerol excretion in a nutrient-rich environment is not clear. Possibly it is a wasteful means to dispose of superfluous products of metabolism in a nutrient-rich environment, much like synthesis and excretion of amino acids to dispose of end products of nitrogen metabolism. This is consistent with the observation that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> are typical opportunistic species that need dense bacterial populations to maintain rapid growth and fecundity. Rapid excretion of glycerol to the external medium is also associated with recovery from hypertonic stress (see <link linkend="sec7_4">Section 7.4</link>). Like other soil nematodes, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is hyperosmotic with its normal environment. The animals accumulate and excrete glycerol as needed to maintain cellular osmotic homeostasis (<link linkend="bib86">Lamitina et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID: 14644776-->; <link linkend="bib171">Wheeler and Thomas, 2006</link><!--: PMID: 16980399-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Energy storage and production</title>
<sect2 id="sec5_1">
<title>Lipids and carbohydrates</title>
<para>Free-living nematodes have the ability to synthesize saturated and unsaturated fatty acids <emphasis>de novo</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib132">Rothstein, 1970</link>), and they typically store energy as lipids. Recently, it was found that most lipid species in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (triglycerides, phospholipids, sphingolipids, etc.) are composed of fatty acids directly absorbed from the bacterial food source (C. Perez and M. Van Gilst, personal communication). Up to 35&#x00025; of the dry body mass of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is lipid, and triacyl glyceride fat stores (~40-55&#x00025; of total lipids) are the major energy storage molecules (<link linkend="bib30">Cooper and Van Gundy, 1971</link>; <link linkend="bib89">Lee and Atkinson, 1976</link>; see <ulink url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/wormbook.1.130.1" role="_blank">Obesity and the regulation of fat metabolism</ulink><!--, http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/wormbook.1.130.1-->). Carbohydrate stores consist primarily of glycogen (3.3&#x00025; of the dry body mass, <link linkend="bib29">Cooper and Van Gundy, 1970</link>), but significant amounts of trehalose and glucose are also present (<link linkend="bib43">F&#x000F6;ll et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10631804-->; <link linkend="bib54">Hanover et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16051707-->). Interestingly, O-GlcNac transferase (OGT) modulates the relative use of these macronutrient storage molecules. OGT knockout mutants have a 3-fold elevation of trehalose levels and glycogen stores with a concomitant 3-fold decrease in triglyceride levels (<link linkend="bib54">Hanover et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16051707-->). <link linkend="bib29">Cooper and van Gundy (1970</link>) observed that the <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species rapidly metabolized glycogen when starved. Dauer larvae rely on their lipid reserves for long-term survival (<link linkend="bib118">O'Riordan and Burnell, 1990</link>).</para>
<para>Biochemical studies have provided evidence for a complete tricarboxylic acid cycle in <emphasis>T. aceti</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib132">Rothstein et al., 1970</link>) and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib111">Murfitt et al., 1976</link><!--: PMID 131020-->). When <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> encounters adverse conditions, the flow of glycolytic products to the TCA cycle may be prevented by pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase (a negative regulator of PDH) activity. Thus, this enzyme may act as a molecular switch for energy metabolism, like it does in hibernating mammals (E-J. Shin, J-E. Hwang and Y-K. Paik, personal communication). Evidence for the occurrence of the phosphogluconate pathway (also called hexose monophosphate shunt or pentose phosphate pathway) has been reported for <emphasis>T. aceti</emphasis>. This pathway oxidizes glucose to generate pentoses, CO<subscript>2</subscript> and reduced NADP and is important for maintaining the cellular redox balance. Interestingly, this pathway produces free ribitol that is excreted (<link linkend="bib121">Panagides and Rothstein, 1973</link>). The advantage to the animals of ribitol production and excretion is not clear. One possible explanation is that it serves as a regulatory mechanism of NADPH production although ribitol was not excreted by <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5_2">
<title>Glyoxylate cycle</title>
<para>Nematodes, including <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, also possess the glyoxylate cycle enzymes, which convert two acetyl-CoA units into succinate and malate (<link linkend="bib133">Rothstein and Mayoh, 1964a</link><!--: PMID 14233905-->; <link linkend="bib134">1964b</link><!--: PMID 5836539-->; <link linkend="bib135">Rothstein and Mayoh, 1965</link><!--: PMID 5894048-->; <link linkend="bib136">1966</link>; <link linkend="bib28">Colonna and McFadden, 1975</link><!--: PMID 242262-->; <link linkend="bib123">Patel and McFadden, 1977</link><!--: PMID 907353-->). Key enzymes are isocitrate lyase, which cleaves isocitrate to succinate and glyoxylate, and malate synthase, which condenses glyoxylate with acetyl-CoA to form malate. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has only one bifunctional glyoxylate cycle protein, which contains separate domains for both enzyme activities on a single polypeptide (<link linkend="bib93">Liu et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7781887-->). In plants, the glyoxylate cycle operates in specialized peroxisomes, called glyoxysomes. The malate produced in glyoxysomes can be converted to oxaloacetate, completing the cycle. Alternatively, succinate is either transported to the mitochondria where it is converted to malate and thereby consumed in the citric acid cycle, making the glyoxylate cycle an anaplerotic (refilling) process, or transported to the cytosol and further oxidized to oxaloacetate for entry into gluconeogenesis (net production of carbohydrate from triacylglycerols) (<link linkend="bib154">Tolbert, 1981</link>).</para>
<para>Analysis of subcellular fractions from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib123">Patel and McFadden, 1977</link><!--: PMID 907353-->) and <emphasis>T. aceti</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib7">Aueron and Rothstein, 1974</link><!--: PMID 4154049-->) has also detected the presence of glyoxysome-like bodies in these species. On the other hand, glyoxylate enzymes have been reported in mitochondrial fractions from <emphasis>T. aceti</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib106">McKinley and Trelease, 1978a</link><!--: PMID 666763-->; <link linkend="bib107">1978b</link>) and <emphasis>Ascaris suum</emphasis> larvae (<link linkend="bib138">Rubin and Trelease, 1976</link><!--: PMID 939782-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Metabolic patterns during development and aging</title>
<sect2 id="sec6_1">
<title>Development</title>
<para>Metabolic rate measured as oxygen consumed or heat produced per unit time and normalized to protein content exhibits life-cycle dependent modulation: it is higher in L1 larvae than in developing eggs and it further increases to reach the highest values in L2-L4 larvae, followed by a steep decrease as worms reach adulthood. The metabolic rate then gradually decreases as the worms traverse this final stage of the life cycle toward senescence (<link linkend="bib31">De Cuyper and Vanfleteren, 1982</link>; <link linkend="bib163">Vanfleteren and De Vreese, 1996</link><!--: PMID 8742689-->; <link linkend="bib68">Houthoofd et al., 2002b</link><!--: PMID 12213552-->). The low oxygen consumption rates of developing eggs and freshly hatched larvae are likely related to the shift in energy metabolism away from the TCA cycle. In embryos, the high activity of the glyoxylate cycle is necessary for converting stored lipids so that they can be used for energy production and gluconeogenesis. After hatching, the activity of isocitrate lyase progressively decreases, whereas energy production through the TCA cycle increases substantially (<link linkend="bib168">Wadsworth and Riddle, 1989</link><!--: PMID 2917691-->). Interestingly <link linkend="bib94">Liu et al. (1997</link><!--: PMID 8993341-->) reported that glyoxylate cycle mRNA and protein increased during early development, peaked at the L2 stage and declined afterwards. Starvation induced glyoxylate cycle expression throughout juvenile development (<link linkend="bib77a">Khan and McFadden, 1982</link><!--: PMID 7095076-->; <link linkend="bib94">Liu et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 8993341-->). However, in L2 predauers and in dauer larvae, which do not feed, the glyoxylate cycle enzyme activities do not increase but closely parallel those from L2 (<link linkend="bib168">Wadsworth and Riddle, 1989</link><!--: PMID 2917691-->), suggesting that the regulation of glyoxylate cycle protein expression in dauers is different from that during normal development (<link linkend="bib94">Liu et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 8993341-->). The ATP profiles reflect these changes in energy production (<link linkend="bib68">Houthoofd et al., 2002b</link><!--: PMID 12213552-->). NMR spectra showed that ATP was below detection limits in L1 larvae and dauers, whereas AMP was detectable throughout development and was particularly high in L1 larvae (<link linkend="bib168">Wadsworth and Riddle, 1989</link><!--: PMID 2917691-->).</para>
<para>Movement accounts for about 37&#x00025; of the total energy expenditure of L4 larvae and this fraction decreases further to 25&#x00025; in adult animals (<link linkend="bib163">Vanfleteren and De Vreese, 1996</link><!--: PMID 8742689-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6_2">
<title>Dauer metabolism</title>
<para>The dauer stage is an alternative third stage larva that is formed under unfavorable conditions, and is specialized for survival and dispersal (see <ulink url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/wormbook.1.144.1" role="_blank">Dauer</ulink><!--, http://dx.doi.org/10.1895/wormbook.1.144.1-->). Since dauers do not feed, they must metabolize stored macronutrients, mainly lipids, but also glycogen and trehalose, and suppress energy-consuming metabolic activities. This is indeed the case; dauers consume less oxygen when compared to other juvenile stages (<link linkend="bib117">O'Riordan and Burnell, 1989</link>; <link linkend="bib163">Vanfleteren and De Vreese, 1996</link><!--: PMID 8742689-->; <link linkend="bib68">Houthoofd et al., 2002b</link><!--: PMID 12213552-->) and produce less heat (<link linkend="bib68">Houthoofd et al., 2002b</link><!--: PMID 12213552-->), consistent with an overall reduction of metabolic rate. This appears to be caused by the reduced activities of the enzymes involved in the glycolytic, gluconeogenic, TCA cycle and oxidative phosphorylation pathways in dauers, relative to those of adults (<link linkend="bib117">O'Riordan and Burnell, 1989</link>). Micro-array and SAGE analyses of dauer larvae versus recovered dauers or mixed stage populations suggested that the transcription of enzymes involved in the <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation of fatty acids, glycolysis, glyoxylate and gluconeogenesis pathways was enhanced, indicating that triglycerides were being converted into sugars (<link linkend="bib170">Wang and Kim, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12620986-->; <link linkend="bib104">McElwee et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15308663-->; <link linkend="bib105">2006</link><!--: PMID 16522328-->; <link linkend="bib75">Jones et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11483575-->; <link linkend="bib63">Holt and Riddle, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12875742-->). The flux of metabolites through the glyoxylate cyle is relatively more important in the dauer, although this shift is mainly due to a substantial decrease of the carbon flux through the TCA cycle rather than an increased flux through the glyoxylate cycle (<link linkend="bib118">O'Riordan and Burnell, 1990</link>). Phosphoenolpyruvate-carboxykinase (PEPCK) levels are relatively high in the dauer, indicating that gluconeogenesis is elevated, but glycogen re-synthesis is apparently suppressed, as indicated by the relatively low activity of fructose 1,6-bisphosphatase (<link linkend="bib117">O'Riordan and Burnell, 1989</link>). Thus, the high level of PEPCK activity in dauers is more likely to be associated with the fixation of CO<subscript>2</subscript> into phosphoenolpyruvate to form oxaloacetate, which can be converted to malate and used in other pathways, thereby providing a useful anaplerotic mechanism for the starving dauer larva. The conversion of lipids into sugars may also be required for transportation of energy from lipid-containing cells (intestine and epidermis) into other tissues (muscle, neurons) (<link linkend="bib119">Ogg et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9353126-->). Since the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome does not contain a functional glucose-6-phosphatase, it is assumed that trehalose, rather than glucose is used as a transport sugar (<link linkend="bib104">McElwee et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15308663-->) (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>).</para>
<para>It is not clear whether ethanol fermentation is upregulated in the dauer. SAGE analyses detected enhanced transcription of the gene <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=K12G11.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">K12G11.3</ulink> that encodes a protein with high similarity to sorbitol dehydrogenase (which catalyzes the reversible oxidation-reduction reaction between fructose and sorbitol) and alcohol dehydrogenases from other species (<link linkend="bib63">Holt and Riddle, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12875742-->). However, it has not been shown that the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=K12G11.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">K12G11.3</ulink> protein is involved in ethanol fermentation. Microarray analysis detected the upregulation of two alcohol dehydrogenase genes and the downregulation of a third one (<link linkend="bib105">McElwee et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16522328-->). Lactate dehydrogenase expression was lower in dauers, either compared to larvae 12 hours after the onset of dauer recovery (<link linkend="bib105">McElwee et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16522328-->) or mixed-stage worms (<link linkend="bib63">Holt and Riddle, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12875742-->). Thus there is little evidence that pyruvate fermentation is upregulated in the dauer.</para>
<para>Another anaerobic process that seems to be important in dauers is malate dismutation. Malate, formed from oxaloacetate by malate dehydrogenase or produced by the glyoxylate pathway, can enter mitochondria for aerobic (TCA cycle) or anaerobic combustion (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). Here, malate can be oxidized to pyruvate via malic enzyme and further converted into acetyl-CoA and acetate. Alternatively, malate can be reduced to fumarate and succinate, using the reverse action of fumarase and complex II of the electron transport chain. Complex II can act as succinate dehydrogenase or as fumarate reductase (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). In addition to the electron transporter ubiquinone, dauers also contain rhodoquinone, which has a lower reduction potential and favors the reverse action of complex II (<link linkend="bib150">Takamiya et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10545216-->; <link linkend="bib63">Holt and Riddle, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12875742-->; <link linkend="bib25">Burnell et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16221538-->). Oxidation of malate to acetate and reduction to succinate in a ratio of 1:2 would maintain the redox balance in equilibrium in the absence of oxygen (<link linkend="bib25">Burnell et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16221538-->). The malate dismutation pathway and the excretion of succinate, propionate and acetate has been well documented for parasitic helminths, including <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib153">Thielens et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12417132-->). These end products of anaerobic mitochondria are also excreted by <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> under anoxic conditions (<link linkend="bib43">F&#x000F6;ll et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10631804-->).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="6.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Dauers are very long-lived and it has been shown that the adult lifespan of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is independent of the time spent as a dauer larva (<link linkend="bib78">Klass and Hirsh, 1976</link><!--: PMID 1264206-->). Dauers, however, show time-dependent metabolic changes, including a reduced superoxide production rate potential (as defined in <link linkend="bib15">Braeckman et al., 2002a</link><!--: PMID 11718805-->), accumulation of lipofuscin and oxidized flavins and a gradual decline in aconitase activity (<link linkend="bib68">Houthoofd et al., 2002b</link><!--: PMID 12213552-->). Thus, dauers seem to age slowly, but the changes accompanying the process can be reversed when the dauers develop to the L4 and adult stages. The long lifespan of dauers (up to 8 times the 2-week adult lifespan) is associated with increased protection against molecular damage (<link linkend="bib64">Honda and Honda, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10428762-->; <link linkend="bib151">Taub et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10335847-->; <link linkend="bib9">Birnby et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10790386-->; <link linkend="bib75">Jones et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11483575-->; <link linkend="bib177">Yu and Larsen, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11743719-->; <link linkend="bib68">Houthoofd et al., 2002b</link><!--: PMID 12213552-->; <link linkend="bib103">McElwee et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12882324-->; <link linkend="bib170">Wang and Kim, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12620986-->; <link linkend="bib104">McElwee et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15308663-->; <link linkend="bib44">Gems and McElwee, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15664624-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6_3">
<title>Aging</title>
<sect3 id="sec6_3_1">
<title>Metabolic decrease</title>
<para>Notwithstanding its short lifespan, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> shows clear morphological and behavioral signs of aging (<link linkend="bib37">Epstein et al., 1972</link>; <link linkend="bib35">Duhon and Johnson, 1995</link><!--: PMID 7671016-->; <link linkend="bib12">Bolanowski et al., 1981</link><!--: PMID 7253717-->; <link linkend="bib60">Herndon et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12397350-->). Surprisingly, the relative transcriptional and translational profiles do not change dramatically during the aging process in wild-type <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib100">Lund et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12372248-->; <link linkend="bib72">Johnson and McCaffrey, 1985</link><!--: PMID 4021560-->). However, many metabolic parameters decline steeply with age (<link linkend="bib18">Braeckman et al., 2003</link>; <link linkend="bib70">Houthoofd et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15708444-->) and this is reflected in decreased rates of transcription and translation over time (<link linkend="bib72">Johnson and McCaffrey, 1985</link><!--: PMID 4021560-->; <link linkend="bib39">Fabian and Johnson, 1995</link><!--: PMID 8583834-->; <link linkend="bib23a">Budovskaya et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18662544-->).</para>
<para>Several biochemical and physiological parameters, such as oxygen consumption, heat generation, standing ATP levels, ATP:AMP ratios, superoxide production rate potential, bioreduction capacity, and ammonia production, have been monitored over the adult lifespan and all of them have displayed a remarkable exponential decline during the adult life of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib152">Thaden and Shmookler Reis, 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib68">Houthoofd et al., 2002b</link><!--: PMID 12213552-->; <link linkend="bib5">Apfeld et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15574588-->). Recently, the exponential decline of oxygen consumption was modeled mathematically and shown to correlate with survival (<link linkend="bib146">Shoyama et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17707465-->). The nature of the exponential metabolic decline is still poorly understood, but <link linkend="bib152">Thaden and Schmookler Reis (2000)</link> suggested that it might result from an evolutionary strategy for energy use that has been shaped by the predominant effect of early reproduction. The exponential decline of metabolic parameters, such as CO<subscript>2</subscript> production, was not found in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib125">Promislow and Haselkorn, 2002</link><!--: PMID 12882355-->).</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec6_3_2">
<title>Insulin/IGF signaling mutants</title>
<para>Several functional gene families cause lifespan extension when mutated in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. The best studied groups (reviewed by <link linkend="bib173">Wolff and Dillin, 2006</link><!--: PMID 16919905-->; <link linkend="bib4">Antebi, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17907808-->) are involved in Insulin/IGF-signaling (<link linkend="bib77">Kenyon, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15734678-->; <link linkend="bib19">Braeckman et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 16829009-->; <link linkend="bib110">Mukhopadhyay et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16839734-->), mitochondrial performance (<link linkend="bib127">Rea, 2005</link><!--: PMID 16137850-->; <link linkend="bib167">Ventura et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16945497-->; <link linkend="bib143">Sedensky and Morgan, 2006</link><!--: PMID 16919906-->) and dietary restriction (<link linkend="bib71">Houthoofd et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17063035-->; see <link linkend="sec7_2">Section 7.2</link>). These mutants are excellent tools for testing whether extended lifespan is supported by, or at least correlated with, distinct metabolic patterns.</para>
<para>Long-lived insulin/IGF-signaling mutants produce less heat per unit oxygen consumed, resulting in a relatively low calorimetric/respirometric ratio (<link linkend="bib16">Braeckman et al., 2002b</link><!--: PMID 12882336-->; <link linkend="bib70a">Houthoofd et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15771612-->; <link linkend="bib23">Brys et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17379464-->). This seems to point to enhanced mitochondrial efficiency (likely due to better coupling of oxygen uptake and ATP synthesis) in the Ins/IGF mutants, which in turn should lead to enhanced ATP synthesis. Indeed, high ATP levels (<link linkend="bib70a">Houthoofd et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15771612-->; <link linkend="bib32">Dillin et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12471266-->) and mitochondrial ATP production rates (<link linkend="bib23">Brys et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17379464-->) were found in these strains. However, differences in age-dependent ATP and calorimetric/respirometric ratio patterns suggest that the coupling efficiency is probably not the sole determinant of the high ATP levels found in Ins/IGF mutants. Moreover, high ATP is not a prerequisite to long lifespan in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib23">Brys et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17379464-->). In contrast to these findings, low metabolic rates for Ins/IGF-mutant strains were reported by <link linkend="bib158">Van Voorhies and Ward (1999</link><!--: PMID 10500188-->). This discrepancy was possibly based on methodological differences and normalization issues, which were discussed at great length in <link linkend="bib157">Van Voorhies (2002</link><!--: PMID 12882338-->) and <link linkend="bib16">Braeckman et al. (2002b</link><!--: PMID 12882336-->). The AMP-activated protein kinase <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-subunit <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AAK-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">AAK-2</ulink> functions in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as an energy sensor that couples lifespan to energy levels and insulin-like signals (<link linkend="bib5">Apfeld et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15574588-->).</para>
<para>Isolated mitochondria of the Ins/IGF-mutant <emphasis>daf-2(e1370)</emphasis> tend to produce more reactive oxygen species (ROS) than wild type (<link linkend="bib23">Brys et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17379464-->). It has long been known that the antioxidant activity in Ins/IGF-mutant strains is markedly increased (<link linkend="bib162">Vanfleteren, 1993</link><!--: PMID 8389142-->; <link linkend="bib88">Larsen, 1993</link><!--: PMID 8415630-->; <link linkend="bib70a">Houthoofd et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15771612-->), which could counteract the elevated ROS-production rates (<link linkend="bib23">Brys et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17379464-->).</para>
<para>Apart from direct physiological measurements, Ins/IGF-mutant metabolism was also studied by analyzing transcriptional profiles of metabolism-related genes. <link linkend="bib105">McElwee and co-workers (2006</link><!--: PMID 16522328-->) found that, in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants, gluconeogenesis, glyoxylate pathway activity and trehalose biosynthesis were upregulated relative to the appropriate controls (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> versus <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink>; daf-16</emphasis> adults). These authors found similar qualitative changes in dauer larvae compared to recovered dauer larvae. Unlike dauer stage animals, TCA-cycle and respiratory chain activities were not downregulated in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants, supporting the physiological data discussed above (<link linkend="bib105">McElwee et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16522328-->). In addition, in part explanation for the high ATP levels found in these mutants, the mitochondrial F<subscript>1</subscript>-ATPase inhibitor protein (IF<subscript>1</subscript>), which specifically inhibits the ATPase activity of ATP synthase under anoxic conditions, was found to be upregulated in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis>.</para>
<para>Transcriptional studies using SAGE analysis on sterile <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fer-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">fer-15</ulink>;daf-2</emphasis> worms and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fer-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">fer-15</ulink></emphasis> controls did not yield identical results. <link linkend="bib52">Halaschek-Wiener et al. (2005</link><!--: PMID 15837805-->) found a clear reduction in transcripts for general metabolic activities (including DNA/RNA, lipid, protein and energy metabolism) in 6-day-old <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fer-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">fer-15</ulink>;daf-2</emphasis> adults compared to age-matched <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fer-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">fer-15</ulink></emphasis>. This led the authors to conclude that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fer-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">fer-15</ulink>;daf-2</emphasis> mutants must be hypometabolic at mid-life, although metabolic rate appeared to be restored at advanced age. A more recent study of the same SAGE library confirmed the decline in TCA pathway transcripts, but no concomitant upregulation of fermentation-related genes was detected (<link linkend="bib139">Ruzanov et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17543485-->). On the contrary, higher transcript levels of enzymes associated with the glyoxylate shunt, possibly compensating for the reduced TCA cycle activity and electron transport machinery were found in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fer-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">fer-15</ulink>;daf-2</emphasis>. It is still unclear, however, how the glyoxylate cycle, which yields at least four times fewer reducing equivalents relative to the TCA cycle, could compensate for the 4-5-fold reported decrease of the TCA cycle and still reduce similar amounts of oxygen through the electron transport chain.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec6_3_3">
<title>Mitochondrial mutants</title>
<para>Mutations that compromise the function of the mitochondrial electron transport chain might be predicted to shorten the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> lifespan but, remarkably, such mutations frequently confer lifespan extension (<link linkend="bib57">Hartman et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11389932-->). In a systematic RNAi screen for genes conferring longevity, genes related to mitochondrial function were over-represented tenfold (<link linkend="bib91">Lee et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12447374-->). Long-lived worms, in which mitochondrial function was disturbed by RNAi, displayed low ATP levels and oxygen consumption rates compared to appropriate controls. These metabolic phenotypes confirmed an earlier study in which the function of several subunits of the electron transport chain complexes I, III, IV and V were compromised by RNAi knockdown (<link linkend="bib32">Dillin et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12471266-->). These animals were small and showed slow development and behavior (pharyngeal pumping and defecation). Small size, however, is not a universal hallmark of mitochondrial mutants. Hypometabolic <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=isp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">isp-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants, which contain a defect in an iron-sulphur protein subunit of complex III, were reported to have a normal body size (<link linkend="bib42">Feng et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11709184-->). Some mitochondrial mutants of the Clock family, such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=clk-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">clk-1</ulink></emphasis> (a gene involved in ubiquinone synthesis) (<link linkend="bib38">Ewbank et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9020081-->; review by <link linkend="bib1">Aguilaniu et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16230529-->) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gro-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gro-1</ulink></emphasis> (involved in the efficiency and fidelity of mitochondrial protein synthesis), are not hypometabolic (<link linkend="bib14">Braeckman et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10330373-->; <link linkend="bib17">2002c</link><!--: PMID 12425951-->). Indeed, in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=clk-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">clk-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants complex I activity remains unaltered (<link linkend="bib41">Felkai et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10202142-->; <link linkend="bib109">Miyadera et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11244089-->; <link linkend="bib74">Jonassen et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14530273-->), although this was challenged by <link linkend="bib76">Kayser et al. (2004</link><!--: PMID 15269213-->) who found that complex I activity was decreased by approximately 70&#x00025; while complex II activity was left intact when compared to wild type.</para>
<para>Major questions that remain unanswered include: How does a mutation affecting mitochondrial function lead to extended lifespan? and What kind of metabolic changes are involved in the process? <link linkend="bib127">Rea (2005</link><!--: PMID 16137850-->) presented plausible biochemical scenarios in partial explanation, ranging from a reduction in overall metabolic rate to activation of compensatory metabolic pathways to combat ROS. For example, mild increases in ROS could evoke hormesis effects resulting in enhanced ROS scavenging. Alternatively, other pathways that produce less ROS, such as fermentation, could be induced (<link linkend="bib127">Rea, 2005</link><!--: PMID 16137850-->). Although many of these proposed mechanisms are indirectly supported by existing literature, these hypotheses still await direct experimental validation.</para>
<para>The exact location and severity of the defect in the mitochondrial electron transport chain determines whether the worm will be short- or long-lived. Inhibiting the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nuo-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">nuo-2</ulink></emphasis> subunit of complex I by RNAi leads to lifespan extension (<link linkend="bib32">Dillin et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12471266-->), whereas inhibiting two other subunits of complex I, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nuo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">nuo-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib49">Grad and Lemire, 2004</link><!--: PMID 14662656-->) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gas-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gas-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib57">Hartman et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11389932-->), shortens lifespan. Interestingly, <emphasis>nuo-1(lf)</emphasis> animals arrested in development at the third larval stage and the total lifespan of these animals exceeded that of wild-type worms (<link linkend="bib155">Tsang et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11410594-->). However, transgenic strains lacking wild-type <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nuo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">nuo-1</ulink></emphasis> and expressing mutant forms of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nuo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">nuo-1</ulink></emphasis> that have single amino acid replacements, completed the normal life cycle, but suffered from lactic acidosis and were shorter-lived (<link linkend="bib49">Grad and Lemire, 2004</link><!--: PMID 14662656-->). The lactacidosis phenotype could be partially rescued by heterologous expression of yeast <emphasis>CYB2</emphasis>, an L-lactate:cytochrome <emphasis>c</emphasis> oxidoreductase that shuttles electrons from lactate to the electron transport chain (<link linkend="bib50">Grad et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16344465-->). Recently, <link linkend="bib166">Ventura and Rea (2007</link><!--: PMID 17443764-->) showed that only a small window of mitochondrial dysfunction might lead to longevity in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>: severe defects result in sickness and shortened lifespan.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>Influence of external factors on intermediary metabolism</title>
<sect2 id="sec7_1">
<title>Temperature</title>
<para>Lifespan of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is inversely correlated with environmental temperature (<link linkend="bib79">Klass, 1977</link><!--: PMID 926867-->), whereas development and metabolic rate show a positive correlation within an acceptable physiological range (<link linkend="bib158">Van Voorhies and Ward, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10500188-->). These characteristics are typical for exothermic organisms and one would expect that they reflect a mere thermodynamic process; it is well known that enzymatic reactions show faster rates at elevated temperatures. However, the rates of complex processes, such as development and behavior, were shown to be also genetically determined. Clk mutants, which show slow behavior and development, were unable to adjust their growth and behavioral rates to temperature (<link linkend="bib174">Wong et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7768437-->; <link linkend="bib21">Branicky et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11729148-->). It was suggested that worms possess a temperature compensation mechanism, which allows them to keep certain traits temperature independent.</para>
<para>Commonly, under anaerobic conditions, an increase in temperature results in an increase in lactate formation. Surprisingly, lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) activity was also increased at 20&#x000B0;C relative to 10&#x000B0;C under normoxic conditions, but without a corresponding increase in lactate concentration (<link linkend="bib124">Paul et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 11281264-->; <link linkend="bib43">F&#x000F6;ll et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10631804-->). The reasons for the discrepancy in the enzyme activity and the amount of detectable metabolite are not understood.</para>
<para>Temperature also has an indirect effect on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> metabolism by influencing the dauer decision. It was shown that high temperatures facilitate the dauer decision at the L1 larval stage (<link linkend="bib47">Golden and Riddle, 1984a</link><!--: PMID 6706004-->; <link linkend="bib48">1984b</link><!--: PMID 6583682-->), resulting in dauer larvae with distinct metabolic characteristics (see <link linkend="sec6_2">Section 6.2</link>).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec7_2">
<title>Food restriction</title>
<para>It is well documented that food restriction can substantially increase the lifespan of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib169">Walker et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15896824-->; <link linkend="bib56">Hansen et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16103914-->; <link linkend="bib141">Schulz et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17908557-->; <link linkend="bib46">Greer et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17900900-->). The transcription factors <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PHA-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHA-4</ulink>/Foxa and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> mediate this effect. Food restriction activates <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> in both ASI neurons, which signal peripheral tissues to increase metabolic activity (<link linkend="bib10">Bishop and Guarente, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17538612-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PHA-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHA-4</ulink> increases the transcription of several superoxide dismutase <emphasis>(sod)</emphasis> genes (<link linkend="bib122">Panowski et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17476212-->). However, the precise mechanisms that underlie the longevity phenotype are largely unknown, although TOR signaling and autophagy are involved (<link linkend="bib165">Vellai et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14668850-->; <link linkend="bib73">Jia and Levine, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17912023-->; <link linkend="bib55">Hansen et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18282106-->). It has been long thought that nutrient restriction lowers ROS production by decreasing the metabolic rate (<link linkend="bib147">Sohal and Weindruch, 1996</link><!--: PMID 8658196-->; <link linkend="bib83">Lakowski and Hekimi, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9789046-->). The mitochondrial electron transport chain is generally considered to be the main source of ROS production, particularly, but not exclusively, at the level of complexes I and III, where electrons can leak to molecular oxygen and generate a superoxide radical (<link linkend="bib8">Beckman and Ames, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9562038-->; <link linkend="bib53">Halliwell and Gutteridge, 1999</link>; <link linkend="bib84">Lambert and Brand, 2007</link><!--; PMID 17635416-->). Thus it is tempting to speculate that respiration and ROS production are inherently positively correlated. However, electrochemical considerations suggest the opposite is more likely; the membrane potential increases and more electrons tend to leak as the rate of reduction of oxygen to water by complex IV decreases (<link linkend="bib81">Korshunov et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9369223-->; <link linkend="bib45">Gnaiger et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 11005877-->; <link linkend="bib20">Brand, 2000</link><!--: PMID 11053672-->; <link linkend="bib115">Nicholls, 2002</link><!--: PMID 12200032-->).</para>
<para>The stimulatory effect of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink> signaling on metabolic activity and the metabolic rate studies of <link linkend="bib67">Houthoofd and co-workers (2002a</link><!--: PMID 12559406-->; <link linkend="bib69">2002c</link><!--: PMID 12559405-->; <link linkend="bib66">2003</link><!--: PMID 12954481-->; <link linkend="bib70">2005</link><!--: PMID 15708444-->) also argue against a hypometabolic effect induced by food restriction. They studied the oxygen consumption and heat production rates of normally fed controls and worms that were restricted by three dietary restriction (DR) protocols: bacterial dilution in liquid culture, axenic liquid culture and the use of Eat mutants. <emphasis>eat</emphasis> mutations produce defects in pharyngeal pumping that lead to a reduction in food uptake and concomitant DR phenotypes, including a starved appearance, reduced brood size and extended lifespan. Both proxies of metabolic rate remained unchanged or were elevated in restricted worms. Thus food restriction does not act by lowering the rate of metabolism. At first glance the failure to reduce energy expenditure when food is scarce may seem wasteful. One possible explanation is that there is an increased requirement for <emphasis>de novo</emphasis> synthesis of compounds that are otherwise adequately supplied by food. This is consistent with the lower standing levels of ATP measured in young adult (for about the first 5 days of adulthood) worms grown in axenic culture, which induced the strongest DR phenotype. It is not known if DR animals produce more ROS. DR by all three methods increased SOD and catalase activities, and axenic culture effectively enhanced resistance to thermal and oxidative stress. However, these effects may be part of a complex longevity assurance program that can be induced by a number of unfavorable conditions, including DR, rather than a specific response to increased ROS.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec7_3">
<title>Metabolic responses to hyperoxia and anoxia</title>
<sect3 id="sec7_3_1">
<title>Hyperoxia</title>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has an unusually broad oxygen tolerance. The metabolic rate of the animals was not affected by increasing oxygen levels to 100&#x00025; oxygen for 24 h. (<link linkend="bib159">Van Voorhies and Ward, 2000</link><!--: PMID 10903161-->). Worm populations survived and appeared healthy after 50 generations of continuous exposure to 100&#x00025; (91 kPa) oxygen. The biochemical basis of this unusual resistance to hyperoxia has not been investigated. Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mev-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">mev-1</ulink></emphasis>, encoding the cytochrome <emphasis>b</emphasis> unit of complex II, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gas-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gas-1</ulink></emphasis>, which affects complex I-dependent mitochondrial respiration, resulted in enhanced ROS production and sensitivity to hyperoxia (<link linkend="bib144">Senoo-Matsuda et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11527963-->; <link linkend="bib80">Kondo et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15888316-->).</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec7_3_2">
<title>Anoxia</title>
<para>The anoxic tolerance of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is also well developed. The animals survive anoxic conditions for at least 24 h at 20&#x000B0;C with a viability of 90-100&#x00025; (<link linkend="bib43">F&#x000F6;ll et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10631804-->; <link linkend="bib159">Van Voorhies and Ward, 2000</link><!--: PMID 10903161-->; <link linkend="bib120">Padilla et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12006646-->; <link linkend="bib51">Hajeri et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16368008-->), and they consume about 2/3 of their carbohydrate stores during this time (<link linkend="bib43">F&#x000F6;ll et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10631804-->). Lipid utilization is needed for prolonged survival, but at least 5 kPa external O<subscript>2</subscript> is required (<link linkend="bib29">Cooper and Van Gundy, 1970</link>). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> are able to maintain stable metabolic rates (oxygen consumption/CO<subscript>2</subscript> production) down to 3.6&#x02013;5.1 kPa O<subscript>2</subscript> (<link linkend="bib3">Anderson and Dusenbery, 1977</link>; <link linkend="bib159">Van Voorhies and Ward, 2000</link><!--: PMID 10903161-->). The metabolic rate then decreases with further reduction of the oxygen tension; 50&#x00025; of the aerobic value is attained at 1 kPa O<subscript>2</subscript> and only 3&#x02013;5&#x00025; under anoxic conditions (<link linkend="bib43">F&#x000F6;ll et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10631804-->; <link linkend="bib159">Van Voorhies and Ward, 2000</link><!--: PMID 10903161-->). When animals are subjected to oxygen deprivation, free and protein-bound NADH fluorescence increases rapidly during the first 30 minutes, followed by a further more gradual increase during the next 130 minutes. After approximately 220 minutes of anoxia, the worms enter a rigor state, which is correlated with an accelerated increase of free NADH (<link linkend="bib124">Paul et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID: 11281264-->). The long time span before entering the rigor state may indicate that the metabolic cost of movement is relatively small, which is consistent with previous studies (<link linkend="bib36">Dusenbery et al., 1978</link>; <link linkend="bib163">Vanfleteren and De Vreese, 1996</link><!--: PMID 8742689-->).</para>
<para>Anoxic incubation induces significant increases in the activities of the NADP-dependent isocitrate dehydrogenase, 3-hydroxyacyl-CoA dehydrogenase (HCDH) and, at lower temperatures (10&#x000B0;C), lactate dehydrogenase (<link linkend="bib124">Paul et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 11281264-->). HCDH normally operates in the <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation of fatty acids in the mitochondria. <link linkend="bib124">Paul et al. (2000</link><!--: PMID 11281264-->) proposed that a reversed <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation pathway results in the synthesis of excretory fatty acids and provides a sink for electrons to maintain the redox balance under anoxia. The glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase isoenzymes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GPD-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPD-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GPD-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPD-3</ulink> are also involved in the oxygen-deprivation response, although it is unlikely that they merely enhance the flux through glycolysis (<link linkend="bib108">Mendenhall et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16980394-->). L-lactate, acetate, succinate and propionate are the main waste products of anaerobic metabolism, and they are predominantly excreted. Malate excretion is substantially reduced under anoxic conditions. Branched fatty acids like 2-methylbutyrate or 2-methylvalyrate, which are typically excreted by parasitic nematodes, are not produced in measurable amounts by anoxic <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib43">F&#x000F6;ll et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10631804-->). <link linkend="bib30">Cooper and Van Gundy (1971)</link> reported that ethanol is an important end product of anaerobic fermentation, but <link linkend="bib43">F&#x000F6;ll et al., (1999</link><!--: PMID 10631804-->) found ethanol levels to be below the limits of detection. The reason for this discrepancy is not known, but may be related to differences in culture conditions, analytical methods, or possibly to bacterial contamination. Interestingly, anoxic worms cultured axenically excrete more succinate but almost no propionate, suggesting that the enzymes for the conversion of succinate to propionate are not active or are lacking under these conditions. Axenic culture conditions may also affect the lactate carrier, since axenic animals retain most of the lactate produced under anoxia in their tissues (<link linkend="bib43">F&#x000F6;ll et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10631804-->). These metabolic adaptations to oxygen deprivation are consistent with an induction of the pyruvate fermentation and malate dismutation pathways (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). Enhanced malate dismutation is also observed during dauer diapause. Dauers are resistant to several environmental stresses, including hypoxia (<link linkend="bib2">Anderson, 1978</link>; <link linkend="bib142">Scott et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12065745-->).</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec7_3_3">
<title>Genetic control of hypoxic metabolism</title>
<para>The metabolic adaptations to low oxygen are controlled by several genetic pathways. Unlike wild-type animals, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=hif-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">hif-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants survive poorly in the range of 0.5 - 1&#x00025; oxygen (<link linkend="bib145">Shen and Powell-Coffman, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12814951-->). In this range of oxygen concentration, animals decrease oxygen consumption, but continue to grow and reproduce. Thus <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HIF-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIF-1</ulink> is required for adaptation to hypoxia but not anoxia, where the worms enter a state of suspended animation (<link linkend="bib120">Padilla et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12006646-->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos can survive in both anoxia and hypoxia, but not in the oxygen concentration range between 0.01 and 0.1 kPa O<subscript>2</subscript>. Carbon monoxide can protect embryos and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=hif-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">hif-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants from hypoxic damage by inhibiting respiration and inducing suspended animation (<link linkend="bib116">Nystul and Roth, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15184665-->). Prolonged survival without oxygen is regulated by the insulin/IGF receptor homolog <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink> and the genes encoding glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpd-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpd-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpd-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpd-3</ulink></emphasis> contribute to this effect (<link linkend="bib142">Scott et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12065745-->; <link linkend="bib108">Mendenhall et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16980394-->). Anoxic conditions also induce upregulation of several globin genes and this effect requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HIF-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIF-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib65">Hoogewijs et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17916248-->).</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec7_4">
<title>Osmotic stress</title>
<para>Soil and freshwater nematodes are hyperosmotic to their normal environment and, when exposed to sudden fluctuations in external osmolarity, must be able to mount efficient osmoregulatory mechanisms. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> readily survives and adapts to growth in media containing 21-500 mM NaCl, primarily by adjusting the cellular concentration of glycerol. Hypertonic stress induces strong and sustained expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpdh-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpdh-1</ulink>,</emphasis> one of two <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes encoding glycerol 3-phosphate dehydrogenase, and weak and transient elevation of the other gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpdh-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpdh-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib86">Lamitina et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14644776-->; <link linkend="bib87">2006</link><!--: PMID 16880390-->; <link linkend="bib85">Lamitina and Strange, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15496475-->). GPDH mediates accumulation of glycerol, but the relevant biochemical pathway remains to be elucidated since a worm homolog of yeast glycerol 3-phosphate phosphatase has not been identified.</para>
<para>The mechanisms by which the animals sense osmotic stress and launch the osmoregulatory response are quite complex. Both disruption of the cuticle and osmotically induced protein damage are believed to induce osmoprotective gene induction. The genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=osm-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">osm-7</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=osm-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">osm-11</ulink></emphasis> and several <emphasis>dpy</emphasis> genes are believed to monitor cuticle integrity and to increase glycerol synthesis in response to osmotic stress (<link linkend="bib171">Wheeler and Thomas, 2006</link><!--: PMID 16980399-->). Genome-wide RNAi screening identified 122 genes that suppress the osmotic stress response under normal conditions. When inactivated by RNAi, they cause expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpdh-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpdh-1</ulink></emphasis> and glycerol accumulation, attenuating further hypertonic protein damage (<link linkend="bib87">Lamitina et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16880390-->). Defective insulin/IGF signaling also contributes to hypertonic stress resistance by increasing the intracellular level of trehalose and activating genes that protect against, or repair, osmotic stress-induced protein damage (<link linkend="bib85">Lamitina and Strange, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15496475-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>Aknowledgements</title>
<para>BPB and JRV are supported by the Fund for Scientific Research-Flanders (G.0025.06) and the European Community (LSHM-CT-2004-512020), Ghent University (12050101).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec9">
	<title>References</title>
		&intermetab_Refs;
		<para/>
</sect1>
</article>