<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'gabafig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'gabafig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'gabafig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'gabafig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'gabafig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'gabafig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'gabafig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'gabafig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'gabafig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'gabafig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'gabafig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'gabafig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY gaba_Refs SYSTEM 'gabarefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="gaba_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
           <title>GABA<footnote><para>Edited by Joshua M. Kaplan. Last revised August 31, 2005. Published August 31, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Jorgensen, E.M. GABA (August 31, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.14.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 Erik M. Jorgensen. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
</footnote>
       </title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>2.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 8/29/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory> 
-->
        <author>
            <firstname>Erik M.</firstname>
            <surname>Jorgensen<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:jorgensen@biology.utah.edu">jorgensen@biology.utah.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Howard Hughes Medical Institute and Department of Biology, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, UT 84112-0840 USA</address>
           </affiliation>
       </author>
   </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The most abundant synapses in the central nervous system of vertebrates are inhibitory synapses that use the neurotransmitter <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B3;</symbol>-aminobutyric acid (GABA). GABA is also an important neurotransmitter in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans;</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">however, in contrast to vertebrates where GABA acts at synapses of the central nervous system, in nematodes GABA acts primarily at neuromuscular synapses. Specifically, GABA acts to relax the body muscles during locomotion and foraging and to contract the enteric muscles during defecation. The importance of this neurotransmitter for basic motor functions of the worm has facilitated the genetic analysis of proteins required for GABA function. Genetic screens have identified the GABA biosynthetic enzyme, the vesicular transporter, inhibitory and excitatory receptors, and a transcription factor required for the differentiation of GABA cell identity. The plasma membrane transporter and other GABA receptors  have been identified by molecular criteria.</emphasis></para>
   </abstract>
    <sect1 id="sec1_1">
        <title>History of GABA</title>
            <para><symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B3;</symbol>-aminobutyric acid (GABA) is an amino acid neurotransmitter synthesized by decarboxylation of glutamate by the enzyme glutamic acid decarboxylase (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). GABA had been long known to exist in plants and bacteria, where it serves a metabolic role in the Krebs cycle. In 1950, Eugene Roberts and Jorge Awapara independently discovered that there were prodigious amounts of GABA in the mammalian central nervous system &#x02014; 1 mg per gram &#x02014; and GABA was virtually undetectable in other tissues (for historical perspectives, see <link linkend="bib48">Roberts, 2000</link><!-- PMID --> and <link linkend="bib21">Florey, 1991</link><!-- PMID 1954562 -->). However, GABA was not accepted as neurotransmitter until the 1960's after a great deal of physiological experimentation. In 1953, Ernst Florey observed that an unknown compound from horse brain inhibited the crayfish stretch receptor when applied exogenously (<link linkend="bib20">Florey, 1953</link><!-- PMID -->). Florey demonstrated that this same fraction inhibited the patellar reflex in cats and thus extended the action of this factor to vertebrates (<link linkend="bib22">Florey and McLennan, 1955</link><!-- PMID -->). With the help of Alva Bazemore from Merck Inc. Florey purified the molecule from 100 pounds of cow brain and determined that the active compound was GABA. They further demonstrated that chemically synthesized GABA could inhibit the crayfish stretch receptor (<link linkend="bib4">Bazemore et al., 1957</link><!-- PMID -->). This observation prompted Ernst Florey to propose that GABA was acting as an inhibitory neurotransmitter in the brain. However, GABA's extraordinary qualities soon became a burden to its acceptance into the pantheon of neurotransmitters; its enormous abundance in the vertebrate brain &#x02014; 1000-fold higher than known monoamine neurotransmitters, its simple structure and and its role in the Krebs cycle (the "GABA shunt") suggested that it was likely to be involved in metabolism rather than signaling. Moreover, it was demonstrated that GABA was not responsible for blocking the cat knee-jerk response (which is mediated by glycine that contaminated Florey's early preparations; <link linkend="bib11">Curtis et al., 1959</link><!-- PMID -->). Finally, GABA was not found in significant concentrations in any invertebrates. Thus, GABA did not act as a neurotransmitter in organisms that made it; and it was not found in organisms in which it acted. GABA no longer fulfilled the qualifications of a neurotransmitter and by 1960 it had been demoted to a mere metabolite (<link linkend="bib18">Edwards et al., 1999a</link><!-- PMID 10407419 -->).</para>
                <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig1" width="3.4in" align="center"/>
                   </imageobject><textobject>
                        <phrase> figure 1</phrase></textobject>
                    &fig1legend;
                </mediaobject>
            <para>Only a few years later, in part due to studies in nematodes, GABA was rehabilitated as a potential neurotransmitter. First, del Castillo and colleagues, working with the parasitic nematode <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis>, demonstrated that application of GABA [10 uM] or the GABA mimic piperazine [1mM] potently abolished spontaneous action potentials in muscles (<link linkend="bib12">Del Castillo et al., 1964a</link><!-- PMID -->; <link linkend="bib13">Del Castillo et al., 1964b</link><!--  PMID-->; <link linkend="bib15">Del Castillo et al., 1963</link><!-- PMID -->). This inhibition was caused by a hyperpolarization of the muscle from a resting potential of -30mV to -45mV, mediated by increased chloride conductance. Furthermore, stimulation of the inhibitory motor neurons in <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis> and crayfish duplicated the effect observed by GABA application (<link linkend="bib14">Del Castillo et al., 1967</link><!--  PMID -->; <link linkend="bib47">Otsuka et al., 1966</link><!-- PMID -->). GABA's presumed absence in invertebrates was contradicted by the discovery that it was found to be highly concentrated in inhibitory motor neurons of <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib24">Guastella et al., 1991</link><!-- PMID 1869633 -->; <link linkend="bib34">Johnson and Stretton, 1987</link><!-- PMID 3543249 -->) and crayfish (<link linkend="bib38">Kravitz et al., 1963</link><!-- PMID -->). Furthermore, lysates from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> exhibited enzymatic activity from the GABA biosynthetic enzyme, glutamic acid decarboxylase (<link linkend="bib27">Hedgecock, 1976</link><!-- PMID -->).</para>
   </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec1_2">
        <title>GABA action</title>
        <sect2 id="sec2_1">
            <title>GABA<subscript>A</subscript> receptors</title>
            <para>Electrophysiological recordings from <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis> by del Castillo demonstrated that GABA application inhibits body muscles by opening chloride channels (<link linkend="bib15">Del Castillo et al., 1963</link><!-- PMID -->). It is now known that these actions of GABA are mediated by the GABA<subscript>A</subscript> receptor, a GABA-gated chloride channel (<link linkend="bib50">Schofield et al., 1987</link><!-- PMID 3037384 -->). In vertebrate neurons, chloride ions are pumped out of the cell; thus, activation of GABA receptors will permit chloride to diffuse into the cell, hyperpolarize the membrane and decrease the excitability of the cell. This type of inhibition is called hyperpolarizing inhibition. In some cells, internal chloride is at concentrations higher than the equilibrium potential. In these cases, opening chloride channels caused an efflux of this anion, creating an inward current, and depolarizing the membrane. Nevertheless, this depolarization still inhibits muscle contraction because the increase in chloride conductance creates a 'current shunt' for excitatory currents (<link linkend="bib39">Kuffler and Eyzaguirre, 1955</link><!-- PMID -->). Specifically, the abundance of open chloride channels clamps the membrane voltage at the chloride equilibrium potential and 'shunts'  further depolarization. In addition, the weak depolarization caused by chloride conductance inactivates Na<superscript>+</superscript> channels (<link linkend="bib19">Edwards et al., 1999b</link><!-- PMID 10203852 -->). This type of inhibition is called depolarizing inhibition. Thus, activation of GABA receptors will inhibit cell activity whether it hyperpolarizes or depolarizes the cell.</para>
       </sect2>
           <sect2 id="sec2_2">
            <title>GABA<subscript>B</subscript> receptors.</title>
            <para>GABA can also inhibit membrane excitability by opening K<superscript>+</superscript> channels and inhibiting Ca<superscript>+</superscript><superscript>+</superscript> channels. These actions are mediated by the GABA<subscript>B</subscript> receptor, a 7-pass transmembrane receptor (<link linkend="bib35">Kaupmann et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9069281 -->; for a review see <link linkend="bib8">Calver et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12566919 -->). A functional GABA<subscript>B</subscript> receptor is composed of two subunits that form a heterodimer. GABA binding to the GABA<subscript>B</subscript> receptor activates the trimeric G protein Gi/o (<link linkend="bib9">Campbell et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8308719 -->). The activated G<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>o subunit can inhibit voltage-gated Ca<superscript>+</superscript><superscript>+</superscript> channels or activate K<superscript>+</superscript> channels.</para>
            <para>The actions of the different GABA receptor types were originally defined by independent pharmacological sensitivities. GABA<subscript>A</subscript> receptors are activated by muscimol, whereas GABA<subscript>B</subscript> receptors are activated by baclofen (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). The GABA<subscript>A</subscript> receptors are blocked by bicuculline, whereas the GABA<subscript>B</subscript> receptor can be blocked by saclofen or phaclofen (<link linkend="bib26">Guillon et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID -->). Although the pharmacology of GABA receptors in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> differs somewhat compared to GABA receptors in vertebrates, nematodes possess both GABA<subscript>A</subscript> and GABA<subscript>B</subscript> receptors based on sequence similarity.</para>
       </sect2>
   </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec1_3">
        <title>GABA neurons in nematodes</title>
        <para>To identify the GABA-containing cells in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, wild-type animals were stained with antibodies against the neurotransmitter. Antibody staining revealed that 26 of the 302 neurons present in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> express the neurotransmitter GABA (<xref linkend="figure2"/>A). These 26 GABA neurons are comprised of 6 DD, 13 VD, 4 RME, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RIS;class=Cell" role="_blank">RIS</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVL;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVL</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink> (<xref linkend="figure2"/>B). These neurons fall into different classes based on their synaptic outputs: the D-type neurons, that is, the 6 DD and 13 VD motor neurons, innervate the dorsal and ventral body muscles, respectively; the 4 RME motor neurons innervate the head muscles; the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVL;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVL</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink> motor neurons innervate the enteric muscles; and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RIS;class=Cell" role="_blank">RIS</ulink> is an interneuron (<link linkend="bib55">White et al., 1986</link><!-- PMID -->).</para>
        <para>Although <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are diverged by 500 million years, their nervous systems are remarkably conserved. In <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis>, a nearly equivalent set of 26 major GABA-synthesizing neurons were identified by immunostaining (<link linkend="bib24">Guastella et al., 1991</link><!-- PMID 1869633 -->; <link linkend="bib34">Johnson and Stretton, 1987</link><!-- PMID 3543249 -->). In the ventral nerve cord 6 DD-like and 13 VD-like cells express GABA. In the head, there are 4 RME-like cells and in the tail a DVB-like cell. Variable staining was observed for additional cells in the head; although there are 6 bilaterally symmetric cells which stained in the cephalic ganglia, they do not appear to be homologs of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVL;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVL</ulink> and RIS.</para>
            <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.5in" align="center"/>
               </imageobject><textobject>
                    <phrase> figure 2</phrase></textobject>
            &fig2legend;
            </mediaobject>
     <sect2 id="sec2_3">
            <title>GABA neuron function</title>
            <para>To determine the <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> behavioral role of the GABA neurons, laser ablation of specific classes of neurons was performed (<link linkend="bib43">McIntire et al., 1993</link><!--  PMID 8332191 -->). Functions were identified for the D-type body muscle motor neurons, for the RME head muscle motor neurons, and for the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVL;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVL</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink> enteric muscle motor neurons. No function was identified for the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RIS;class=Cell" role="_blank">RIS</ulink> interneuron. Based on these studies, it was concluded that GABA acts as both an inhibitory and excitatory neurotransmitter in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
            <sect3 id="sec3_1">
                <title>Inhibitory GABA function - locomotion</title>
                <para>The 19 ventral cord D-type neurons inhibit contraction of the ventral and dorsal body wall muscles during locomotion (<link linkend="bib43">McIntire et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8332191 -->). A bend in the body is made by contracting muscles on one side of the body while relaxing muscles via GABA innervation on the opposite side (<xref linkend="figure3"/>C), which gives the worm its distinctive sinusoidal body posture. Movement occurs when a body bend is propagated from one end of the animal to the other (<xref linkend="figure3"/>A). Because the VD and DD neurons are required for relaxation of the body wall muscles, when these neurons are killed, the operated worm only has excitatory input into its muscles. Operated animals can still adopt a sinusoidal posture and can swim, albeit with reduced wave amplitudes. However, when an animal lacking D-type neuron function is touched, it "shrinks", that is, it pulls in its head and shortens its body due to hypercontraction of the body wall muscles on both sides of the body (<xref linkend="figure3"/>B). Therefore, GABA released from the ventral cord D-type neurons is required to relax muscles, to reset posture when changing directions, and provide normal wave shape when swimming.</para>
                <mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4.7in" align="center"/>
                   </imageobject><textobject>
                        <phrase> figure 3</phrase></textobject>
                    &fig3legend;
               </mediaobject>
           </sect3>
            <sect3 id="sec3_2">
                <title>Inhibitory GABA function - foraging</title>
                <para>The RME neurons regulate foraging movements of the head. During normal foraging the tip of the nose moves from side to side within a narrow arc of movement (<xref linkend="figure4"/>A). Killing the four RME motor neurons by laser microsurgery resulted in worms with "loopy" foraging in which the flexures of the nose became grossly exaggerated (<xref linkend="figure4"/>B). Thus, the RMEs appear to limit the extent of head deflection during foraging. The RMEs receive input from sensory neurons of the head and nose; for example, SMB and SAA innervate the ipsilateral RME, either directly or indirectly (<xref linkend="figure4"/>C). Both of these neurons have long undifferentiated processes that run anteriorly and posteriorly along the dorsal side of the head, and these neurons may provide proprioceptive information about head position (<link linkend="bib55">White et al., 1986</link><!-- PMID -->). The RMEs send outputs to contralateral muscles of the head. It is possible that bending of the head during foraging activates stretch receptors in the SMB and SAA neurons, which then activate an RME neuron, which in turn relaxes the muscles on the opposite side of the bend and restores head posture.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
                <mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4.5in" align="center"/>
                   </imageobject><textobject>
                        <phrase> figure 4</phrase></textobject>
                    &fig4legend;
               </mediaobject>
           </sect3>
            <sect3 id="sec3_3">
                <title>Excitatory GABA function</title>
                <para>The GABA motor neurons, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVL;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVL</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink>, stimulate the enteric muscles during defecation (<xref linkend="figure5"/>B; <link linkend="bib43">McIntire et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8332191 -->). Every 50 seconds a worm undergoes a stereotypic pattern of muscle contractions, which ultimately leads to the expulsion of intestinal contents (<xref linkend="figure5"/>A; <link linkend="bib54">Thomas, 1990</link><!-- PMID -->). The final step of the motor program is the contraction of the enteric muscles (Emc). This contraction squeezes the intestine and opens the anus so that the intestinal contents can be expelled. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVL;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVL</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink> are required in the last step to contract the enteric muscles (<link linkend="bib43">McIntire et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8332191 -->). When these neurons are killed using a laser, the worm fails to contract its enteric muscles and becomes bloated with food. Addition of GABA or the GABA agonist muscimol will restore contractions of this muscle. Therefore, GABA released from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVL;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVL</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink> is required to induce contraction of these muscles.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
                    <mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4in" align="center"/>
                       </imageobject><textobject>
                            <phrase> figure 5</phrase></textobject>
                        &fig5legend;
                   </mediaobject>
           </sect3>
       </sect2>
        <sect2 id="sec2_4">
            <title>Genetic screen</title>
            <para>To identify genes required for GABA function, mutants were identified that resembled worms in which the GABA neurons were killed (<link linkend="bib44">McIntire et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8332190 -->; <link linkend="bib54">Thomas, 1990</link><!-- PMID -->). A total of six genes were identified that caused all or a subset of the behavioral defects when mutated (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). Three of these mutants (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-46" role="_blank">unc-46</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-47" role="_blank">unc-47</ulink></emphasis>) were shrinkers and expulsion defective, suggesting that these genes were important for universal functions of GABA. Two of these mutants (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-30" role="_blank">unc-30</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-49" role="_blank">unc-49</ulink></emphasis>) were shrinkers but had normal expulsions indicating that they specifically eliminated the inhibitory functions. One of these mutants (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=exp-1" role="_blank">exp-1</ulink></emphasis>) was only defective for the enteric muscle contractions indicating that it was specific for the excitatory functions of GABA (<link linkend="bib54">Thomas, 1990</link>). Shrinking or expulsion-defective mutants that also exhibited pleiotropic phenotypes were ignored.</para>
<?newpage?>
            <table id="table1" frame='all'>
                <title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1. GABA mutant phenotypes</emphasis></title>
                <tgroup cols='7' align='center' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="0.6*" align="center" />
                <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="0.8*" align="center" />
                <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="0.8*" align="center" />
                <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="0.8*" align="center" />
                <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="1*" align="left" />
                <colspec colname="c6" colwidth="1.5*" align="left" />
                <colspec colname="c7" colwidth="1*" align="left" />
                    <thead>
                    <row  valign="middle">
                        <entry>Mutant</entry>
                        <entry>Inhibitory function present<footnote id='a'><para>- = defective behavior, + = wild type behavior, (+) = wild type GABA level, (-) = low GABA level, (++++) = high GABA level (<link linkend="bib44">McIntire et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8332190 -->).</para></footnote></entry>
                        <entry>Excitatory function present<footnoteref linkend='a'/></entry>
                        <entry>Muscimol sensitive<footnoteref linkend='a'/></entry>
                        <entry>GABA levels<footnoteref linkend='a'/></entry>
                        <entry>Protein</entry>
                        <entry>Reference</entry>
                    </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row  valign="middle">
                            <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                            <entry>yes</entry>
                            <entry>(-)</entry>
                            <entry>GAD</entry>
                            <entry>Jin, 1999</entry>
                       </row>
                       <row  valign="middle">
                            <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-30" role="_blank">unc-30</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                            <entry>+</entry>
                            <entry>yes</entry>
                            <entry valign="middle"><simplelist type="horiz" columns="1">
                                    <member>VDs and DDs</member> <member>(-)</member>
                                    <member>RMEs, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVL;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVL</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RIS;class=Cell" role="_blank">RIS</ulink></member> <member>(+)</member>
                                </simplelist></entry>
                            <entry>Transcription factor</entry>
                            <entry>Jin, 1994</entry>
                       </row>
                       <row  valign="middle">
                            <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-46" role="_blank">unc-46</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                            <entry>yes</entry>
                            <entry>(+)</entry>
                            <entry>?</entry>
                            <entry>N/A</entry>
                       </row>
                       <row  valign="middle">
                            <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-47" role="_blank">unc-47</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                            <entry>yes</entry>
                            <entry>(++++)</entry>
                            <entry>VGAT</entry>
                            <entry>McIntire, 1997</entry>
                       </row>
                       <row  valign="middle">
                            <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-49" role="_blank">unc-49</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                            <entry>+</entry>
                            <entry>no</entry>
                            <entry>(+)</entry>
                            <entry>Anionic GABA-R</entry>
                            <entry>Bamber, 1999</entry>
                       </row>
                       <row  valign="middle">
                            <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=exp-1" role="_blank">exp-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                            <entry>+</entry>
                            <entry>-</entry>
                            <entry>no</entry>
                            <entry>(+)</entry>
                            <entry>Cationic GABA-R</entry>
                            <entry>Beg, 2003</entry>
                       </row>
                </tbody>
                </tgroup>
                </table>
            <sect3 id="sec3_4">
                <title><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis>: GABA biosynthesis</title>
                <para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis> encodes the biosynthetic enzyme for GABA, glutamic  acid decarboxylase (GAD; <xref linkend="figure6"/>; <link linkend="bib33">Jin et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID -->). Previously, <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> data had indicated that GABA could be involved in neuronal development, specifically in cell proliferation, cell migration, neurite extension, or synapse formation (<link linkend="bib6">Belhage et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9777639 -->). However, genetic studies in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (below) and more recently in mice have demonstrated that GABA does not play a role in development (<link linkend="bib30">Ji et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10211762 -->).</para>
                <para>Careful analysis of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis> mutant phenotype failed to reveal defects in neuronal development. Axon morphology of GABA neurons is normal in adult <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib33">Jin et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID -->). Synaptic varicosities, assayed by clusters of fluorescently-tagged synaptic vesicles, are at normal positions and densities in the ventral cord GABA motor neurons (<link linkend="bib33">Jin et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID -->). The post-synaptic GABA receptor also has a normal distribution in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib23">Gally and Bessereau, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12684444 -->). A reconstruction of the ventral nerve cord from serial electron micrographs demonstrated that the synaptic ultrastructure and connectivity were correct (<link linkend="bib33">Jin et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID -->). Definitive proof that GABA synapses are functional was provided by rescuing <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis> function as an adult: addition of exogenous GABA provided the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVL;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVL</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink> neurons with an external source of GABA, GABA was pumped into cells via the plasma membrane transporter, and normal behavior was restored (<link linkend="bib44">McIntire et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8332190 -->). These data demonstrate unequivocally that GABA release is not required for axon outgrowth, synapse formation or synapse maintenance in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
           </sect3>
            <sect3 id="sec3_5">
                <title><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-47" role="_blank">unc-47</ulink></emphasis>: vesicular GABA transporter</title>
                <para>The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-47" role="_blank">unc-47</ulink></emphasis> gene encodes the transporter that pumps GABA into the synaptic vesicle (<xref linkend="figure6"/>; <link linkend="bib45">McIntire et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID -->) <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-47;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-47</ulink> is an 11-pass transmembrane protein which was not related to other transporter families known at the time. The rat homolog of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-47;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-47</ulink> was cloned by homology and it was found that rUNC-47 (currently called VIAAT or VGAT) is capable of transporting GABA and glycine into acidified vesicles (<link linkend="bib45">McIntire et al., 1997</link><!--  PMID-->; <link linkend="bib49">Sagne et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9395291 -->). The discovery of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-47;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-47</ulink> made possible the identification several families of amino acid transporters based on homology to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-47;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-47</ulink>. The System N and A transporters (SLC38 family of solute carrier proteins) transport neutral amino acids across the plasma membrane using the Na<superscript>+</superscript> gradient for coupled transport (N: glutamine, asparagine, and histidine; A: alanine asparagine cysteine, glutamine, glycine, methionine, and serine; <link linkend="bib42">Mackenzie and Erickson, 2004</link><!-- PMID 12845534 -->). The SLC36 family transports amino acids from the lysosome or at the apical membrane of the intestine using the H<superscript>+</superscript> ion gradient for coupled transport (<link linkend="bib7">Boll et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 12748860 -->). Like all other vesicular neurotransmitter transporters, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-47;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-47</ulink> uses a proton gradient generated by the vacuolar ATPase as a secondary energy source to transport GABA against its concentration gradient. Surprisingly, there are two other unrelated families of proteins which transport neurotransmitters into synaptic vesicles: the vesicular monoamine and acetylcholine transporter family (<link linkend="bib16">Duerr et al., 1999</link><!--  PMID -->; <link linkend="bib41">Liu et al., 1992</link><!-- PMID 1505023 -->), and the glutamate transporter family (<link linkend="bib40">Lee et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 9870947 -->; <link linkend="bib53">Takamori et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 11001057 -->). Why these classes of neurotransmitter transporters, which all use a proton gradient for an energy source, did not evolve from a common ancestor is a mystery. Moreover, these transporters are also unrelated to the plasma membrane neurotransmitter transporters. Plasma membrane neurotransmitter transporters remove secreted neurotransmitters from the synaptic cleft by pumping them back across the plasma membrane, but use the Na<superscript>+</superscript> gradient for active transport instead of a H<superscript>+</superscript> gradient (see '<link linkend="sec2_5">Other GABA genes</link>' below).</para>
                <literallayout></literallayout>
                <mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata entityref="fig6" width="3in" align="center"/>
                       </imageobject><textobject>
                            <phrase> figure 6</phrase></textobject>
                        &fig6legend;
                   </mediaobject>
           </sect3>
            <sect3 id="sec3_6">
                <title><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-46" role="_blank">unc-46</ulink></emphasis>: an auxiliary protein for transport</title>
                <para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-46" role="_blank">unc-46</ulink></emphasis> mutants are defective for both the inhibitory and excitatory functions of GABA which suggests that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=-46;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-46</ulink> acts presynaptically (<link linkend="bib44">McIntire et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8332190 -->). However, the phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-46" role="_blank">unc-46</ulink></emphasis> mutants is weaker than <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-47" role="_blank">unc-47</ulink></emphasis> mutants. Overexpression of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=-47;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-47</ulink> GABA transporter in an <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-46" role="_blank">unc-46</ulink></emphasis> mutant background partially rescues the defects in these animals (K. Schuske and E. Jorgensen, unpublished). Thus, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=-46;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-46</ulink> may regulate the activity or localization of the vesicular GABA transporter but it is not absolutely required for transport activity (<xref linkend="figure6"/>).</para>
           </sect3>
            <sect3 id="sec3_7">
                <title><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-30" role="_blank">unc-30</ulink></emphasis>: a homeodomain transcription factor for GABA neuron identity</title>
                <para>The biosynthetic enzyme and vesicular transporter for GABA are the key enzymes that determine neurotransmitter-specific identity for GABA neurons. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-30" role="_blank">unc-30</ulink></emphasis> gene is a transcription factor that coordinately regulates the expression of these enzymes. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-30;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-30</ulink> was the founding member of a class of homeodomain-containing transcription factors that include Pitx1, Pitx2 and Pitx3 in vertebrates (<link linkend="bib32">Jin et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID -->). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-30" role="_blank">unc-30</ulink></emphasis> gene is expressed in the VD and DD neurons and these cells show defects in GABA cell identity in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-30" role="_blank">unc-30</ulink></emphasis> mutants. First, axonal outgrowth of the D neurons is defective in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-30" role="_blank">unc-30</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib44">McIntire et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8332190 -->). Second, selection of synaptic targets is abnormal in these mutants (J. White, personal communication). Third, neither GAD, the biosynthetic enzyme for GABA, nor the vesicular GABA transporter are expressed in the VD and DD neurons in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-30" role="_blank">unc-30</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib17">Eastman et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10414952 -->). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-30;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-30</ulink> protein binds to promoter elements in both the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis>/ GAD and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-47" role="_blank">unc-47</ulink></emphasis> /VGAT genes, and these elements were necessary for expression of these genes in the DD and VD neurons (<link linkend="bib17">Eastman et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10414952 -->). Ubiquitous expression of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-30;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-30</ulink> protein led to the ectopic synthesis of GABA in many non-GABA neurons as well as in some non-neuronal tissues. These data suggest that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-30;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-30</ulink> is sufficient to express GABA neuron identity in cells, even if these cells, such as  hypodermal cells, lack factors for neuronal cell identity (<link linkend="bib32">Jin et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID -->). It is thus surprising that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-30;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-30</ulink> is expressed in six cells that do not express GABA cell identity - why don't these neurons express <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-47" role="_blank">unc-47</ulink></emphasis> given that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-30;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-30</ulink> expression is sufficient for activation of these genes in epidermal cells? The other GABA neurons, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVL;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVL</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RIS;class=Cell" role="_blank">RIS</ulink> and the RMEs, do not require <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-30;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-30</ulink> for the expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-47" role="_blank">unc-47</ulink></emphasis>. In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lim-6" role="_blank">lim-6</ulink></emphasis> mutants, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis> expression is reduced in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RIS;class=Cell" role="_blank">RIS</ulink>, but <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-47" role="_blank">unc-47</ulink></emphasis> expression is normal; moreover, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lim-6" role="_blank">lim-6</ulink></emphasis> is involved in the fate of nonGABA and non-neuronal cells as well, suggesting it does not specifiy neurotransmitter type (<link linkend="bib28">Hobert et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10068647 -->). GABA neuron identity in these cells requires other as yet unidentified genes. Other genes specify cell identities among GABA neurons; for example, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ahr-1" role="_blank">ahr-1</ulink></emphasis> specifies <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RMEL;class=Cell" role="_blank">RMEL</ulink>/R fates as different from an <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RMED;class=Cell" role="_blank">RMED</ulink>/V ground state (<link linkend="bib29">Huang et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14757639 -->); <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-55" role="_blank">unc-55</ulink></emphasis> specifies VD cell identity as unique from a DD ground state (<link linkend="bib56">Zhou et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9852581 -->; <link linkend="bib52">Shan et al.; 2005</link><!-- PMID 15882588 -->). However, once again, these transcription factors do not define the GABA neurotransmitter identity in these cells.</para>
                <para>What are all the targets of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-30;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-30</ulink> in the genome? Microarray expression studies of GABA neurons combined with computational searches for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-30;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-30</ulink> binding motifs revealed 24 potential <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-30;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-30</ulink> target genes, which were not identified in the GABA screen (<link linkend="bib10">Cinar et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID 15723795 -->). Although many of these are not unique to GABA neurons, analysis of expression patterns indicate that at least some of these require <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-30;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-30</ulink> for expression in GABA neurons.</para>
                <para>In summary, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-30;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-30</ulink> is required for GABA neuron specification in the D-type neurons and its expression is sufficient for conferring GABA neuron identity. However, its role in cell identity is complicated. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-30;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-30</ulink> is not required by all GABA neurons for GABA cell identity. How these cells regulate neurotransmitter specificity is not known. Moreover, some cells that express <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-30;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-30</ulink> do not display GABA cell identity. Why these cells do not express GABA specific genes is not known.</para>
           </sect3>
            <sect3 id="sec3_8">
                <title><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-49" role="_blank">unc-49</ulink></emphasis>: the GABA<subscript>A</subscript> receptor</title>
                <para>GABA<subscript>A</subscript> receptors are GABA-gated chloride channels that inhibit cell activity. The GABA<subscript>A</subscript> receptor, that inhibits body muscle contraction during locomotion, is encoded by the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-49" role="_blank">unc-49</ulink></emphasis> gene (<xref linkend="figure6"/>; <link linkend="bib1">Bamber et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10377345 -->; <link linkend="bib2">Bamber et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID 15655525 -->). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-49" role="_blank">unc-49</ulink></emphasis> locus encodes three distinct GABA receptor subunits by splicing a common N-terminal ligand-binding domain to one of three alternative C-terminal domains, producing the UNC-49A, UNC-49B, and UNC-49C subunits (<link linkend="bib1">Bamber et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10377345 -->). Keep in mind that these alternative gene products are all subunits of a GABA<subscript>A</subscript> ligand-gated ion channel and are not related to GABA<subscript>B</subscript> receptors. This unusual gene structure is conserved in the distantly-related nematode <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>. The UNC-49B and UNC-49C subunits are expressed in the muscles and localized to synapses from the D-type GABA motor neurons (<link linkend="bib1">Bamber et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10377345 -->; <link linkend="bib2">Bamber et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID 15655525 -->; <link linkend="bib23">Gally and Bessereau, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12684444 -->). The GABA receptor at neuromuscular junctions is a heteromer composed of the B and C subunits (<link linkend="bib2">Bamber et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID 15655525 -->). The B subunit is required for localization of the receptor to neuromuscular junctions and the C subunit imparts specific pharmacological properties to the heteromeric receptor (<link linkend="bib2">Bamber et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID 15655525 -->; <link linkend="bib3">Bamber et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12642390 -->). The UNC-49A subunit is barely detectable <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>, and does not heteromultimerize with UNC-49B or UNC-49C to form a functional receptor <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib1">Bamber et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10377345 -->).</para>
           </sect3>
            <sect3 id="sec3_9">
                <title><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=exp-1" role="_blank">exp-1</ulink></emphasis>: a GABA-gated cation channel</title>
                <para>Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=exp-1" role="_blank">exp-1</ulink></emphasis> were originally identified in screens for mutants with defects in the defecation cycle (<link linkend="bib54">Thomas, 1990</link><!-- PMID -->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=exp-1" role="_blank">exp-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants exhibit defects in excitatory GABA functions but are normal for the inhibitory GABA functions. Specifically, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=exp-1" role="_blank">exp-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants lack enteric muscle contractions yet move and forage normally, and thus resemble animals in which the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVL;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVL</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink> GABA motor neurons were killed (<link linkend="bib43">McIntire et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8332191 -->). Consistent with its role in excitatory GABA transmission, it was found that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=exp-1" role="_blank">exp-1</ulink></emphasis> encodes a novel GABA-gated cation channel (<xref linkend="figure6"/>; <link linkend="bib5">Beg and Jorgensen, 2003</link><!-- PMID 14555952 -->). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EXP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">EXP-1</ulink> protein is expressed in the enteric muscles, and is  localized to the synaptic inputs from the GABA neurons <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVL;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVL</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink>. Electrophysiological characterization of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EXP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">EXP-1</ulink> GABA receptor demonstrated that the channel is selective for cations (<link linkend="bib5">Beg and Jorgensen, 2003</link><!-- PMID 14555952 -->), in contrast to all the other GABA-gated ion channels, which are anion selective (<link linkend="bib46">Olsen, 1991</link><!-- PMID -->). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EXP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">EXP-1</ulink> protein resembles conventional GABA receptors except in the pore-forming domain which contains amino acid changes which permit cation permeability (<link linkend="bib36">Keramidas et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10866951 -->,  <link linkend="bib37">2002</link><!-- PMID 11981020 -->).</para>
            </sect3>
            </sect2>
<?newpage?>
            <sect2 id="sec2_5">
            <title>Other GABA genes</title>
            <sect3 id="sec3_10">
            <title>Receptors</title>
            <para>Examination of the genome indicates that there are several genes involved in GABA function that were not identified in the genetic screens for GABA function. There are multiple GABA receptor subunits that can be observed in the genome by sequence homology that were not mutated in screens for shrinker or expulsion-defective mutants. Notably, there are <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> and <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> GABA<subscript>A</subscript> receptor subunits (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T19B10.10;class=Gene" role="_blank">T19B10.10</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ZC482.1;class=CDS" role="_blank">ZC482.1</ulink>), another <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-49;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-49</ulink> like receptor subunit (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F11H8.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">F11H8.2</ulink>), another <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EXP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">EXP-1</ulink>-related receptor subunit (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y46G5A.26;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y46G5A.26</ulink>, A. Beg and E. Jorgensen, unpublished), and there is a heteromeric metabotropic GABA<subscript>B</subscript> receptor encoded in the genome (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y41G9A.4;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y41G9A.4</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ZK180.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ZK180.1</ulink>; J. Dittman and J. Kaplan, personal communication). The GABA-mediated behaviors controlled by these four additional GABA receptors are unknown; however, one of these receptors might be responsible for mediating foraging behavior, which is defective in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis>/GAD mutants but is not defective in either <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-49" role="_blank">unc-49</ulink></emphasis> mutants or in  <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=exp-1" role="_blank">exp-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants.</para>
            <para>Once neurotransmitters are secreted into the cleft, they must be cleared by active  processes. GABA is removed from the cleft by a plasma membrane transporter which pumps the transmitter back into the neuron (<link linkend="bib25">Guastella et al., 1990</link><!-- PMID 1975955 -->). The plasma membrane GABA transporter was not identified in the genetic screens for shrinkers or for expulsion-defective mutants. Nevertheless, the activity of the GABA transporter could be observed. Specifically, the addition of exogenous GABA to mutants that lacked GABA (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis>), restored GABA immunoreactivity and function (<link linkend="bib44">McIntire et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8332190 -->). Moreover, pharmacological antagonists of the GABA transporter blocked GABA uptake into neurons of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-25" role="_blank">unc-25</ulink></emphasis>. The gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=snf-11" role="_blank">snf-11</ulink></emphasis> is highly similar to the vertebrate GABA transporter (<xref linkend="figure6"/>), and the transporter is expressed in all GABA neurons (<link linkend="bib31">Jiang et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID 15542610 -->). Expression of this transporter in heterologous cells confirmed that it is a functional plasma membrane GABA transporter (<link linkend="bib31">Jiang et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID 15542610 -->).</para>
            </sect3>
       </sect2>
        <sect2 id="sec2_6">
            <title>Similarities with vertebrates</title>
            <para>Nematodes and vertebrates diverged over 800 million years ago. Nevertheless the proteins governing GABA cell identity, biosynthesis and transport are conserved in the nematode and vertebrate nervous systems. Notably, studies in the nematode identified the vesicular GABA transporter and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-30;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-30</ulink> homeodomain transcription factor, and subsequent genome comparisons identified the vertebrate orthologs of these genes. Although there does not appear to be a GABA-gated cation channel related to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EXP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">EXP-1</ulink> in the vertebrate genome, the GABA<subscript>A</subscript> chloride channel and the GABA<subscript>B</subscript> G-protein coupled receptor are both found in the vertebrate and nematode genomes.</para>
        </sect2>
        </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec1_4">
        <title>References</title>
        <para/>
        &gaba_Refs;
    </sect1>
</article>
