<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'geneticmosaicsfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'geneticmosaicsfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'geneticmosaicsfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'geneticmosaicsfig2leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY geneticmosaics_Refs SYSTEM 'geneticmosaicsrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="geneticmosaics_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Genetic mosaics<footnote>
                <para>Edited by Jonathan Hodgkin and Philip Anderson. Last revised March 14, 2005. Published December 27, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Yochem, J. and Herman, R. K. Genetic mosaics (December 27, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.58.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 John Yochem and Robert K. Herman. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
            </footnote>
        </title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 3/14/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
-->
        <author>
            <othername>John Yochem<remark>
                    <footnote>
                        <para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:yoche001@umn.edu">yoche001@umn.edu</ulink></para>
                    </footnote>
                </remark>, Robert K. Herman</othername>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Department of Genetics, Cell Biology, and Development, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN 55455 USA</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Genetic mosaics can be used to gain insight into the cell specificity of gene
            function. How</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">mosaics are typically
            generated is reviewed, and several examples with relevance to developmental studies are
            mentioned. One example is</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mpk-1" role="_blank">mpk-1</ulink>,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">which encodes a member of the
            Ras-MAP-kinase pathway.</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mpk-1" role="_blank">mpk-1</ulink></emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">mosaics have been a means of studying
            the distinct cells that require the gene for distinct fates during development. The gene</emphasis>
            <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=bre-5" role="_blank">bre-5</ulink></emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">is used as an example of the usefulness of mosaic analysis
            for non-developmental studies. Potential problems with mosaic analysis are discussed,
            and the power of combining mosaic analysis with cell- or tissue-specific promoters is
            mentioned.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
    <sect1>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>A genetic mosaic is an individual in which different cells have different genotypes.
            In <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis>, genetic mosaics have been generated,
            identified, and analyzed for the purpose of defining where in the animal a gene of
            interest must be expressed to cause a particular phenotypic effect. Most <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> mosaics that have been studied were homozygous mutant for a recessive
            mutation in all cells and carried additionally, in some cells, one or more copies of the
            wild-type allele of the same gene on an extrachromosomal element. Before mosaic analysis
            is undertaken, a mutant phenotype corresponding to the absence of the wild-type gene
            from all cells is analyzed and described. Some mutant phenotypes are described in
            whole-animal terms, such as uncoordinated movement, longer-than-normal lifespan,
            abnormal body shape, or inviability. Such traits can be analyzed in mosaic animals. The
            overall phenotypes are recorded for mosaic animals in which it is known which cells
            carry the wild-type gene and which do not, with the goal of establishing which cells
            must carry the wild-type gene to prevent the appearance of the mutant phenotype. The
            responsible cell or group of cells is referred to as the anatomical focus of the action
            of the gene with respect to the phenotype under study.</para>
        <para>In a second class of mutants, it is known at the outset that particular cells—specific
            nerve or muscle cells, for example—exhibit an abnormality, which is generally detected
            microscopically. Mosaic animals can then be used to ask whether or not the cellular
            focus of action with respect to this phenotype is in the very cell or cells that exhibit
            the abnormality; this is equivalent to asking whether or not the gene acts cell
            autonomously with respect to the cellular phenotype. When a gene acts cell autonomously,
            the phenotype of a cell is determined solely by the genotype of that cell and not by the
            genotypes of neighboring or other cells. A gene is said to act cell nonautonomously when
            a genotypically homozygous mutant cell exhibits a wild-type phenotype or when a cell
            carrying a wild-type allele exhibits a mutant phenotype. Cell non-autonomy is caused by
            intercellular interactions, and mosaic analysis can help elucidate the nature of the
            interaction. For example, a gene that produces a ligand that must be recognized by a
            receptor on a second cell could act cell nonautonomously with respect to a phenotypic
            effect in the receiving cell.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>How worm genetic mosaics are generated</title>
        <para>The generation, identification, and analysis of genetic mosaics in <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> have recently been reviewed (<link linkend="bib3">Herman, 1995</link><!--: PMID 8531723-->; <link linkend="bib17">Yochem et
            al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10791339-->; <link linkend="bib16">Yochem and Herman, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12952898-->). Also, a few of the
            technical details concerning mosaics are mentioned elsewhere in WormBook (see <ulink
                url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_nomarskianatomymosaic/nomarskianatomymosaic.html" role="_blank">Nomarski images for learning the anatomy, with tips for mosaic
                analysis</ulink>). Thus, these issues shall only be briefly mentioned here. Worm
            genetic mosaics have usually been generated from zygotes that were homozygous mutant for
            the gene under study and carried the wild-type allele of the same gene on an
            extrachromosomal element—either an extrachromosomal array or a free duplication of part
            of a chromosome—that was subject to spontaneous mitotic loss. If the extrachromosomal
            element is present in all cells, the animal exhibits a wild-type phenotype. But if the
            extrachromosomal element fails to be transmitted to a daughter cell during the
            development of the animal, all of the descendants of that cell, a clone, will lack the
            wild-type allele and be homozygous mutant. The extrachromosomal element should carry a
            second gene that behaves cell autonomously and can be scored to track which cells carry
            the extrachromosomal element and which do not. The well-described and nearly invariant
            cell lineage (<link linkend="bib12">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!--: PMID 6684600-->) is a great aid in determining where in
            the lineage the extrachromosomal element was lost. This allows one to determine
            precisely, without scoring every cell, the genotypes of essentially every cell in the
            mosaic animal. Although the primary method has been described above, <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> mosaics have also been generated by other methods (<link linkend="bib3">Herman, 1995</link><!--:
           PMID 8531723-->), and chimeric partial embryos have been formed <emphasis>in
            vitro</emphasis> from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> and P<subscript>2</subscript> blastomeres for genetic studies
            of Wnt signaling during early development (<link linkend="bib13">Thorpe et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9288749-->; <link linkend="bib10">Schlesinger
            et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10444600-->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>A few examples of mosaic analysis in worms</title>
        <para>Over 75 genes have been analyzed in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genetic mosaics.
            Several examples of how mosaic analysis has contributed important insights into worm
            development were recently reviewed (<link linkend="bib17">Yochem et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10791339-->; <link linkend="bib16">Yochem and
            Herman, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12952898-->). Included were genes implicated in cell-to-cell signaling,
            with the functions of some genes assigned to the signaling cell and the functions of
            others assigned to the signal-receiving cell. Other examples in which anatomical foci
            were determined included genes affecting whole-animal phenotypes such as uncoordination,
            body size, and lifespan. A few additional examples are noted here.</para>
        <para>Mutations that confer uncoordinated movement often affect the body-wall muscles or the
            nervous system. The nature of the cell lineage makes it possible quickly to distinguish
            these candidate cell types: all of the body neurons, except for two, descend from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink>, a
            daughter of the zygote; and all of the body-wall muscles, with the exception of one,
            descend from P<subscript>1</subscript>, the other daughter of the zygote (<link linkend="bib12">Sulston et
            al., 1983</link><!--: PMID 6684600-->; <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). A thorough analysis of mosaics is,
            or course, required for rigorous determination of the actual focus of activity of the
            gene, which could be in a cell type other than muscle or neuron. In a recent analysis,
            the anatomical focus of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-122" role="_blank">unc-122</ulink></emphasis> has been traced to muscle (<link linkend="bib8">Loria et
            al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14999070-->). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-71" role="_blank">unc-71</ulink></emphasis> gene, which regulates both
            motor-axon guidance and sex-myoblast migration, is thought to act cell nonautonomously
            for both functions. The gene is required in both neurons and epidermis for proper
            motor-axon guidance (<link linkend="bib5">Huang et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12783787-->).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>The early embryo figure 1</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>A problem for developmental studies is the use of signal-transduction molecules in
            several distinct processes. In some cases, later requirements for such molecules can be
            masked by a critical requirement for the molecules earlier in development. Mosaics can
            in some cases uncover the foci of activity of the gene in these various processes. A
            good example is <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mpk-1" role="_blank">mpk-1</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes an ERK2-type MAP-kinase known
            to affect vulval development (<link linkend="bib7">Lackner et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID 8299936-->; <link linkend="bib15">Wu and Han, 1994</link><!--:
            PMID 8299935-->). For proper vulval development, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mpk-1" role="_blank">mpk-1</ulink></emphasis> is required in
            the vulval precursor cells (<link linkend="bib7">Lackner et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID 8299936-->).
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mpk-1" role="_blank">mpk-1</ulink></emphasis> is also known to affect the exit of germ nuclei from the
            pachytene stage of meiosis, and in this case, the focus is the germ line itself (<link linkend="bib1">Church
            et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7671816-->). The focus of a vital function for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mpk-1" role="_blank">mpk-1</ulink></emphasis>
            has now been shown to be hyp7, the large syncytium that composes most of the skin of the
            animal (<link linkend="bib4">Huang and Stern, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15115754-->).</para>
        <para>Illustrating the power of mosaics for non-developmental studies is
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=bre-5" role="_blank">bre-5</ulink></emphasis>, mutation of which confers resistance to a toxin from
            <emphasis>Bacillus thuringiensis</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib2">Griffitts et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11486087-->). Animals expressing the
            dominant wild-type gene (conferring sensitivity to toxin) in the intestine were
            sensitive to the toxin, whereas 67 mosaics that were resistant to the toxin were always
            homozygous mutant in all of the cells of the intestine (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). The
            bacterial toxin appears to be harmful to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> only if it can
            be ingested, which may require binding to a carbohydrate expressed by the intestinal
            cells. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=bre-5" role="_blank">bre-5</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a <symbol
            role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-1,3-galactosyltransferase, may be required for
            synthesis of the carbohydrate (<link linkend="bib2">Griffitts et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11486087-->).</para>
    <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata entityref="fig2" width="5in" align="center"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
            <phrase>Mosaics for non-developmental studies figure 2</phrase>
        </textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Potential problems</title>
        <para>Potential problems with mosaic analysis have been mentioned in more detail in the
            recent reviews cited above and are only briefly mentioned here. Perhaps the foremost
            problem with mosaic analysis in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is that it requires
            detailed knowledge of the anatomy and cell lineage. Another problem is the potential for
            a cell that fails to inherit a wild-type gene carried by an extrachromosomal element
            nonetheless to receive some wild-type gene product made earlier in a progenitor cell
            that inherited the wild-type gene. Such perdurance of the gene product might weaken the
            expected mutant phenotype even when the cells that constitute the anatomical focus do
            not contain the wild-type gene.</para>
        <para>A potential complication for mosaic analysis derives from the nature of the worm cell
            lineage. This is generally not a problem when investigating a cellular phenotype because
            mosaics can usually be identified in which the cell under investigation is genotypically
            different from cells that are candidates for interaction. The cell lineage can be
            limiting, however, when a focus of action of a gene is diffuse and distributed among
            cells of disparate lineage. The fully mutant phenotype may then only be apparent in
            mosaic animals when the duplication or array is lost by a progenitor of all or nearly
            all of the responsible cells, in which case it may be difficult to pinpoint the
            responsible cell types. A particularly difficult tissue is hyp7, a syncytium formed by
            the fusion of many mononucleate cells that descend from both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> and
            P<subscript>1</subscript>, the daughters of the very first embryonic cleavage (<link linkend="bib12">Sulston
            et al., 1983</link><!--: PMID 6684600-->); therefore, no mosaic animal can contain a single, completely
            mutant hyp7 clone. Mosaic analyses have nonetheless been used to implicate hyp7 as the
            focus of action for several genes. Recent examples are <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-52" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis>
            (<link linkend="bib11">Spike et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12397108-->); <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mpk-1" role="_blank">mpk-1</ulink></emphasis>, which was mentioned
            above (<link linkend="bib4">Huang and Stern, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15115754-->); genes of the TGF<symbol
            role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> pathway (<link linkend="bib14">Wang et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12397107-->); and
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tsp-15" role="_blank">tsp-15</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a tetraspanin that affects epidermal
            morphology (<link linkend="bib9">Moribe et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15454573-->).</para>
        <para>The activity of a gene in a particular cell or tissue may be missed if the gene
            functions redundantly with another gene in that cell or tissue (see <ulink
                url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_geneticenhancers/geneticenhancers.html" role="_blank">Genetic enhancers</ulink> and <ulink url="http://wormbook.org/chapters/www_geneduplication/geneduplication.html"
                role="_blank">Gene duplications and genetic redundancy in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). One may be suspicious if a GFP or other reporter construct indicates
            expression in a particular cell but genetic mosaics do not support an actual function.
            Of course, a reporter construct can give spurious results, if, for instance,
            <emphasis>cis</emphasis>-acting negative regulators are missing from the construct, and
            bona fide expression of a gene in a particular cell does not establish that the gene
            actually functions in that cell. If a redundant gene is identified, mosaic analysis can
            be performed in a background that is mutant for the redundant gene and vice versa. We
            are not aware that such analyses have yet been done in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>,
            but in principle, they should be possible. An intriguing possibility is that two genes
            that redundantly affect a structure or function will have different foci with respect to
            that structure or function.</para>
        <para>Mosaic analysis can also be difficult if the phenotype of a mutation is not completely
            penetrant. The question then arises whether a mosaic lacking the mutant phenotype is
            rescued in the appropriate cell type or is simply an escaper that has coincidental
            mosaicism. Analysis of a leaky mutation therefore requires caution and many mosaics.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>The continued importance of mosaic analysis</title>
        <para>In expression studies, some have no doubt encountered the situation in which a
            reporter construct rescued the mutant phenotype, but expression of the reporter gene could not be reliably detected. In some cases, antibodies against the reporter can provide increased
            sensitivity, but the concern remains that expression of a reporter construct gives
            spurious results, as mentioned above. Mosaic analysis, on the other hand, provides a
            functional test of the gene that does not depend on the ability to detect a reporter.
            Although there are potential limitations, as discussed above, mosaic analysis in many
            cases can provide an unbiased analysis of the activity of a gene, and the analysis can
            provide insight into the function of genes that are not easily amenable to
            immunocytochemical and other studies, because they are expressed at low levels in only a
            few cells.</para>
        <para>A maternal contribution of a gene can be assessed when germ-line clones are generated
            following the loss of an extrachromosomal element in P<subscript>1</subscript>,
            P<subscript>2</subscript>, P<subscript>3</subscript>, or P<subscript>4</subscript>, the
            precursors of the germ cells (<link linkend="bib12">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!--: PMID 6684600-->). A maternal
            contribution is evident when the progeny of a germ-line mosaic have a more severe
            phenotype than progeny that segregate from a mother who is heterozygous for the gene
            (for an example, see <link linkend="bib3">Herman, 1995</link><!--: PMID 8531723-->). A full-fledged mosaic analysis is not
            necessary for an analysis of germ-line clones. They can be seen in the course of
            maintaining lines rescued by an extrachromosomal element. If many individuals are put
            one to a plate, a few of the plates may have received a germ-line mosaic. For a gene
            with a completely penetrant phenotype, all of the progeny will have a mutant phenotype.
            A maternal contribution can also be assessed with RNA interference (RNAi),
            although the potential for cross-interference and for incomplete depletion of gene
            product should be kept in mind.</para>
        <para>Another method for asking about the anatomical focus of the activity of a gene is to
            introduce transgenic copies of the wild-type gene controlled by cell- or tissue-specific
            promoters into otherwise homozygous mutant animals. Rescue of a mutant defect by a
            particular transgene indicates that expression in the indicated cell type can provide
            the needed function. There are, however, some concerns when using this approach. One is
            the fidelity of expression of such transgenes, especially from arrays that contain
            multiple copies of the engineered gene and other heterologous DNA. Also, a bit of gene
            cloning is involved, because a new construct must be made for each promoter under study.
            The formal possibility also remains that rescue by expression (or overexpression) from a
            transgene does not prove that the wild-type gene normally acts in the same cell type or
            tissue. Nevertheless, this approach, especially in combination with mosaic analysis, is
            very powerful, as recent examples demonstrate (<link linkend="bib19">Zhen and Jin, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10517634-->; <link linkend="bib6">Inoue
            and Thomas, 2000</link><!--: PMID 10625546-->; <link linkend="bib18">Zhen et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10839353-->; <link linkend="bib14">Wang et al., 2002</link><!--:
            PMID 12397107-->; <link linkend="bib5">Huang et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12783787-->; <link linkend="bib4">Huang and Stern, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15115754-->;
            <link linkend="bib8">Loria et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14999070-->). Such combined analyses should continue to provide
            some of the most convincing insight into the cell specificity of gene function in
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
		<para/>
		&geneticmosaics_Refs;</sect1>
</article>