<caption>
<formalpara>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Figure 4. Chips for controlled stimulus delivery.</emphasis></title>
<para>A) Oxygen gradient in aerotaxis microfluidic device. Top: top view, bottom: side view. (<link linkend="bib25">Gray et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID: 15220933-->) <emphasis>Reprinted by permission from Macmillan Publishers Ltd: Nature, copyright 2004.</emphasis> B) Microfluidic chip for temporal delivery of oxygen, scale bar of cross-section is 100 &micro;m. (<link linkend="bib57">Zimmer et al., 2009</link><!-- PMID: 19323996-->) <emphasis>Reprinted with permission from Elsevier</emphasis>. C) Olfactory maze for olfactory preference investigation. Maze width is ~ 5 cm. Worms are located between the agar surface and the PDMS maze, and can thus access directly test chambers containing bacterial lawns. (<link linkend="bib56">Zhang et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID: 16281027-->) <emphasis>Reprinted by permission from Macmillan Publishers Ltd: Nature, copyright 2005.</emphasis> D) Designs of microfluidic chips for different types of stimulus delivery to a worm arena. Arena is a chamber 20 mm in length. This area is a pillar-filled microfabricated PDMS chip bonded to a glass slide, which allows worms to crawl in the fluid-filled chamber. Profiles of the stimulus that can be generated with each design are shown to the right. (<link linkend="bib1">Albrecht and Bargmann, 2011</link><!-- PMID: 21666667-->) <emphasis>Reprinted by permission from Macmillan Publishers Ltd: Nature Methods, copyright 2011.</emphasis> E) Olfactory chip for delivery of chemicals to the worm nose. Top shows micrographs of chip with a worm loaded and its nose protruding to the stimulus injection region. Bottom shows the control of stimulus injection by alternating with buffer injection. Scale bars: upper left image, 2 mm; right images, 150 &micro;m. (<link linkend="bib13">Chronis et al., 2007</link><!-- PMID: 17704783-->) <emphasis>Reprinted by permission from Macmillan Publishers Ltd: Nature Methods, copyright 2007.</emphasis></para>
</formalpara>
</caption>
