<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig7 SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig7.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig8 SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig8.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig7legend SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig7leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig8legend SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_fig8leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY nematodeisolation.2_ref SYSTEM 'nematodeisolation.2_ref.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="nematodeisolation.2">
<articleinfo>
<title>Isolation of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and related nematodes<footnote><para>Edited by Ralf Sommer. Last revised  September 20, 2013. Published May 2, 2014. This chapter should be cited as: Barri&#x00E8;re A., F&#x00E9;lix M.-A. Isolation of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and related nematodes (May 2, 2014), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.115.2, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2014 Antoine Barri&#x00E8;re, Marie-Anne F&#x00E9;lix. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para></footnote></title>
<author><othername>Antoine Barri&#x00E8;re<superscript>1</superscript> and Marie-Anne F&#x00E9;lix<superscript>2</superscript><remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:felix@biologie.ens.fr">felix@biologie.ens.fr</ulink></para></footnote></remark></othername>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>1</superscript>Present address: Institut de Biologie du D&#x00E9;veloppement de Marseille-Luminy, CNRS, France</orgname></affiliation>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>2</superscript>Institut de Biologie de l&#x0027;Ecole Normale Sup&#x00E9;rieure, CNRS-Inserm-ENS, Paris, France</orgname></affiliation>
</author></articleinfo>
<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Isolating <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and other nematodes from the wild first requires field sampling (reviewed in <link linkend="sec1">Section 1</link>). The easiest and most efficient way to recover the animals from any substrate is to place the sample onto a standard <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> culture plate (<link linkend="sec2-1">Section 2.1</link>). Alternative methods used by nematologists to recover soil nematodes (<link linkend="sec2-2">Sections 2.2</link>, <link linkend="sec2-3">2.3</link>, and <link linkend="sec2-4">2.4</link>) are in our hands more difficult to implement and only yield a fraction of the individuals in the sample. A tricky step is to recognize your species of interest out of the zoo of nematode species that comes with a typical sample (<link linkend="sec3">Section 3</link>). Culture (<link linkend="sec4">Section 4</link>) and freezing (<link linkend="sec5">Section 5</link>) conditions are then reviewed. Finally, we briefly summarize the organization and timing of an isolation experiment (<link linkend="sec6">Section 6</link>), as well as the available collections (<link linkend="sec7">Section 7</link>). Bear in mind that this chapter is strongly focused towards the isolation of <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> and close relatives.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Field collection</title>
<para>Because of their size, nematodes such as <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> cannot be seen directly during sampling in the field. Collection thus proceeds blindly until return to the laboratory. The type of substrate to collect depends on the target nematode species. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> was first isolated from humus, compost heaps (decaying leaves or vegetal matter) and garden soil, yet mostly in the dauer stage (<link linkend="bib31">Maupas, 1900</link>; <link linkend="bib24">Hodgkin and Doniach, 1997</link><!--PMID: 9136008-->; <link linkend="bib22">Haber et al., 2005</link><!--PMID: 15371529-->; <link linkend="bib5">Barri&#x00E8;re and F&#x00E9;lix, 2005</link><!--PMID: 16005289-->; <link linkend="bib38">Sivasundar and Hey, 2005</link><!--PMID: 16139217-->; <link linkend="bib7">Cutter, 2006</link><!--PMID: 16272415-->). Recently, large proliferating and feeding populations of various <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species including <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have been found in more naturally rotting vegetal matter such as flowers and fruits decaying under their tree, and rotting stems of some herbaceous plants (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>) (<link linkend="bib13">F&#x00E9;lix and Braendle, 2010</link><!--PMID: 21093785-->; <link linkend="bib30">Kiontke et al., 2011</link><!--PMID: 22103856-->; <link linkend="bib17">F&#x00E9;lix and Duveau, 2012</link><!--PMID: 22731941-->; <link linkend="bib18">F&#x00E9;lix et al., 2013</link><!--PMID: 23311925-->). <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species have only been rarely found in soil, leaf litter (including rotting grass) and rotting wood, so unless for reasons of detailed survey designs, such samples are best avoided. Many nematode species including <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are also associated with invertebrates (arthropods, molluscs, etc.), chiefly but not only during their dauer stage (cf. WormBook chapter <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_ecolCaenorhabditis/ecolCaenorhabditis.html">Ecology of Caenorhabditis species</ulink>; <link linkend="bib26">Kiontke, 1997</link>; <link linkend="bib46">Sudhaus et al., 2010</link>). Some <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species appear to have specialized invertebrate carriers (cf. <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_ecolCaenorhabditis/ecolCaenorhabditis.html">Ecology of Caenorhabditis species</ulink>), especially <emphasis>C. japonica</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib29">Kiontke et al., 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib33">Okumura et al., 2013</link><!--PMID: 23077159-->), <emphasis>C. drosophilae</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib26">Kiontke, 1997</link>) and perhaps <emphasis>C. angaria</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib46">Sudhaus et al., 2010</link>). Note that the list of possible substrates from which <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species can be isolated (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>) will certainly grow.</para>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1. Occurrence of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species in different substrates.</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<thead>
<row valign="bottom" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Substrates where <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> are often found</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Substrates where <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> have rarely been found</emphasis></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="bottom" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">
<para>rotting fruits</para>
<para>rotting flowers</para>
<para>rotting stems (especially thick stems of biannual species and banana pseudostems)</para>
<para>compost</para>
<para>invertebrate carriers (slugs, snails, isopods for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>, others for other <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species)</para>
</entry>
<entry align="left">
<para>soil</para>
<para>rotting leaves</para>
<para>rotting wood</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>In sum, to collect <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species, generally aim for VERY rotten vegetal substrates such as fruits, large flowers, stems or compost heaps. Collect either in plastic zip bags (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1A</link>) or in plastic tubes, for a volume of 1-100 ml per sample (typically 20 ml). The only important recommendation is to keep the samples aerated, i.e., unscrew slightly the cap of tubes, or do not close the bags too well. You can keep them at least 2-3 weeks (depending on the goal of your sampling, see <link linkend="sec6">Section 6</link>). Avoid overheating, and overcooling below 10&#x00B0;C, unless it is the natural temperature. It is best if the samples are quite humid but not flooded in the field, nor in the bag&#x2014;excess liquid upon long-term conservation in a bag can be soaked up by adding a piece of paper towel (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson3263#012--10">Christian Braendle</ulink>, personal communication).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>An alternative strategy is to use a bait to attract the nematodes, such as fruit pieces left to rot for <emphasis>Caenorhabditis.</emphasis> Worms can either move directly into the bait, or be brought through phoretic association with larger invertebrates. Fruit pieces are placed on, or in close proximity to, a substrate of interest, and collected 12 to 48 hours later. It might be necessary to protect the bait from mammals and birds with a metallic mesh. The bait is then transferred to an agar plate, and nematodes are recovered as described below.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Isolation</title>
<sect2 id="sec2-1">
<title>Agar culture plate method (preferred)</title>
<para>The easiest way to recover nematodes from a sample is simply to place the sample around the bacterial lawn of a standard <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> culture dish (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html">Maintenance of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html#d0e161">Section 3</ulink>). Bacteria-feeding nematodes such as <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are attracted and crawl out of the sample towards the bacterial lawn (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). For fast-moving species like <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, this occurs within minutes to hours. If you want to avoid contamination by <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis>, a possibility is to attract the worms out of the sample using the attractant diacetyl.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>- Spread about 1-10 grams of sample around the <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP50;class=Strain" role="_blank">OP50</ulink> lawn of a standard NGM Petri dish (55 mm or 90 mm diameter depending on the volume of sample), and moisten with about 1 ml M9 solution (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html">Maintenance of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html#d0e671">Section 6</ulink>, Protocol 6) or water.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>- Pick to a new plate individual nematodes that have crawled out. In obligate male-female species, worms of both sexes, or a mated female, are required. Animals are ideally picked within a few hours after the sample has been placed on the plate. Later on, growing bacteria and fungi species that have been introduced with the sample may prevent worms from accessing the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP50;class=Strain" role="_blank">OP50</ulink> lawn (to avoid such growth, the sample can be moistened with 0.01% thimerosal in M9).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Using this agar plate method, all developmental stages can be recovered in a more or less quantitative manner&#x2014;except for the embryonic stages, which can only be retrieved after hatching. The number of individuals in the original sample can thus be estimated (<link linkend="bib5">Barri&#x00E8;re and F&#x00E9;lix, 2005</link>)<!--PMID: 16005289-->. <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> <emphasis>elegans</emphasis> will eventually form dauers that present a characteristic waving behavior: they &#x2018;stand&#x2019; on their tail on any substrate with a narrow tip (the substrate or the molds that grow out of it) and move their body, putatively as a way to make contact with and be carried away by an invertebrate (<link linkend="bib48">V&#x00F6;lk, 1950</link>; <link linkend="bib41">Sudhaus, 1976</link>) and sometimes form large masses of up to thousands of individuals (<link linkend="bib17">F&#x00E9;lix and Duveau, 2012</link>)<!--PMID: 22731941-->. One can <emphasis>a posteriori</emphasis> check that every <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> individual has been picked by the absence of waving dauer larvae after 6-10 days. Note that dauer larvae of other genera, such as <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis>, also adopt this behavior.</para>
<para>To recover nematodes from larger invertebrates (molluscs, arthropods, etc.), place the putative carrier onto an NGM agar plate, either alive (if you wish to test whether nematodes may disembark), naturally dead, or after sacrificing it. Wait for the nematodes to move to the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP50;class=Strain" role="_blank">OP50</ulink> lawn or collect them directly by dissection of the decaying invertebrate host.</para>
<para>If you target slow-growing species, a variant protocol is to place the sample onto an agar plate without nutrients (plain agar in water) and to add a chunk of NGM medium seeded with <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis>. Nematodes that like a lot of bacteria will crawl to the NGM. Species that are not so fond of extremely high bacterial density will thrive at a little distance from this chunk. This way, slowly developing species can still be isolated a little later whereas they die or get overrun by other species or fungi on NGM plates (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson2076#012--10">Karin Kiontke</ulink>, personal communication).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-2">
<title>Baermann funnel</title>
<para>This is the classical method to recover a variety of nematode species, and may be particularly useful to isolate nematodes that are not attracted to <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis>, or to isolate nematodes without contamination by <emphasis>E. coli.</emphasis> Many modifications and improvements are possible, and here we describe only a single basic design.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>- Fit a rubber tube onto the stem of a funnel (diameter ca. 50 mm). Close the tube with a clamp (a simple paperclip can be used instead) and fill the rubber tubing with M9 solution up to the neck of the funnel (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>- Line the funnel cone with a piece of sieve (standard cleaning tissue, muslin, mosquito mesh&hellip;), then fill with material and fold to enclose the sample. Add M9 solution or water until the sample is wet but not fully submerged.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>- Active nematodes crawl through the sieve and will then sediment at the end of the tubing. Recover them by opening the clamp (from a few hours to several days later).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>A problem with the Baermann funnel technique, especially when isolating worms from bacteria-rich samples, is that the poor oxygenation of the sample or rapid growth of parasitic fungi will result in high nematode mortality.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-3">
<title>Tray extraction (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson2097#012--10http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson2097">Paul De Ley</ulink>, personal communication)</title>
<para>As with the Baermann funnel, this method is not quantitatively reliable because it selects against slow and non-moving nematodes, but it is less prone to oxygen depletion and very good at yielding large numbers of active worms from larger samples. The three components required are: (1) a large plastic tray, (2) a fitting flat mesh or strainer, and (3) sheets of strong kitchen towel paper that are larger than the mesh. The larger the tray, the more material can be extracted in one run. Do not use trays or mesh with bare metal surfaces, as these may release toxic ions.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>- Place the mesh in the tray, cover its bottom and sides with one or two layers of paper, then spread a thin, uniform layer of your sample over the paper.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>- Gently pour clean water into the tray and then place the mesh in the tray, making sure the sample is wet but not submerged.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>- Let the tray stand for 2-12 hours, covered partly or completely to minimize evaporation. During this time, actively moving nematodes will crawl down through the paper and collect on the bottom of the tray. If the sample is very water-absorbent then check periodically underneath to ensure its soaking up of water does not leave the tray partly dry.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>- After the desired time, remove the mesh with sample and pour the water out of the tray through a fine sieve (pore size 25 &#x03BC;m or less), then wash the nematodes off the fine sieve into a small beaker with about 20-30 ml water. If you do not have a fine sieve, pour the tray water into a sufficiently large beaker and allow the nematodes to settle for about 30 min. Pour off most of the supernatant, transfer the remainder to a smaller beaker, and repeat until you have 20-30 ml of concentrated nematode suspension left.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-4">
<title>Centrifugal flotation</title>
<para>Terrestrial nematodes have a specific gravity of 1.08 and can be recovered by flotation on a solution with a specific gravity of 1.15 (<link linkend="bib25">Hooper, 1986</link>). This method is best used with soil samples, because decaying vegetal matter yields too much detritus.</para>
<para>Several solutions can be used:</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Sucrose</emphasis> &#x2013; is inexpensive, but sticky and has a strong osmotic effect that harms the worms (1.71 mol/L for a density of 1.15).</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">MgSO<subscript>4</subscript></emphasis> &#x2013; less sticky than sucrose, but also has a strong osmotic effect (1.38 mol/L)</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Ludox</emphasis> &#x2013; colloidal silica: expensive, but weak osmotic effect; samples can therefore be extracted several times, in contrast to extraction with the other solutions. Ludox comes in two forms: Ludox HS40, toxic, that may be used for fixed samples, and Ludox AS, non-toxic, that is best used to recover live material. A 50% solution in water has a specific gravity of 1.15.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>- If your sample contains a lot of debris, rinse it first over a 1 mm mesh to remove the bulkiest fragments (this will however remove some of the nematodes).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>- Soak the sample in water and centrifuge at 1,800 g to obtain a compact pellet, and eliminate the supernatant.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>- Resuspend the pellet in 20 ml of the chosen solution of density 1.15 and centrifuge at 1,800 g for 1 min. Add 2 to 5 ml of water or M9 buffer on top and centrifuge again for 5-15 min. Nematodes will accumulate at the interface between the two solutions.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>- Pipet the worms at the interface (some can be seen with the naked eye) using a cut 1 ml micropipette tip.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>- Rinse them in M9, centrifuge, and pipet the pellet onto a standard NGM culture plate.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>More detailed information on different isolation methods can be found in <link linkend="bib25">Hooper (1986)</link> or <link linkend="bib8">De Ley and Mundo-Ocampo (2004)</link>.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Identifying <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> and other species</title>
<para>A good way to identify the genus and possibly the species is to compare observations, mostly of buccal parts and sexual organs, with published drawings or already identified cultures. For a detailed guide of soil nematodes with plenty of drawings, see <link linkend="bib1">Andr&#x00E1;ssy (1983</link>, or <link linkend="bib2">1984</link>, in German); for the Rhabditidae, see the recent key in <link linkend="bib42">Sudhaus (2011)</link>. For the different <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species, see <link linkend="bib44">Sudhaus and Kiontke (1996)</link> and <link linkend="bib30">Kiontke et al. (2011)</link><!--PMID: 22103856-->. Be aware that (1) some genera may be redefined due to new knowledge, especially molecular sequences (<link linkend="bib34">Scholze and Sudhaus, 2011</link>); and (2) nematode diversity is huge and most species are still undescribed.</para>
<para>The increasingly used alternative to morphological identification of nematodes is based on molecular sequence tags available in databases, mostly 18S, 28S and ITS rDNA sequences. 18S rDNA is useful at a broad taxonomic level, while ITS sequences are generally useful for distinguishing conspecific strains or closely related species (<link linkend="bib30">Kiontke et al., 2011</link>)<!--PMID: 22103856-->.</para>
<para>Finally, in the last step, the species identity can be determined or confirmed using crosses with cultures of known species of the genus. Modes of reproduction of different nematode species come in many flavors: male-female reproduction (as in <emphasis>C. remanei</emphasis>), hermaphrodite selfing with facultative male outcrossing (as in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>), parthenogenesis (as in some <emphasis>Diploscapter</emphasis>, <emphasis>Panagrolaimus,</emphasis> <emphasis>Cephalobus</emphasis>, or <emphasis>Rhabditophanes</emphasis> spp.), partial pseudogamy (as in some <emphasis>Mesorhabditis</emphasis> spp.), and complex combinations with two possible reproductive modes&#x2014;hermaphrodite selfing and male-female crosses, such as in the species related to SB347 et al. (in a yet undescribed genus) (<link linkend="bib12">F&#x00E9;lix, 2004</link><!--PMID: 14730447-->; <link linkend="bib37">Shakes et al., 2011</link><!--PMID: 21245838-->). In all cases but parthenogenesis, crossing tests can be performed.</para>
<para>We mostly focus below on how to tell <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> from other genera, using morphology (<link linkend="sec3-1">Section 3.1</link>), molecular sequences (<link linkend="sec3-2">Section 3.2</link>), and crosses with known species (<link linkend="sec3-3">Section 3.3</link>).</para>
<sect2 id="sec3-1">
<title>Morphology</title>
<para>The nematodes can be identified by morphological criteria either as they come out of the substrate, or perhaps more easily by observation of their progeny after they were brought into pure culture. First, most nematodes from rotting plant samples belong to one of four groups/families that can be distinguished by mouth morphology (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>): Rhabditidae (including <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>, <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis>, <emphasis>Mesorhabditis</emphasis>, etc.), diplogastrids (<emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis>), Panagrolaimidae (<emphasis>Panagrellus</emphasis>, <emphasis>Panagrolaimus</emphasis>), and Cephalobidae (<emphasis>Cephalobus</emphasis>, generally slower growing). Note that diplogastrids are phylogenetically nested within family Rhabditidae (<link linkend="bib27">Kiontke et al., 2007</link>)<!--PMID: 18024125-->. See <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_quicktourdiversity/quicktourdiversity.html">A quick tour of nematode diversity ahd the backbone of nematode phylogeny</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_phylogrhabditids/phylorhab.html">The phylogenetic relationships of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and other rhabditids</ulink> for their phylogenetic relationships.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<para>We first review in <link linkend="sec3-1-1">Section 3.1.1</link> characteristic traits of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> to look for, some but not all of which are shared with other genera. For those interested, some key features of nematodes that cohabit with <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> are presented: in <link linkend="sec3-1-2">Section 3.1.2</link> for nematodes outside the rhabditids, in <link linkend="sec3-1-3">Section 3.1.3</link> for some other rhabditid genera outside <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>. At the species level, morphological criteria distinguishing different <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species are then presented in <link linkend="sec3-1-4">Section 3.1.4</link>.</para>
<sect3 id="sec3-1-1">
<title>A few traits to look for when searching for <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis></title>
<para>Here are some tips to distinguish <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> from other genera. Some traits are most easily scored on populations, possibly cleaned by bleaching (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html">Maintenance of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html#d0e671">Section 6</ulink>), rather than on single individuals coming out of the sample, which may look very different because of various life adventures including pathogens. For a first triage of nematodes coming out from the sample under the dissecting microscope, look for the characters in bold.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> hermaphrodites/females generally move relatively fast and elegantly, have a <emphasis role="bold">long and pointy tail</emphasis>, which folds back on itself when the worm is moving backwards.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Most characteristically, their <emphasis role="bold">gut has a homogeneous brown color</emphasis> in the dissecting microscope under transmitted illumination, except for <emphasis role="bold">few large cell nuclei</emphasis>, which appear white in this brown background (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>). This intestinal morphological feature allows you to rule out most bacteriovorous nematodes, which have a grey or blackish intestinal color, and/or more heterogeneous coloration with a large number of small or barely visible cell nuclei (Figures <link linkend="figure4">4</link>, <link linkend="figure5">5</link>, and <link linkend="figure6">6</link>).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <emphasis role="bold">vulva is central</emphasis>, i.e., located towards the middle of the animal along the antero-posterior axis.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Embryos are oval</emphasis>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The <emphasis role="bold">middle and basal pharyngeal bulbs</emphasis> (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>) can both be seen with proper illumination and good magnification in the dissecting microscope. The basal bulb includes a <emphasis role="bold">grinder</emphasis>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>When the worms are mounted and observed under a compound microscope, look for the rhabditid mouth morphology (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>), the two-armed (didelphic) gonad in hermaphrodites or females and the wide cytoplasmic rachis (cf. <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link> in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transformationmicroinjection/transformationmicroinjection.html">Transformation and microinjection</ulink>) in the center of the dorsal gonad arms. Only <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> sp. 1 has a single fertile arm, the anterior one (<link linkend="bib14">F&#x00E9;lix and Sternberg, 1996</link>)<!--PMID: 8681794-->.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>A characteristic feature of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> (with few exceptions) is a wide ray 6 in the male tail (see <ulink url="http://www.wormatlas.org/male/rays/Rayframeset.html">Wormatlas, Ray Composition and Structure</ulink>) (<link linkend="bib44">Sudhaus and Kiontke, 1996</link>).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 4</phrase>
</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-1-2">
<title>Vignettes of non-rhabditid nematodes co-habiting with <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis></title>
<para><link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link> presents nematodes outside rhabditids that are often encountered in the same sample types as <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>, mostly of the Panagrolaimidae and &#x201C;Diplogastridae&#x201D; families, but not solely.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 5</phrase>
</textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The Panagrolaimidae family includes a number of genera, at least three of which are readily found in rotting fruit or stem samples. Particularly frequent and specific to rotting fruits (but not stems) are <emphasis>Panagrellus</emphasis> spp. These large worms share with <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> a brownish intestinal color and finely tapering tail under the dissecting microscope, yet (1) their vulva is quite posterior, (2) their gonad includes a single anterior ovary arm and a large post-vulval sac on the posterior side of the vulva, (3) their uterus contains all embryonic stages up to hatching as they lay their progeny as small L1 larvae, and (4) the pharynx lacks a median bulb (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>) (<link linkend="bib40">Sternberg and Horvitz, 1981</link>)<!--PMID: 7286441-->. Related to them are <emphasis>Panagrolaimus</emphasis> spp., found in a variety of substrates including dry ones. Like <emphasis>Panagrellus</emphasis> spp., <emphasis>Panagrolaimus</emphasis> spp. display a single ovary arm, yet are thinner and darker; their vulva is located almost in the middle of the animal; and they usually do not retain more than one or two embryos in their uterus and lay early-stage embryos. Finally, members of the <emphasis>Rhabditophanes</emphasis> genus, commonly found in cool meteorological conditions, are recognizable by a black intestine, roundish embryos, and fast growth (2-3 days) at 15-20&#x00B0;C.</para>
<para>Most Diplogastridae found together with <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> are first recognizable by their scary teeth (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). Among them, <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis> spp. can be recognized by strong lines all over the adult cuticle and a generally dumpyish body morphology (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>). Also, diplogastrid species lack the grinder in the terminal pharynx bulb.</para>
<para>Two groups of slow-growing nematodes are generally only spotted several days after the samples have been placed on plates, if nothing else bloomed: (1) cephalobs are found in many environments including dry ones, and are generally below 1 mm in length; and (2) <emphasis>Bunonema</emphasis> nematodes are particularly small (0.3-0.4 mm; <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>), and easily recognizable under the compound microscope by the left-right asymmetry of their cuticular pattern and their peculiar behavior with water films (they do not wet well and float).</para>
<para>Fungi eaters called aphelenchids are found in fungi-rich samples, are not attracted to the <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> lawn and have a pale intestine (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>). In addition, one can sometimes find plant parasitic nematodes, which are very long nematodes with a stylet in the mouth that helps them allows them to puncture plant cells and ingest their contents.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-1-3">
<title>Vignettes of other rhabditid genera co-habiting with <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis></title>
<para>In the Rhabditidae, a variety of genera may be found in the same samples as <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>. Unlike <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>, most of them show a grey or black intestinal color (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>). To distinguish different rhabditid genera, we like to use vulval precursor cell lineages as observed under Nomarski optics in the early L4 stage (<link linkend="bib27">Kiontke et al., 2007</link>)<!--PMID: 18024125-->, yet admit that this requires specialized training. Some species can instead be distinguished by a short or blunt female tail (not shown) or a posterior vulva (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>) (<emphasis>Mesorhabditis</emphasis>, <emphasis>Teratorhabditis</emphasis>, <emphasis>Cruznema</emphasis>). The group of species related to SB347 (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>) is common in rotting fruits and stems and may display three sexes in culture (<link linkend="bib12">F&#x00E9;lix, 2004</link><!--PMID: 14730447-->; <link linkend="bib37">Shakes et al., 2011</link><!--PMID: 21245838-->), as well as tube waving behavior of the dauers, which it shares with close relatives such as <emphasis>Rhabditella</emphasis> spp.: the dauer remains inside the L2d cuticle, can exit at the front end and wave perpendicularly, yet also may retract in its shelter tube.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig6" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 6</phrase>
</textobject> &fig6legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Most common in terrestrial habitats are <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> spp. The <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> genus is divided into two clear clades: (1) the <emphasis>Dolichura</emphasis> clade (to which <emphasis>O. tipulae</emphasis> belongs), with quite small animals; and (2) the <emphasis>Insectivora</emphasis> clade with animals that grow large during adulthood (2-3 mm) and often stop laying embryos in late life, resulting in bagging (<link linkend="bib27">Kiontke et al., 2007</link>)<!--PMID: 18024125-->. <emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_genomesOtipulae/genomesOtipulae.html"><emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis></ulink>) and close relatives are very common and are selfers like <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. They should be easily distinguished from <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> by their smaller size, darker and more spotted intestinal color, smaller intestinal nuclei, lack of middle pharyngeal bulb, and elongated rectum (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>).</para>
<para>Finally, the sister group to <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> is composed of small, slow-growing animals such as <emphasis>Diploscapter</emphasis> and <emphasis>Protorhabditis</emphasis> spp., which often move slowly through the agar of the culture plate, leaving brownish contorted trails. <emphasis>Protorhabditis</emphasis> and <emphasis>Prodontorhabditis</emphasis> species show a jerking backwards movement when disturbed (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson2076#012--10">Karin Kiontke</ulink>, personal communication)<emphasis>. Diploscapter</emphasis> is unusual in having refringent labial hooks that are visible with a good dissection microscope (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson2097#012--10">Paul De Ley</ulink>, personal communication).</para>
<para><emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> animals in the dauer stage are difficult to recognize by the above criteria&#x2014;so let the culture bloom from the dauer(s). However, if you see waving dauers, singly or in large masses (<link linkend="bib17">F&#x00E9;lix and Duveau, 2012</link>)<!--PMID: 22731941-->, they may be <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>; note that many other species also adopt this behavior.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-1-4">
<title>Morphological characteristics of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species</title>
<para><emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> spp. overall look similar to each other in the dissecting microscope (see <link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link> for three examples). Indeed, most criteria mentioned below (except the spiral mating position) require mounting and observing the animals in the compound microscope, preferrably using Nomarski optics. We use these traits to narrow down of possibilities within <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> to prioritize the crosses to known species. If these morphological criteria appear difficult to you, use molecular tags (<link linkend="sec3-2">Section 3.2</link>).</para>
<para>The <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> genus includes two large supergroups, <emphasis>Elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>Drosophilae</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib30">Kiontke et al., 2011</link>)<!--PMID: 22103856-->, and a few basally branching species such as <emphasis>C. plicata</emphasis> and <emphasis>C.</emphasis> sp. 1. The latter is a small species with a single fertile ovary arm (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>) (<link linkend="bib14">F&#x00E9;lix and Sternberg, 1996</link>)<!--PMID: 8681794-->. Defining derived morphological criteria that are diagnostic for the <emphasis>Elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>Drosophilae</emphasis> super-groups is presently difficult. Indeed, when mapped onto the present molecular phylogeny, most morphological characters that vary in the genus show patterns of convergence and reversion (<link linkend="bib30">Kiontke et al., 2011</link>)<!--PMID: 22103856-->. A good character seems to be the closer position of rays 2 and 3, which appears derived in the branch leading to the <emphasis>Elegans</emphasis> super-group (<link linkend="bib30">Kiontke et al., 2011</link>)<!--PMID: 22103856-->. In contrast, finding a character such as a dorsal ray 4 (instead of a dorsal ray 5), the absence of a hook, a fan that is open on the anterior side, a short spiculum, or a spiral mating position so far excludes the possibility that the species is in the <emphasis>Elegans</emphasis> super-group and assigns them to a basal branch or to the <emphasis>Drosophilae</emphasis> super-group.</para>
<para>The <emphasis>Drosophilae</emphasis> super-group indeed harbors most behavioral and morphological diversity. A subclade including <emphasis>C. angaria</emphasis> and <emphasis>C.</emphasis> sp. 8 displays spiral mating (as panagrolaims and diplogastrids may also do; see <emphasis>Panagrellus</emphasis> in <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>), whereas all other <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> mate in a parallel orientation as <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> does (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_malematingbehavior/malematingbehavior.html">Male mating behavior</ulink>). Refer to Figures 6 and 5 in <link linkend="bib30">Kiontke et al. (2011)</link><!--PMID: 22103856--> for the combination of male tail morphological traits (hook and fan morphology, respective positions of rays) of different species, up to <emphasis>C.</emphasis> sp. 20; or to <ulink url="http://128.122.60.136/fmi/iwp/cgi?-db=RhabditinaDB&amp;-loadframes">http://128.122.60.136/fmi/iwp/cgi?-db=RhabditinaDB&#x0026;-loadframes</ulink> which will be updated on a regular basis with the newest species. These traits may narrow down possibilities for species identity, which is useful to prioritize crosses with known species (<link linkend="sec3-3">Section 3.3</link>). However, be prepared and enjoy the fact that puzzling combinations of characters or new traits are still being found in the newest <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species (Marie-Anne F&#x00E9;lix, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson2076#012--10">Karin Kiontke</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson22463#012--10">Lise Fr&#x00E9;zal</ulink>, unpublished data).</para>
<para>In the <emphasis>Elegans</emphasis> super-group, species are very similar morphologically and in some cases cannot be distinguished from each other by specialists (e.g., <link linkend="bib45">Sudhaus and Kiontke, 2007</link>). Here the mode of reproduction may provide a useful indication. So far, only three <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species, all of the <emphasis>Elegans</emphasis> super-group, are selfing hermaphrodites, namely <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <emphasis>briggsae,</emphasis> and <emphasis>tropicalis</emphasis>, while all other <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species known so far reproduce through mating of males and females. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> co-occur in the world regions we sample most (France). After having performed numerous diagnostic PCRs (<link linkend="sec3-2">Section 3.2</link>) and crosses (<link linkend="sec3-3">Section 3.3</link>), we learnt to distinguish them by several morphological and behavioral features. Specifically, <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> animals are thinner and paler, lay eggs at an earlier stage and do not clump as <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> do (<link linkend="figure7">Figure 7</link>). These features are only clear for a pure strain culture descended from one wild-caught animal and cleaned from microbial contaminants other than <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> OP50.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure7" xreflabel="Figure 7">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig7" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 7</phrase>
</textobject> &fig7legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Unless one can guess which crosses to prioritize due to biogeographical species distribution (<link linkend="bib30">Kiontke et al., 2011</link><!--PMID: 22103856-->; <link linkend="bib30">F&#x00E9;lix and Duveau, 2012</link><!--PMID: 22731941-->), going through a molecular sequencing tag (<link linkend="sec3-2">Section 3.2</link>) is now advisable for species of the <emphasis>Elegans</emphasis> super-group.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-2">
<title>Molecular identification</title>
<para>Different gene fragments are preferrably used for different taxonomic levels.</para>
<sect3 id="sec3-2-1">
<title>Placement within nematodes: 18S rDNA sequence</title>
<para>Sequencing of the 18S ribosomal RNA (small subunit) gene with nematode-specific primers (<link linkend="bib19">Floyd et al., 2002</link><!--PMID: 11972769-->; <link linkend="bib22">Haber et al., 2005</link><!--PMID: 15371529-->) is a good way to identify the group to which a nematode belongs by BLASTing it against sequence databases. Possible primers are:</para>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>SSU18A (5&#x2019;-AAAGATTAAGCCATGCATG)</para>
<para>and SSU26R (5&#x2019;-CATTCTTGGCAAATGCTTTCG),</para>
<para>which amplify a 1 kb fragment of 18S rDNA in rhabditid nematodes (<link linkend="bib19">Floyd et al., 2002</link>)<!--PMID: 11972769-->, or</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>RHAB1350F (5&#x2019;-TACAATGGAAGGCAGCAGGC)</para>
<para>and RHAB1868R (5&#x2019;-CCTCTGACTTTCGTTCTTGATTAA),</para>
<para>which amplify a fragment of about 500 bp (<link linkend="bib22">Haber et al., 2005</link>)<!--PMID: 15371529-->, or</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>G18S4a:	GCTCAAGTAAAAGATTAAGCCATGC (F)</para>
<para>and DF18S-8:	GTTTACGGTCAGAACTASGGCGG (R),</para>
<para>which amplify a fragment of around 1 kb (<link linkend="bib28">Kiontke et al., 2004</link>)<!--PMID: 15184656--> in Rhabditidae, Diplogastridae, Panagrolaimidae, and Cephalobidae. Sequence with either PCR primer or with KK18S-8S: CGGTATCTAATCGCCTTCG (R).</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-2-2">
<title>Placement within <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>: ITS2 sequence of rDNA</title>
<para>At a smaller phylogenetic scale, the ITS2 region (Internally Transcribed Spacer) between the 5.8S and 28S rDNA genes provides a convenient species tag within <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib30">Kiontke et al., 2011</link>)<!--PMID: 22103856-->. Possible primers are:</para>
<para>5.8S-1 (5&#x2019;-CTGCGTTACTTACCACGAATTGCARAC)</para>
<para>and KK28S-4 (5&#x2019;-GCGGTATTTGCTACTACCAYYAMGATCTGC),</para>
<para>which amplify a fragment of ca. 2 kb. Sequence the fragment using the forward PCR primer and the sequencing primer KK-28S-22 (5-CACTTTCAAGCAACCCGAC).</para>
<para>Overall, this fragment is a useful species tag because of the significant divergence among known species (20 nucleotides or many more) and the low polymorphism within a given species (one or two single-nucleotide polymorphisms). The fact that some species (such as <emphasis>C.</emphasis> sp. 8) display more than a couple of nucleotide polymorphisms precludes a clear-cut new species prediction with this marker (<link linkend="bib30">Kiontke et al., 2011</link>)<!--PMID: 22103856-->. However, once a <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> culture is identified, the ITS2 sequence is a great test to narrow down possible species or species group.</para>
<para>A convenient method (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson22463#012--10">Lise Fr&#x00E9;zal</ulink>, personal communication) to compare a new sequence to the known ones makes use of the &#x201C;Align two or more sequences&#x201D; of NCBI Blast. First, retrieve known <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> ITS2 sequences from the additional file S6 of <link linkend="bib30">Kiontke et al. (2011</link>)<!--PMID: 22103856--> or at <ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/?term=barcodes+for+Caenorhabditis+AND+spacer">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/?term=barcodes+for+Caenorhabditis+AND+ITS2</ulink>. Prepare a file with these ITS2 sequences in fasta format. Blast your new sequence using the &#x201C;Align two or more sequences&#x201D; option of <ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">NCBI</ulink>/ <ulink url="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi?CMD=Web&amp;PAGE_TYPE=BlastHome">BLAST</ulink>/ <emphasis role="bold">blastn</emphasis>. You can thus find the closest species. You can also visualize the results using the distance tree, but be aware that a tree solely based on ITS2 is poorly supported (<link linkend="bib30">Kiontke et al., 2011</link>)<!--PMID: 22103856-->. The results indicate whether the ITS2 is identical or close to a known species.</para>
<para>An alternative method is to use the Rhabditina DB database by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson1491#012--10">Walter Sudhaus</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson178#012--10">David Fitch</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson2076#012--10">Karin Kiontke</ulink> at <ulink url="http://128.122.60.136/fmi/iwp/cgi?-db=RhabditinaDB&amp;-loadframes">http://128.122.60.136/fmi/iwp/cgi?-db=RhabditinaDB&#x0026;-loadframes</ulink> where you can BLAST against known rDNA sequences (even unpublished ones) using &#x201C;BLAST search&#x201D; in the menu on the left.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-2-3">
<title>Species-specific oligonucleotides: e.g., <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> versus <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis></title>
<para>In order to discriminate between <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> (or a few locally-known species), one can perform a PCR using species-specific oligonucleotides (<link linkend="bib5">Barri&#x00E8;re and F&#x00E9;lix, 2005</link>)<!--PMID: 16005289-->. For example, the following species-specific PCR primers in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001609;class=Gene" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> gene amplify different fragment sizes in the two target species. PCR can be performed using all four primers in the same reaction (annealing T&#x00B0; of 60&#x00B0;C).</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>: CCGCTTGGATTCTATGGATTG and CTCTCCTTGCTCCGGGATTG, product: 208 bp in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>; none in <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>: GAACCTGCGAGTGCATGTAC and CCGTCTGCAAACGAACGGGC, product: 302 bp in <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>; none <emphasis>in C. elegans</emphasis>.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>We have also successfully used other primer pairs that were available in the lab and generally only matched one species.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-2-4">
<title>Other genera</title>
<para>Different <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> species of the <emphasis>Oscheius tipulae</emphasis> group can be distinguished using a PCR-RFLP test (<link linkend="bib16">F&#x00E9;lix et al., 2001</link>)<!--PMID: 19266004-->.</para>
<para>Different <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis> species have been distinguished by sequencing of 18S RNA (<link linkend="bib23">Herrmann et al., 2006</link>)<!--PMID: 16616467-->.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-3">
<title>Crosses</title>
<para>The biological species is defined and bounded by the ability to give fertile progeny in a cross. With the increasing number of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species (>30 in culture), identifying a species solely based on crosses becomes cumbersome if no educated guess can be made. However, once the possibilities have been narrowed down using morphology and/or ITS sequence data, crosses are the methods of choice to formally identify a species or prove the discovery of a new species within a sub-group of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib15">F&#x00E9;lix et al., 2014</link>). Before starting the test crosses, make sure your culture contains a single species by deriving it from a single individual or male-female pair.</para>
<para>Species identity can be tested by crossing several virgin (L4 stage) females or hermaphrodites of the new culture with males of identified laboratory strains, and <emphasis>vice versa</emphasis>. See <link linkend="sec7">Section 7</link> for collections from which you can obtain various species; most are at the <ulink url="http://www.cbs.umn.edu/research/resources/cgc">Caenorhabditis Genetics Center</ulink> (CGC), except for the last discovered species. About 5 animals of each sex are placed onto a culture plate and the culture observed over several days. In female-male species, the presence of fertile progeny of both sexes indicates that the new wild isolate is of the same species as the tester strain. In hermaphrodite-male species, successful crosses can be scored by the occurrence of a high proportion of male progeny (<link linkend="bib32">Nigon and Dougherty, 1949</link>)<!--PMID: 15404785-->. A refined method is to use males of laboratory strains that express dominant markers (e.g., GFP), currently available for only a few species including the three selfers. In this case, cross-progeny are identified by the presence of the marker in the F1 generation and the cross-progeny may be left to reproduce to test for its fertility. Crosses between some closely related species (<link linkend="bib3">Baird, 2002</link><!--PMID: 12136036-->; <link linkend="bib45">Sudhaus and Kiontke, 2007</link>; <link linkend="bib30">Kiontke et al., 2011</link>) may yield a few (sterile) larval and adult F1 progeny, but most of the eggs that are laid in these crosses never hatch.</para>
<para>As the phylogenetic density of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species increases, the biological species tests are no longer clearcut: a whole continuum of cross-sterility is found. Clear instances of different species are: absence of embryonic progeny, absence of larval progeny, sterile F1 adults (often only females, Haldane&#x0027;s rule), or F1 adults that are fully sterile with sibs or either parent (for example <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> x <emphasis>C.</emphasis> <emphasis>nigoni</emphasis>; <link linkend="bib49">Woodruff et al., 2010</link><!--PMID: 20823339-->). However, in some cases, the sterility may be partial, and the species boundary becomes fuzzy, with a continuum of partial sterility phenomena. For example, crosses between some pairs of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> isolates (e.g., N2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CB4856;class=Strain" role="_blank">CB4856</ulink>) present 25% dead F2 progeny, yet the causal locus for this phenomenon still recombines with the rest of the genomic diversity (<link linkend="bib35">Seidel et al., 2008</link>)<!--PMID: 18187622-->, so here a single species should be considered. Other examples of outbreeding depression are found in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib10">Dolgin et al., 2007</link>)<!--PMID: 17542844-->, <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib4">Baird and Stonisefer, 2012</link>)<!--PMID: 24058847-->, and <emphasis>C.</emphasis> <emphasis>tropicalis</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib20">Gimond et al., 2013</link>)<!--PMID: 24151995-->. At the other end of the fuzzy zone, the cross of <emphasis>C. remanei</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. latens</emphasis> yields hybrid F1 progeny that give very few descendants when crossed to each other (<link linkend="bib9">Dey et al., 2012</link>)<!--PMID: 22649079-->. Note that although problematic for systematics, such situations are treasures for studying the first steps of speciation.</para>
<para>No progeny of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> with any other species has been reported so far. Finding a sister species to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<ulink url="http://forums.wormbase.org/index.php?topic=308.0">http://forums.wormbase.org/index.php?topic=308.0</ulink>; <link linkend="bib10">Dolgin, 2007</link><!--PMID: 17542844-->), whether partially hybridizing with it or not, is still an unattained grail. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is indeed presently alone on a phylogenetic branch that goes back to the divergence with the <emphasis>C. briggsae / C. remanei /C. brenneri</emphasis> group. The molecular divergence of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> with species in this clade is as high as that of mouse to human. This distance is highly problematic for ancestral state inferences, because of saturation of neutral nucleotide site turnover (<link linkend="bib39">Stein et al., 2003</link><!--PMID: 14624247-->; <link linkend="bib28">Kiontke et al., 2004</link><!--PMID: 15184656-->). Finding a sister species to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> would break this long branch and thus be very precious for ancestral state inference and the use of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> in evolutionary studies<emphasis>.</emphasis> Please sample!</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-4">
<title><emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species numbering and naming</title>
<para>New species are transiently ascribed a number so that one can refer to them unambiguously. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson2076#012--10">Karin Kiontke</ulink> acts as the unofficial curator of species numbers. If you think you may have a new <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species, please write to her to check on this and request a number. The latest species can be seen at <ulink url="http://evolution.wormbase.org/index.php/LIST_OF_AVAILABLE_CAENORHABDITIS_SPECIES_and_the_state_of_their_genome_projects">http://evolution.wormbase.org/index.php/LIST_OF_AVAILABLE_CAENORHABDITIS_SPECIES_and_the_state_of_their_genome_projects</ulink>. Rhabditina DB also updates morphological and molecular information about yet unpublished species (<ulink url="http://128.122.60.136/fmi/iwp/cgi?-db=RhabditinaDB&amp;-loadframes">http://128.122.60.136/fmi/iwp/cgi?-db=RhabditinaDB&#x0026;-loadframes</ulink>).</para>
<para>The actual Latin naming of these species lagged far behind because of the requirements for formal nematode species description according to zoological systematics guidelines (measurements, drawings, morphological characterization and comparison with previously descriptions; e.g., <link linkend="bib46">Sudhaus et al., 2010</link>). A recent article (<link linkend="bib15">F&#x00E9;lix et al., 2014</link>) argues for the use of crosses as the defining and diagnostic character of the biological species in <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>, a group of species where crosses are readily performed, and where taxonomic morphological characters may be polymorphic within a species, as well as conserved between species. Based on crosses, <link linkend="bib15">F&#x00E9;lix et al. (2014)</link> thus named 15 <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Culture conditions</title>
<para>When starting a culture, it is important to keep track of the number and developmental stage of the founders.</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>For selfing species, the culture may be started from a single animal born in the wild and kept potentially genetically heterogeneous by the absence of further bottlenecks. This is important if studies of the natural outcrossing rate are planned. A small but not negligible proportion of wild animals are the products of recent crosses (<link linkend="bib5">Barri&#x00E8;re and F&#x00E9;lix, 2005</link><!--PMID: 16005289-->; <link linkend="bib38">Sivasundar and Hey, 2005</link><!--PMID: 16139217-->; <link linkend="bib6">Barri&#x00E8;re and F&#x00E9;lix, 2007</link><!--PMID: 17409084-->). Thus, to obtain a genetically pure and stable isogenic line (mutation notwithstanding), it is advisable to self it by transferring a single virgin hermaphrodite animal for ca. 4-5 generations.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>For male-female species, the culture is generally started from a single mated female or a virgin female and a male, yielding an isofemale line. The culture remains genetically heterogeneous unless an isogenic line is derived by inbreeding through many generations of brother-sister mating. Note that a culture from a mated female or hermaphrodite may carry more than four alleles in its progeny since the mother may have been mated multiple times. It is thus best for diversity studies to keep track of the developmental stage of the individual that was used to start the culture. Alternatively, a strain of a male-female species can be started from several wild-born animals, yielding a population strain that minimizes inbreeding and the associated depression, and may later be a good starting material to derive inbred lines.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Many species of the Rhabditidae, Diplogastridae, Panagrolaimidae and Cephalobidae families can be grown on standard NGM plates seeded with <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OP50;class=Strain" role="_blank">OP50</ulink> (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html">Maintenance of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). Beware that many tropical <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species do not tolerate a storage temperature of 15&#x00B0;C and grow well at 30&#x00B0;C, whereas temperate ones grow at 15&#x00B0;C but are sterile at 30&#x00B0;C (<link linkend="bib30">Kiontke et al., 2011</link>)<!--PMID: 22103856-->. As a rule, keep temperate species at 20&#x00B0;C, tropical ones at 23-25&#x00B0;C.</para>
<para>The cultures can be cleaned of associated micro-organisms using the bleaching procedure (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html">Maintenance of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html#d0e671">Section 6</ulink>) - possibly associated with serial transfers for problematic bacteria that tend to resist this treatment. Note however that (1) associated micro-organisms may be of interest, and (2) some of these nematodes do not grow well or even enter dauer if cultured with <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> only, and are thus more easily cultured on standard NGM plates with carried-along bacteria.</para>
<para>Some species of other families require special culturing media or conditions (De Ley and Mundo-Ocampo, 2004). <emphasis>Bunonema</emphasis>, <emphasis>Tylocephalus</emphasis> and <emphasis>Plectus</emphasis> can be best cultured on soil plates (1% agar + 1% soil + 5 &#x03BC;g/ml cholesterol), and <emphasis>Teratocephalus</emphasis> on water plates (1% agar in water + 5 &#x03BC;g/ml cholesterol). Add ca. 2 ml of M9 solution to the <emphasis>Plectus</emphasis> and <emphasis>Teratocephalus</emphasis> cultures (they like to swim). Keep cultures at 15-20&#x00B0;C, except for <emphasis>Bunonema</emphasis>, which grows best at 25&#x00B0;C.</para>
<para>Male-female species are generally subject to inbreeding depression, which can be very strong in some cases. This is best avoided by taking a large number of worms (>10) at each transfer and/or culturing them on larger (90 mm diameter) culture plates for larger population sizes.</para>
<para>Security proceedures: Be aware that some nematodes that can be found in soil samples such as <emphasis>Halicephalobus</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib36">Shadduck et al., 1979</link>)<!--PMID: 495570--> or <emphasis>Pelodera</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib21">Ginsburg et al., 1984</link><!--PMID: 6542207-->; <link linkend="bib47">Tanaka et al., 2004</link><!--PMID: 15577765-->) have been described to be potentially harmful to humans. However, the major danger you may encounter is to contaminate your lab with wild mites, either nematophagous ones, swallowing worms like spaghettis, or bacterivorous ones, competing with nematodes and messing up cultures by transferring eggs and larvae between plates. Good practice is keeping your sampling plates apart from your culture plates, and wrapping them with tight Parafilm. Mites can be killed by heating plates/incubators to 50-60&#x00B0;C for a few hours; alternatively, dichlorobenzene moth balls have been reported to kill mites but not nematodes (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/resources/person/WBPerson2076#012--10">Karin Kiontke</ulink>, personal communication).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Freezing conditions</title>
<para>Many species can be frozen using the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> freezing protocol (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html">Maintenance of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strainmaintain/strainmaintain.html#d0e920">Section 7</ulink>). However, several species do not survive freezing using this method.</para>
<para>For species of the <emphasis>Mesorhabditis</emphasis>, <emphasis>Teratorhabditis</emphasis>, <emphasis>Pelodera</emphasis>, <emphasis>Poikilolaimus</emphasis>, <emphasis>Oscheius</emphasis> (Insectivora group) and <emphasis>Panagrolaimus</emphasis> genera, recovery may be greatly increased if 1 mM CaCl<subscript>2</subscript> is added to the freezing solution (<ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_ppageneticprotocols.2/ppageneticprotocols.html"><emphasis>Pristionchus pacificus</emphasis> protocols</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_ppageneticprotocols.2/ppageneticprotocols.html#sec2">Section 2</ulink>). Adding a heat-shock treatment (e.g., 1 hr at 37&#x00B0;C) considerably helps with some difficult species, such as <emphasis>Caenorhabditis angaria</emphasis> or &#x201C;<emphasis>Rhabditis</emphasis>&#x201D; sp. SB347 and their close relatives.</para>
<para>Finally, species of the Cephalobidae family are particularly drought-resistant and can be frozen by directly placing large chunks of a half-dried culture plate (slightly before it turns into an agar &#x2018;chip&#x2019;) into a tube at &#x2013;80&#x00B0;C; for &#x2018;revival&#x2019;, H<subscript>2</subscript>O or M9 solution is added to the tube for a few hours and the tube contents are then transferred to a new culture plate.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Typical time course and organization of an isolation experiment</title>
<para>When sampling, keep track of geographical coordinates (GPS), date, nature of landscape, nature of substrate, so as to be able to fill in information such as found in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/#012-3-6">Wormbase</ulink>, e.g., <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_sp. 11/strain/JU1848?query=JU1848#02--10">http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_sp.%2011/strain/JU1848?query=JU1848#02&#x2013;10</ulink>. Try to recognize your worms of interest (see an example in <link linkend="figure8">Figure 8</link>). When starting the culture, also keep track of the number, sex and stage of individuals the culture was started from.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure8" xreflabel="Figure 8">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig8" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 8</phrase>
</textobject> &fig8legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The incidence of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> in wet tropical areas is high, and half of the samples of rotting fruits, flowers and stems may yield a <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species, sometimes several (<link linkend="bib18">F&#x00E9;lix et al., 2013</link>)<!--PMID: 23311925-->. However, the incidence of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> in temperate areas appears much lower, and even in a location where <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> is found, only one in ten samples may be positive (<link linkend="bib17">F&#x00E9;lix and Duveau, 2012</link>)<!--PMID: 22731941-->.</para>
<para>The organization of a nematode isolation experiment depends on its goal:</para>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>If the goal is to study wild worms to directly determine their number, sex, stage, associated flora, etc., the worms need to be isolated within minutes to a few hours after sample collection.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>If the goal is to obtain an accurate representation of genetic diversity of a natural population, one needs to isolate the individuals that were present at the time of sampling, that is, within a single generation (obviously, the time between sample isolation and plating must be reduced to the minimum).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>If the goal is to keep a maximum of one genotype of each species per sample, the sample can be plated several days after its collection (up to several months for some drought-resistant nematodes). Specifically, <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> can be recovered after up to three weeks of sample collection, yet most likely with a much reduced efficiency compared to fresh samples. Do not hesitate to pool several flowers or small fruits or several pieces of different fruits at the time of sampling in the same bag, then keep a single isolate per species per sample.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>Available collections</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>&#x2022; Caenorhabditis Genetics Center: <ulink url="http://www.cbs.umn.edu/CGC/strains/">http://www.cbs.umn.edu/CGC/strains/</ulink></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>&#x2022; Many wild isolates are listed in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/#012-3-6">Wormbase</ulink> under &#x00AB; Strain &#x00BB; with their sampling details and lab of origin, e.g., <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/strain/JU2001?query=JU2001#02--10">http://www.wormbase.org/species/c_elegans/strain/JU2001?query=JU2001#02&#x2013;10</ulink></para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Individual labs:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>&#x2022; F&#x00E9;lix lab collection: <ulink url="http://www.justbio.com/worms/index.php">http://www.justbio.com/worms/index.php</ulink></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>&#x2022; Braendle lab collection: <ulink url="http://www.braendlelab.net/worms.html">http://www.braendlelab.net/worms.html</ulink></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>&#x2022; Cutter lab database: <ulink url="http://labs.eeb.utoronto.ca/cutter/map/">http://labs.eeb.utoronto.ca/cutter/map/</ulink> (includes isolates from the above labs).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>&#x2022; Fitch lab collection (especially for Rhabditidae outside <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis>): <ulink url="http://www.nyu.edu/projects/fitch/Rhabditina/NYURC_strainslist.htm">http://www.nyu.edu/projects/fitch/Rhabditina/NYURC_strainslist.htm</ulink></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>&#x2022; Sommer lab collection (Pristionchus): <ulink url="http://www.pristionchus.org/cgi-bin/strain_req.pl">http://www.pristionchus.org/cgi-bin/strain_req.pl</ulink></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>&#x2022; See also <ulink url="http://evolution.wormbase.org/index.php/Main_Page">http://evolution.wormbase.org/index.php/Main_Page</ulink> for news on <emphasis>Caenorhabditis species</emphasis>, especially on sampling and species discovery</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>We are grateful to Karin Kiontke and Paul De Ley for providing drawings, pictures and protocols. We thank Asher Cutter, Lise Fr&#x00E9;zal, Christian Braendle, Karin Kiontke and the reviewers for helpful comments.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec9">
<title>References</title>
<para/>
&nematodeisolation.2_ref;
</sect1>
</article>