<caption>
<formalpara>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Figure 6: Neurotransmitter pathways.</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">(A)</emphasis> Pathways for different neurotransmitters. Numbers in parentheses refer to the number of neurons of that neurotransmitter type in the adult hermaphrodite (<link linkend="bib156">Rand and Nonet, 1997</link>). Neurotransmitter identity is inferred from the expression of genes shown in the schematic or by antibody staining (GABA, 5-HT). The identity of all glutamatergic neurons has not yet been determined. Note that after synaptic release, glutamate is taken up not only by presynaptic neurons but also by cells in immediate proximity of neurons, as assessed by the analysis of expression patterns of the glutamate reuptake transporters (Mano et al., 2007<!--: PMID 17681948-->). The yellow circles indicate the substrates or cofactors required by individual enzymes (see panel B and C). The GABA degradation pathway generates succinic semialdehyde from GABA via GABA transaminase (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gta-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gta-1</ulink></emphasis>, not yet studied in worms), which is then broken down to succinate by succinic semialdehyde dehydrogenase (SSADH, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=alh-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">alh-7</ulink></emphasis> in worms, also not yet studied in worms). The site of action of the degradation pathway likely is within GABA neurons but also in other cell types, as the GABA reuptake transporter <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=snf-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">snf-11</ulink></emphasis> is expressed not just in GABA neurons but also other in cell types. The two separate degradation pathway for monoamine transmitters, either via the monoamine oxidase MAO-A/B (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=amx-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">amx-2</ulink></emphasis> in worms, not yet studied) or the Catechol-O-Methyltransferase COMT (five <emphasis>comt</emphasis> genes in worms), are likely to act cell-autonomously since DA and 5HT reuptakes are restricted to DA and 5HT neurons. <emphasis role="bold">(B)</emphasis> Acetylcholine biosynthesis. Acetyl-CoA and choline are the substrates for acetylcholine synthesis. Acetyl-CoA is synthesized by an enzyme, ACLY (<emphasis>acly-1, 2</emphasis> in worms, both uncharacterized), which is enriched in cholinergic neurons in adult vertebrates. <emphasis role="bold">(C)</emphasis> Monoamine synthesis. Pathway for <emphasis>de novo</emphasis> synthesis or recycling of BH<subscript>4,</subscript> which is an essential cofactor of TH, TPH and TBH (panel A). BH<subscript>4</subscript> is also used as a cofactor for TBH in the octopaminergic pathway as inferred by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cat-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">cat-4</ulink></emphasis> expression in TBH(+) octopaminergic neurons (unpubl. data). Enzyme names are in red, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> gene names in blue. The SPR (sepiapterin reductase) enzyme belongs to the large superfamily of related short-chain dehydrogenases and reductases (SDRs), and a specific sepiapterin reductase-subtype is too difficult to identify within this family in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. All other enzymes in the BH<subscript>4</subscript> pathways have clear single orthologs in the worm genome. GTPCH = GTP cyclohydrolase; GFRP = GTP cyclohydrolase feedback regulator protein (a regulatory factor used in serotonergic, but not dopaminergic neurons in vertebrates); PTPS = 6-pyruvoyl-tetrahydropterin synthase; SR = sepiapterin reductase; PCD = pterin-4-alpha-carbinolamine dehydratase; DHPR = dihydropteridine reductase. The BH<subscript>4</subscript> synthetic intermediates are as follows: H<subscript>2</subscript>NTP = 7,8-dihydroneopterin triphosphate; PTP = 6-pyruvoyl-5,6,7,8- tetrahydropterin; BH<subscript>4</subscript>&alpha;C = tetrahydrobiopterin-4&alpha;-carbinolamine; qBH<subscript>2</subscript> = quinoid dihydrobiopterin. The content of this panel is adapted from (<link linkend="bib42">Deneris and Wyler, 2012</link><!--: PMID 22366757-->).</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>
