<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>

<title>WormBook news</title>
<description>WormBook is the online review of C. elegans biology and serves as a text companion to WormBase, the comprehensive nematode genomics and proteomics information resource.</description>
<language>en-us</language>
<webMaster>wormbook-help@wormbase.org (WormBook Help Desk)</webMaster>
<managingEditor>mendelj@caltech.edu (Jane Mendel)</managingEditor>
<copyright>Copyright &#xA9; 2005, 2006, 2007, 2008, 2009, 2010, 2011, 2012 WormBook.  All WormBook content, except where otherwise noted, is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution License.</copyright>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2013 23:30:50 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<ttl>360</ttl>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org</link>

<item>
<title>Sperm motility chapter updated</title>
<description>Nematode sperm motility, by Harold Smith, has been published in the Cell biology section of WormBook.  This chapter updates the information presented in Sperm motility and MSP and includes expanded discussion on the acquisition, directionality, force generation and guidance of sperm motility.
</description>
<pubDate>Tuesday, 8 April 2014 10:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_spermmotilityMSP.2/spermmotility.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_spermmotilityMSP.2/spermmotility.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>New chapter added to WormMethods</title>
<description>Modern techniques for the analysis of chromatin and nuclear organization in C. elegans , by Peter Askjaer, Sevinç Ercan, and Peter Meister, has been published in the Cell and molecular biology section of WormMethods. This chapter provides detailed methods for using ChIP and DamID to identify binding sites for chromatin-associated proteins, methods for ChIP and DamID quantification, and methods for live chromatin imaging.
</description>
<pubDate>Friday, 4 April 2014 10:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_chromatinanalysis/chromatinanalysis.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_chromatinanalysis/chromatinanalysis.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>New issue of The Worm Breeder's Gazette now available</title>
<description>Volume 20, No. 1 of The Worm Breeder's Gazette has been published. Among the articles are descriptions of improved techniques for mutant identification via whole genome sequencing, culturing C. elegans cells, and preserving histological samples. Meeting and new lab announcements are included along with worm art and humor. 
</description>
<pubDate>Wednesday, 26 March 2014 10:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Thermotaxis methods published in WormBook</title>
<description>Thermotaxis navigation behavior, by Miriam Goodwin et al., has been added to the Behavioral assays section of WormMethods. This chapter gives multiple protocols to assay the navigation of C. elegans hermaphrodites on spatial thermal gradients. A method to assay avoidance of noxious temperatures is also included. 
</description>
<pubDate>Monday, 24 February 2014 10:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_thermonav/thermonav.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_thermonav/thermonav.html</guid>
</item>


<item>
<title>WormBook congratulates Scott Emmons and colleagues</title>
<description>The Connectome of a Decision-Making Neural Network, by Travis A. Jarrell, Yi Wang, Adam E. Bloniarz, Christopher A. Brittin, Meng Xu, J. Nichol Thomson, Donna G. Albertson, David H. Hall, and Scott Emmons, has received the Newcomb Cleveland Prize, awarded to the most outstanding paper published in Science in the year June 2012 to May 2013. Cited as a tour de force among many competitive entries by Science editor-in-chief Marcia McNutt, this paper presents the wiring diagram of the posterior nervous system of the C. elegans adult male, providing a step toward understanding the connection between neural activity and behavior. 
</description>
<pubDate>Wednesday, 19 February 2014 10:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.sciencemag.org/content/337/6093/437.abstract?sid=f0eea501-17f4-4fed-bc84-c739e9aeb520</link>
<guid>http://www.sciencemag.org/content/337/6093/437.abstract?sid=f0eea501-17f4-4fed-bc84-c739e9aeb520</guid>
</item>


<item>
<title>Mutagenesis protocols added to WormMethods</title>
<description>'Forward and reverse mutagenesis in C. elegans' by Lena Kutscher and Shai Shaham has been published in the Forward and reverse genetics section of WormMethods.  This chapter provides an overview of historical and contemporary mutagenesis techniques, and discusses principles and strategies for forward (genome-wide) and reverse (target-selected and gene-specific) genetic screens. Protocols for recently-developed systems for gene-targeted mutagenesis in C. elegans, including those using Zinc-finger or transcription activator-like nucleases and CRISPR/Cas9, are provided.
</description>
<pubDate>Tuesday, 21 January 2014 10:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_frmutagenesis/frmutagenesis.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_frmutagenesis/frmutagenesis.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Genetics methods chapter published in WormMethods</title>
<description>Classical genetic methods, by David Fay, has been published in the Forward genetics and genetic mapping section of WormMethods. This chapter combines several previous chapters by David Fay, Aaron Bender, Andy Spencer, and Wade Johnson.
</description>
<pubDate>Tuesday, 7 January 2014 10:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_classicalgenmethods/classicalgenmethods.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_classicalgenmethods/classicalgenmethods.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Microparticle bombardment chapter added to WormMethods</title>
<description>C. elegans gene transformation by microparticle bombardment by Peter Schweinsberg and Barth Grant has been published in the Microinjection and transformation section of WormMethods. This chapter provides a detailed description of the reagents, equipment, and method for biolistic transformation of C. elegans.
</description>
<pubDate>Tuesday, 7 January 2014 09:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_microbombard/microbombard.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_microbombard/microbombard.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Insulin signaling chapter added to WormBook</title>
<description>Insulin/insulin-like growth factor signaling in C. elegans, by Coleen Murphy and Patrick Hu, has been added to the Signal transduction section. This chapter reviews what is currently known about the components, function, and regulation of the C. elegans insulin/IGF-1 signaling (IIS) pathway. 
</description>
<pubDate>Tuesday, 7 January 2014 07:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_insulingrowthsignal/insulingrowthsignal.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_insulingrowthsignal/insulingrowthsignal.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Wnt signaling chapter updated</title>
<description>Wnt signaling in C. elegans by Hitoshi Sawa and Hendrik Korswagen has been added to Signal transduction.  This chapter is an update of Wnt signaling by David Eisenmann. Canonical and non-canonical Wnt signaling pathways and their components are described and an animated model of asymmetric cell division is included.
</description>
<pubDate>Monday, 9 December 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_wntsignaling.2/wntsignal.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_wntsignaling.2/wntsignal.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Transgenesis chapter added to WormMethods</title>
<description>'Transgenesis in animal parasites nematodes: Strongyloides spp. and Brugia spp.' by James Lok and Thomas Unnasch has been added to the 'Methods for nematode species other than C. elegens' section of WormMethods.  This chapter describes methods for gene transfer for these parasites as well as providing information on their rearing and maintenance.  Germline transformation, sustained transgene expression, and establishment of stable transgenic lines in Strongyloides ratti is also discussed.
</description>
<pubDate>Monday, 30 September 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transgenesis/transgenesis.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transgenesis/transgenesis.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Microfluidics chapter published in WormMethods</title>
<description>'Microfluidics as a tool for C. elegans research' by Adriana San-Miguel and Hang Lu has been published in the 'Microscopy and other instrumentation' section of WormMethods.  This chapter includes resources for chip fabrication and  methods for in-house fabrication of devices with soft lithography, as well as applications such as behavioral assays, imaging, microsurgery and screening.
</description>
<pubDate>Tuesday, 24 September 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_microfluidics/microfluidics.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_microfluidics/microfluidics.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Volume 19, Number 4 of The Worm Breeder's Gazette now available</title>
<description>Volume 19, #4 of The Worm Breeder's Gazette has just been published. This issue contains important announcements from the CGC and the WormBase Gene Name Curator, articles describing new techniques and research results, summaries and abstracts from workshops presented at the recent International C. elegans meeting, new lab announcements, and a humorous 'News' section.
</description>
<pubDate>Tuesday, 20 August 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>New chapter added to Neurobiology and behavior</title>
<description>'The Neuronal genome of Caenorhabditis elegans', by Oliver Hobert, has been published in the Development section of Neurobiology and behavior. This comprehensive chapter provides a compendium of more than 2,800 putative terminal differentiation genes expressed in neurons. Several tables listing genes by family are included.
</description>
<pubDate>Wednesday, 14 August 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_neuronalgenome/neuronalgenome.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_neuronalgenome/neuronalgenome.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Ras signaling chapter updated in Signal transduction</title>
<description>'Canonical RTK-Ras-ERK signaling and related alternative pathways' by Meera Sundaram has been added to the Signal transduction section of WormBook. This chapter updates 'RTK/Ras/MAPK signaling' also by Meera Sundaram. In addition to describing the basic framework, roles, and regulation of the canonical RTK-Ras-ERK pathway, this chapter also discusses alternative RTK- or Ras-dependent pathways. 
</description>
<pubDate>Thursday, 11 July 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RTKRasMAPKsignaling.2/RTKRasERKsignal.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RTKRasMAPKsignaling.2/RTKRasERKsignal.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Chapter on the UCSC Genome Browser added to WormMethods</title>
<description>'An introduction to the UCSC Genome Browser' by Raymond Lee has been published in the Basic methods for C. elegans section of WormMethods. The Genome Browser at the University of California Santa Cruz provides a graphical interface to sequences, features, and annotations of genomes across a wide spectrum of organisms including seven nematodes. This article provides a brief introduction for using the Genome Browser from the perspective of a C. elegans researcher. 
</description>
<pubDate>Thursday, 11 July 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_gbrowser/gbrowser.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_gbrowser/gbrowser.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>TGF-β signaling chapter updated</title>
<description>'TGF-β signaling in C. elegans' by Tina Gumienny and Cathy Savage-Dunn has been published in the Signal transduction section of WormBook. This chapter updates 'TGF-β signaling' by Cathy Savage-Dunn. In addition to describing the TGF-β family members, this chapter discusses their ligands, DBL-1, DAF-7, and UNC-129, their signaling pathways, and their biological functions. 
</description>
<pubDate>Wednesday, 10 July 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_tgfbsignal.2/TGFbetasignal.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_tgfbsignal.2/TGFbetasignal.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Faucett Catalyst Grant deadline</title>
<description>The deadline for applications for the Faucett Catalyst Grants to attract C. elegans researchers to work on parasitic nematodes is August 15, 2013. Additional information can be found in the linked pdf file. 
</description>
<pubDate>Wednesday, 10 July 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/Faucett_Catalyst_applications.pdf</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/Faucett_Catalyst_applications.pdf</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Statistics chapter added to WormMethods</title>
<description>'A biologist's guide to statistical thinking and analysis' by David Fay and Ken Gerow has been added to the Basic methods for C. elegans section of WormMethods. Using examples drawn from C. elegans biology, this chapter lucidly describes the concepts of statistics likely to be used by many nematode researchers. The chapter includes discussions on sample size, normality, means, proportions, probabilities, correlations, and non-parametric methods.
</description>
<pubDate>Tuesday, 9 July 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_statisticalanalysis/statisticalanalysis.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_statisticalanalysis/statisticalanalysis.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>WormBook launches WormHistory section</title>
<description>WormBook is pleased to announce the addition of our newest section, 'WormHistory'. This section will contain articles that give a personal view of highlights in nematode research. We launch the section with 'Getting into the mind of a worm-a personal view' by John White, in which he describes his recruitment into the world of C. elegans by Sidney Brenner and the work that led to the publication of "The Mind of a Worm". WormHistory also contains links to Nobel Lectures, Genetics Perspectives, and People and Ideas interviews from The Journal of Cell Biology. 
</description>
<pubDate>Tuesday, 25 June 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_mindofworm/mindofworm.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_mindofworm/mindofworm.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Transcription regulation chapter updated in Molecular Biology</title>
<description>Transcriptional regulation of gene expression in C. elegans by Valerie Reinke, Michael Krause and Peter Okkema has been added to the Molecular biology section.  This chapter updates Transcriptional regulation by Peter Okkema and Michael Krause, and includes discussions of gene organization and regulation, transcription factors and their targets, chromatin regulatory complexes, and genome-scale analyses of transcription regulation. Sortable Excel lists of transcription factors and their targets are also provided.
</description>
<pubDate>Tuesday, 4 June 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transcriptionalregulation.2/transregulate.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transcriptionalregulation.2/transregulate.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Pristionchus pacificus protocols updated in WormMethods</title>
<description>Pristionchus pacificus protocols has been revised and greatly expanded by Andre Pires da Silva.  In addition to updated  protocols for freezing, mutagenesis, deletion libraries and gene knockdown in P. pacificus, the revised chapter includes protocols for: in situ hybridization, isolating genomic DNA for whole genome sequencing, extracting compounds from worm supernatant, electron microscopy, immunofluorescence, transgenesis, and mapping mutants with molecular markers.
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 14 March 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_ppageneticprotocols.2/ppageneticprotocols.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_ppageneticprotocols.2/ppageneticprotocols.html</guid>
</item>


<item>
<title>New Worm Breeder's Gazette published</title>
<description>Volume 19, #3 of The Worm Breeder's Gazette has just been published.  In addition to beautiful cover artwork by Greg Nelson and Feng Xue, this issue contains 18 articles as well as announcements of 5 new labs. 
</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 22 February 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>New chapter added to WormMethods</title>
<description>Cell isolation and culture by Sihui Zhang and Jeffrey Kuhn has been published in the Methods in cell biology section of WormMethods.  This chapter provides comprehensive techniques and media recipes for large-scale isolation and culture of primary embryonic and larval cells from C. elegans.  The chapter also includes a brief discussion on the application of cell isolation and culture.  Appendices list necessary equipment and supplies, and for those unfamiliar with working in a sterile culture hood, there is an appendix describing common cell culture techniques.
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 21 February 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_cellculture/cellculture.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_cellculture/cellculture.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>New chapter published in Biochemistry</title>
<description>"Ascaroside signaling in C. elegans", by Andrease Ludewig and Frank Schroeder, has been added to the Biochemistry section. This chapter describes the function, structure, biosynthesis and receptors of these small signaling molecules.
</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 18 January 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_ascarosidesignal/ascarosidesignal.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_ascarosidesignal/ascarosidesignal.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Updated chapter added to Signal transduction</title>
<description>"Notch signaling: genetics and structure" by Iva Greenwald and Rhett Kovall, which updates "LIN-12/Notch signaling in C. elegans" by Iva Greenwald, has been published in the Signal transduction section. In addition to covering the genetics of Notch in C. elegans, the updated chapter describes how recent advances in the structural biology of Notch signaling have enhanced understanding of its molecular mechanism.  
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 17 January 2013 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_lin12Notch.2/notchsignaling.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_lin12Notch.2/notchsignaling.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Feeding behavior chapter added to WormMethods</title>
<description>"Methods for measuring pharyngeal behaviors", by David Raizen, Bo-mi Song, Nick Trojanowski and Youn-Jai You, has been published in the Behavior section of WormMethods. Protocols for measuring and analyzing pharyngeal activity such as feeding rate, the timing of pharyngeal movements and the cessation of feeding are provided. 
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 18 December 2012 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_measurepharyngeal/measurepharyngeal.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_measurepharyngeal/measurepharyngeal.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>smFISH protocol now available in WormMethods</title>
<description>"Single molecule fluorescent in situ hybridization (smFISH) of C. elegans worms and embryos" by Ni Ji and Alexander van Oudenaarden has just been published in the Gene expression section of WormMethods. The authors provide the necessary technical details to set up and perform smFISH, from sample preparation to data analysis. 
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 13 December 2012 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_smFISH/smFISH.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_smFISH/smFISH.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>New Chapter added to Sex determination</title>
<description>"Morphogenesis of the vulva and the vulva-uterine connection" by Bhagwati Gupta, Wendy Hanna-Rose and Paul Sternberg has been published in the Sex determination section. This chapter updates the information on vulva morphogenesis found in "Vulva development" and provides more in-depth discussion on this topic.
</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 30 November 2012 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_vulvamorph/vulvamorph.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_vulvamorph/vulvamorph.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>New chapter on Eph receptor signaling published</title>
<description>"Eph receptor signaling in C. elegans" by Michael A. Miller and Ian D. Chin-Sang is available in the Signal transduction section. This chapter describes advances in our understanding of the biological functions and transduction mechanisms of this important class of receptor protein-tyrosine kinases.
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 29 November 2012 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_Ephsignaling/Ephsignaling.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_Ephsignaling/Ephsignaling.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Updated chapter published in Biochemistry</title>
<description>"Trans-splicing and operons in C. elegans" by Thomas Blumenthal is available in the Biochemistry section of WormBook. This is an update of "Trans-splicing and operons", published in 2005. The updated chapter describes advances in our understanding of the mechanism and evolution of trans-splicing, and the structure and function of operons in C. elegans.
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 20 November 2012 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transsplicingoperons.2/transsplicingoperons.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transsplicingoperons.2/transsplicingoperons.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Worm trackers described in WormMethods</title>
<description>"Keeping track of worm trackers", by Steven Husson et al. has been added to the Behavior section of WormMethods. This chapter describes several methods for automated image capture and quantitation of nematode locomotion.
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 13 September 2012 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_tracking/tracking.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_tracking/tracking.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>New Worm Breeder's Gazette published</title>
<description>The latest issue, Volume 19, number 2, of The Worm Breeder's Gazette is now available. Please visit http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/ to read about new techniques, research advances, useful web resources and more. This issue also includes lists of notable recent papers in genetics, biochemistry and reproductive biology as well as announcements of new C. elegans labs. 
</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 6 July 2012 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>New chapter published in Neurobiology and behavior</title>
<description>"C. elegans feeding" has been published in the Neurobiology and behavior section of WormBook. This chapter, by Leon Avery and Young-jai You, describes the mechanics of feeding, the actions of the neurons and muscles involved, and the effects of food on behavior.  
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 22 May 2012 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_feeding/feeding.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_feeding/feeding.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Updated chapter added</title>
<description>"Pre-mRNA splicing and its regulation" by Alan Zahler has just been added to the Molecular biology section. This chapter updates the review of constitutive splicing factors, identification of alternatively spliced genes, and regulation of alternative splicing found in it's predecessor, "Alternative splicing in C. elegans". It also and adds discussions on the coupling of alternative splicing to nonsense-mediated decay and the progress toward identifying the alternative splicing code in C. elegans. 
</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 23 March 2012 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_altsplicing.2/pre-mRNA.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_altsplicing.2/pre-mRNA.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>The Worm Breeder's Gazette Publishes A New Issue</title>
<description>The Worm Breeder's Gazette, Volume 19, number 1 is now available. This issue contains improved protocols for imaging, snPCR, immunoblotting, transgenesis and worm pick construction. 
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 20 December 2011 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Third issue of the Worm Breeder's Gazette now available</title>
<description>Volume 18, number 3 of the Worm Breeder's Gazette is now available at http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/, or by clicking the Gazette cover. This issue includes new protocols for mounting worms for microscopy, preparation of dauer larvae, and establishing gradients for chemotaxis assays. Additional articles describe sequence corrections, new software, expression profiles, neural networks, available expression clones, and studies of chemotaxis and self recognition. 
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 21 December 2010 23:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Neurogenesis chapter updated</title>
<description>'Neurogenesis in the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans' by Oliver Hobert has been added to the Neurobiology and behavior section. This new chapter is an update and expansion of his previous chapter, 'Specification of the nervous system'.
</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 4 October 2010 8:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_specnervsys.2/neurogenesis.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_specnervsys.2/neurogenesis.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>The Worm Breeder's Gazette, Volume 18, number 2 now available </title>
<description>A new issue of The Worm Breeder's Gazette is now available at http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/. This issue includes 25 contributions describing new methods for selecting transformants, useful strains and vectors, bioinformatics resources, visualization methods and more.
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 17 June 2010 19:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Ethanol chapter now available</title>
<description>Ethanol, by Steven McIntire, is now available in html and pdf formats. 
</description>
<pubDate>Sun, 2 May 2010 19:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_ethanol/ethanol.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_ethanol/ethanol.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>New chapter on evolution available</title>
<description>'Molecular evolution inferences from the C. elegans genome' by Asher Cutter has been added to the Evolution and ecology section. This chapter discusses mutation, recombination, natural selection, genetic drift and population dynamics in C. elegans. 
</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 5 Mar 2010 19:36:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://wormbook.org/chapters/www_molecularevol/molecularevol.html</link>
<guid>http://wormbook.org/chapters/www_molecularevol/molecularevol.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>New chapter added to WormMethods</title>
<description>'Transgenic solutions for the germline' by Cristopher Merritt and Geraldine Seydoux has been added to the Transformation and microinjection section of WormMethods. This chapter gives advice and protocols for designing and transforming germline-expressing transgenes.
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 18 Jan 2010 20:03:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://wormbook.org/chapters/www_transgenic/transgenic.html</link>
<guid>http://wormbook.org/chapters/www_transgenic/transgenic.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>WBG Volume 18, number 1 now available</title>
<description>The first issue of The Worm Breeder’s Gazette in its new on-line format is now available online. This issue includes over 30 contributions on diverse topics including an editorial by Marty Chalfie, information on a common background mutation, new ways to visualize molecules, and several new techniques. We thank the authors and the worm community for their enthusiastic response to the revival of The Worm Breeder’s Gazette.
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2009 23:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/wbg/</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>WormBook down SEP. 9, 1-5PM EDT</title>
<description>*** Due to server maintenance, WormBook pages may be unavailable on Wednesday September 9th, 1-5pm EDT. ***
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2009 16:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Aug 24, 2009 Autophagy added to Cell biology section</title>
<description>'Autophagy' by Alicia Melendez and Beth Levine has been published in the Cell biology section of WormBook.  This chapter details the evolutionarily conserved features autophagy in C. elegans, and describes the role of autophagy in several aspects of C. elegans biology including survival during starvation, dauer and reproductive development, lifespan extension, programmed and necrotic cell death, and neurodegenerative diseases.
</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2009 16:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_autophagy/autophagy.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_autophagy/autophagy.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Feb 26, 2009 New chapter added to Biochemistry section</title>
<description>A new chapter 'Intermediary metabolism' has been added to the Biochemistry section of WormBook. This chapter, by Bart Braeckman, Koen Houthoofd and Jacques Vanfleteren, describes the major metabolic  pathways in C. elegans, and discusses how metabolic activity changes in response to development, aging and environmental stress.
</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2009 16:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_intermetabolism/intermetabolism.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_intermetabolism/intermetabolism.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Oct 8, 2008 Breaking News: Martin Chalfie wins Nobel Prize for GFP in C. elegans</title>
<description>WormBook Editor-in-Chief Martin Chalfie (with Osamu Shimomura and Roger Y. Tsien) has won the 2008 Nobel Prize in Chemistry for pioneering
the use of GFP in C. elegans. This is the third Nobel Prize awarded for research on C. elegans in the last six years. Congratulations to Martie!
</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 8 Oct 2008 16:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/chemistry/laureates/2008/index.html</link>
<guid>http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/chemistry/laureates/2008/index.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Sep 26, 2008 SNP methods chapter updated</title>
<description>SNPs: introduction and 2-point mapping by David Fay has been updated in the Forward genetics and genetic mapping section of WormMethods.  This updated chapter includes expanded instruction on the use of SNP databases and additional graphics related to SNP mapping.
</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2008 11:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_SNPsintrotwopointmap.2/SNPsintrotwopointmap.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_SNPsintrotwopointmap.2/SNPsintrotwopointmap.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Sep 26, 2008 New chapter added to Neurobiology and Behavior</title>
<description>Neuropeptides has been added to the Neurotransmitters section of  Neurobiology and behavior.  This chapter provides comprehensive coverage of all aspects of neuropeptide biology in C. elegans as well as extensive tables detailing peptide sequences, expression patterns and functions.
</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2008 10:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_neuropeptides/neuropeptides.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_neuropeptides/neuropeptides.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Sep 9, 2008 New chapter added to The germ line section</title>
<description>Germline survival and apoptosis chapter has been added to The germ line section. WormBook readers are welcome to read the new chapter and post feedbacks at the WormBook forum.
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 9 Sep 2008 23:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlinesurvival/germlinesurvival.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlinesurvival/germlinesurvival.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>May 13, 2008 Discussion forum expanded</title>
<description>Links to the WormBook discussion forum now appear on each chapter page. Clicking 'View/Add Comments' will take you to a new chapter level folder in the discussion board. If you would like to be notified when new comments are posted to a particular chapter, please login and then use the ‘NOTIFY’ button on the chapter level. Please register or log in and let us know what you think.
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2008 23:35:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbase.org/forums/index.php?board=31.0</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbase.org/forums/index.php?board=31.0</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>May 13, 2008 Figures resized in HTML chapters</title>
<description>WormBook chapters are now easier to read online because all figures have been resized for clarity. Figures can also be further expanded with a simple mouse click.
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2008 23:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Jan 25, 2008 Post-embryonic development section expanded</title>
<description>The measurement and analysis of age-related changes in Caenorhabditis elegans is now available in the Post-embryonic development section of WormBook. Please visit this chapter to read about aging in C. elegans.
</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2008 23:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_measurementanalysisCelegans/measurementanalysisCelegans.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_measurementanalysisCelegans/measurementanalysisCelegans.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Jan 24, 2008 WormBook chapters indexed in PubMed</title>
<description>We are pleased to announce that most WormBook chapters are now indexed in PubMed. Abstracts are linked directly to the full text at WormBook.
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2008 23:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez</link>
<guid>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Nov 2, 2007 New chapter added to the Disease models and drug discovery section</title>
<description>Anthelmintic drugs has just been published in the Disease models and drug discovery section of WormBook. This chapter summarizes the modes of action of the main classes of anthelmintic drugs, their utility in studying cell signaling in C. elegans, and the use of C. elegans in drug discovery programs.
</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 2 Nov 2007 23:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_anthelminticdrugs/anthelminticdrugs.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_anthelminticdrugs/anthelminticdrugs.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Aug 9, 2007 Dauer has been added to the Post-embryonic development section</title>
<description>Dauer has just been published in the Post-embryonic development section of WormBook. Please visit this section to read about the signaling pathways and molecular mechanisms regulating dauer arrest.
</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 9 Aug 2007 23:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_dauer/dauer.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_dauer/dauer.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Aug 6, 2007 WormBook staff change</title>
<description>Tristan Fiedler, who led the software development group at WormBook, has left WormBook. He has taken a faculty position at the Florida Institute of Technology. Tristan guided the development of every aspect of the web site. He developed the methods to convert manuscripts to web-ready articles; he designed the initial layout of the web site; and he generated the programs to search WormBook, download reference citations, and provide feedback. His input on all aspects of WormBook will be missed.
</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 6 Aug 2007 21:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/index.html#newsfront</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/index.html#newsfront</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Jul 30, 2007 WormBook staff change</title>
<description>We are fortunate that Jane Mendel has joined us as the new WormBook Editor.  Jane, a WormBook author, is a Senior Research Associate and Lecturer at Caltech, and has a strong background in C. elegans research as well as experience in teaching Introductory Biology and in using C. elegans as a teaching tool.
</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2007 9:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/index.html#newsfront</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/index.html#newsfront</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Jul 30, 2007 WormBook staff change</title>
<description>WormBook Editor Lisa Girard has moved to a position at the Harvard Stem Cell Institute.  Lisa guided WormBook from its beginning, and her creativity, dedication, and efficiency were essential for its success.  Lisa was involved in all aspects of WormBook production: she prodded authors, reviewers, and editorial board members to keep WormBook on schedule, edited and oversaw the publication of 140 articles on the web, and successfully negotiated WormBook's inclusion on the NIH Bookshelf and in PubMed. Lisa leaves WormBook in excellent shape.  We wish her continued success in her new position.
</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2007 9:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/index.html#newsfront</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/index.html#newsfront</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>May 24, 2007 New parasitic nematode chapter added</title>
<description>Strongyloides spp. has just been published in the Genetics and genomics section of WormBook, further expanding our coverage of parasitic nematodes.</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2007 19:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_genomesStrongyloides/genomesStrongyloides.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_genomesStrongyloides/genomesStrongyloides.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>May 7, 2007 Disease models and drug discovery section expanded</title>
<description>C. elegans and volatile anesthetics is now available in the Disease models and drug discovery section of WormBook. This addition contributes to our coverage of this quickly growing area.</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 7 May 2007 19:00:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_anesthetics/anesthetics.html</link>
<guid>http://dev.wormbook.org/chapters/www_anesthetics/anesthetics.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>May 4, 2007 New chapters added to Molecular biology and Genetics and genomics section</title>
<description>Roles of chromatin factors in C. elegans development has just been added to the Molecular biology section of WormBook and Genomics and biology of the nematode Caenorhabditis briggsae has just been added to the Genetics and genomics section. Please visit these sections to read the latest additions to WormBook.</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 4 May 2007 12:50:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_chromatinfactors/chromatinfactors.html</link>
<guid>http://dev.wormbook.org/chapters/www_chromatinfactors/chromatinfactors.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Apr 28, 2007 Introducing Caenorhabditis brenneri</title>
<description>The previously undescribed C. sp. 4 (also known as 'CB5161' or 'PB2801') is now Caenorhabditis brenneri, named after Sydney Brenner (Sudhaus and Kiontke, 2007).</description>
<pubDate>Sat, 28 Apr 2007 01:15:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2007f/zt01456p062.pdf</link>
<guid>http://www.mapress.com/zootaxa/2007f/zt01456p062.pdf</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Mar 29, 2007 New chapter added to Developmental control section</title>
<description>The C. elegans intestine has just been published in the Developmental control section of WormBook. Please visit this section for coverage of early developmental events.</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 29 Mar 2007 18:26:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_intestine/intestine.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_intestine/intestine.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Mar 29, 2007 Disease models and drug discovery section launched</title>
<description>WormBook is pleased to launch its new Disease models and drug discovery section with the publication of Obesity and the regulation of fat metabolism. Please watch for the publication of more chapters in this section describing progress in our understanding of disease and therapeutics.</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 29 Mar 2007 17:40:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_obesity/obesity.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_obesity/obesity.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Mar 22, 2007 Cell biology section expanded</title>
<description>The cuticle has just been published in the Cell biology section of WormBook. Readers are encouraged to visit the Cell biology section to read this chapter and related chapters exploring the cell biology of C. elegans.</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 22 Mar 2007 18:49:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_cuticle/cuticle.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_cuticle/cuticle.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Mar 6, 2007 WormBook Survey</title>
<description>Please take a few minutes to complete the WormBook Survey. Your response will help us improve the nature and quality of the service we provide our readers.</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 6 Mar 2007 04:49:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://dev.wormbase.org/db/surveys/2007_wormbook</link>
<guid>http://dev.wormbase.org/db/surveys/2007_wormbook</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Feb 24, 2007 Heterorhabditis bacteriophora chapter added to Genetics and Genomics section</title>
<description>WormBook has further expanded its coverage of parasitic nematodes with the addition of The biology and genome of Heterorhabditis bacteriophora. Please visit the Genetics and genomics section of WormBook to read this and other chapters describing the biology and genomes of nematodes other than C. elegans.</description>
<pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2007 19:38:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_genomesHbacteriophora/genomesHbacteriophora.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_genomesHbacteriophora/genomesHbacteriophora.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Feb 21, 2007 New Neurobiology and Behavior Chapter Added</title>
<description>Wormbook readers are invited to read our newly added chapter Biogenic amine neurotransmitters in C. elegans in WormBook's Neurobiology and behavior section.</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2007 22:46:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_monoamines/monoamines.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_monoamines/monoamines.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Feb 21, 2007 New Neurobiology and Behavior Chapter Added</title>
<description>Wormbook readers are invited to read our newly added chapter Strongyloides stercoralis: a model for translational research on parasitic nematode biology in WormBook's WormMethods section.</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2007 22:45:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strongyloides/strongyloides.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_strongyloides/strongyloides.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Feb 17, 2007 16th International C. elegans Meeting-Abstract Submission Site Now Open</title>
<description>16th International C. elegans Meeting will be held June 27- July 1, 2007 at the University of California, Los Angeles.  Meeting information can be found at http://genetics.faseb.org/genetics/Celegans/. The abstract submission site is now open. The deadline for abstract submissions is March 22. The deadline for registration is May 25.</description>
<pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2007 06:05:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://genetics.faseb.org/genetics/Celegans/</link>
<guid>http://genetics.faseb.org/genetics/Celegans/</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Feb 16, 2007 Ronald Plasterk Joins Dutch Government</title>
<description>Effective February 22nd 2007, longtime C. elegans researcher Ronald Plasterk will join the Government  of the Netherlands, serving as Minister of Education, Science and  Culture.</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2007 14:44:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ronald_Plasterk</link>
<guid>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ronald_Plasterk</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Feb 6, 2007 GSA Meeting Announcement</title>
<description>The Genetics Society of America's upcoming Genetic Analysis: Model Organisms to Human Biology Meeting will be held January 5-8, 2008 in San Diego, CA at the Town and Country Hotel.</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 6 Feb 2007 18:57:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.genetics-gsa.org/genetics/g-gsa/meetings-mohb.shtml</link>
<guid>http://www.genetics-gsa.org/genetics/g-gsa/meetings-mohb.shtml</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Jan 30, 2007 Acetylcholine Chapter Added to WormBook</title>
<description>Wormbook readers are invited to read our newly added chapter Acetylcholine in WormBook's Neurobiology and behavior section.</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2007 19:59:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_acetylcholine/acetylcholine.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_acetylcholine/acetylcholine.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Jan 26, 2007 EndNote version 8 import</title>
<description>A set of instructions for importing the entire WormBook reference set into Endnote v. 8 has been added to the WormBook website.</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2007 22:14:50 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/endnote/#v8</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/endnote/#v8</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Jan 24, 2007 RSS feed added</title>
<description>WormBook now provides an rss feed for worm researchers to remain up-to-date with the rapid addition of new chapters.</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2007 09:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/rss.xml</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/rss.xml</guid>
</item>


<item>
<title>Jan 23, 2007 Pharynx Organogenesis Chapter Added to WormBook</title>
<description>The C. elegans pharynx: a model for organogenesis has been added to the Developmental control section of WormBook. Readers are encouraged to visit this section to read this chapter and others pertaining to early developmental events.</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2007 08:23:48 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_organformation/organformation.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_organformation/organformation.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Jan 5, 2007 Gene expression changes associated with aging in C. elegans</title>
<description>The Post-embryonic development section of WormBook has been launched with the publication of  Gene expression changes associated with aging in C. elegans. Additional chapters related to the topics of aging and development will be upcoming.</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2007 14:07:22 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_geneexpressionaging/geneexpressionaging.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_geneexpressionaging/geneexpressionaging.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Dec 31, 2006 Happy New Year!  C. briggsae WormMethods added</title>
<description>Wormbook readers are invited to read our last new chapter before 2007 Caenorhabditis briggsae methods in WormBook's WormMethods section.</description>
<pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2006 23:59:59 GMT</pubDate>
<link>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_Cbriggsaemethods/Cbriggsaemethods.html</link>
<guid>http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_Cbriggsaemethods/Cbriggsaemethods.html</guid>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
