<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 10:</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Worms choose higher quality food.</emphasis> These graphs show the result of experiments in which worms were given the choice between two different foods. In <emphasis role="bold">A-C</emphasis>, small spots of bacteria of two different types were placed on a plate in the arrangements shown, then na&#x00EF;ve worms were placed in the center of the plate. After 1, 3, 9, and 27 hours, each worm was scored to see whether it was inside a bacterial spot, and if so, which type of bacteria. In each plot light gray is the percentage of worms in the higher quality food, dark gray those in lower quality food, and white those outside the food. <emphasis role="bold">A.</emphasis> Wild-type worms choosing between pairs selected from four different bacterial strains. <emphasis role="bold">B.</emphasis> Wild-type, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-5</ulink></emphasis> worms choosing between <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> strains HB101 and DA837. <emphasis role="bold">C.</emphasis> Wild-type, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-5</ulink></emphasis> choosing between <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> DA837 and <emphasis>Bacillus megaterium</emphasis>.  <emphasis role="bold">D.</emphasis> A different task, in which worms are required to leave one food source to find another. One strain of bacteria was placed in the center of a plate, while a second strain was placed in e circle completely surrounding the center spot. Worms were placed outside the circle, then the proportion in the center spot were scored after 7 or 21 hours. When the circle was made of low-quality food, worms were able to cross it to find high-quality food in the center. Reproduced, with permission, from <link linkend="bib71">Shtonda and Avery (2006)</link><!--: PMID 16354781-->.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>
