<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'feeding_fig01.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'feeding_fig02.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'feeding_fig03.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'feeding_fig04.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'feeding_fig05.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'feeding_fig06.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig7 SYSTEM 'feeding_fig07.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig8 SYSTEM 'feeding_fig08.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig9 SYSTEM 'feeding_fig09.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig10 SYSTEM 'feeding_fig10.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig11 SYSTEM 'feeding_fig11.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig12 SYSTEM 'feeding_fig12.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig13 SYSTEM 'feeding_fig13.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig14 SYSTEM 'feeding_fig14.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'feeding_fig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'feeding_fig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'feeding_fig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'feeding_fig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'feeding_fig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'feeding_fig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig7legend SYSTEM 'feeding_fig7leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig8legend SYSTEM 'feeding_fig8leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig9legend SYSTEM 'feeding_fig9leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig10legend SYSTEM 'feeding_fig10leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig11legend SYSTEM 'feeding_fig11leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig12legend SYSTEM 'feeding_fig12leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig13legend SYSTEM 'feeding_fig13leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig14legend SYSTEM 'feeding_fig14leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY feeding_refs SYSTEM 'feeding_ref.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="feeding_id">
<articleinfo>
<title><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> feeding<footnote>
<para>Edited by Erik M. Jorgensen. Last revised February 13, 2012. Published May 21, 2012. This chapter should be cited as: Avery, L. and You, Y.J. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> feeding (May 21, 2012), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.150.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2012 Leon Avery and Young-Jai You. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
</footnote>
</title>
<author>
<othername>Leon Avery<superscript>1</superscript><remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:lavery3@vcu.edu">lavery3@vcu.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark>, Young-Jai You<superscript>2</superscript></othername>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>1</superscript>Department of Physiology and Biophysics</orgname></affiliation>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>2</superscript>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Virginia</orgname></affiliation>
</author>
</articleinfo>
<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> feeding depends on the action of the pharynx, a neuromuscular pump that joins the mouth to the intestine. The pharyngeal muscle captures food&#x2014;bacteria&#x2014;and transports it back to the intestine. It accomplishes this through a combination of two motions, pumping and isthmus peristalsis. Pumping, the most visible and best understood of the two, is a cycle of contraction and relaxation that sucks in liquid from the surrounding environment along with suspended particles, then expels the liquid, trapping the particles. Pharyngeal muscle is capable of pumping without nervous system input, but during normal rapid feeding its timing is controlled by two pharyngeal motor neuron types. Isthmus peristalsis, a posterior moving wave of contraction of the muscle of the posterior isthmus, depends on a third motor neuron type.</para>
<para>Feeding motions are regulated by the presence and quality of food in the worm&#x0027;s environment. Some types of bacteria are better at supporting growth than others. Given a choice, worms are capable of identifying and seeking out higher-quality food. Food availability and quality also affect behavior in other ways. For instance, given all the high-quality food they can eat, worms eventually become satiated, stop eating and moving, and become quiescent.</para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Part 1: Feeding</title>
<sect2 id="sec2-1">
<title>Feeding: overview</title>
<para>The pharynx is a tubular pump responsible for sucking bacteria into the worm from outside, concentrating them, and grinding them up (<link linkend="bib25">Doncaster, 1962</link>: <link linkend="bib68">Seymour et al., 1983</link>). Its cellular and nuclear composition is shown in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>, and the arrangement of the cells is diagrammed in <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>. <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link> and the following anatomical description are based on EM reconstructions by <link linkend="bib1">Albertson and Thomson (1976</link><!--: PMID 8805-->). This review is concerned with two of the five cell types, the muscle cells and the neurons. The pharyngeal muscle is divided into three functional groups: the corpus, the isthmus, and the terminal bulb (TB) (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1b</link>).</para>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1.</emphasis> Cells and nuclei in the pharynx</title>
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<thead>
<row valign="bottom" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">Cell type</entry>
<entry align="left">Cells</entry>
<entry align="left">Nuclei</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">muscle</entry>
<entry align="left">20</entry>
<entry align="left">37</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">neurons</entry>
<entry align="left">20</entry>
<entry align="left">20</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">glands</entry>
<entry align="left">4</entry>
<entry align="left">5</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">epithelial cells</entry>
<entry align="left">9</entry>
<entry align="left">9</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="left">marginal cells</entry>
<entry align="left">7</entry>
<entry align="left">9</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">Total</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">60</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">80</emphasis></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The pharyngeal nervous system contains 20 neurons of 14 different types (8 bilaterally symmetric pairs and 6 unpaired) (<link linkend="bib1">Albertson and Thomson, 1976</link><!--: PMID 8805-->). Three of these 14 are particularly important for normal feeding. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink> is necessary and sufficient for normal isthmus peristalsis, and is essential for growth under some conditions (<link linkend="bib7">Avery and Horvitz, 1987</link><!--PMID 3690660-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M3;class=Cell" role="_blank">M3</ulink> control the timing of pumping: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> controls when a contraction starts (<link linkend="bib55">Raizen and Avery, 1994</link><!--PMID 8155316-->; <link linkend="bib57">Raizen et al., 1995</link><!--PMID 8601480-->), and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M3;class=Cell" role="_blank">M3</ulink> when it ends (<link linkend="bib5">Avery, 1993</link><!--PMID 8440973-->; <link linkend="bib55">Raizen and Avery, 1994</link><!--PMID 8155316-->). Surprisingly, these three neuron types are sufficient for nearly normal behavior in the laboratory: even when all 11 other neuron types are killed together, the worm grows well and shows only subtle feeding abnormalities.</para>
<para>Pharyngeal neurons contain both neuropeptides and small-molecule neurotransmitters. The most important of the small transmitters are acetylcholine, glutamate, and serotonin. What we know of their functions is described below. Neuropeptides are certain to play important roles, but they are still for the most part poorly understood. For more information about peptides and feeding see <link linkend="bib29">Franks et al. (2006</link><!--PMID 16862440-->) and <link linkend="bib48">Papaioannou et al. (2005</link><!--PMID 16187307-->).</para>
<para>Pharyngeal neurons lie under the basal lamina that surrounds the entire pharynx and isolates it from the rest of the worm, in indentations of the muscle cell membrane. Aside from the connections to the mouth and the intestine there are only two holes in the basal lamina, one on either side, through which the processes of a pair of extrapharyngeal neurons, the RIPs, pass to connect to the pharyngeal nervous system.</para>
<para>There are two feeding motions. The motion that gets food into the worm is called pumping (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). (The following description is based on <link linkend="bib6">Avery (1993</link><!--PMID 8462849-->) and references therein.) A pump begins with a near-simultaneous contraction of the muscles of the corpus, anterior isthmus, and terminal bulb. Since the pharyngeal muscles are radially oriented, contraction pulls the lumen open to a triangular cross-section, sucking in liquid and suspended bacteria from outside. Contraction is followed by a near-simultaneous relaxation, which expels liquid but traps bacteria. Correct timing of these motions is critical (<link linkend="bib5">Avery, 1993</link><!--: PMID 8440973-->). The second feeding motion, isthmus peristalsis, occurs shortly after some but not all pumps. It is a peristaltic contraction of the muscles of the posterior isthmus that carries food from the corpus to the TB (<link linkend="bib7">Avery and Horvitz, 1987</link><!--PMID 3690660-->).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>It was not at first obvious how particles are separated from liquid during pumping and transported posteriorly, since there is no obvious filter in the pharyngeal lumen. Avery and Shtonda (<link linkend="bib9">Avery and Shtonda, 2003</link><!--PMID 12796460-->) proposed that a slight difference in timing between corpus and isthmus contractions together with trapping of bacteria by the walls of the closed pharyngeal lumen could account for posteriorward transport. Fang-Yen and Avery (<link linkend="bib27">Fang-Yen et al., 2009</link><!--PMID 19903886-->), using high-speed video recordings confirmed some but not all parts of this model. In addition, they identified two filtering mechanisms that allow rough particle size-selection.</para>
<para>The pharynx must generate these two motions, pumping and isthmus peristalsis, at the right frequency and with the right timing. Pumping is the better understood of the two. Each contraction/relaxation cycle corresponds to a single pharyngeal muscle action potential. The action potential is produced through the sequential action of five ion channels: a nicotinic acetylcholine receptor activated by pharyngeal <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> motor neurons, a low-threshold voltage-gated calcium channel, a high-threshold voltage-gated calcium channel, a glutamate-gated chloride channel activated by pharyngeal <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M3;class=Cell" role="_blank">M3</ulink> motor neurons, and a voltage-gated potassium channel.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-2">
<title>The pharyngeal muscle action potential</title>
<para><link linkend="figure3">Figure 3a</link> shows a train of action potentials recorded from TB muscle (M. Wayne Davis, personal communication). The pharynx is quiet for the first half second, then begins to pump, first with a long-lasting (400 ms) action potential, followed by a regular series of shorter (150 ms) action potentials. Besides the shape of the typical pharyngeal muscle action potential, this figure shows that action potentials, and therefore pumping, are regulated in both frequency and duration. Both neurons and muscle-intrinsic molecules contribute to this regulation.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<sect3 id="sec3-1">
<title>Nicotinic acetylcholine receptor: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EAT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EAT-18;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-18</ulink></title>
<para>During rapid regular pumping each action potential is initiated by the firing of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> motor neurons, whose activity can be detected indirectly by means of the postsynaptic potentials they produce in muscle (<link linkend="bib55">Raizen and Avery, 1994</link><!--PMID 8155316-->; <link linkend="bib57">Raizen et al., 1995</link><!--PMID 8601480-->). Fast neurotransmission at the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink>&#x2192;pharyngeal muscle neuromuscular junction (NMJ) is mediated by acetylcholine acting on nicotinic receptors (<link linkend="bib45">McKay et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 15020415-->; <link linkend="bib55">Raizen and Avery, 1994</link><!--PMID 8155316-->; <link linkend="bib57">Raizen et al., 1995</link><!--PMID 8601480-->). In the presence of food adult worms pump 200&#x2013;300 times per minute on average, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-18;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-18</ulink></emphasis> are necessary for this rapid pumping. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> encodes a nicotinic receptor subunit, expressed in pharyngeal muscle and localized to the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink>&#x2192;corpus muscle NMJ (<link linkend="bib45">McKay et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 15020415-->). A functional <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EAT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-2</ulink>::GFP fusion is found only at this NMJ. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-18;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-18</ulink></emphasis> encodes a small novel single-pass transmembrane protein, also expressed in pharyngeal muscle, that is necessary for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EAT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-2</ulink> function, probably by direct binding to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EAT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-2</ulink>. &#x03B1;-bungarotoxin (a specific nicotinic receptor probe) binds to much of the pharyngeal muscle surface. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EAT-18;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-18</ulink> is necessary for this binding, but <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EAT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-2</ulink> is not (<link linkend="bib45">McKay et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 15020415-->), suggesting there are multiple pharyngeal muscle nicotinic receptors. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EAT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-2</ulink> is a subunit of one of them specific for the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> NMJ, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EAT-18;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-18</ulink> is necessary for the proper targeting or function of most or all of them. Alan Chiang (personal communication) has confirmed these hypotheses by showing that, in mutants lacking the calcium-activated potassium channel <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EAT-18;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-18</ulink> but not <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EAT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-2</ulink> is necessary for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink>&#x2192;TB muscle transmission.</para>
<para>Neither <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib57">Raizen et al., 1995</link><!--PMID 8601480-->) nor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> (<link linkend="bib8">Avery and Horvitz, 1989</link><!--: PMID 2642006-->) is necessary for pumping. In the absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> function, the pharyngeal muscle will spontaneously generate action potentials, which lead to functional pumping. Pumping in the absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> function is slow and irregular, and the worms grow slowly, but are nonetheless viable in the lab. (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> might of course be more important in the wild&#x2014;in the lab, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is grown literally swimming in food.) This slow, irregular, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink>-independent pumping may also occur in normal worms in the absence of food. It is not known how <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink>-independent action potentials are initiated. Based on ion substitution experiments, Franks et al. (<link linkend="bib30">Franks et al., 2002</link><!--PMID 11826060-->) proposed the existence of a hyperpolarization-induced sodium channel, functionally somewhat similar to that of vertebrate cardiac muscle, that might serve this purpose. (See also <link linkend="bib81">Vinogradova et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16622683-->). They also suggested that a voltage-gated sodium channel contributes to the action potential. Neither of these channels has been identified molecularly.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-2">
<title>T-type calcium channel: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CCA-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CCA-1</ulink></title>
<para>Low threshold-activated or T-type calcium channels are postulated to mediate a variety of bursting and rhythmic electrical firing events. They allow excitable cells to respond to small depolarizations from rest, and mediate low-threshold calcium spikes (<link linkend="bib50">Perez-Reyes, 2003</link><!--PMID 12506128-->). <link linkend="bib70">Shtonda and Avery (2005</link><!--PMID 15914661-->) showed that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cca-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cca-1</ulink></emphasis> encodes the &#x03B1;<subscript>1</subscript> (pore-forming) subunit of a T-type <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ca;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ca</ulink><superscript>2+</superscript> channel active at the beginning of the pharyngeal muscle action potential. Steger et al. (<link linkend="bib75">Steger et al., 2005</link><!--PMID 15914662-->) showed that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cca-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cca-1</ulink></emphasis> is necessary for efficient initiation of action potentials in response to stimulation by the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> motor neuron. When wild-type <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cca-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cca-1</ulink></emphasis> is absent, the depolarizing phase of the pharyngeal action potential tends to plateau or stall near &#x2212;30mV, the voltage at which the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CCA-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CCA-1</ulink> channel is likely to be activated. Therefore, loss of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cca-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cca-1</ulink></emphasis> function decreases the chance that excitatory input from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> will successfully trigger an action potential, and reduces the ability of an animal to take in food.</para>
<para>Thus, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CCA-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CCA-1</ulink> T-type calcium channel boosts the excitatory effect of synaptic input, allowing for reliable and rapid depolarization and contraction of the pharyngeal muscle. However, pharyngeal muscle employs alternative strategies for initiating action potentials in certain cases of compromised <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> motor neuron function as in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib70">(Shtonda and Avery, 2005</link><!--PMID 15914661-->; <link linkend="bib75">Steger et al., 2005</link><!--PMID 15914662-->).</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-3">
<title>L-type Calcium Channel: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EGL-19;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-19</ulink></title>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-19</ulink></emphasis> encodes the &#x03B1;<subscript>1</subscript> subunit of a homolog of vertebrate L-type voltage-activated <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ca;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ca</ulink><superscript>2+</superscript> channels and plays a pivotal role in regulating muscle excitation and contraction in all <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> muscles. Raymond Lee (<link linkend="bib42">Lee et al., 1997</link><!--PMID 9321386-->) isolated several <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-19</ulink></emphasis> mutants and sorted them into three classes: (1) myotonic group (semidominant, gain-of-function mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-19</ulink></emphasis> cause myotonia), mutant muscle action potentials are prolonged and the relaxation delayed; (2) flaccid group, partial loss-of function mutations cause slow muscle depolarization and feeble contraction; and (3) lethal group, the most severe loss-of-function mutants (including nulls) lack all muscle contraction and die as embryos. <link linkend="bib42">Lee et al. (1997</link><!--PMID 9321386-->) localized two myotonic mutations in the sixth membrane-spanning domain of the first repeat (IS6) region, which has been shown to be responsible for voltage-dependent inactivation. A third myotonic mutation implicates IIIS4, a region involved in sensing plasma-membrane voltage change, in the inactivation process.</para>
<para><link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link> summarizes how the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EAT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-2</ulink> nicotinic acetylcholine receptor, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CCA-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CCA-1</ulink> T-type <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ca;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ca</ulink><superscript>2+</superscript> channel, and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EGL-19;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-19</ulink> L-type <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ca;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ca</ulink><superscript>2+</superscript> channel could cooperate to produce the upstroke of the pharyngeal muscle action potential.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 4</phrase>
</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-4">
<title>Glutamate gated chloride channel: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVR-15;class=Protein" role="_blank">AVR-15</ulink></title>
<para>The timing of pharyngeal muscle relaxation is important for proper trapping of bacteria (<link linkend="bib9">Avery and Shtonda, 2003</link><!--PMID 12796460-->). A bilaterally symmetric pair of pharyngeal motor neurons, the M3s, which synapse on the corpus muscle (<link linkend="bib1">Albertson and Thomson, 1976</link><!--: PMID 8805-->), modulate the timing of relaxation. The M3s generate fast inhibitory postsynaptic potentials (IPSPs) in the contracted pharyngeal muscle. When the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M3;class=Cell" role="_blank">M3</ulink> neurons are ablated with a laser, the IPSPs disappear and the muscle contractions have a longer average duration (<link linkend="bib5">Avery, 1993</link><!--PMID 8440973-->; <link linkend="bib55">Raizen and Avery, 1994</link><!--PMID 8155316-->). Two genes were discovered to be necessary for M3&#x2192;muscle transmission. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-4</ulink></emphasis> is necessary presynaptically in all glutamatergic neurons and encodes a vesicular glutamate transporter, which loads glutamate into synaptic vesicles (<link linkend="bib12">Bellocchio et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 10938000-->; <link linkend="bib23">Dent et al., 1997</link><!--PMID 9312045-->; <link linkend="bib43">Lee et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 9870947-->; <link linkend="bib55">Raizen and Avery, 1994</link><!--PMID 8155316-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=avr-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis>, a gene that confers sensitivity to the drug ivermectin on worms, is necessary postsynaptically for a functional <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M3;class=Cell" role="_blank">M3</ulink> synapse and for the hyperpolarizing effect of glutamate on pharyngeal muscle (<link linkend="bib23">Dent et al., 1997</link><!--PMID 9312045-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=avr-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis> encodes two alternatively spliced channel subunits that share ligand binding and transmembrane domains and are members of the family of glutamate-gated chloride channel subunits. An <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=avr-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-15</ulink></emphasis>-encoded subunit forms a homomeric channel that is ivermectin-sensitive and glutamate-gated. These results indicate that: (1) an ivermectin-sensitive chloride channel mediates fast inhibitory glutamatergic neuromuscular transmission; and (2) a nematocidal property of ivermectin derives from its activity as an agonist of glutamate-gated chloride channels in essential excitable cells such as those of the pharynx. In fact, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVR-15;class=Protein" role="_blank">AVR-15</ulink> is one of three targets of ivermectin; the others are encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=avr-14;class=Gene" role="_blank">avr-14</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=glc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">glc-1</ulink></emphasis>, which also encode glutamate-gated chloride channel subunits. Ivermectin acting on any of these three is sufficient to kill a worm (<link linkend="bib24">Dent et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 10716995-->). A crystal structure of ivermectin bound to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GLC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">GLC-1</ulink> was recently published (<link linkend="bib32">Hibbs and Gouaux, 2011</link><!--PMID 21572436-->).</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVR-15;class=Protein" role="_blank">AVR-15</ulink> is a member of the family of ligand-gated chloride channels, which also includes vertebrate glycine and GABA-A receptors (<link linkend="bib4">Arena et al., 1991</link><!--PMID 1716730-->; <link linkend="bib23">Dent et al., 1997</link><!--PMID 9312045-->). Although glutamate-gated chloride channels are found in many animals, vertebrates lack them, and the vertebrate ligand-gated chloride channels are far less sensitive to ivermectin than are glutamate-gated chloride channels. This explains why ivermectin is relatively harmless to mammals even though it is effective against nematodes and some other parasitic animals.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-5">
<title>Potassium Channel: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EXP-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EXP-2</ulink></title>
<para>The most unusual of the pharyngeal ion channels is <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EXP-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EXP-2</ulink>. EXP-2 is a member of the Kv family of voltage-gated potassium channels. The phenotypes of loss-of-function and gain-of-function mutations (<link linkend="bib22">Davis et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 10617464-->) suggested that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=exp-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">exp-2</ulink></emphasis> encodes a subunit of the negative <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=spike;class=Cell" role="_blank">spike</ulink> channel which mediates fast repolarization of pharyngeal muscle, first identified in the pharynx of the large parasitic nematode <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis> by <link linkend="bib15">Byerly and Masuda (1979</link><!--: PMID 469718-->). Voltage-clamp recordings confirm this: wild-type <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> pharynxes have an outward current whose properties match those of Byerly and Masuda&#x0027;s negative <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=spike;class=Cell" role="_blank">spike</ulink> current (<link linkend="bib70">Shtonda and Avery, 2005</link><!--PMID 15914661-->) and of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EXP-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EXP-2</ulink> expressed in oocytes (<link linkend="bib28">Fleischhauer et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 10632580-->)&#x2013;it turns on when voltage changes from positive to negative. An <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=exp-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">exp-2</ulink></emphasis> null mutant lacks this current (<link linkend="bib22">Davis et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 10617464-->; <link linkend="bib70">Shtonda and Avery, 2005</link><!--PMID 15914661-->).</para>
<para><emphasis>exp-</emphasis>2 was first identified on the basis of a gain-of-function mutation that changes a cysteine at position 480 in the S6 transmembrane helix to a tyrosine (<link linkend="bib60">Reiner and Thomas, 1995</link><!--PMID 7666193-->; <link linkend="bib76">Thomas, 1990</link> <!--PMID-->). In oocytes the mutant channel was unable to close fully, explaining the mutant phenotype (<link linkend="bib22">Davis et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 10617464-->). Modeling the S5/pore/S6 region of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EXP-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EXP-2</ulink> on the Kcsa structure suggested that the rotation of the S6 helix that accompanies channel closing (<link linkend="bib51">Perozo et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 10390363-->) was compatible with a cysteine at position 480, but would be blocked by a large tyrosine side chain bumping into the S5 helix. <link linkend="bib26">Espinosa et al. (2001</link><!--PMID 11479343-->) showed that indeed small amino acids at position 480 give wild-type channel function, but large ones prevent channel closing. Replacement of a conserved glycine in the S5 helix opposite C480 with bulky amino acids also produces a channel that cannot close fully.</para>
<para>Channels of the Kv family open when the membrane depolarizes. Typically inactivation follows opening, but it is slower. Thus the channel will conduct when membrane potential goes from negative to positive (as the channel is open but not yet inactivated for a while), but not when the membrane repolarizes, since in this direction the channel closes faster than it deinactivates. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EXP-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EXP-2</ulink>, however, inverts this logic: it activates rather slowly, but inactivates very rapidly (<link linkend="bib28">Fleischhauer et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 10632580-->). Thus, it conducts only when membrane potential goes from positive to negative. Since the opening of the channel allows potassium to exit the cell, causing membrane potential to become more negative, which causes more <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EXP-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EXP-2</ulink> channels to open, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EXP-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EXP-2</ulink> mediates a fast regenerative negative-going current <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=spike;class=Cell" role="_blank">spike</ulink>, entirely analogous to the positive-going sodium current <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=spike;class=Cell" role="_blank">spike</ulink> that underlies the upstroke of a typical neuronal action potential (<link linkend="bib15">Byerly and Masuda, 1979</link><!--: PMID-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EXP-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">EXP-2</ulink> can thus remain dormant during an action potential of unpredictable length, yet efficiently return the muscle cell to resting potential when membrane potential drops below its threshold, because of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M3;class=Cell" role="_blank">M3</ulink> firing, for instance. It is thus well adapted to end action potentials of varying duration (<link linkend="bib70">Shtonda and Avery, 2005</link><!--PMID 15914661-->). Although mammals do not have a negative <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=spike;class=Cell" role="_blank">spike</ulink> channel, a distantly related member of the Kv family, the HERG potassium channel, has a similar inversion of gating and inactivation kinetics and plays a similar role in the heart. Pharmacological or genetic disruptions in HERG function lead to long-lasting cardiac action potentials, a dangerous condition called long QT syndrome, which can lead to fatal arrhythmia (<link linkend="bib20">Curran et al., 1995</link><!--PMID 7889573-->; <link linkend="bib66">Sanguinetti et al., 1995</link><!--PMID 7663486-->; <link linkend="bib78">Tseng, 2001</link><!--PMID 11343409-->).</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-6">
<title>Gap junctions couple pharyngeal muscles</title>
<para>During a pump, the muscles of the corpus, anterior isthmus, and TB all contract together and electrophysiological recordings show that action potentials in the corpus and TB begin simultaneously (<link linkend="bib55">Raizen and Avery, 1994</link><!--PMID 8155316-->). However, as described above, during rapid pumping action potentials are initiated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> firing and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> does not have output onto TB muscle. Furthermore, corpus and TB contractions remain synchronized even when all pharyngeal neurons are killed (<link linkend="bib8">Avery and Horvitz, 1989</link><!--PMID 2642006-->). This suggests that, like vertebrate cardiac muscle cells, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> pharyngeal muscles are electrically coupled by gap junctions. In fact, dye injected into one pharyngeal muscle cell diffuses into others in seconds (<link linkend="bib73">Starich et al., 1996</link><!--PMID 8707836-->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, however, does not have any genes encoding connexins, the subunits of most vertebrate gap junctions. This apparent contradiction was resolved with the identification of the innexins, a family of gap junction-forming proteins found in invertebrates (<link linkend="bib52">Phelan et al., 1998</link><!--PMID 9769729-->). In mutants lacking one of these, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EAT-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-5</ulink>, corpus and TB contractions are not synchronized, and dye injected into the TB does not diffuse into the corpus (<link linkend="bib73">Starich et al., 1996</link><!--PMID 8707836-->).</para>
<para>Interestingly, uncoupled corpus and TB muscle may be the ancestral state. Chiang et al. (<link linkend="bib17">Chiang et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16651552-->) found that in most free-living nematode species, corpus and TB can contract independently. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> controlled the corpus in all species, but in species in which the TB was not strongly electrically coupled to the corpus, TB contractions were controlled by motor neuron <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink>. In wild-type <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink> controls isthmus peristalsis (see below) but has no detectable effect on TB. However, in a mutant lacking the BK <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ca;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ca</ulink><superscript>2+</superscript>-activated potassium channel <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink> is able to excite TB muscle (<link linkend="bib17">Chiang et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16651552-->). This is consistent with other studies suggesting that BK channels act presynaptically to suppress synaptic transmission (<link linkend="bib21">Davies et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 14675531-->; <link linkend="bib49">Pattillo et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11226687-->; <link linkend="bib64">Roberts et al., 1990</link><!--PMID 1700083-->; <link linkend="bib65">Robitaille and Charlton, 1992</link><!--PMID 1370323-->; <link linkend="bib82">Wang et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11738032-->). Apparently in wild-type <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink>&#x2192;TB transmission is suppressed, but the ancestral state can be recovered by increasing synaptic transmission by knocking out <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis>.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-7">
<title>Nervous system control of pumping</title>
<para>The rate of pumping determines the amount of food intake and the rate of growth. Pumping rate is determined most directly by the motor neuron <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink>, whose firing initiates pharyngeal muscle contraction. Mutants defective in neurotransmission from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> to pharyngeal muscle have the appearance of severely starved worms and retarded growth due to the reduced pumping rate (<link linkend="bib45">McKay et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 15020415-->; <link linkend="bib57">Raizen et al., 1995</link><!--PMID 8601480-->). This has been shown by both genetic and laser killing studies (<link linkend="bib8">Avery and Horvitz, 1989</link><!--PMID 2642006-->; <link linkend="bib57">Raizen et al., 1995</link><!--PMID 8601480-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> is controlled by two factors: food sensed (probably mechanically) by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> itself (<link linkend="bib8">Avery and Horvitz, 1989</link><!--PMID 2642006-->; <link linkend="bib57">Raizen et al., 1995</link><!--PMID 8601480-->) and serotonin (<link linkend="bib10">Avery and Thomas, 1997</link><!--PMID 21413237-->; <link linkend="bib33">Hobson et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16204223-->). When food is present, mechanosensation and serotonin signal redundantly on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> in order to cause fast pumping.</para>
<para>Electron micrograph (EM) reconstruction shows that of the 14 pharyngeal neuron types, only I1 has chemical synapses to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> (<link linkend="bib1">Albertson and Thomson, 1976</link><!--: PMID 8805-->). I1 is also the only pharyngeal neuron that receives direct inputs from the extrapharyngeal nervous system, specifically from the collection of head ganglia called the nerve ring where most neurons and their processes are concentrated, the worm equivalent of the brain. Food and serotonin can still stimulate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> when I1 is killed with a laser (<link linkend="bib57">Raizen et al., 1995</link><!--PMID 8601480-->, David Raizen, personal communication), suggesting that in the presence of food, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> is the master neuron responsible for fast pumping. However, I1 might still mediate fine tuning of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> firing. One example is I1 regulation of basal pumping rate. In the absence of food, well-fed worms pump at a low basal rate, whose purpose David Raizen (personal communication) has speculated is to sample the environment. This basal pumping rate was significantly decreased when I1 was killed with a laser. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> ablation also decreases basal pumping. Killing both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> and I1 has the same effect as killing either alone. These data together with knowledge from EM reconstructions that I1 synapses on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> suggest that basal pumping probably results from I1 stimulating <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink>.</para>
<para>In the absence of food, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> activity is normally low. However, exogenous serotonin causes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> to fire as fast in the absence of food as in the presence of food. This is one of several examples of serotonin mimicking the effects of food on behavior (<link linkend="bib34">Horvitz et al., 1982</link><!--PMID 6805073-->). Two pharyngeal serotonin receptors have been identified; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SER-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-1</ulink> in the pharyngeal muscle (<link linkend="bib77">Tsalik et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 14568548-->) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SER-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-7</ulink> in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> is not stimulated by serotonin in a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ser-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">ser-7</ulink></emphasis> knockout mutant (<link linkend="bib33">Hobson et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16204223-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SER-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">SER-7</ulink> is thus the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/MC">MC</ulink> serotonin receptor.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-3">
<title>Isthmus peristalsis</title>
<para>The second feeding motion, isthmus peristalsis, is less well understood. It is a posterior-moving peristaltic contraction of the muscles of the posterior half of the isthmus, which carries food accumulated in the anterior half of the isthmus back to the TB (<link linkend="bib7">Avery and Horvitz, 1987</link><!--: PMID 3690660-->). This always occurs immediately following a pump, but it doesn&#x0027;t happen after every pump&#x2014;during rapid pumping, only about one out of four pumps is followed by an isthmus peristalsis. A posterior-moving <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ca;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ca</ulink><superscript>2+</superscript> wave occurs in the posterior isthmus following some but not all pumps (<link linkend="bib69">Shimozono et al., 2004</link><!--PMID 15088067-->) and is likely to correspond to isthmus peristalsis, but the calcium wave has not been directly shown to correlate with contraction. The anterior half of the isthmus, in contrast, contracts with every pump, and its contraction, although slightly delayed, overlaps that of the corpus and TB (<link linkend="bib9">Avery and Shtonda, 2003</link><!--PMID 12796460-->). Posterior isthmus peristalsis is absolutely dependent on motor neuron <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink>, but anterior isthmus contraction is unchanged when <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink> is killed (<link linkend="bib7">Avery and Horvitz, 1987</link><!--: PMID 3690660-->). Furthermore, since as described above corpus and TB contractions are synchronized by electrical coupling and since the isthmus is between them, the entire isthmus must be electrically excited at every pump, and yet only the anterior isthmus contracts at this time. The isthmus contains three pm5 muscle cells, each of which runs its entire length (<link linkend="bib1">Albertson and Thomson, 1976</link><!--: PMID 8805-->), so the differing motions of the anterior and posterior isthmus are subcellular specializations.</para>
<para>Isthmus peristalsis is an all-or-none event and, since it depends on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink>, it is tempting to speculate that an isthmus peristalsis occurs only if <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink> fires an action potential. This hypothesis receives some support from electrophysiological recordings from <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants, in which an <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink> excitatory postsynaptic potential can sometimes be detected immediately following a pump, at just the time that isthmus peristalsis might occur (<link linkend="bib17">Chiang et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16651552-->), but there is no direct evidence correlating <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink> firing with isthmus peristalsis. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink> is cholinergic as shown by its expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-17;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-17</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes the vesicular acetylcholine transporter (<link linkend="bib2">Alfonso et al., 1993</link><!--PMID 8342028-->; <link linkend="bib80">Varoqui et al., 1994</link><!--PMID 8143858-->). The acetylcholine agonist arecoline can cause posterior isthmus muscle to contract in worms whose <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink> neurons have been killed with a laser, although the contractions are uncoordinated (Bomi Song, personal communication), and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink> EPSPs seen in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants depend on cholinergic transmission. This suggests that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink> acts, at least in part, by releasing acetylcholine onto pharyngeal muscle. However, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/search/anatomy_term/M4">M4</ulink> also expresses neuropeptides (<link linkend="bib53">Pocock and Hobert, 2010</link><!--PMID 20400959-->), and it is likely that these also contribute.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Part 2: Effects of food on behavior</title>
<sect2 id="sec2-4">
<title>Hunger</title>
<sect3 id="sec3-8">
<title>Muscarinic signaling: Arecoline sensitivity</title>
<para>The gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-11</ulink></emphasis>, identified by a mutation that makes <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> hypersensitive to the muscarinic agonist arecoline (<link linkend="bib14">Brundage et al., 1996</link><!--PMID 8630258-->), was cloned by Robatzek et al. (<link linkend="bib63">Robatzek et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11250160-->). At the same time two other labs knocked out the gene (<link linkend="bib16">Chase et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11250150-->; <link linkend="bib79">van der Linden et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11333232-->), which they called <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpb-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpb-2</ulink></emphasis>. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpb-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpb-2</ulink></emphasis> encodes the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog of G<subscript>&#x03B2;</subscript>5. Vertebrate G<subscript>&#x03B2;</subscript>5 binds to RGS proteins that contain a G-&#x03B3;-like (GGL) domain, allowing them to inhibit G&#x03B1; by stimulating the intrinsic GTPase activity (<link linkend="bib54">Posner et al., 1999</link><!--PMID 10521509-->; <link linkend="bib72">Snow et al., 1998</link><!--PMID 9789084-->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has two GGL-RGS proteins, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EGL-10;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-10</ulink>, which inhibits G<subscript>o</subscript>&#x03B1;, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EAT-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-16</ulink>, which inhibits G<subscript>q</subscript>&#x03B1;. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GPB-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPB-2</ulink> is necessary for the function of both (<link linkend="bib16">Chase et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11250150-->; <link linkend="bib63">Robatzek et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11250160-->; <link linkend="bib79">van der Linden et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11333232-->) (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 5</phrase>
</textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
<para>G<subscript>q</subscript>&#x03B1; and G<subscript>o</subscript>&#x03B1; are opposing elements of a regulatory circuit that operates in many <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> cells. The action of G<subscript>q</subscript>&#x03B1; is normally restrained, directly by the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GPB-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">GPB-2</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EAT-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">EAT-16</ulink> RGS complex, and indirectly by G<subscript>o</subscript>&#x03B1; inhibition of its downstream effects through diacylglycerol kinase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DGK-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">DGK-1</ulink>. Steger and coworkers (<link linkend="bib63">Robatzek et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11250160-->; <link linkend="bib74">Steger and Avery, 2004</link><!--PMID 15238517-->) showed that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpb-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpb-2</ulink></emphasis> is hypersensitive to the muscarinic agonist arecoline because of unrestrained G<subscript>q</subscript>&#x03B1; activation in pharyngeal muscle in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpb-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpb-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants. There are three muscarinic receptor genes in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome: <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gar-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gar-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gar-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gar-2</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gar-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">gar-3</ulink></emphasis>, and Steger and Avery identified <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GAR-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">GAR-3</ulink> as the relevant muscarinic receptor by isolating a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gar-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">gar-3</ulink></emphasis> mutation as a suppressor of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpb-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpb-2</ulink></emphasis> hypersensitivity to arecoline. They also found that atropine, a specific muscarinic antagonist, protects <emphasis>gpb-2(ad541)</emphasis> worms against arecoline, confirming that hypersensitivity requires muscarinic receptor activation. Furthermore, overexpression of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GAR-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">GAR-3</ulink> makes worms hypersensitive to arecoline. In support of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GAR-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">GAR-3</ulink> function in pharyngeal muscle as a G<subscript>q</subscript> coupled receptor, a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gar-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">gar-3</ulink></emphasis> reporter fusion is expressed in pharyngeal muscle, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GAR-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">GAR-3</ulink> expressed in heterologous systems activates phospholipase C (PLC) and protein kinase C (PKC) (<link linkend="bib41">Lee et al., 2001</link><!--PMID 11418117-->; <link linkend="bib47">Min et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 10854271-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gar-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gar-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gar-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gar-2</ulink></emphasis> mutations have no effect on arecoline hypersensitivity.</para>
<para>The immediate effect of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GAR-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">GAR-3</ulink> pathway is to increase muscle contraction, by increasing both the duration of the muscle action potential and the strength of contraction (<link linkend="bib74">Steger and Avery, 2004</link><!--PMID 15238517-->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gar-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">gar-3</ulink></emphasis> mutants the TB action potential is briefer than in wild type. In <emphasis>gpb-2(ad541)</emphasis> worms, arecoline causes the pharynx to contract and stay contracted for as long as a minute, and a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gar-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">gar-3</ulink></emphasis> mutation prevents this hypercontraction. However, EPGs show that action potentials continue during the hypercontraction. That the pharynx remains contracted between action potentials under these conditions shows that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GAR-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">GAR-3</ulink> also increases contraction in a membrane potential-independent way.</para>
<para>There are no data that suggest a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gar-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gar-1</ulink></emphasis> function in the pharynx. However, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gar-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gar-2</ulink></emphasis> is likely to function in neurons for the following two reasons: (1) A <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gar-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gar-2</ulink>::GFP</emphasis> fusion is expressed exclusively in the nervous system (pharyngeal and extrapharyngeal); and (2) <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gar-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gar-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants are hypersensitive to the acetylcholinesterase inhibitor aldicarb, an extensively characterized phenotype that results from increased synaptic release of acetylcholine (<link linkend="bib59">Rand and Nonet, 1997</link><!--PMID 21413238-->). This suggests that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=GAR-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">GAR-2</ulink> inhibits acetylcholine release. Most neurons contain receptors for their own neurotransmitters that mediate feedback inhibition&#x2014;this may be one function of GAR-2.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-9">
<title>Muscarinic signaling as hunger signal</title>
<para>Hunger is the internal state that results from starvation and that motivates the behavioral response. Hungry animals seek food, increase exploratory behavior, increase alertness and feed when food is available. What mediates the changes in behavior? You et al. found that the muscarinic receptor &#x2192; MAPK (Mitogen-Activated Protein Kinase) pathway is part of hunger signaling in the pharynx (<link linkend="bib84">You et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16581001-->): the activation of this pathway by starvation can be detected by phospho-specific antibody to MAPK. Muscarinic signaling during starvation causes pharyngeal muscle to undergo specialized changes, which probably prepare it to encounter food later. Moreover, overactivation of this pathway in the sensitized mutant <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpb-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpb-2</ulink></emphasis> causes lethality due to a pharyngeal muscle change that directly interferes with feeding motions, suggesting that fine-tuned regulation of this pathway is essential for worm survival during starvation.</para>
<para>To understand the purpose of the muscarinic signaling to MAPK pathway during starvation, You et al. measured pumping rate (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>). Wild type worms initially pump slowly when they are taken off food, but they increase pumping rate gradually in the first 2 hours of starvation. When the pharyngeal muscle GAR-3&#x2192;MPK-1 pathway is blocked with a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gar-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">gar-3</ulink></emphasis> mutation, the increase in pumping rate is reduced. Conversely, in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpb-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpb-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants, in which the pathway is hyperactive, pumping rate increases more on starvation. These data suggest that activation of the muscarinic receptor during starvation contributes to the increase in starvation-induced pharyngeal activity.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig6" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 6</phrase>
</textobject> &fig6legend;</mediaobject>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-10">
<title>Muscarinic signal and autophagy</title>
<para>By what molecular mechanisms does the activation of muscarinic receptor &#x2192; MAPK pathway allow worms to cope with starvation? Kang et al. (<link linkend="bib38">Kang et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17785524-->) found that the pathway activates autophagy, helping worms to survive starvation, and that excessive autophagy during starvation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpb-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpb-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants kills the animals, contributing to their hypersensitivity to starvation.</para>
<para>Autophagy is a major pathway used to degrade long-lived proteins and organelles. It is thought to promote both cell and organism survival by providing fundamental building blocks to maintain energy homeostasis during starvation. Under different conditions, however, autophagy may instead act to promote cell death through an autophagic cell death pathway distinct from apoptosis. Kang et al. (<link linkend="bib38">Kang et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17785524-->) found that autophagy can also promote survival or cause death of the whole organism. Physiological levels of autophagy act to promote survival in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> during starvation, whereas insufficient or excessive levels of autophagy contribute to death (<link linkend="figure7">Figure 7</link>). When autophagy is inhibited during starvation, it decreases survival of wild-type worms (<link linkend="figure7">Figure 7</link>). In contrast, in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gpb-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpb-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants, in which muscarinic signaling cannot be down-regulated, starvation induces excessive autophagy in pharyngeal muscles, which in turn, causes damage that may contribute to death (<link linkend="figure7">Figure 7B</link>).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure7" xreflabel="Figure 7">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig7" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 7</phrase>
</textobject> &fig7legend;</mediaobject>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-5">
<title>Food seeking</title>
<para>Shtonda and Avery (<link linkend="bib71">Shtonda and Avery, 2006</link><!--PMID 16354781-->) showed that worms are able to distinguish food based on quality (operationally defined as ability to support growth) and to seek out higher quality food.</para>
<sect3 id="sec3-11">
<title>Food quality</title>
<para>Hydrodynamic simulation (<ulink url="http://elegans.som.vcu.edu/~leon/pharynx_sim/">http://elegans.som.vcu.edu/~leon/pharynx_sim/</ulink>; <link linkend="bib9">Avery and Shtonda, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12796460-->) to understand how bacteria are transported within the pharynx led to a prediction: large bacteria would be poor food. Shtonda (<link linkend="bib9">Avery and Shtonda, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12796460-->; <link linkend="bib71">Shtonda and Avery, 2006</link><!--PMID 16354781-->) isolated bacteria from soil samples and tested them for their ability to support <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> growth. He defined <emphasis>food quality</emphasis> as the ability of a food to support <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> growth, as measured by growth rate: the inverse of the time for a worm to grow from hatching to adulthood. (Growth rates range from approximately 0.48/day on the best food to 0.) <link linkend="figure8">Figure 8</link> shows the almost perfect inverse correlation between bacterial size and food quality: big bacteria are poor food. There is one conspicuous exception: <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> strain DA837. It is the same size as <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> HB101 but a far worse food source because DA837 bacteria clump, making the effective size of the bacteria bigger than an individual bacterium.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure8" xreflabel="Figure 8">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig8" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 8</phrase>
</textobject> &fig8legend;</mediaobject>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-12">
<title>Food-seeking behavior: leaving</title>
<para>Shtonda and Avery (<link linkend="bib71">Shtonda and Avery, 2006</link><!--PMID 16354781-->) characterized two behaviors that allow worms to find high quality food: (1) leaving, in which a worm leaves a poor food in search of better, and (2) preference, in which worms given a choice between two foods will choose the higher quality one. Worms that have found food are reluctant to leave, but if the food is of poor quality, they will do so. <link linkend="figure9">Figure 9</link> shows that naive worms (hatched in the absence of food and starved until the assay) will leave food that can&#x0027;t support growth at a rate of 0.4/day or better. Time courses show that leaving probability P<subscript>L</subscript> reaches its steady-state value within ten minutes, suggesting that assessment of food quality happens quickly. P<subscript>L</subscript> depends on the worms as well as the food: <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-5</ulink></emphasis> mutants show a substantial probability of leaving DA837, while wild-type worms will not. Since the direct effects of mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-5</ulink></emphasis> are specific to the pharynx, this suggests that assessment of food quality depends on something that occurs in or past the pharynx.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure9" xreflabel="Figure 9">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig9" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 9</phrase>
</textobject> &fig9legend;</mediaobject>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-13">
<title>Food-seeking behavior: preference</title>
<para>To test whether worms would seek out better food (showing preference), Shtonda (<link linkend="bib71">Shtonda and Avery, 2006</link><!--PMID 16354781-->) placed several hundred na&#x00EF;ve L1s on plates containing spots of two different types of bacteria. The distribution of worms at later times is shown in <link linkend="figure10">Figure 10</link>. Without exception, more worms are found in the better food. The strength of the preference usually correlates with the disparity in food quality. Significantly, preference is usually higher for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-5</ulink></emphasis> mutant worms than for wild-type and is never lower.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure10" xreflabel="Figure 10">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig10" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 10</phrase>
</textobject> &fig10legend;</mediaobject>
<para>A simple explanation for preference would be that it is just a consequence of differences in leaving probability. If worms leave poor food frequently and good food rarely, they will, on average, spend more time in the good food than the poor. But a quantitative argument shows that differences in na&#x00EF;ve leaving probability cannot be the whole story. Preferences can be very strong: ratios near 100 are routinely observed. For instance, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants show a 200-fold preference for DA837 over <emphasis>B. megaterium</emphasis>. The ratio of na&#x00EF;ve P<subscript>L</subscript>&#x0027;s, however, is only 0.23/0.062 = 3.7 (<link linkend="figure9">Figure 9</link>). The accumulation in the better of two foods cannot be explained solely by the reactions of the worms to the individual foods considered separately. Somehow a comparison is being made.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-14">
<title>Experience-dependence</title>
<para>Worms modify their behavior depending on their previous experience of food quality (<link linkend="bib9">Avery and Shtonda, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12796460-->; <link linkend="bib71">Shtonda and Avery, 2006</link><!--PMID 16354781-->). Worms grown for 3 hrs on high-quality food then presented with medium-quality food were dissatisfied&#x2014;they left the mediocre food at high frequency. But when worms were presented with the same mediocre food after conditioning on low-quality food they were satisfied&#x2014;they left the mediocre food at low frequency (<link linkend="figure11">Figure 11A</link>). Likewise, in a biased preference assay in which worms are required to cross a ring of medium quality food to find good food, worms conditioned on high-quality food performed better (<link linkend="figure11">Figure 11B</link>). Furthermore, Shtonda found that the extrapharyngeal interneuron AIY is critical for this behavior. When AIY was inactivated either by mutation or laser-killing, the worms were strongly biased towards dwelling (the food-exploiting locomotory behavior (<link linkend="bib31">Fujiwara et al., 2002</link><!--PMID 12495624-->)) and away from roaming (food-seeking), as if they perceived the food to be of higher quality than it was (<link linkend="bib71">Shtonda and Avery, 2006</link><!--PMID 16354781-->).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure11" xreflabel="Figure 11">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig11" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 11</phrase>
</textobject> &fig11legend;</mediaobject>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-6">
<title>Satiety</title>
<sect3 id="sec3-15">
<title>Satiety quiescence</title>
<para>Shtonda&#x0027;s discovery that worms respond to food quality led to the discovery of another feeding behavior called satiety quiescence. Satiated animals of various species stop eating, decrease exploratory behavior and often fall asleep, a pattern called the &#x2018;behavioral sequence of satiety&#x2019; (<link linkend="bib3">Antin et al., 1975</link><!--PMID 1176672-->). No such behavior had been reported in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, however. Most worm labs fed worms <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> OP50 (of which DA837 is a derivative), which turns out to be relatively poor quality food. You et al. (<link linkend="bib85">You et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 18316030-->) found that under certain conditions, one of the more important being high quality food, worms display the behavioral sequence of satiety. When satiated, they stop eating (measured by pumping rate), stop moving, and often become quiescent (movie and <link linkend="figure12">Figure 12A,B</link>). You et al. called this behavior &#x2018;satiety quiescence&#x2019; because: (1) The quiescence is dependent on food quality&#x2013;worms become quiescent on good food but not on poor food (<link linkend="figure12">Figure 12C</link>); (2) decrease in food intake (in feeding mutants such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis>) or decrease in food absorption in the intestine (in absorption mutants such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=act-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">act-5</ulink></emphasis>) reduces quiescence (<link linkend="figure12">Figure 12D</link>); and (3) The behavior is dependent on the animal&#x0027;s past experience of starvation&#x2013;worms that have experienced starvation show enhanced satiety quiescence compared to worms that have not (<link linkend="figure12">Figure 12E</link>). Satiety quiescence is regulated by peptide signals since <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-21;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-21</ulink></emphasis> mutants, which don&#x0027;t produce most peptide signals (<link linkend="bib36">Husson et al., 2007</link><!--PMID 17564681-->), are completely defective in satiety quiescence (<link linkend="figure12">Figure 12F</link>).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure12" xreflabel="Figure 12">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig12" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 12</phrase>
</textobject> &fig12legend;</mediaobject>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-16">
<title>TGF&#x03B2;, insulin and cGMP signaling and <emphasis>pkg-1</emphasis></title>
<para>Intriguingly, this sleep-like behavior was not completely unprecedented. In a screen for feeding-defective mutants Avery (<link linkend="bib6">Avery, 1993</link><!--PMID 8462849-->) isolated mutants that had a starved appearance, although there was no obvious defect in feeding motions or the feeding rate. However, whenever he examined them after a long period in which they had not been disturbed, he found them to be completely quiescent, neither eating nor moving. He speculated that they appeared starved because they were quiescent most of the time and as a result didn&#x0027;t eat as much as wild type. This mutation was eventually mapped to <emphasis>pkg-1</emphasis> (formerly <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-4</ulink></emphasis>), which encodes cyclic GMP-dependent Protein Kinase (PKG) (<link linkend="bib31">Fujiwara et al., 2002</link><!--PMID 12495624-->; <link linkend="bib56">Raizen et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16547093-->). You et al. (<link linkend="bib85">You et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 18316030-->) found that <emphasis>pkg-1</emphasis> loss of function mutants show no quiescence, whereas the gain of function mutation isolated by Avery shows excessive quiescence (<link linkend="figure13">Figure 13</link>). This finding suggested a role for cGMP signaling in satiety quiescence, confirmed by the observation that the membrane guanylate cyclase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink> and the cGMP-gated cation channel are necessary for satiety quiescence (<link linkend="figure14">Figure 14B</link>). Consistent with the evidence for peptide signaling, insulin and TGF&#x03B2; signals are also necessary for worms to show satiety quiescence (<link linkend="figure14">Figure 14A</link>). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, insulin, TGF&#x03B2; and cGMP pathways are involved in sensing a favorable environment, and in making the decision to keep growing and reproducing instead of becoming a dauer, a non-reproductive form specialized for long-term survival (<link linkend="bib62">Riddle et al., 1981</link><!--PMID 7219552-->). In other words, these signals are used to ensure that worms will be in nutritionally favorable conditions. You et al.&#x0027;s findings imply that these same signals of good conditions control satiety and quiescence in adults.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure13" xreflabel="Figure 13">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig13" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 13</phrase>
</textobject> &fig13legend;</mediaobject>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-17">
<title>Neuronal regulation of satiety quiescence</title>
<para>Expressing <emphasis>pkg-1</emphasis> under the control of a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tax-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">tax-4</ulink></emphasis> promoter rescued the quiescence defect of <emphasis>pkg-1</emphasis> mutants. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tax-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">tax-4</ulink></emphasis> encodes a cGMP-gated channel expressed in a dozen neuron types that sense the worm&#x0027;s environment and internal state (<link linkend="bib40">Komatsu et al., 1996</link><!--PMID 8893027-->). These neurons have critical roles in controlling body fat, determining body size and changing behaviors depending on environmental factors such as oxygen concentration (<link linkend="bib18">Coates and de Bono, 2002</link><!--PMID 12410311-->; <link linkend="bib31">Fujiwara et al., 2002</link><!--PMID 12495624-->; <link linkend="bib44">Mak et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16462744-->), temperature (<link linkend="bib58">Ramot et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 19020047-->), and light (<link linkend="bib83">Ward et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 18604203-->).</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TAX-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">TAX-4</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TAX-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">TAX-2</ulink> are &#x03B1; and &#x03B2; subunits of a cGMP-gated channel (<link linkend="bib40">Komatsu et al., 1996</link><!--PMID 8893027-->) and their neuronal expression overlaps. When You et al. tested <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tax-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">tax-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants, they showed no quiescence (<link linkend="figure14">Figure 14B</link>). (They were unable to test <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tax-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">tax-4</ulink></emphasis> mutants because, unlike <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tax-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">tax-2</ulink></emphasis>, they don&#x0027;t stay on food.) These results suggest that the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TAX-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">TAX-2</ulink>/4 expressing neurons and their neuronal activities mediated by the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TAX-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">TAX-2</ulink>/4 cGMP-gated channel are necessary for quiescence after fasting and refeeding.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure14" xreflabel="Figure 14">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig14" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 14</phrase>
</textobject> &fig14legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TAX-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">TAX-2</ulink>/4 expressing neurons only ASIs express <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink> (<link linkend="bib61">Ren et al., 1996</link><!--PMID 8910282-->), and the quiescence defect of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink></emphasis> mutants is fully rescued by expressing <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink></emphasis> in ASI (<link linkend="bib85">You et al., 2008</link><!--PMID 18316030-->). Unfavorable conditions such as shortage of food, high temperature and high concentration of dauer pheromone induce dauer formation in worms. Worms become dauers even under favorable conditions if ASI is killed (<link linkend="bib11">Bargmann and Horvitz, 1991</link><!--PMID 2006412-->). Recent findings suggest that ASI is necessary for life span extension by diet restriction (<link linkend="bib13">Bishop and Guarente, 2007</link><!--PMID 17538612-->). These results suggest a role of the ASI neurons in regulating or sensing food intake. That quiescence after fasting and refeeding is mediated by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink></emphasis> in ASI neurons supports this role of ASI.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec3-18">
<title>Fat storage and satiety quiescence</title>
<para>Interestingly, most mutants defective in satiety quiescence have darker intestines than wild type. A dark intestine usually correlates with more fat storage (<link linkend="bib46">McKay et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 12530969-->). In fact, some of these mutants, including <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink>,</emphasis> store more fat than wild type (<link linkend="bib39">Kimura et al., 1997</link><!--PMID 9252323-->). Quiescence resulting from satiety suggests that worms don&#x0027;t feed constantly, but rather regulate their feeding depending on nutritional status and environment. Quiescence-defective mutants that have reduced &#x201C;good conditions&#x201D; signaling could be defective in regulating feeding, which might cause more feeding and fat accumulation. Recent studies suggest that natriuretic peptide receptors, homologs of the guanylate cyclase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-11;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-11</ulink>, have a role in storing and degrading fat through PKG in adipose tissue (<link linkend="bib67">Sengenes et al., 2000</link><!--PMID 10877827-->) and that TGF-&#x03B2; signaling in neurons regulates adiposity during exercise (<link linkend="bib37">Ishikawa et al., 2006</link><!--PMID 16822963-->). These results suggest the possibility of conserved linkage of these signaling pathways to regulation of feeding and metabolism in worms and mammals.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-7">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<para>An animal must regulate its feeding based on internal status and external environment. Worms alter their feeding motions depending on their nutritional status: They pump more if they are hungry, and they don&#x0027;t pump at all if they are satiated. But feeding is not an isolated behavior. Hunger not only makes worms pump more but move more, too. They are willing to leave food they have to seek better food if past experience suggests better food might be found. The opposite is also true: satisfied worms never leave their food, often stop pumping when they are satiated and become quiescent. Understanding feeding and its regulation may help us to understand how animals think, respond and behave so as to survive in an unpredictable environment.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-8">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>Leon Avery&#x0027;s research is funded by research grants HL46154 and DK83593 from the National Institutes of Health. Young-Jai You&#x0027;s research is funded by grant 09SDG2150070 from the American Heart Association.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>References</title>
<para/>
&feeding_refs;
</sect1>
</article>