<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 12:</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Satiety quiescence. A, B.</emphasis> Worms were starved for 12 hours, then placed on high-quality food (<emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> HB101). With time they stopped eating (<emphasis role="bold">A</emphasis>) and became quiescent (<emphasis role="bold">B</emphasis>). <emphasis role="bold">C.</emphasis> Quiescence depends on food quality. Most worms fed good foods <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> HB101 or <emphasis>Comamonas</emphasis> become quiescent; few worms fed the relatively poor food <emphasis>E. coli</emphasis> DA837 do. <emphasis role="bold">D.</emphasis> Quiescence depends on food intake. A mutation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=eat-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">eat-2</ulink></emphasis>, which slows the rate of feeding, or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=act-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">act-5</ulink></emphasis>, which decreases nutrient absorption in the intestine, reduces quiescence. <emphasis role="bold">E.</emphasis> Fasting prior to full feeding increases quiescence. Fasted worms were left for 12 hours without food before feeding on high-quality food for the indicated times. <emphasis role="bold">F.</emphasis> Quiescence depends on peptide signals. A mutation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-21;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-21</ulink></emphasis> that prevents the processing of most peptide transmitters completely blocks quiescence. (Note that the y-axis has been displaced to allow bars of 0 height to be visible). An <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-3</ulink></emphasis> mutation that also blocks almost all peptidergic transmission (<link linkend="bib35">Husson et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16945111-->) has the same effect (not shown). Reproduced, with permission, from <link linkend="bib85">You et al. (2008)</link><!--: PMID 18316030-->.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>
