<caption>
     <formalpara>
         <title>Figure 2. Two condensin complexes in <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis></title>
	<para>(A) <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis> has one condensin complex specialized for dosage compensation (middle) and one specialized for the resolution, compaction, and segregation of both mitotic and meiotic chromosomes (left). The canonical 13S condensin complex (right) is conserved from yeast to humans. Proteins in all three complexes are color-coded to denote homologous proteins. In addition to the condensin-like proteins, the dosage compensation complex contains proteins (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SDC-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SDC-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SDC-3;class=protein" role="_blank">SDC-3</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DPY-30;class=protein" role="_blank">DPY-30</ulink>) that are essential for the recruitment of the entire complex to X. The SMC2-like protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MIX-1;class=protein" role="_blank">MIX-1</ulink> is shared between the dosage compensation and mitotic/meiotic condensin complexes. Preliminary biochemical analysis of the dosage compensation complex has identified an XCAP-G homolog (Csankovszki and Meyer, unpublished). Preliminary biochemical analysis of the mitotic complex has identified an XCAP-H homolog and a different XCAP-G homolog (Hagstrom and Meyer, unpublished). (B) The dosage compensation complex localizes to both X chromosomes of hermaphrodites. Shown is a multi-cell embryo stained with the DNA intercalating dye DAPI (blue) and an antibody to the dosage compensation protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SDC-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SDC-2</ulink> (red). (C) The <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis> mitotic/meiotic condensin complex co-localizes with centromere proteins on the holocentric mitotic chromosomes. Shown is a two-celled embryo stained with the DNA dye DAPI (red) and antibodies to SMC-4 (green) and to tubulin (blue). One cell (left) is in metaphase, and the other (right) is in prometaphase, where individual condensed chromosomes are readily apparent, and the centromeres appear as parallel tracts on the poleward sides of the sister chromatids. (D) Once bound to X chromosomes, the dosage compensation complex remains localized to X throughout the cell cycle. Shown is an XX L1 larva stained with an antibody to the dosage compensation protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DPY-26;class=protein" role="_blank">DPY-26</ulink> (green) and one to histone H3 phosphorylated on serine 10 (red), which associates only with mitotic chromosomes. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DPY-26;class=protein" role="_blank">DPY-26</ulink> is bound to both X chromosomes of the two mitotic larval cells. (E) The <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis> mitotic/meiotic condensin complex localizes to meiotic chromosomes in diplotene/diakinesis. Shown is MIX-1(green) co-localized with wild-type diakinesis bivalents counterstained with DAPI (red).</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>