<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % local.notation.class '| MOV'>
<!NOTATION MOV SYSTEM 'MOV'>
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'AltSplicingfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'aspfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'AltSplicingfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'aspfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'AltSplicingfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'aspfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'AltSplicingfig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'aspfig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY Asp_Refs SYSTEM 'AspRefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="AltSplicing_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title>Alternative splicing in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis><footnote><para>Edited by Thomas Blumenthal. Last revised January 28, 2005. Published September 26, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Zahler, A.M. Alternative splicing in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (September 26, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.31.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 Alan M. Zahler. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
</footnote></title>
<!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 1/28/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory> 
-->
		<author>
			<firstname>Alan M.</firstname>
			<surname>Zahler<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:zahler@biology.ucsc.edu">zahler@biology.ucsc.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></surname>
			<affiliation>
				<address>Department of Molecular, Cellular and Developmental Biology, Center for Molecular Biology of RNA, Sinsheimer Laboratories, University of California, Santa Cruz, CA 95064 USA</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<abstract>
		<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Alternative splicing is a common mechanism for the generation of multiple isoforms of proteins. It can function to expand the proteome of an organism and can serve as a way to turn off gene expression post-transcriptionally. This review focuses on splicing and its regulation in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans.</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">The fully-sequenced</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">genome combined with its elegant genetics offers unique advantages for exploring alternative splicing regulation in metazoans. The topics covered in this review include constitutive splicing factors, identification of alternatively spliced genes, examples of alternative splicing in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">and alternative splicing regulation. Key genes whose regulated alternative splicing are reviewed include</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-2" role="_blank">let-2</ulink>,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-32" role="_blank">unc-32</ulink>,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-52" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink>,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-15" role="_blank">egl-15</ulink></emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">and</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xol-1" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink>.</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">Factors involved in alternative splicing that are discussed include</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mec-8" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink>,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=smu-1" role="_blank">smu-1</ulink>,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=smu-2" role="_blank">smu-2</ulink>,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fox-1" role="_blank">fox-1</ulink>,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=exc-7" role="_blank">exc-7</ulink></emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">and</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-75" role="_blank">unc-75</ulink>.</emphasis></emphasis></para>
	</abstract>
	<sect1>
		<title>The Importance of alternative splicing</title>
		<para>Advances in animal genome sequencing have led to many questions concerning the very nature and number of genes and how they help to promote the diversity of cellular and organismal functions. One of the interesting disappointments of the analysis of the human genome sequence is that we may possess less than 25,000 genes (<link linkend="bib0">International Human Genome Sequencing Consortium, 2004<!-- PMID 15496913 --></link>), only one third more than the number of predicted genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. How can we explain all the complexity and wonder of human biology with such a limited gene set? One way to explain this paradox is to point out that the number of possible proteins from the genome can far exceed the possible number of genes if a large percentage of the genes have the ability to encode multiple proteins. This expansion of the proteome can be accomplished through alternative precursor messenger RNA (pre-mRNA) splicing, which can allow one gene to encode multiple proteins. Comparison of cDNAs with genomic sequence has provided evidence for extensive alternative splicing of human genes (<link linkend="bib1">Modrek et al., 2001<!-- PMID 11433032 --></link>). Many different studies predict that from 40 to 60<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of human genes are alternatively spliced (<link linkend="bib2">Croft et al., 2000<!-- PMID 10742092 --></link>; <link linkend="bib3">Hide et al., 2001<!-- PMID 11691849 --></link>; <link linkend="bib4">Kan et al., 2001<!-- PMID 11337482 --></link>; <link linkend="bib1">Modrek et al., 2001<!-- PMID 11433032 --></link>). Alternative splicing occurs in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and plays an important role in development. This chapter builds upon a previous review in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> II of constitutive splicing signals in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib5">Blumenthal and Steward, 1997<!-- PMID  --></link>).</para>
		
	     <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.5in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
			<textobject><phrase>Types of alternative splicing Figure 1</phrase></textobject>
            &fig1legend;
        </mediaobject>
		<para>Many genes are alternatively spliced in tissue-specific, developmentally-regulated, and hormone-responsive manners, providing an additional mechanism for regulation of gene expression (<link linkend="bib6">Bandman, 1992<!-- PMID 1358730 --></link>; <link linkend="bib7">Caceres and Kornblihtt, 2002<!-- PMID 11932019 --></link>; <link linkend="bib8">Grabowski, 1998<!-- PMID 9529247 --></link>; <link linkend="bib9">Grabowski and Black, 2001<!-- PMID 11473790 --></link>; <link linkend="bib10">Singh, 2002<!-- PMID 11868989 --></link>; <link linkend="bib11">Stamm et al., 1994<!-- PMID 8202349 --></link>). Types of alternative splicing include the use of alternative 5' splice sites, alternative 3' splice sites, cassette exons, retained introns and mutually exclusive exons (<xref linkend="figure1" />). Alternative splicing often leads to changes in the primary amino acid sequence of the protein, sometimes subtle and sometimes quite dramatic. Alternative splicing can control where the site of 3' end cleavage and polyadenlyation occurs, indicating a strong interaction between the splicing and 3' end formation machineries. Alternative splicing can lead to messages with premature termination codons, for example by including a cassette exon with an in-frame stop codon. These premature termination codon-containing messages can be substrates for the nonsense-mediated decay (NMD) pathway in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib12">Mango, 2001<!-- PMID 11672865 --></link>). Evidence for this was first demonstrated in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> in a genetic screen for alternative splicing factors. Morrison et al. showed that two of the genes encoding SR protein splicing factors have alternative isoforms with premature termination codons. These alternatively spliced forms were preferentially stabilized in suppressor with morphogenetic effects on genitalia (<emphasis>smg</emphasis>) mutants (<link linkend="bib13">Morrison et al., 1997<!-- PMID 9275202 --></link>). This use of alternative splicing to generate NMD substrates is very common in mammals (<link linkend="bib14">Lewis et al., 2003<!-- PMID 12502788 --></link>). In humans, polypyrimidine tract binding protein (PTB), which has multiple roles in mRNA processing including alternative splicing regulation, 3' end formation, and stability, regulates its own abundance by influencing the splicing of its own message. In this negative feedback loop, PTB promotes skipping of its own exon 11, leading to an isoform with an in-frame stop codon that is a substrate for NMD (<link linkend="bib15">Wollerton et al., 2004<!-- PMID 14731397 --></link>). In addition to turning off transcription to downregulate gene expression, alternative splicing is commonly used to downregulate gene expression by producing messages with truncated open reading frames that are rapidly degraded by NMD.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Splicing of precursors to messenger RNA</title>
		<para>Alternative splicing is regulated at the sites on the pre-mRNA where the splicing machinery assembles. The two transesterification reaction steps of pre-mRNA splicing occur in a large multi-component ribonucleoprotein complex, the spliceosome (<link linkend="bib16">Burge et al., 1999<!-- PMID  --></link>; <link linkend="bib17">Caceres and Krainer, 1997<!-- PMID  --></link>; <link linkend="bib18">Kramer, 1996<!-- PMID 8811184 --></link>). The spliceosome assembles onto the pre-mRNA via an ordered binding of its subunits, the uridine-rich small nuclear ribonucleoprotein complexes (U snRNPs). SnRNP assembly is guided by RNA-RNA interactions between the U snRNAs and the pre-mRNA and the snRNAs with each other. First U1 binds to the pre-mRNA guided by base-pairing interactions between its 5' end and the 5' splice site. U2 binding is guided by base pairing interactions with the branchpoint sequence in the intron. Then the U4/U6-U5 tri-snRNP is recruited to the forming spliceosome. Extensive rearrangements of RNA-RNA interactions then occur in the spliceosome (<link linkend="bib19">Ares and Weiser, 1994<!-- PMID 7754032 --></link>; <link linkend="bib20">Madhani and Guthrie, 1994<!-- PMID 7534458 --></link>). There is evidence from recent studies that the spliceosomal components can be found together in a pre-assembled penta-snRNP complex (<link linkend="bib21">Stevens et al., 2002<!-- PMID 11804584 --></link>). The mammalian penta-snRNP has been shown to assemble onto 5' splice sites and undergo rearrangements that replace U1 interactions with U5 interactions (<link linkend="bib22">Malca et al., 2003<!-- PMID 12724403 --></link>). The functional importance of the pre-assembled penta-snRNP compared to models of step-wise spliceosome assembly on the substrate pre-mRNA is still being studied.</para>
		<para>Several classes of splicing factor proteins have been identified as essential for metazoan spliceosome assembly yet are not integral components of the snRNPs (<link linkend="bib18">Kramer, 1996<!-- PMID 8811184 --></link>). The SR protein family of splicing factors is required for the earliest interactions of U1 snRNP with the pre-mRNA and for subsequent spliceosome assembly steps (<link linkend="bib23">Fu, 1995<!-- PMID 7585252 --></link>; <link linkend="bib24">Graveley, 2000<!-- PMID 0010999598 --></link>; <link linkend="bib25">Manley and Tacke, 1996<!-- PMID 8682289 --></link>). SR proteins have redundant functions in promoting constitutive splicing, but certain family members have distinct roles in promoting specific alternative splice site usage. SR protein family members have distinct binding specificities for sequences within exons that serve as splicing enhancer elements (<link linkend="bib26">Cartegni and Krainer, 2002<!-- PMID 11925564 --></link>). U2 auxiliary factor (U2AF) is a heterodimeric splicing factor composed of 35 and 65 kD subunits. It binds to the polypyrimidine tract and recognizes the AG dinucleotide at the 3' end of the intron to promote U2 snRNA interactions with the intron branchpoint sequence (<link linkend="bib27">Merendino et al., 1999<!-- PMID 10617208 --></link>; <link linkend="bib28">Wu et al., 1999<!-- PMID 10617206 --></link>; <link linkend="bib65">Zorio and Blumenthal, 1999b<!-- PMID 10617207 --></link>). U2AF, SR proteins and U1 snRNP assemble onto the pre-mRNA in an ATP-independent manner to form the early (E) complex (<link linkend="bib30">Michaud and Reed, 1991<!-- PMID 1836445 --></link>; <link linkend="bib31">Staknis and Reed, 1994<!-- PMID 7935481 --></link>). It is important to note that assembly of the E complex essentially identifies both the 5' end 3' splice site for further spliceosome assembly, and thus control of this assembly can be a way of regulating alternative splice site choice. Splicing factors interact with the pre-mRNA, with other splicing factors and with protein components of the snRNPs (<link linkend="bib16">Burge et al., 1999<!-- PMID  --></link>; <link linkend="bib17">Caceres and Krainer, 1997<!-- PMID  --></link>; <link linkend="bib18">Kramer, 1996<!-- PMID 8811184 --></link>). This cooperative assembly increases the local concentration of the snRNAs in the vicinity of splice sites and therefore is likely to promote the RNA-RNA interactions required for spliceosome assembly.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Models for alternative splicing regulation</title>
		<para>From research over the past 20 years, some general themes have emerged for alternative splicing regulation, although the exact mechanisms still need to be determined. Alternatively spliced exons often have weak consensus sequences at the 5' and 3' ends of the introns, suggesting that additional signals are required for recognition of the exon by the splicing machinery (<link linkend="bib32">Lopez, 1998<!-- PMID 9928482 --></link>). <emphasis>Cis</emphasis>-acting pre-mRNA sequences responsible for regulation of splicing have been identified for many genes (<link linkend="bib33">Cooper and Mattox, 1997<!-- PMID 9311728 --></link>). These regions are found in exons or in introns and can be enhancers or silencers of splice site usage (<xref linkend="figure2" />). These sequence motifs serve as binding sites for protein factors that can enhance or inhibit the ability of the spliceosome to recognize the exons. The exonic elements not only encode amino acids but also regulate their own ability to be spliced into the mature message. <emphasis>Trans</emphasis>-acting splicing factors that interact with splicing regulatory elements in exons have been identified. Subsets of the SR proteins bind with regulatory sequences important for splicing control (<link linkend="bib34">Gontarek and Derse, 1996<!-- PMID 8628299 --></link>; <link linkend="bib35">Kanopka et al., 1996<!-- PMID 8632829 --></link>; <link linkend="bib36">Lavigueur et al., 1993<!-- PMID 8253386 --></link>; <link linkend="bib37">Nagel et al., 1998<!-- PMID 9436904 --></link>; <link linkend="bib38">Ramchatesingh et al., 1995<!-- PMID 7651409 --></link>; <link linkend="bib31">Staknis and Reed, 1994<!-- PMID 7935481 --></link>; <link linkend="bib39">Sun et al., 1993<!-- PMID 8276242 --></link>). Heterogeneous nuclear ribonucleoprotein (hnRNP) A/B family members can bind to high-affinity sequences in exons and inhibit splicing through blocking SR proteins from binding to the exons (<link linkend="bib40">Caputi et al., 1999<!-- PMID 10406810 --></link>; <link linkend="bib41">Zhu et al., 2001<!-- PMID 11779509 --></link>).</para>
		
	<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.25in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
			<textobject><phrase> Locations of regions on the pre-mRNA that can affect alternative splicing figure 2</phrase></textobject>
            &fig2legend;
        </mediaobject>
		<para>Splicing factors important for tissue-specific regulation of vertebrate splicing often assemble into multicomponent complexes on intronic splicing regulatory elements. The downstream control sequence (DCS), found in the intron downstream of the human neural-specific c-src N1 exon, is one such example. Factors that bind to the DCS regulate N1 splicing; these include hnRNP H, hnRNP F, <emphasis role="underline">K</emphasis>H-type <emphasis role="underline">s</emphasis>plicing <emphasis role="underline">r</emphasis>egulatory <emphasis role="underline">p</emphasis>rotein (KSRP) and a neural-specific homolog of PTB (nPTB; <link linkend="bib42">Chou et al., 1999<!-- PMID 9858532 --></link>; <link linkend="bib43">Markovtsov et al., 2000<!-- PMID 11003644 --></link>; <link linkend="bib44">Min et al., 1995<!-- PMID 7590243 --></link>; <link linkend="bib45">Min et al., 1997<!-- PMID 9136930 --></link>). Comparison of the factors that assemble onto this element from neuronal cell nuclear extract vs. epithelial cell nuclear extract indicate that a subset of these proteins bind from both extracts. Factors in the neuronal extract promote assembly of a different complex that is required to activate splicing of the neural-specific exon. PTB was identified by its ability to bind to polypyrimidine tracts. It has been shown to regulate the alternative splicing of its own message, as well as others including cardiac troponin T, alpha-actinin, fibroblast growth factor receptor R2, calcitonin/CGRP, and alpha tropomyosin pre-mRNAs (<link linkend="bib46">Wagner and Garcia-Blanco, 2001<!-- PMID 11313454 --></link>; <link linkend="bib47">Wollerton et al., 2001<!-- PMID 11421360 --></link>). In these systems, PTB binding to both introns flanking an exon promotes exon skipping (<link linkend="bib46">Wagner and Garcia-Blanco, 2001<!-- PMID 11313454 --></link>). CUG binding protein and related family members known as CELF proteins interact with CUG repeats in introns to regulate splicing (<link linkend="bib48">Ladd et al., 2001<!-- PMID 11158314 --></link>; <link linkend="bib49">Philips et al., 1998<!-- PMID 9563950 --></link>). An antagonistic interaction between one of the CELF proteins, ETR-3, and PTB regulates troponin t alternative splicing (<link linkend="bib50">Charlet-B et al., 2002<!-- PMID 11931771 --></link>). The nova-1 protein is important for regulation of alternative splicing in the nervous system. This neuronal protein binds the sequence UCAY (<link linkend="bib51">Jensen, Dredge, et al., 2000<!-- PMID 10719891 --></link>; <link linkend="bib52">Jensen, Musunuru, et al., 2000<!-- PMID 10811881 --></link>). A balance between nova activity and PTB is important in regulation of alternative splicing in neurons (<link linkend="bib53">Polydorides et al., 2000<!-- PMID 10829067 --></link>). The mechanism by which binding of these factors to intronic elements regulates exon inclusion is not clear. Genomic analysis indicates that homologs of all of the major vertebrate splicing factors discussed above can also be found in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (AMZ, unpublished observations).</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Constitutive splicing factors in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
		<para>The spliceosomal snRNAs of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are very similar to their yeast and mammalian counterparts (<link linkend="bib54">Thomas et al., 1990<!-- PMID 2339054 --></link>). The importance of U1 snRNA base-pairing with the 5' splice site is demonstrated by two extragenic allele-specific suppressors of mutations of the canonical G that begins <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> introns. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-6" role="_blank">sup-6</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sup-39" role="_blank">sup-39</ulink></emphasis> encode two of the 12 U1 snRNA genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and were identified in screens as suppressors that can allow mutated splice donors to be recognized by the splicing machinery (<link linkend="bib55">Roller et al., 2000<!-- PMID 10757761 --></link>; <link linkend="bib56">Run et al., 1996<!-- PMID 8722777 --></link>). The suppressor mutations are compensatory mutations in the 5' end of U1 snRNA genes (<link linkend="bib57">Zahler et al., 2004<!-- PMID 15342508 --></link>). These U1 snRNA suppressors are informational suppressors, allele-specific gene-nonspecific suppressors, and join the amber suppressors and the <emphasis>smg</emphasis> genes as members of this group (<link linkend="bib58">Mount and Anderson, 2000<!-- PMID 10729829 --></link>).</para>
		<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> contains seven different members of the SR protein family called the <emphasis>rsp</emphasis> genes (<link linkend="bib59">Kawano et al., 2000<!-- PMID 10906451 --></link>; <link linkend="bib60">Longman et al., 2000<!-- PMID 10747030 --></link>; <link linkend="bib13">Morrison et al., 1997<!-- PMID 9275202 --></link>). Family members are expressed in all cells at all stages of development (<link linkend="bib59">Kawano et al., 2000<!-- PMID 10906451 --></link>). There is functional overlap among the family members as studies suggest that, with the exception of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rsp-3" role="_blank">rsp-3</ulink></emphasis>, multiple SR proteins need to be targeted by RNA interference in order for a phenotype to become evident (<link linkend="bib59">Kawano et al., 2000<!-- PMID 10906451 --></link>; <link linkend="bib60">Longman et al., 2000<!-- PMID 10747030 --></link>; <link linkend="bib61">Longman et al., 2001<!-- PMID 11747818 --></link>). The phenomenon of trans splicing is common in nematode species (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transsplicingoperons/transsplicingoperons.html" role="_blank">Trans-splicing and operons</ulink>). Using splicing competent embryonic extracts from parasitic nematode <emphasis>Ascaris lumbricoides</emphasis>, Sanford and Bruzik have shown that SR proteins are essential for the trans splicing reaction in nematodes and that the phosphorylation state and activity level of these proteins change during early development (<link linkend="bib62">Sanford and Bruzik, 1999a<!-- PMID 10385619 --></link>; <link linkend="bib63">Sanford and Bruzik, 1999b<!-- PMID 10411135 --></link>).</para>
		<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has a homolog of each U2AF subunit, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=uaf-1" role="_blank">uaf-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=uaf-2" role="_blank">uaf-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib29">Zorio and Blumenthal, 1999a<!-- PMID 10199565 --></link>; <link linkend="bib64">Zorio et al., 1997<!-- PMID 9001248 --></link>). Using the short defined polypyrimidine tract at the 3' end of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> introns (<link linkend="bib5">Blumenthal and Steward, 1997<!-- PMID  --></link>), studies in this organism were able to demonstrate the specificity with which the U2AF heterodimer subunits recognize the polypyrimidine tract and 3' splice site at the end of the intron. The U2AF65 homolog, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=uaf-1" role="_blank">uaf-1</ulink></emphasis>, interacts with the polypyrimidine tract while the U2AF35 homolog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=uaf-2" role="_blank">uaf-2</ulink></emphasis> recognizes the AG dinucleotide at the 3' end of the intron (<link linkend="bib65">Zorio and Blumenthal, 1999b<!-- PMID 10617207 --></link>). This showed that even though the AG at the 3' end of the intron is involved in the second transesterification reaction of splicing, it also has an important role in early spliceosome assembly. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UAF-1;class=protein" role="_blank">UAF-1</ulink> regulates its own expression. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=uaf-1" role="_blank">uaf-1</ulink></emphasis> message is alternatively spliced to contain an unusual exon with an in-frame stop codon that should be a subject for nonsense mediated decay. This exon is unusual because it contains 10 matches to the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> 3' splice acceptor sequence UUUUCAG/R, the sequence recognized directly by <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> U2AF (<link linkend="bib65">Zorio and Blumenthal, 1999b<!-- PMID 10617207 --></link>; <link linkend="bib64">Zorio et al., 1997<!-- PMID 9001248 --></link>). MacMorris et al.. showed that these splice acceptor repeats cause the pre-mRNA to be retained in the nucleus and thus not become a substrate for translation or nonsense-mediated decay. Experiments in which the UUUUCAG/R repeats were placed in a GFP transgene indicate that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UAF-1;class=protein" role="_blank">UAF-1</ulink> is responsible for the nuclear retention of its message (<link linkend="bib66">MacMorris et al., 1999<!-- PMID 10097120 --></link>).</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Identification of alternatively spliced genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
		<para>Intron and exon structure in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is similar to that found in other higher eukaryotes (<link linkend="bib5">Blumenthal and Steward, 1997<!-- PMID  --></link>). The completed genome sequence and >200,000 expressed sequence tag (EST) complementary DNA (cDNA) sequences are available in public databases such as Wormbase at <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/" role="_blank">http://www.wormbase.org/</ulink> (<link linkend="bib67"><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Sequencing Consortium, 1998<!-- PMID 9851916 --></link>; <link linkend="bib68">Stein et al., 2001<!-- PMID 11125056 --></link>). Computational approaches have been developed to identify alternatively spliced <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes by comparing cDNA and genomic sequences (<link linkend="bib69">Kent and Zahler, 2000<!-- PMID 0010592190 --></link>). This led to the initial identification of 844 alternatively spliced genes. Regularly updated lists of alternatively spliced genes can be found at the Intronerator web site, <ulink url="http://genome-test.cse.ucsc.edu/Intronerator/" role="_blank">http://genome-test.cse.ucsc.edu/Intronerator/</ulink>. Wormbase annotations of genes indicate alternatively spliced isoforms. These are generated by hand annotation based on cDNA and EST data as well as experimental data reported by researchers. As of release WS132, there are 2,562 alternatively spliced genes annotated in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org" role="_blank">Wormbase</ulink>, accounting for 13<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of annotated <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes. This is likely an underestimate of the total percentage of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes that are alternatively spliced as these values are dependent on EST and cDNA coverage of the genome and at the current time 25<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of the 19,726 annotated <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> coding sequences have no cDNA transcriptional evidence (Wormbase WS132 release notes). Genes with alternative isoforms are denoted by a lower case letter after the assigned gene name, for example T01D7.1a. Many of the genes with alternative isoforms are generated by using alternative promoters with unique first exons that splice into a common second exon. Even though these alternative promoters will lead to alternative 5' exons spliced to common downstream exons (<xref linkend="figure1" />). the generation of the unique first exon is not regulated at the level of alternative splicing but instead by transcription.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Some examples of alternatively spliced <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes</title>
		<para>There are four genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> that encode the <emphasis role="underline">a</emphasis> subunit of the vacuolar ATPase, suggesting a mechanism for regulating the activity of this pump (<link linkend="bib70">Oka et al., 2001<!-- PMID 11441002 --></link>). One of these genes, encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-32" role="_blank">unc-32</ulink></emphasis>, can be alternatively spliced to yield six different isoforms, adding even more complexity (<xref linkend="figure3" />A). There are three different mutually exclusive exons for exon 4, and two for exon 7 leading to six possible transcripts (<link linkend="bib71">Pujol et al., 2001<!-- PMID 11110798 --></link>). In the study by Pujol et al., GFP was fused in frame to exon 4B of an <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-32" role="_blank">unc-32</ulink></emphasis> genomic clone and transfected into animals. The expression of GFP was limited to neurons suggesting that splicing of exon 4B is neural-specific (<link linkend="bib71">Pujol et al., 2001<!-- PMID 11110798 --></link>).</para>
		<para>Alternative splicing can be used to transcribe two distinct genes from a single promoter, in a way that accomplishes the same end but is distinct from trans-splicing of operons. This occurs for the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cha-1" role="_blank">cha-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-17" role="_blank">unc-17</ulink></emphasis> genes. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cha-1" role="_blank">cha-1</ulink></emphasis> encodes choline acetyl-transferase while <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-17" role="_blank">unc-17</ulink></emphasis> encodes a synaptic vesicle-associated acetylcholine transporter. Analysis of transcripts of these two genes involved in acetylcholine metabolism indicate that they share a common promoter and 5' untranslated exon (<xref linkend="figure3" />B). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-17" role="_blank">unc-17</ulink></emphasis> transcript is nested within the long first intron of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cha-1" role="_blank">cha-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib72">Alfonso et al., 1994<!-- PMID 8057385 --></link>). In this case, two proteins with related functions but with no peptide sequences in common are produced as a result of alternative splicing of a common mRNA precursor.</para>
       
        <para>The fibroblast growth factor receptor homolog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-15" role="_blank">egl-15</ulink></emphasis> is alternatively spliced to yield five different C-termini. In addition, the gene has two distinct mutually exclusive central exons, 5A and 5B (<xref linkend="figure3" />C). These two exons encode a domain in the extracellular portion of the protein that gives ligand specificity to the receptor. Exon 5A is required for the response to the FGF chemoattractant <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-17;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-17</ulink>, which guides migrating sex myoblasts to their final positions. Exon 5B is required for the essential functions mediated by this receptor through interaction with the ligand <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-756;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-756</ulink> (<link linkend="bib73">Goodman et al., 2003<!-- PMID 12835392 --></link>). In this case of alternative splicing, two mutually exclusive exons allow one gene to code for a receptor tyrosine kinase with two distinct functional specificities.</para>
        <literallayout></literallayout>
	<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="7in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
			<textobject><phrase> Examples of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> alternatively spliced genes figure 3</phrase></textobject>
            &fig3legend;
        </mediaobject>
        </sect1>
        <sect1>
		<title>Regulation of alternative splicing in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
		<para>Splicing studies in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have demonstrated the importance of varying strengths among splice site consensus sequences to allow for splicing regulation. 5' splice site strength is determined by the extent of complementarity of the splice donor region to the 5' end of U1 snRNA. The alpha 2(IV) collagen gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-2" role="_blank">let-2</ulink></emphasis> is alternatively spliced to yield two forms of the protein containing one of two mutually exclusive exons, exon 9 or exon 10 (<xref linkend="figure4" />A).There is developmental regulation of this alternative splicing; 95<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of embryonic <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-2;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-2</ulink> messages contain exon 9 while in adults 90<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> contain exon 10. The larval stages show a gradual shift in usage between these isoforms, indicating developmental control of alternative splicing (<link linkend="bib74">Sibley et al., 1993<!-- PMID 7691828 --></link>). The intron downstream of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-2" role="_blank">let-2</ulink></emphasis> exon 10 begins with a rare GC dinucleotide instead of the canonical GU. Only 0.5<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of introns in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> begin with a GC dinucleotide (<link linkend="bib75">Farrer et al., 2002<!-- PMID 12140320 --></link>). In <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis>, which maintains the same developmentally regulated alternative splicing of this alpha 2 (IV) collagen gene, the same intron begins with GU (<link linkend="bib76">Pettitt and Kingston, 1994<!-- PMID 8293875 --></link>). The GC splice donor serves as a weak consensus sequence that allows for the proper regulation of alternative splicing. Replacement of this sequence with a GU donor (such as the one from Ascaris) that has weak overall base-pairing with the 5' end of U1 snRNA, allows for maintenance of splicing regulation. Replacing the GC donor with a moderate or strong consensus GU donor abolishes the splicing regulation and leads to high usage of exon 10 in embryos (<link linkend="bib75">Farrer et al., 2002<!-- PMID 12140320 --></link>). The presence of a weak splice donor for exon 10 allows developmentally regulated factors to control the recognition of this exon by the splicing machinery. The identity of these factors is not yet known, but our group has identified an 11 base sequence element in the intron between exons 10 and 11 that is required for efficient inclusion of exon 10 in late larval stages. This element may serve as an interacting site for developmentally regulated splicing factors (Tracy Farrer and AMZ, unpublished observation).</para>
	<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4.5in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
			<textobject><phrase> Alternative splicing regulation in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>genes figure 4</phrase></textobject>
            &fig4legend;
        </mediaobject>
        <para>Genetic analysis in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has led to the identification of splicing regulatory pathways. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEC-8;class=protein" role="_blank">MEC-8</ulink> is a two RNA recognition motif (RRM)-containing, nuclear protein. Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mec-8" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink></emphasis> lead to mechanosensory and other defects. Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mec-8" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink></emphasis> are synthetically lethal with viable mutations in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-52" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> gene (<link linkend="bib77">Lundquist et al., 1996<!-- PMID 8625846 --></link>). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-52;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink> is a homolog of the mammaliam perlecan protein, an extracellular matrix molecule important in muscle anchorage (<link linkend="bib78">Rogalski et al., 1993<!-- PMID 8393416 --></link>). These viable <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-52" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> mutations occur in the alternatively spliced exons 17 and 18 (<xref linkend="figure4" />b). Every possible combination of inclusion or skipping of exons 16, 17 and 18 has been detected (<link linkend="bib79">Rogalski et al., 1995<!-- PMID 7535716 --></link>). Skipping of exons 17 and 18 is dependent on the function of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mec-8" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib77">Lundquist et al., 1996<!-- PMID 8625846 --></link>). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEC-8;class=protein" role="_blank">MEC-8</ulink> protein is found in all nuclei in embryos, but only in a subset of mechanosensory neurons and hypodermal cells in adults (<link linkend="bib80">Spike et al., 2002<!-- PMID 12397108 --></link>). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-52" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> mutant alleles with stop codons in exons 17 and 18 develop a progressive paralysis at later developmental stages. Null mutations in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-52" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> gene lead to embryonic lethality (<link linkend="bib79">Rogalski et al., 1995<!-- PMID 7535716 --></link>). Animals containing both viable mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-52" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> and viable mutations in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mec-8" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink> have a synthetic lethal phenotype that mimics the embryonic lethality of the lethal <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-52" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> alleles (<link linkend="bib81">Lundquist and Herman, 1994<!-- PMID 8001796 --></link>). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mec-8" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink></emphasis>(+) animals with viable <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-52" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> mutations, there is a loss of full-length <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-52;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink> production in the later developmental stages, leading to the adult paralysis phenotype. In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mec-8" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink></emphasis>; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-52" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> double mutant animals, loss of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mec-8" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink></emphasis>-enhanced skipping of exons 17 and 18 (containing stop codons) leads to insufficient production of full-length <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-52;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink> in embryos and thus to the more severe embryonic lethality. Two suppressors of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mec-8" role="_blank">mec-8</ulink></emphasis>; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-52" role="_blank">unc-52</ulink></emphasis> synthetic lethality were identified (<link linkend="bib81">Lundquist and Herman, 1994<!-- PMID 8001796 --></link>). One of these, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=smu-1" role="_blank">smu-1</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a nuclear protein that contains five WD motifs, is ubiquitously expressed and is 62<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> identical to a human spliceosome associated protein fSAP57 (<link linkend="bib82">Spike et al., 2001<!-- PMID 11438655 --></link>). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=smu-2" role="_blank">smu-2</ulink></emphasis> encodes a <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of the RED protein, which has also been shown to be associated with the human spliceosome. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMU-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SMU-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMU-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SMU-2</ulink> bind to each other; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMU-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SMU-2</ulink> stabilizes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMU-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SMU-1</ulink> but <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMU-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SMU-1</ulink> does not stabilize <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMU-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SMU-2</ulink>. Based on their homology with components of the mammalian spliceosome, it is hypothesized that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMU-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SMU-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMU-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SMU-2</ulink> might interact with the spliceosome and modulate splice site choice (<link linkend="bib83">Spartz et al., 2004<!-- PMID 15254247 --></link>).</para>
		<para>Alternative splicing factors play a role in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> sex determination. In hermaphrodites, the feminizing locus on X (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fox-1" role="_blank">fox-1</ulink></emphasis>) gene is a regulator of sex determination that acts as a numerator for counting X chromosomes (<link linkend="bib84">Hodgkin et al., 1994<!-- PMID 7821230 --></link>). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fox-1" role="_blank">fox-1</ulink></emphasis> encodes an RRM protein that acts post-transcriptionally to inhibit the expression of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xol-1" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis> gene, the major specifier of male fate. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FOX-1;class=protein" role="_blank">FOX-1</ulink> inhibits splicing of the terminal intron of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=xol-1" role="_blank">xol-1</ulink></emphasis> pre-mRNA, preventing production of active <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=XOL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">XOL-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib85">Nicoll et al., 1997<!-- PMID 9217163 --></link>).</para>
		<para>Tissue specific expression of alternative splicing factors has been demonstrated in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Two genetically identified neuronal, nuclear RNA binding proteins involved in synaptic transmission have been cloned in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. These are <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-75" role="_blank">unc-75</ulink></emphasis>, which is an ortholog of the human CELF family of alternative splicing factors, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=exc-7" role="_blank">exc-7</ulink></emphasis>, which is a homolog of the <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> neuronal splicing factor ELAV (<link linkend="bib86">Loria et al., 2003<!-- PMID 12906792 --></link>). Another ELAV homolog in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=etr-1" role="_blank">etr-1</ulink></emphasis>, is expressed only in muscle cells and is essential for development (<link linkend="bib87">Milne and Hodgkin, 1999<!-- PMID 10556089 --></link>).</para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1>
			<title>Conclusions</title>
			<para>With its many alternatively spliced genes and evolutionarily conserved alternative splicing factors, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> offers a tractable model system for the study of pre-mRNA splicing regulation. With much smaller average intron size compared to vertebrates, a fully sequenced genome, and a highly developed and simple genetics system, research in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has the potential to provide important contributions to our understanding of alternative splicing regulation.</para>
			</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Acknowledgements</title>
		<para>I am grateful to the members of my laboratory at UC Santa Cruz for many helpful comments on this manuscript. Research in my laboratory is supported by grant GM61646 from the National Institute of General Medical Sciences.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>References</title>
        <para/>
		&Asp_Refs;
	</sect1>
</article>