<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 4. Terminal selectors define neuronal identity.</title>
<para>Three examples of terminal selector transcription factors that co-regulate batteries of genes that define the identity of an individual neuron type (<link linkend="bib43">Hobert, 2008</link><!--PMID: 19104055-->). Terminal selectors autoregulate their expression, thereby ensuring the maintained expression of their targets throughout the life of a neuron. Terminal selectors may also regulate transcription factors that regulate specific subaspects of a neuron&#x0027;s identity. Other well-studied terminal selectors are the Pitx2-type homeobox gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-30;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-30</ulink></emphasis>, which controls GABAergic neuron identity and the ETS factor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ast-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ast-1</ulink></emphasis>, which controls dopaminergic neuron identity. As both factors are expressed in more neuron types, they likely pair up with as yet unidentified co-factors. The same principle applies to the AIY terminal selectors <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ttx-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">ttx-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ceh-10;class=Gene" role="_blank">ceh-10</ulink></emphasis>: both factors are expressed in more cells than AIY but uniquely overlap in AIY (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1C</link>). Note that other regulatory routines act in parallel to terminal selector genes. For example, terminal selectors tend not to affect the expression of pan-neuronal genes; those may be co-regulated by other factors (<link linkend="bib81">Ruvinsky et al., 2007</link><!--PMID: 17046742-->). Also note that one central feature of the terminal selector concept is its &#x201C;hourglass&#x201D;-shaped regulatory topology, as indicated in the panel on the bottom: multiple regulatory inputs funnel into the establishment of terminal selector gene expression, a regulatory bottleneck. Once established, downstream regulatory events then again fan out. Table 1 lists additional candidate terminal selector genes.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>
