<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 1. An exemplary view of some structural and molecular features of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> nervous system.</title><para/></formalpara>
<formalpara><title/><para><emphasis role="bold">(A)</emphasis> Overall organization of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> nervous system (<link linkend="bib108">White et al., 1986</link>). Neurons are in red. In the first larval stage, shown here schematically, there are 222 neurons (202 somatic, 20 pharyngeal). During larval development a number of neurons are added resulting in a total number of 302 neurons in the adult hermaphrodite and 383 in the adult male (most of the male specific neurons are in the tail). For a more detailed description of the anatomy, see <ulink url="http://www.wormatlas.org/">WormAtlas</ulink>.</para></formalpara>
<formalpara><title/><para><emphasis role="bold">(B)</emphasis> Individual neuron types are highly connected information processing devices (<link linkend="bib108">White et al., 1986</link>). Some of the circuitry processing various sensory modalities is shown (adapted from <link linkend="bib98">Tsalik and Hobert, 2003</link><!--PMID: 12838583-->), reviewed in de Bono and Maricq (<link linkend="bib15">2005</link><!--PMID: 16022603-->) and Hobert (<link linkend="bib40">2003</link><!--PMID: 12486705-->). Arrows indicate chemical synapses, bars indicate electrical synapses, according to <link linkend="bib108">White et al. (1986)</link>.</para></formalpara>
<formalpara><title/><para><emphasis role="bold">(C)</emphasis> Combinatorial gene expression patterns are unique identifiers of terminal neuron fates. Individual neuron types, exemplified here with the AIY interneuron class, are defined not by the expression of unique terminal differentiation genes, but by the expression of a unique combination of more broadly expressed genes (shown here is only a small selection: the GPCR <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sra-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">sra-11</ulink>,</emphasis> the secreted ligand <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=hen-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">hen-1</ulink>,</emphasis> the matrix protein <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=kal-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">kal-1</ulink></emphasis> and the vesicular acetylcholine transporter <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-17;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-17</ulink></emphasis>; not all cells expressing these genes are shown) (<link linkend="bib1">Altun-Gultekin et al., 2001</link><!--PMID: 11493519-->). This holds both for &#x201C;terminal differentiation genes&#x201D;, i.e. genes coding for nuts-and-bolts proteins that define the property of a neuron (neurotransmitter receptors, signaling molecules etc.), and also usually for transcription factors that act combinatorially to define the respective individual neuron classes. Neuron type specification therefore involves hierarchical levels of combinatorial codes of co-expressed genes. The binary &#x201C;on&#x201D;/&#x201C;off&#x201D; behavior of gene expression is likely an oversimplification since intermediary, differential levels of gene expression may also be instructive (for example, the <emphasis>cut</emphasis> gene in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib34">Grueber et al., 2003</link><!--PMID: 12654247-->)). Adapted from Wenick and Hobert (<link linkend="bib106">2004</link><!--PMID: 15177025-->).</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>