<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'maledevfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'maledevfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'maledevfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'maledevfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'maledevfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'maledevfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'maledevfig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'maledevfig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'maledevfig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'maledevfig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'maledevfig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'maledevfig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig7 SYSTEM 'maledevfig7.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig7legend SYSTEM 'maledevfig7leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig8 SYSTEM 'maledevfig8.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig8legend SYSTEM 'maledevfig8leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig9 SYSTEM 'maledevfig9.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig9legend SYSTEM 'maledevfig9leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig10 SYSTEM 'maledevfig10.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig10legend SYSTEM 'maledevfig10leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig11 SYSTEM 'maledevfig11.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig11legend SYSTEM 'maledevfig11leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig12 SYSTEM 'maledevfig12.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig12legend SYSTEM 'maledevfig12leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig13 SYSTEM 'maledevfig13.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig13legend SYSTEM 'maledevfig13leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY maledev_Refs SYSTEM 'maledevrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
    <article id="maledev_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Male development<footnote><para>Edited by Barbara J. Meyer. Last revised October 20, 2005. Published November 10, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Emmons, S.W. Male development (November 10, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.33.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 Scott W. Emmons. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
</footnote></title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 3/31/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory> 
-->
        <author>
            <firstname>Scott W.</firstname>
            <surname>Emmons<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:emmons@aecom.yu.edu">emmons@aecom.yu.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></surname>
            <affiliation>
            <address>Department of Molecular Genetics, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Bronx, NY 10461 USA</address>
            </affiliation>
            </author>
            </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The features that differentiate the</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">male from the hermaphrodite arise during postembryonic development. The major male mating structures, consisting of the blunt tail with fan and rays, the hook, the spicules and proctodeum, and the thin body, form just before the last larval molt. Male and hermaphrodite embryogenesis are similar but some essential male cell fates are already established at hatching. The male mating structures arise from three important sets of male-specific blast cells. These cells generate a total of 205 male-specific somatic cells, including 89 neurons, 36 neuronal support cells, 41 muscles, 23 cells involved in differentiating the hindgut, and 16 hypodermal cells associated with mating structures. Genetic and molecular studies have identified many genes required for male development, most of which also function in the hermaphrodite. Cell-cell interactions play a role in patterning all three of the  generative tissues. Male-specific neurons, including sensory neurons of the rays, hook, post-cloacal sensilla, and spicules, differentiate at the end of the last larval stage and send out axons to make connections into the existing neuropil, greatly enlarging the posterior ganglia. The hindgut is highly differentiated to accommodate the spicules and the joining of the reproductive tract to the cloaca. A complex male-specific program generates many new muscles for copulation. The cell lineage and genetic program that gives rise to the one-armed male gonad appears to be a variation on that of the hermaphrodite.</emphasis></para>
      </abstract>
                <sect1>
                <title>Male and hermaphrodite reproductive structures arise during postembryonic development</title>
                <para>An L1 larval male just hatched from the egg is not easily distinguished from a hermaphrodite of the same age. Yet by the time it is a mature adult it will be a very different animal. Not only will it have a radically distinct male gonad full of sperm joined to a posterior cloaca rather than a midbody vulva, it will also have a smaller, thinner body, a tail differentiated for copulation, new muscles, and an augmented and modified nervous system that gives it a whole new set of behaviors (<xref  linkend="figure1"/>). These differences arise because the developmental events that occur postembryonically are extensively different in the male and hermaphrodite. In some  tissues, cells that divide postembryonically (blast cells) do so in only one of the two sexes, giving rise to sex-specific cell lineages and differentiated cells. In other tissues, identical blast cells follow different cell lineages and generate different sets of progeny cells. Some already terminally differentiated cells reprogram significantly. Finally, in a matter of hours at the end of the last larval stage, dramatic morphogenetic processes reshape the male tail and generate the hypodermal mating structures.</para>
                <para>The detailed cellular architecture of the adult male and its postembryonic cell  lineages and development were described by Sulston and coworkers (<link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->). In this work, the lineal ancestry of each non-gonadal cell was identified from reconstruction of lineaged animals. The lineage and fates of cells in the male gonad were determined by <link linkend="bib40">Kimble and Hirsh (1979<!-- PMID 478167 -->)</link>. These papers are the starting points for any survey of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> male anatomy or development.</para>
                <para>In the present chapter, the results of studies on the genetic, cellular, and morphogenetic basis for development of each structure or feature, in so far as they are known, are summarized. These studies have revealed that male and hermaphrodite development involve largely the same set of genes. Some genes required for male development have been identified in genetic screens for defective males (many are named <emphasis>mab</emphasis> for <emphasis>m</emphasis>ale <emphasis>ab</emphasis>normal; e.g., <link linkend="bib31">Hodgkin, 1983</link><!-- PMID-->). Almost all of these genes also have functions in the hermaphrodite. The exceptions are the DM domain transcription factor genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-23;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-23</ulink></emphasis>, which appear to be dedicated specifically to aspects of male development (<link linkend="bib44">Lints and Emmons, 2002</link><!-- PMID 12231628 -->; <link linkend="bib60">Shen and Hodgkin, 1988</link><!-- PMID 3046751 -->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_somaticsexdeterm/somaticsexdeterm.html" role="_blank">Somatic sex determination</ulink>). Many additional genes required for male development have been identified among hermaphrodite developmental genes because of their pleiotropic effects on the male.</para>
                <para>Molecular studies of transcription patterns have given a similar result: only a small proportion of the genes are enriched in males. Whole-genome microarray analysis found that 4% of the genes were enriched greater than 2-fold in the male soma as compared to the hermaphrodite (<link linkend="bib36">Jiang et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11134517 -->). Of these, 14 were transcription factors that might play a more significant role in male development. Overall it appears that the difference between male and hermaphrodite development arises by the differential use of a common set of genes, directed into male-specific or hermaphrodite-specific developmental programs by the sex determination pathway (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_somaticsexdeterm/somaticsexdeterm.html" role="_blank">Somatic sex determination</ulink>).</para>
                <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
                <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig1" width="6in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 1</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig1legend; </mediaobject>
                </sect1>
                <sect1>
                <title>The major male mating structures form just before the last larval molt</title>
                <sect2>
                <title>The blunt, scalloped male tail with its extended fan forms in a rapid retraction of tail cells</title>
                <para>The major somatic reproductive structures of the adult male tail are the acellular fan, the rays, the sclerotic, hardened spicules, the specialized proctodeal chamber with its sclerotic, hardened roof (gubernaculum), and the hook (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). These structures form in the latter half of the L4 larval stage in a rapid morphogenetic episode covering only a few hours before the last larval molt. This period is characterized by a dramatic anterior retraction of the cells of the tail region (<link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->; <xref linkend="figure2"/>). Simultaneously, the fan is formed and the rays extend. Retraction is accompanied by fusion of the tail tip hypodermal cells, hyp8-11 (<link linkend="bib51">Nguyen et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10049567 -->). As retraction begins, first hyp8-11 and then more anterior hypodermal cells progressively withdraw from the L4 cuticle, which retains its tapered shape, the intervening space becoming filled with fluid. If the L4 cuticle is broken during this process (by making a hole with a laser), retraction stops, suggesting that one morphogenetic force driving the retraction process might be a build up of fluid pressure between the L4 and adult cuticles (unpublished experiments).</para>
                <para>The fan, consisting of a fold in the outer layer of the three-layered adult cuticle, forms as the cells of the tail retract. The adult cuticle forms under the L4 cuticle before retraction begins. Over most of the body the inner and outermost layers are attached by struts, but where the fan forms this is apparently not the case. As a consequence, as the future adult body surface pulls away, the inner layer of the adult cuticle withdraws with it, while laterally the outer layer separates and folds to make the fan. During retraction, muscles in the tail, including the sex-specific muscles (oblique muscles, diagonal muscles) pull and twitch, aiding the remodeling process.</para>
                <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
                        <imageobject>
                        <imagedata entityref="fig2" width="2.5in" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject>
                        <phrase> figure 2</phrase>
                        </textobject>
                        &fig2legend;
                </mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Retraction is a property of hypodermal cells</title>
<para>Hypodermal cells covering the surface of the tail that are likely to be involved in retraction and fan formation are hyp8-11, several cells descended from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">B.p</ulink>, and the posterior daughters of the ray precursor cells, the Rn.p cells. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">B.p</ulink> lineage hypodermal cells are arrayed on the ventral side of the L4 tail and constitute a large fraction of the volume of the tail at this time. They retract and withdraw significantly, probably shrinking in volume, during morphogenesis and eventually come to lie above the dorsal roof of the proctodeal chamber, where they form the gubernaculum (see <xref linkend="figure13"/>; <link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->).</para>
<para>The Rn.p cells, the hypodermal cells generated by the ray sublineage (<xref linkend="figure7"/>), at first enlarge over the lateral surfaces underlying the region where the fan cuticle will fold out (<xref linkend="figure3"/>A-C). Possibly they synthesize special cuticle in this region without attachments between the inner and outer layers. Later, R1.p to R5.p fuse to form a separate tail seam (<xref linkend="figure3"/>D and E), while R6.p to R9.p fuse with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=hyp;class=Cell" role="_blank">hyp</ulink> 7 (<xref linkend="figure3"/>F and G; <link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->).</para> 
<?newpage?>
<para>Lep (<emphasis role="underline">lep</emphasis>toderan, that is, having a pointed tail) mutants prevent retraction of hyp8-11 while leaving retraction of the other cells unaffected, giving rise to animals with normally-shaped tails except for having long tail tips (<link linkend="bib51">Nguyen et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10049567 -->). A number of so-called leptoderan species have a similar tail phenotype (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_phylogrhabditids/phylorhab.html" role="_blank">The phylogenetic relationships of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and other Rhabditids</ulink>). One Lep gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tlp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tlp-1</ulink></emphasis>, encodes a C2H2 Zn-finger presumptive transcription factor that may act downstream of a Wnt signal and cell-autonomously promote hyp8-11 retraction (<link linkend="bib78">Zhao et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 11880358 -->). Mutations in the posterior Hox gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> have the opposite effect of Lep mutants: hyp8-11 retract but the remaining tail cells do not and animals have blunt, rounded tails with little or no fan and no rays (<link linkend="bib14">Chisholm, 1991</link><!-- PMID 1879361 -->). An <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> reporter gene has robust expression in tail hypodermal cells for a brief period at the end of L4, suggesting that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> acts cell-autonomously in these cells to promote the retraction process (<link linkend="bib67">Teng et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15581880 -->).</para>
                <mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
                        <imageobject>
                        <imagedata entityref="fig3" width="7in" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject>
                        <phrase> figure 3</phrase>
                        </textobject>
                        &fig3legend;
                </mediaobject>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Male and hermaphrodite embryogenesis are similar but some essential male cell fates are already established at hatching</title>
<para>Male and hermaphrodite embryos generate the same set of cells and presumably have the same cell lineages, although the male embryonic cell lineage has not been explicitly determined. Some of the few overt differences between the male and the hermaphrodite hatchee arise by differential programmed cell deaths: in the male, the HSN neuron, which innervates the vulval muscles, dies, whereas in the hermaphrodite, the four CEM head sensory neurons die (<link linkend="bib63">Sulston and Horvitz, 1977</link><!-- PMID 838129 -->). In addition, in the hermaphrodite, both left-right pairs of coelomocytes are anterior of the gonad whereas in the male one of two left-side coelomocytes is posterior of the gonad primordium (<link linkend="bib63">Sulston and Horvitz, 1977</link><!-- PMID 838129 -->). Finally, the fates of some of the major blast cells appear to have been established by the end of embryogenesis. This is most obvious for the rectal epithelial cell B, which is enlarged in the male. Furthermore, although cellular anatomy of male and hermaphrodite L1 larvae is very similar, comparisons at the ultrastructural level have not been made. In particular, the connectivity of the nervous system in the adult male and in the L1 of either sex has not been determined and so it is not known to what extent the wiring established during embryogenesis may differ between the sexes.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Multiple pattern formation mechanisms specify cell fates in the tissues that generate the reproductive structures</title>
<sect2>
<title>Male mating structures arise from three important sets of male-specific blast cells</title>
<para>The mating structures of the male tail arise postembryonically from three sets of dividing cells (blast cells). The rays are from blast cells in the lateral hypodermis (V5, V6, T), the hook is from blast cells in the ventral hypodermis (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P10;class=Cell" role="_blank">P10</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P12;class=Cell" role="_blank">P11</ulink>), and the spicules and highly differentiated cloacal canal are from blast cells in the rectal epithelium (B, F, U, Y; <xref linkend="figure4"/>). The identities of these blast cells are in part fixed during embryogenesis and in part determined through signaling events that occur postembryonically. However, no major inducer or inducing tissue (such as the gonad), of male-specific tail development or of any male structure has been identified analogous to the anchor cell in development of the hermaphrodite vulva (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_vulvaldev/vulvaldev.html" role="_blank">Vulval development</ulink>; <link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->; <link linkend="bib64">Sulston and White, 1980</link><!-- PMID 7190941 -->). In the male tail, signals appear to come from multiple and sometimes redundant sources. The Hox genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> (ortholog of <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> <emphasis>ftz</emphasis>) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> (ortholog of <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> <emphasis>AbdominalB</emphasis>) play important roles in patterning all three of these generative tissues.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
                <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig4" width="3.5in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 4</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig4legend;
        </mediaobject>
</sect2>
<?newpage?>
<sect2>
<title>Cell-cell interactions specify the fates of the ray blast cells</title>
<para>The nine pairs of rays are generated by the three most posterior pairs of seam cells, V5, V6, and T (<xref linkend="figure4"/>). Though the rays are similar to each other in structure, each also has unique properties (see below). Hence each of these blast cells expresses a different developmental program.</para> <para>T is preprogrammed to give rise to rays 7, 8, and 9 (<xref linkend="figure4"/>). Asymmetric cell divisions in the T lineage require Wnt signaling. Correct orientation of cell divisions is dependent on expression of a Wnt ligand (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-44;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-44</ulink>) from the posteriormost hypodermal tail tip cells, hyp8-11 (<link linkend="bib29">Herman et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 7553861 -->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_wntsignaling/wntsignaling.html" role="_blank">Wnt signaling</ulink>). Hypomorphic alleles of the gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-19</ulink></emphasis> specifically disrupt the T lineage and result in loss of the T rays (<link linkend="bib65">Sutherlin and Emmons, 1994</link><!-- PMID 7851765 -->).</para>
<para>Anterior of  T all the way to the head, all the seam cells are to some degree equivalent to one another. All of them have a propensity to generate rays, but for V1-V4 this propensity is inhibited through a not well understood mechanism activated by contacts with their seam cell neighbor (<link linkend="bib1">Austin and Kenyon, 1994</link><!-- PMID 8149911 -->; <link linkend="bib64">Sulston and White, 1980</link><!-- PMID 7190941 -->). Inhibition requires the <emphasis>hairy</emphasis> homolog <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-22;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-22</ulink> and involves a Wnt pathway, which both promotes ray formation and orients cell division in the seam (<link linkend="bib49">Maloof et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 9834184 -->; <link linkend="bib72">Wrischnik and Kenyon, 1997</link><!-- PMID 9247331 -->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_wntsignaling/wntsignaling.html" role="_blank">Wnt signaling</ulink>). The inhibitory pathway prevents expression of the Hox gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis>, which promotes ray development (<link linkend="bib32">Hunter et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 9895327 -->). There is a directional bias to the signaling system: after a cell is experimentally removed it is the anterior neighbor that replaces it (<link linkend="bib64">Sulston and White, 1980</link><!-- PMID 7190941 -->).</para>
<para>V5 and V6 are preprogrammed to overcome this cell contact-mediated inhibition of ray formation. V6 overcomes the inhibitory effects of its neighbors by expressing the homeobox transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PAL-1</ulink>, an ortholog of <emphasis>Drosophila caudal</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib32">Hunter et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 9895327 -->; <link linkend="bib69">Waring and Kenyon, 1990</link><!-- PMID 2295086 -->). Genes required for establishing V5 identity remain unidentified. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> are essential for the V6 lineage program, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> is essential for V5 (<link linkend="bib14">Chisholm, 1991</link><!-- PMID 1879361 -->; <link linkend="bib38">Kenyon, 1986</link><!-- PMID 3731276 -->). In V6, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> is activated by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pal-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">pal-1</ulink></emphasis> during mid-embryogenesis (<link linkend="bib32">Hunter et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 9895327 -->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> is necessary for activation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> in certain lineage branches, giving rise to some of the differential properties of the rays (see below, <xref linkend="figure9"/>) and also for activation of the proneural bHLH transcription factor gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-32;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-32</ulink></emphasis>, which activates the ray sublineage itself (<link linkend="bib22">Ferreira et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10049576 -->; <link linkend="bib38">Kenyon, 1986</link><!-- PMID 3731276 -->; <link linkend="bib77">Zhao and Emmons, 1995</link><!-- PMID 7800042 -->). In the V5 lineage, the expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> cycles on and off repeatedly to regulate cell proliferation, ray formation, and ray identity (<link linkend="bib55">Salser and Kenyon, 1996</link><!-- PMID 8625851 -->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>EGF and Wnt signaling pattern Hox gene expression in hook blast cells P10-P12</title>
<para>Patterning within the ventral hypodermis that gives rise to the hook is established by the Hox genes. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> is initially expressed in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7</ulink>-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P12;class=Cell" role="_blank">P12</ulink> and remains on throughout postembryonic development in the descendants of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P7;class=Cell" role="_blank">P7</ulink>-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P11;class=Cell" role="_blank">P11</ulink> (<link linkend="bib56">Salser et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8103754 -->). Expression begins during mid-embryogenesis, shortly after these cells are born (<link linkend="bib18">Cowing and Kenyon, 1992</link><!-- PMID 1363090 -->). Expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> is activated in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P12;class=Cell" role="_blank">P12</ulink> descendants during L1 by an EGF signal (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-60;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-60</ulink> pathway) and a Wnt pathway signal (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-44;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-44</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-17;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-17</ulink>) and turns off <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> expression (<xref linkend="figure5"/>; <link linkend="bib22">Ferreira et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10049576 -->; <link linkend="bib34">Jiang and Sternberg, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9584132 -->). Thus, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> are mutually repressing: in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> mutants, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> remains on in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P12;class=Cell" role="_blank">P12</ulink> descendants and in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> mutants, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> comes on in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P10;class=Cell" role="_blank">P10</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P11;class=Cell" role="_blank">P11</ulink> descendants. These expression patterns correlate well with the genetic requirements for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> in specifying the fates of the respective cell sublineages (<link linkend="bib14">Chisholm, 1991</link><!-- PMID 1879361 -->; <link linkend="bib38">Kenyon, 1986</link><!-- PMID 3731276 -->; <link linkend="bib56">Salser et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8103754 -->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Multiple transcription factors, Wnt signaling, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-12;class=Gene" role="_blank"><emphasis>lin-12</emphasis></ulink> signaling specify cell fates in the hindgut</title>
<para>Epidermal blast cell B, which is a greatly enlarged and easily identifiable cell lying posterior of the rectum in the L1 male, is the major contributor to the internal structures of the male tail, giving rise to 42 cells that differentiate into the spicules, proctodeal chamber, and many neurons, including two of the sensory neurons of the post-cloacal sensilla. The remaining cells of the post-cloacal sensilla as well as an interneuron come from Y (11 progeny). F gives rise to two types of interneurons plus rectal epithelium (8 progeny) and U gives neurons similar in type to those from F and two rectal epithelial cells involved in joining the vas deferens to the cloaca (6 progeny). The locations of these cells around the rectum are shown in <xref linkend="figure4"/>.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
                        <imageobject>
                        <imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4.3in" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject>
                        <phrase> figure 5</phrase>
                        </textobject>
                        &fig5legend;
                </mediaobject>
<para>The fates of these cells, as well as the additional rectal cells K and K', are apparently fixed during embryogenesis (<link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->). F and U are sister cells and B and U are lineal homologs, while Y derives from an unrelated branch of the embryonic cell lineage. All of these cells require <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> for correct differentiation, apparently in both sexes (<link linkend="bib14">Chisholm, 1991</link><!-- PMID 1879361 -->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> mutant males, the cell lineages are very abnormal and none of the structures normally derived from them, including the spicules, proctodeum, and post-cloacal sensilla, are made.</para> <para>In addition to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis>, three transcription factors have been identified that contribute to specifying the fates of the rectal epithelial cells. In mutants of the Tbox transcription factor gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-9</ulink></emphasis>, B and F are transformed to Y and U, respectively (<link linkend="bib15">Chisholm and Hodgkin, 1989</link><!-- PMID 2606353 -->; <link linkend="bib71">Woollard and Hodgkin, 2000</link><!-- PMID 10716947 -->). In mutants of the PAX type transcription factor gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-38;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-38</ulink></emphasis>, F is transformed to B and U is transformed to Y (<link linkend="bib8">Chamberlin et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9374390 -->). In mutants for the C2H2-type Zn finger transcription factor gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-48;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-48</ulink></emphasis>, U is transformed to B (<link linkend="bib7">Chamberlin et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10511553 -->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-48;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-48</ulink></emphasis> is a direct transcriptional target of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-38;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-38</ulink> (<link linkend="bib37">Johnson et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11532910 -->). Finally, in mutants of the cell signaling gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis>, Y takes the fate of its sister cell, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DA9;class=Cell" role="_blank">DA9</ulink> motor neuron (<link linkend="bib26">Greenwald et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6616618 -->).</para> <para>A Wnt signaling pathway, activated by the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-44;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-44</ulink>/Wnt signal from the tail tip hypodermal cells through the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-17;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-17</ulink> receptor, is necessary for the asymmetry of the first division of B, which separates the precursor of the spicules (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B.a;class=Cell" role="_blank">B.a</ulink>) from the precursor of ventral hypodermis and dorsal proctodeal hypodermis (which generates the gubernaculum) and a few neurons (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">B.p</ulink>; <link linkend="bib28">Herman and Horvitz, 1994</link><!-- PMID 8026318 -->; <link linkend="bib61">Sternberg and Horvitz, 1988</link><!-- PMID 3181641 -->). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B.a;class=Cell" role="_blank">B.a</ulink> fate requires the <emphasis>Pax6</emphasis> transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-3;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-3</ulink> (<link linkend="bib11">Chamberlin and Sternberg, 1995</link><!-- PMID 7649393 -->). Further cell-cell interactions and inductions that pattern cell fates later in these lineages are described below.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Development of the male sensilla</title>
<sect2>
<title>Rays</title>
<sect3>
<title>Ray extension occurs during retraction</title>
<para>Among the several male-specific sensilla in the tail, the rays are the most  evident (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). The rays extend during the period of retraction when the fan forms (<xref linkend="figure2"/>). Each ray consists primarily of a tube of hypodermis (hyp7) inside of which run processes of two sensory neurons and the ray structural cell (<link linkend="bib17">Chow et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 8582275 -->; <link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->; <xref linkend="figure6"/>). At the tip, the structural cell, attached to the hypodermis by adherens junctions, surrounds the two neurons and creates a hole to the exterior. Either the structural cell grows around the neurons and fuses with itself, or the neurons create a hole through the structural cell. Extension of the ray requires the structural cell but what influence the structural cell exerts on the hypodermis and the mechanics of how the hypodermis itself extrudes this tubular element are not known (<link linkend="bib17">Chow et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 8582275 -->; <link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->).</para> <para>Close apposition of the cuticle around each ray requires a class of at least 8 genes in which mutations result in rays with an expanded, lumpy shape (Ram phenotype for <emphasis role="underline">ra</emphasis>y <emphasis role="underline">m</emphasis>orphology abnormal; <link linkend="bib3">Baird and Emmons, 1990</link><!-- PMID 2245913 -->). Three Ram genes, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ram-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ram-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ram-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">ram-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ram-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">ram-4</ulink></emphasis>, encode collagen proteins required specifically in the male tail (Y. L. Yu, W. S. Hui, Y. M. Lam and K. L. Chow, unpublished data). Two encode modifying enzymes: a membrane bound thioredoxin-like protein (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DPY-11;class=protein" role="_blank">DPY-11</ulink>) and a prolyl hydroxylase (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DPY-18;class=protein" role="_blank">DPY-18</ulink>), both expressed in the hypodermis; these two enzymes are likely responsible for posttranslational modifications of collagens and other matrix molecules synthesized in the hypodermis (<link linkend="bib30">Hill et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID -->; <link linkend="bib41">Ko and Chow, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11874914 -->; <link linkend="bib70">Winter and Page, 2000</link><!--; PMID -->). In addition, a novel transmembrane protein expressed in the ray structural cell (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RAM-5;class=protein" role="_blank">RAM-5</ulink>; <link linkend="bib75">Yu et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10899109 -->) and another type II transmembrane signaling molecule acting non-autonomously in the male tail region (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-7;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-7</ulink>; S. W. Tsang, C. Q. Nguyen, D. H. Hall and K. L. Chow, unpublished) are both required for cell cell communication events between the structural cells and hypodermis in the male tail. These gene products acting on the cell surface and the matrix likely participate in cross-linking ray cell components and transducing signals among the cells in each sensory ray.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig6" width="4.5in"  align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase> figure 6</phrase>
</textobject>
&fig6legend;
</mediaobject>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Rays are positioned by hypodermal cells</title>
<para>The position where each ray forms is determined by the site where its structural cell attaches to the hypodermis and cuticle. Attachment occurs during the L4 larval stage before retraction begins. The ray cells are born within the hypodermal layer, joined to each other and to hypodermal cells by adherens junctions (<xref linkend="figure3"/>A and B). Their anteroposterior order in the seam is the same as their final order within the fan except that ray 6 cells are born between ray 4 and ray 5 cells (<xref linkend="figure7"/>B). Thus, with the exception of ray 6, anteroposterior ray order is determined by the cell lineage.</para>
<para>The spacing and locations of the rays may be determined in part by interactions with the Rn.p cells, the hypodermal cells generated at the first division of the ray sublineage (<xref linkend="figure7"/>A). Ray cell clusters tend to locate at the junctions of two Rn.p cells, which spread out over the surface in a distinctive pattern (<xref linkend="figure3"/>C). Ray 5 and 7 cell clusters are born above their respective Rn.p cells; the others are born below. As the neurons and structural cell differentiate, the attachment point of the ray 1 structural cell moves out of the seam into the dorsal hypodermal territory, those of rays 2 and 4 move into the ventral territory, and those of rays 3 and 9 remain in the seam (<xref linkend="figure3"/>F). As a result of these initial localizations and subsequent displacements, when retraction occurs the tips of rays 1, 5, and 7 open on the dorsal surface of the fan, 2, 4, and 8 open on the ventral surface, and 3 and 9 open at the fan margin (<link linkend="bib4">Baird et al., 1991</link><!-- PMID 1782863 -->). Ray 6 does not open to the exterior and is localized by being below R6.p, which itself moves ventrally out of the seam.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout> 
<mediaobject id="figure7" xreflabel="Figure 7">
                <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig7" width="4.5in"  align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 7</phrase>
                </textobject>
                &fig7legend;
        </mediaobject>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>The rays have distinct morphogenetic identities</title>
<para>In addition to involving interactions between ray cells and surrounding hypodermal cells, ray formation requires a sorting process involving the ray cells themselves. In this sorting process, each structural cell interacts with and surrounds the neurons belonging to its own ray and rejects interactions with the structural cells and neurons of the other rays. Failure of this system in mutants results in adults with fused rays (<link linkend="bib4">Baird et al., 1991</link><!-- PMID 1782863 -->). This phenotype indicates that in wild type, the rays express functions that give the cells distinct morphogenetic identities allowing for their proper assembly into individual organs.</para>
<para>The conserved semaphorin, ephrin, and TGF<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signaling pathways are involved in regulating both the interactions between ray cells and hypodermal cells and the interactions among the ray cells themselves. The sensitive response of the ray system to the functioning of the semaphorin and ephrin signaling pathways has allowed an elegant series of studies defining the components of these pathways. Interaction between ray 1 cells and the hypodermal cell R1.p is regulated by the semaphorins semaphorin 1a (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SMP-1</ulink>) and semaphorin 1b (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMP-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SMP-2</ulink>) and their corresponding receptor PlexinA (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PLX-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PLX-1</ulink>; <link linkend="bib24">Fujii et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 11959816 -->; <link linkend="bib25">Ginzburg et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 11959817 -->). The anteroposterior position of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PLX-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PLX-1</ulink>-expressing ray 1 is influenced by a semaphorin 1 signal emanating from the hook (<link linkend="bib19">Dalpe et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15073148 -->). Interactions between ray cells are regulated by semaphorin 2a (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-20;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-20</ulink>), ephrin-4 (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EFN-4;class=protein" role="_blank">EFN-4</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-26;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-26</ulink>), and a TGF<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signal (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-129;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-129</ulink>) (<link linkend="bib4">Baird et al., 1991</link><!-- PMID 1782863 -->; <link linkend="bib13">Chin-Sang et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12403719 -->; <link linkend="bib16">Chow and Emmons, 1994</link><!-- PMID 7956833 -->; <link linkend="bib33">Ikegami et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15030761 -->; <link linkend="bib54">Roy et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10648234 -->). The ligands <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-20;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-20</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EFN-4;class=protein" role="_blank">EFN-4</ulink> are expressed in most or all the rays (<link linkend="bib27">Hahn and Emmons, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12679110 -->; <link linkend="bib54">Roy et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10648234 -->). The ray-specificity of their effects may be brought about by the ray-specific expression patterns of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-129;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-129</ulink> and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-20;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-20</ulink> receptor <emphasis>plexin 2</emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PLX-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PLX-2</ulink>; <link linkend="bib33">Ikegami et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15030761 -->).</para>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Ray cells are generated by a sublineage</title>
<para>The three cells of each ray descend from a single neuroblast (ray precursor cell) that expresses a stereotyped cell sublineage during the L3 and L4 larval stages (<xref linkend="figure7"/>; <link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->; <link linkend="bib63">Sulston and Horvitz, 1977</link><!-- PMID 838129 -->). Expression of this sublineage requires the proneural bHLH transcription factors <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-32;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-32</ulink>, an ortholog of <emphasis>Drosophila atonal</emphasis>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HLH-2;class=protein" role="_blank">HLH-2</ulink>, an E<emphasis>/daughterless</emphasis> ortholog, presumably acting as a heterodimer (<link linkend="bib52">Portman and Emmons, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11076762 -->; <link linkend="bib77">Zhao and Emmons, 1995</link><!-- PMID 7800042 -->). The DM domain transcription factor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis>, a member of a conserved class of male-specific regulatory transcription factors, enhances the activities of these two proteins and is required for efficient ray production (<link linkend="bib60">Shen and Hodgkin, 1988</link><!-- PMID 3046751 -->; <link linkend="bib73">Yi et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 11003845 -->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-32;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-32</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HLH-2;class=protein" role="_blank">HLH-2</ulink> are required not only for expression of the ray sublineage and neurogenic potential, but also for expression of specific differentiated properties of the ray neurons and support cell (<link linkend="bib52">Portman and Emmons, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11076762 -->).</para> <para>Differentiation of the ray cells occurs very rapidly after they are born. They delaminate out of the hypodermal layer leaving behind cell processes as their cell bodies move into the lumbar ganglia (<link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->; <xref linkend="figure3"/>). From there, ray neuron axons grow through circumferential commissures and enter the preanal ganglion, where they branch and make multiple synaptic contacts (see section 7).</para>
<para>Additional genes expressed in the ray sublineage and in mature ray cells have been identified by microarray experiments, taking advantage of the rayless phenotype of a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-32;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-32</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=hlh-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">hlh-2</ulink></emphasis> double mutant (<link linkend="bib53">Portman and Emmons, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15183729 -->). Prominent among differentiation genes expressed in all the rays are a <symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-tubulin isoform, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tbb-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">tbb-4</ulink></emphasis>, (A and B-type neurons) and components of the presumptively mechanosensory polycystin signaling pathway, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lov-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lov-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pkd-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">pkd-2</ulink></emphasis> (B-type neurons only), as well as four novel genes (<emphasis>cwp</emphasis> genes) co-expressed with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lov-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lov-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pkd-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">pkd-2</ulink></emphasis> and postulated to constitute additional components of the pathway (<link linkend="bib5">Barr et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID 11553327 -->; <link linkend="bib6">Barr and Sternberg, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10517638 -->; <link linkend="bib53">Portman and Emmons, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15183729 -->). There are many additional genes expressed in subsets of the rays as explained in the next section.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Ray identities are determined by a combination of lineage and signaling mechanisms</title>
<para>In addition to having distinct morphogenetic identities, as discussed above (see section 5.1.3), the rays also have distinct molecular identities. Although the A-type and B-type neurons are considered to represent two distinct neuron types because of shared ultrastructural features (<link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->), within each type neurons in different rays also have unique features that define molecular subtypes. This property supports the observation that different rays play somewhat differing roles in guiding male copulation (<link linkend="bib47">Liu and Sternberg, 1995</link><!-- PMID 7826644 -->). Subtype-specific genes include those associated with neurotransmitter synthesis (<xref linkend="figure8"/>; <link linkend="bib43">Lints and Emmons, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10572056 -->; <link linkend="bib45">Lints et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15081363 -->; <link linkend="bib48">Loer and Kenyon, 1993</link><!-- PMID 8254383 -->; <link linkend="bib58">Schinkmann and Li, 1992</link><!-- PMID -->; <link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->) and genes encoding receptors (<link linkend="bib53">Portman and Emmons, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15183729 -->; <link linkend="bib68">Troemel et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 7585938 -->). Subtypes also appear to have subtype-specific patterns of synaptic targets within the lumbar and pre-anal ganglia and hence presumably also differentially express yet to be defined genes associated with axon targeting (SWE, D. Albertson, D. Hall and M. Xu, unpublished observations).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
                <mediaobject id="figure8" xreflabel="Figure 8">
                        <imageobject>
                        <imagedata entityref="fig8" width="4.5in" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject>
                        <phrase> figure 8</phrase>
                        </textobject>
                        &fig8legend;
                </mediaobject>

        <mediaobject id="figure9" xreflabel="Figure 9">
                <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig9" width="5in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 9</phrase>
                </textobject>
                &fig9legend;
        </mediaobject>
        <para>Ray neuron subtype and ray morphogenetic identity are established coordinatelythus each ray has a unique ray identity (<link linkend="bib45">Lints et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15081363 -->). Ray identities are established by the time the ray precursor cells are born. Determined cell fates are established at each division of the cell lineage, no regulation of cell fates being observed in cell ablation experiments once the V5, V6 and T blast cells begin to divide (<link linkend="bib16">Chow and Emmons, 1994</link><!-- PMID 7956833 -->; <link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->; <link linkend="bib64">Sulston and White, 1980</link><!-- PMID 7190941 -->). Critical expression patterns of the Hox genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> in the ray precursor cells and ray sublineages are set up during this postembryonic lineage period and appear to constitute one central element of the pattern formation mechanism for the V5 and V6 lineages (<xref linkend="figure9"/>; <link linkend="bib22">Ferreira et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10049576 -->; <link linkend="bib55">Salser and Kenyon, 1996</link><!-- PMID 8625851 -->). A TGF<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signal further defines the identity of ray 5 (<link linkend="bib43">Lints and Emmons, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10572056 -->). Patterning of the T rays (rays 7-9) is also affected by a TGF<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signal (<link linkend="bib42">Liang et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14627718 -->; <link linkend="bib50">Morita et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10021351 -->; <link linkend="bib57">Savage-Dunn et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8570636 -->; <link linkend="bib66">Suzuki et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 9847238 -->).</para>
<para>Details of a transcription factor code underlying ray identity have been most clearly established for the V6 rays (rays 2-6; <xref linkend="figure10"/>; <link linkend="bib16">Chow and Emmons, 1994</link><!-- PMID 7956833 -->; <link linkend="bib17">Chow et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 8582275 -->; <link linkend="bib43">Lints and Emmons, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10572056 -->; <link linkend="bib45">Lints et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15081363 -->; <link linkend="bib76">Zhang and Emmons, 1995</link><!-- PMID 7659160 -->). For rays 2-6, expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> separates non-ray 2 states from a ray 2 ground state. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> alone promotes ray 3 identity. Addition of a signal of the TGF<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> family (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DBL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DBL-1</ulink>) differentially received by ray 5 elevates this ray to ray 5 identity. Expression of a <emphasis>PAX6</emphasis> isoform (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-18;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-18</ulink>) in ray 6 differentiates this identity from that of other rays. Expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> separates ray 2 identity from ray 1 identity (<link linkend="bib55">Salser and Kenyon, 1996</link><!-- PMID 8625851 -->). Additional regulatory pathways yet to be defined (most likely including the Wnt pathway) are required for a complete model.</para>
                <mediaobject id="figure10" xreflabel="Figure 10">
                        <imageobject>
                        <imagedata entityref="fig10" width="3.25in"  align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <textobject>
                        <phrase>figure 10</phrase>
                        </textobject>
                        &fig10legend;
                </mediaobject>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>The hook and hook sensillum develop from an equivalence group</title>
<para>The hook, which appears during the process of retraction in L4 lethargus, is a sclerotized point of cuticle formed by the ventral hypodermal cell <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P10.papp;class=Cell" role="_blank">P10.papp</ulink>. As the contractions of the diagonal muscles pull the adult cuticle away from the L4 cuticle on the ventral side, the hook is left protruding from the surface. Considerable rearrangements of underlying hypodermal cells that contribute to the structure occur during this process (<link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->).</para>
<para>The nine cells that together form the hook and hook sensillum are born during the L3 larval stage from cell lineages generated by the posterior daughters of the ventral neuroectoblast cells <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P10;class=Cell" role="_blank">P10</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P11;class=Cell" role="_blank">P11</ulink>: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P11.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P11.p</ulink> contributes three hook-associated hypodermal cells and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P10.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P10.p</ulink> generates the cells of the sensillum (the two neurons <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HOA;class=Cell" role="_blank">HOA</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HOB;class=Cell" role="_blank">HOB</ulink>, a socket cell and a sheath cell) and the hypodermal cell that generates the hook proper (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P10.papp;class=Cell" role="_blank">P10.papp</ulink>; <link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->; <xref linkend="figure6" />). As is the case with the Pn.p cells that generate the hermaphrodite vulva (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_vulvaldev/vulvaldev.html" role="_blank">Vulval development</ulink>), the fates of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P10.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P10.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P11.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P11.p</ulink> are established by cell signaling within an equivalence group that also includes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P9.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P9.p</ulink>. P9.p, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P10.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P10.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P11.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P11.p</ulink> fates all require <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib38">Kenyon, 1986</link><!-- PMID 3731276 -->; <link linkend="bib56">Salser et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID 8103754 -->). These three cells have equal potential and form an equivalence group in which <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P11.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P11.p</ulink> fate is 1<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P10.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P10.p</ulink> fate is 2<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P9.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P9.p</ulink> fate (fusion with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=hyp;class=Cell" role="_blank">hyp</ulink> 7 or division followed by fusion of its daughters) is 3<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> (<link linkend="bib64">Sulston and White, 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->). In equivalence groups, cells of equal potential communicate to allocate separate fates. They do so in such a way that after removal of one cell (in a cell ablation experiment) the remaining cells alter their fates in a hierarchical fashion: 2<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> replaces 1<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> and 3<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> replaces 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol>. Patterning within the P9.p-P11.p equivalence group requires genes of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> signaling pathways, with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink> defining the 2<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00B0;</symbol> fate, as it does in the vulval equivalence group (<link linkend="bib26">Greenwald et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6616618 -->). However, so far, no source of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-3;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink>/EGF has been identified and details of the patterning mechanism remain unclear (<link linkend="bib20">Emmons, 1997</link><!-- PMID 9097722 -->; <link linkend="bib21">Emmons and Sternberg, 1997</link><!--; PMID -->).</para>
<para>Specification of the differentiated properties of the neurons has been explored for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HOB;class=Cell" role="_blank">HOB</ulink>. A key element of the signal transduction mechanism of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HOB;class=Cell" role="_blank">HOB</ulink>, which may involve mechanosensation of the vulval lips, is constituted by polycystin proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LOV-1;class=protein" role="_blank">LOV-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PKD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PKD-2</ulink>. These proteins are also present in two other classes of male-specific sensory neurons, the RnB neurons of the rays and the CEM neurons (<link linkend="bib6">Barr and Sternberg, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10517638 -->). The proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-46;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-46</ulink>, a C2H2-type zinc-finger transcription factor, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-44;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-44</ulink>, a transcription enhancer factor of the TEA domain class, are required for expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lov-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lov-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pkd-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">pkd-2</ulink></emphasis> in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HOB;class=Cell" role="_blank">HOB</ulink> (but not in RnB; <link linkend="bib74">Yu et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Post-cloacal sensilla</title>
<para>Sulston and coworkers (1980) established the structure of the paired sensilla, each containing three sensory neurons (PCA, PCB, and PCC) located just posterior of the cloaca, and the lineal origin of each cell (<xref linkend="figure6"/>). All are from the Y lineage except <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PCCL;class=Cell" role="_blank">PCCL</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PCCR;class=Cell" role="_blank">PCCR</ulink>, which are from the B lineage. Apart from the studies of genes that are involved in specifying the Y and B cell fates, discussed above (see section 4.4), studies of specification and differentiation of the cells of the post-cloacal sensilla themselves have not been reported.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Spicules</title>
<sect3>
<title>Spicule elongation occurs by a cell migration induced by a TGF<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> signal</title>
<para>Each hardened, elongated spicule is composed of two sensory neurons which are exposed at the tip (SPV and SPD), two sheath cells, and four socket cells (<xref     linkend="figure6"/>). The sheath cells are fused into a syncytium, as are the socket cells. A third sensory neuron (SPC) is attached to the muscle at the base of the spicule and appears to signal the protracted or retracted state of the spicule to the spicule muscles. Spicule cells are born at the end of the L3 larval stage and differentiate and elongate during the second half of L4 (<link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->).</para>
<para>Spicule elongation and formation of the hardened, sclerotic cuticle that covers the spicule requires the outer socket cells but not the inner sheath cells or neurons (<link linkend="bib35">Jiang and Sternberg, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10373307 -->). Initially a spicule trace is formed in early L4 and elongates following anterior migrations of two B-lineage proctodeal cells (B.a(l/r)apapa and B.a(l/r)appv) that attach at the base of each spicule. Anterior migration of the proctodeal cells and elongation of the spicule require a signal of the TGF<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol> family (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DBL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DBL-1</ulink> ligand, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DAF-4;class=protein" role="_blank">DAF-4</ulink> Type II receptor), probably generated by spicule muscles (<link linkend="bib2">Baird and Ellazar, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10419688 -->; <link linkend="bib35">Jiang and Sternberg, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10373307 -->). A signal of the FGF pathway (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-17;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-17</ulink> receptor) has also been implicated (<link linkend="bib35">Jiang and Sternberg, 1999</link><!-- PMID 10373307 -->). As the spicule cells migrate, they spread around a ridge of proctodeal cells which form a mold for the final, scalloped shape of the spicules (<link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->).</para>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>A complex set of cell-cell interactions specify cell fates in the B lineage</title>
<para>Cell fates in the complex <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B.a;class=Cell" role="_blank">B.a</ulink> cell lineage that generates the cells of the spicules are influenced by a network of partially redundant intercellular signals coming from their neighbors in the rectal epithelium. Signals come from F and U on the anterior side and from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">Y.p</ulink> on the posterior side as well as from cells of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B.a;class=Cell" role="_blank">B.a</ulink> lineage itself (<link linkend="bib9">Chamberlin and Sternberg, 1993</link><!-- PMID 8223264 -->; <link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->). The F/U signal involves the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-3;class=Gene" role="_blank"><emphasis>lin-3</emphasis></ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-23;class=Gene" role="_blank"><emphasis>let-23</emphasis></ulink> EGF pathway; lateral signaling involves the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> pathway (<link linkend="bib10">Chamberlin and Sternberg, 1994</link><!-- PMID 7607066 -->).</para>
<para>The initial division of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B.a;class=Cell" role="_blank">B.a</ulink> is left/right (l/r) and this division generates equivalent cells (<xref linkend="figure11"/>B). These cells next divide along the anteroposterior (a/p) axis two times (<xref linkend="figure11"/>C, D). Unlike the initial l/r division, these a/p divisions generate daughter cells with different potentials, thereby giving rise to two identical l/r sets of four non-equivalent cells (8 cells in all). Next, the most anterior l/r pair migrates around the rectum to its ventral side (<xref linkend="figure11"/>D). These two cells and the most posterior l/r pair interdigitate at the midline respectively below and above the rectal channel, which thereby becomes surrounded by two rings of four cells (<xref linkend="figure11"/>E). As with some other bilateral pairs of cells that come together into a single longitudinal row (for example most of the Pn cells that generate ventral cord neurons), there is no correlation between left/right origin and final anteroposterior position in the rowthe cells are equivalent initially and differences are induced by asymmetric signals after they arrive at the midline. Among the B-lineage cells, the difference in cell fates between the cells of the anterior ring and those of the posterior ring is induced by the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-3</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-23;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-23</ulink></emphasis> signal from F and U, which is modified by the further signals from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">Y.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B.a;class=Cell" role="_blank">B.a</ulink> cells. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B.a;class=Cell" role="_blank">B.a</ulink> cells also have further modulating influences on the primary signals (<xref linkend="figure12" />; <link linkend="bib10">Chamberlin and Sternberg, 1994</link><!-- PMID 7607066 -->).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure11" xreflabel="Figure 11">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig11" width="6in" align="center"/>
</imageobject> <textobject>
<phrase> figure 11</phrase>
</textobject> &fig11legend;
</mediaobject>
<literallayout>
</literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure12" xreflabel="Figure 12">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig12" width="4in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase> figure 12</phrase>
</textobject>
&fig12legend;
</mediaobject>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>A sex-specific structure of the phasmids develops postembryonically</title>
<para>During the second half of postembryonic development, the posterior sensory structure common to both sexes, the phasmid, undergoes different development in the two sexes. The two phasmid socket cells, generated postembryonically from the T lineage, are added to the phasmid by L2. At this time, the two sexes are similar. In the adult hermaphrodite, the two sensory neurons are enveloped by a sheath cell and two layers of socket cells, the outermost, PHso2, attaching to the hypodermis. In the male, there is only a single socket cell, PHso2. PHso1 no longer envelops the sheath cell and develops some apparently neuronal characteristics, extending fingers into the sheath and having a basal body (<link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->). The functional significance of these changes is not known.</para>
</sect2> 
</sect1>
        <sect1>
        <title>The hindgut is highly differentiated to accommodate the spicules and the joining of the reproductive tract</title>
        <para>The proctodeum is the chamber just inside the cloaca where four channels come together: the vas deferens, the gut, and the two left/right spicule channels (<xref linkend="figure13"/>). The roof of the proctodeum is covered by sclerotic cuticle, forming a structure called the gubernaculum. The gubernaculum presumably guides the tips of the spicules down and out of the cloaca. The proctodeal chamber enlarges and the gubernaculum forms along with elongation of the spicules during the second half of L4. The gubernaculum is formed by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B.paa;class=Cell" role="_blank">B.paa</ulink> with possible contributions from B<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x03B3;</symbol>l and B<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x03B3;</symbol>r (<link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->). Other cells making up the walls of the proctodeum include additional cells from the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B.a;class=Cell" role="_blank">B.a</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">B.p</ulink> lineages, K.a and K', and P12.pa (<xref linkend="figure13"/>).</para>
        <para>The gut, which is of course attached to the cloacal canal from embryogenesis, joins the proctodeum via K.a and K'. The vas deferens attaches when the gonad arrives at the posterior during L4. At this time, K.a and K' as well as B.a(l/r)apaav extend out from the rectal wall and reach around the vas deferens cells, attaching to them. Attachment requires that the first-arriving cell of the gonad, the leader cell, be engulfed by either <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=U.lp;class=Cell" role="_blank">U.lp</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=U.rp;class=Cell" role="_blank">U.rp</ulink>. In the absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=U.lp;class=Cell" role="_blank">U.lp</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=U.rp;class=Cell" role="_blank">U.rp</ulink>, K.a and K' show no affinity for the gonad and the connection is not made (<link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->).</para>
        <para>Differentiation of the proctodeum is affected by many of the genes required for patterning the fates and progeny of B (see above; section 4.4; <link linkend="bib7">Chamberlin et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID 10511553 -->; <link linkend="bib59">Sewell et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14512020 -->). Attachment of the proctodeal wall to the gonad requires the DM domain transcription factor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-23;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-23</ulink></emphasis>, which is expressed in the attaching cells K.a and K' and in cells of the U lineage, including the ones necessary to engulf the leader cell. In a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mab-23;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-23</ulink></emphasis> mutant, rectal cells fail to extend towards and contact the gonadal cells, which apparently remain unattached, allowing sperm to pass into the coelomic cavity (<link linkend="bib44">Lints and Emmons, 2002</link><!-- PMID 12231628 -->).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure13" xreflabel="Figure 13">
        <imageobject>
        <imagedata entityref="fig13" width="5.3in" align="center"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
        <phrase> figure 13</phrase>
        </textobject>
        &fig13legend;
        </mediaobject>
        </sect1>
        <sect1>
        <title>Male-specific neuronal circuitry develops during L4</title>
        <para>Male behavior is augmented extensively over that of the hermaphrodite to bring about transfer of the gametes. If a male contacts a hermaphrodite, he makes attempts at copulation. When hermaphrodites are present, males remain with them, but if hermaphrodites are absent, males engage in mate-searching (<link linkend="bib46">Lipton et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15329389 -->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_malematingbehavior/malematingbehavior.html" role="_blank">Male mating behavior</ulink>). The male nervous system has almost the same set of neurons as the hermaphrodite plus some 79 additional neurons, almost all in the tail. Some neurons in the common set are modified in the male. For example, PHC, which has a process in the tail <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=spike;class=Cell" role="_blank">spike</ulink>, has a striated rootlet in the male and many additional synapses over that of the hermaphrodite (<link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->). Similarly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PDB;class=Cell" role="_blank">PDB</ulink>, an interneuron, has many more branches in the male pre-anal ganglion than in the hermaphrodite. How extensive such sex-specific modification of common neurons is will remain unknown until there is a reconstruction of the male nervous system.</para>
        <para>The neurons in the male tail that are born during postembryonic development are the last neurons in the nervous system to differentiate. Some of these differentiate in a matter of hours at the end of the L4 larval stage, sending out their axons into the existing neuropil to find their targets.</para>
        </sect1>
        <sect1>
        <title>A complex male-specific program generates many new muscles for copulation</title>
        <para>The muscles generated during embryogenesis are the same in males and hermaphrodites. Additional muscles arise postembryonically from a single mesoblast, the M cell, the initial divisions of which during L1 are also similar in the two sexes and generate 14 new body wall muscles (<link linkend="bib63">Sulston and Horvitz, 1977</link><!-- PMID 838129 -->). However, whereas in the hermaphrodite two M cell progeny divide further to make sex muscles, in the male these same cells plus four additional cells that in the hermaphrodite become coelomocytes are also sex mesoblasts. In the hermaphrodite, the two sex mesoblasts migrate anteriorly and generate vulval muscles, while in the male the six sex mesoblasts migrate posteriorly into the tail.</para>
        <para>The sex mesoblasts (three left-right symmetrical pairs) begin to divide again during the L3 larval stage and by the end of L3 have generated 41 new muscles and a coelomocyte (<link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->). Ten of the new muscles run longitudinally along the body wall, apparently supplementing the embryonic body wall muscles in this region. Fifteen form muscles called diagonal muscles that attach between the ventral and mid-lateral body wall and aid in the curling of the tail during copulation (<link linkend="bib48">Loer and Kenyon, 1993</link><!-- PMID 8254383 -->). The remaining 16 cells differentiate into muscles that control the spicules (8) and gubernaculum (4), or that run across the tail posterior of the anus to pull the dorsal and ventral body walls together (4).</para>
        <para>In addition to having these new muscles, the male enlarges the intestinal sphincter, which surrounds the gut and controls its opening into the proctodeal chamber, and reorganizes the orientation and attachments of the myofilaments in the anal depressor muscle (<link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->). Each of these changes presumably aid ejaculation.</para>
        </sect1>
<sect1>
         <title>The cell lineage that gives rise to the asymmetric male gonad is a variation on that of the hermaphrodite</title>
        <para>The adult male gonad, radically distinct from that of the hermaphrodite, develops from a superficially identical gonad primordium located at the midbody. The gonadal primordium consists of two germ cells (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z2;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z3;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z3</ulink>) flanked by two somatic precursor cells (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4</ulink>). In both sexes, the developing gonad grows out from this primordium to establish its elongated, tubular form. Compared to that of the hermaphrodite, outgrowth in the male occurs in the opposite orientation with respect to the ultimate polarity of the gonad. That is, whereas in the hermaphrodite the midbody location of the gonad primordium will become the proximal end of the gonad (the site of attachment of the uterus to the vulval opening) and the developing gonad will grow out towards the distal end of the ovary (the site of mitotically dividing germ cells), in the male the site of the primordium becomes the distal end of the testes and the developing gonad grows out towards the future site of attachment and opening of the vas deferens at the cloaca in the tail (<link linkend="bib40">Kimble and Hirsh, 1979</link><!-- PMID 478167 -->). Outgrowth in the male is lead by a linker cell instead of by a distal tip cell as in the hermaphrodite. The linker cell has to be engulfed upon arriving at the cloaca by rectal epithelial cells of the U lineage before additional rectal cells (K.a, K', and B.a(l/r)apaav) attach to the vas deferens (<link linkend="bib62">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7409314 -->).</para>
    <para>A second difference between male and hermaphrodite gonads is that, whereas the hermaphrodite gonad is two-armed and symmetric, that of the male gonad is one-armed and asymmetric. Development of asymmetry in the male gonad appears already after the second division of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4</ulink>, when <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4.a;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4.a</ulink> migrates anteriorly to join <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1.p</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1.a;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1.a</ulink> migrates posteriorly to join <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4.p</ulink>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1.a;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1.a</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4.p</ulink> will not divide again and will remain at midbody, becoming the distal tip cells at the distal end of the testes. These, like their hermaphrodite counterparts, are required to maintain distal germ cells in mitosis. Interactions among descendants of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4.a;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4.a</ulink> result in the selection of a single cell to function as the linker cell. This is analogous to the cell-cell interactions between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1.p</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4.a;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4.a</ulink> descendants (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1.ppp;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1.ppp</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4.aaa;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4.aaa</ulink>) in the hermaphrodite that select one cell to assume the anchor cell fate (<link linkend="bib39">Kimble, 1981</link><!-- PMID 7286433 -->). Anchor cell and male linker cell have the similar function of attaching the proximal end of the gonad to the opening to the exterior. Thus, in spite of radically differing organization, underlying analogies in cell fate assignments in the male and hermaphrodite lineages are clearly discernable (<link linkend="bib40">Kimble and Hirsh, 1979</link><!-- PMID 478167 -->). Both sexes appear to utilize a single underlying gonad developmental program that is modulated at points to suit the sex of the animal. Not surprisingly, a number of developmental genes, including <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> and the Wnt receptor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-17;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-17</ulink></emphasis>, are required for gonad development in both sexes. One transcription factor that appears to play a more significant role in specifying the male pathway is the forkhead transcription factor gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fkh-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">fkh-6</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib12">Chang et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 14993191 -->).</para>
 </sect1>
                <sect1>
                <title>Acknowledgements</title>
                <para>I thank K. Chow, R. Ghosh, G. Kleemann, R. Lints, and P. Sternberg for their comments on the manuscript and D. Portman for contribution to <xref linkend="figure6"/>. Work in the author's laboratory is funded by the US National Institutes of Health. SWE is the Siegfried Ullmann Professor of Molecular Genetics.</para>
                </sect1>
                <sect1>
                <title>References</title>
                <para/>
                &maledev_Refs; 
               </sect1> 
</article>