<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 3. The evolving pattern of cells on the lateral surface of the L4 male tail
            determines where the rays will extend</title>
        <para>Cell boundaries in the hypodermal layer have been drawn as visualized by an antibody
            to a component of adherens junctions. The dashed line is an outline of the body. (A)
            After the first two divisions of the ray sublineage, each ray precursor cell has
            generated three cells. hyp7, the large hypodermal syncytium that covers most of the
            body; hyp8-11, the tail tip hypodermal cells. (B) After the sublineage is completed, the
            two ray neurons (Rn.aaa and Rn.apa) and structural cell (Rn.app, see <xref linkend="figure7"/>) cluster against the corresponding Rn.p hypodermal cell. Rn.p is the posterior hypodermal
            daughter of the ray precursor cell Rn (see <xref linkend="figure7"/>). (C) The neurons and structural
            cells have withdrawn leaving attachments at the surface, while the Rn.p cells have
            enlarged. R1.p and R2.p are beginning to fuse. hyp8-11 have fused to form the tail
            syncytium (tsy). Ph: phasmid. se: body seam. (D) R1.p to R5.p are almost finished fusing
            to form the tail seam (set). The neurons have completely withdrawn, leaving only the
            structural cell attached to the hypodermis. (E) Imunofluorescent photomicrograph of
            animal shown in D. (F) The structural cells (Rnst) are displaced from the lateral line
            where the margin of the fan will form. R1st, R5st, and R7st are dorsal of the lateral
            line, while R2st, R4st and R8st are ventral of it. Rays 3 and 9 remain at the margin.
            Ray 6 does not open to the exterior. (G) The set retracts after the structural cells
            become irreversibly attached on the surface. H. Adult male tail. Ph: phasmid. I. Adult
            hermaphrodite tail for comparison. Reprinted from Fitch and Emmons (1995).</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>
