<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig7 SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig7.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig7legend SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig7leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig8 SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig8.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig8legend SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig8leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig9 SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig9.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig9legend SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig9leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig9 SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig9.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig9legend SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig9leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig10 SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig10.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig10legend SYSTEM 'gastrulationfig10leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY gastrulation_Refs SYSTEM 'gastrulationrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="Gastrulation_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Gastrulation in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis><footnote><para>Edited by James R. Priess and Geraldine Seydoux. Last revised March 11, 2005. Published September 26, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Nance, J. et al. Gastrulation in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (September 26, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.23.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 Jeremy Nance, et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
</footnote></title>
        <!--	<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 3/11/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory> 
-->
        <author>
            <othername>Jeremy Nance<superscript>1,</superscript><remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:nance@saturn.med.nyu.edu">nance@saturn.med.nyu.edu</ulink>, <ulink url="mailto:jenyilee@berkeley.edu">jenyilee@berkeley.edu</ulink> or <ulink url="mailto:bobg@unc.edu">bobg@unc.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark>, Jen-Yi Lee<superscript>2,</superscript><remark><superscript>&#x000A7;</superscript></remark><remark><footnote><para>Current address: Department of Molecular and Cell Biology, University of California, Berkeley, CA 94720 USA</para></footnote></remark>, Bob Goldstein<superscript>2,</superscript><remark><superscript>&#x000A7;</superscript></remark></othername>
           <affiliation>
                <orgname><superscript>1</superscript>Skirball Institute and Department of Cell Biology, New York University School of Medicine</orgname>
				<address>New York, NY 10016 USA</address>
            </affiliation>
            <affiliation>
                <orgname><superscript>2</superscript>Department of Biology, University of North Carolina</orgname>
				<address>Chapel Hill, NC 27599 USA</address>
            </affiliation>
            </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Gastrulation is the process by which the germ layers become positioned in an embryo.</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">gastrulation serves as a model for studying the molecular mechanisms of diverse cellular and developmental phenomena, including morphogenesis, cell polarization, cell-cell signaling, actomyosin contraction and cell-cell adhesion. One distinct advantage of studying these phenomena in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">is that genetic tools can be combined with high resolution live cell imaging and direct manipulations of the cells involved. Here we review what is known to date about the cellular and molecular mechanisms that function in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">gastrulation.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
    <sect1>
        <title>Summary of gastrulation events</title>
        <para>Gastrulation in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is not as overtly dramatic as in many other animal embryos, since cells move only small distances, generally single cell diameters, and the  blastocoel space is small. Despite this, gastrulation plays an essential role in development, internalizing endodermal, mesodermal, and germ-line precursors. Gastrulation occurs when small groups of cells ingress at various times into the small blastocoel space. The blastocoel space forms when specific surfaces of cells separate from one another in the interior of the embryo. Cells acquire an apical-basal polarity that is important for the asymmetric pattern of adhesions that produce the blastocoel space. Certain PAR proteins adopt apical-basal asymmetries in early embryonic cells and are required to properly pattern cell adhesions.</para>
        <para>The endoderm is the first tissue to internalize during gastrulation. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink>, the endoderm precursor cells, constrict their outer (apical) surfaces as they ingress. Apical constriction may provide a force that draws the neighbors of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink> towards each other, displacing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink> into the center of the embryo. Myosin accumulates at  the apical surfaces of cells as they ingress, and myosin activity is required for ingression. PAR proteins found on the apical surface are required for the apical accumulation of myosin in ingressing cells and ingressions are inefficient in  PAR-depleted embryos.</para>
        <para>Cells ingress at reproducible times and positions throughout gastrulation. It is possible that the cellular mechanisms used in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink> are reused by various other ingressing cells, since  myosin also accumulates at the apical surfaces of later ingressing cells. Cell fate appears to play an important role in determining which cells ingress.</para>
        <para><literallayout>Movies of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> gastrulation can be seen at the following web sites:
        <ulink url="http://www.bio.unc.edu/faculty/goldstein/lab/movies.html" role="_blank">http://www.bio.unc.edu/faculty/goldstein/lab/movies.html</ulink> 
        <ulink url="http://dev.biologists.org/cgi/content/full/130/22/5339/DC1" role="_blank">http://dev.biologists.org/cgi/content/full/130/22/5339/DC1</ulink></literallayout>
        <literallayout>Variation in gastrulation patterns among other species of nematodes is addressed in another WormBook chapter:
        <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_embryovariationdevelop/embryovariationdevelop.html" role="_blank">Embryological variation during nematode development</ulink>.</literallayout></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Polarization of gastrulating cells</title>
        <para>The cell movements of gastrulation begin at the 26-cell stage when the two endodermal precursors, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink>, move from the surface of the embryo into a small interior cavity called the blastocoel (<link linkend="bib21">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6684600 -->). Prior to the 26-cell stage, the embryo is organized as a hull of cells one cell in radius that is surrounded by a vitelline envelope and eggshell. Each cell adopts a reproducible position within the hull and has up to three different membrane surfaces: an outer surface that faces the  vitelline envelope (apical surface), surfaces that contact adjacent cells (lateral surfaces), and a surface that faces cells on the opposite side of the hull (basal surface; <xref linkend="figure1"/>A). The blastocoel forms when basal surfaces of cells separate from one another while lateral surfaces remain adherent (<xref linkend="figure1"/>C,D; <link linkend="bib14">Nance and Priess, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11807031 -->). The pattern of cell contacts, rather than adhesive differences between different types of cells, appears to control formation of the blastocoel. For example, a blastocoel-like cavity can form when a single cell (the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> blastomere) is isolated from the embryo and allowed to divide in culture (<xref linkend="figure1"/>B; <link linkend="bib14">Nance and Priess, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11807031 -->). This observation suggests that cell contacts induce an apical-basal polarization in cells that causes their different surfaces to develop different adhesive properties.</para>
        <para>The localization of certain PAR polarity proteins defines an apical-basal axis in early embryonic cells. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink>, a conserved protein with three PDZ domains that is homologous to <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> Bazooka, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink>, a RING finger protein, are cortically enriched proteins that are required for anterior-posterior polarity and occupy reciprocal anterior and posterior cortical domains in the zygote and germ-line precursor cells (see WormBook chapter: <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html" role="_blank">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>). During the four-cell stage, PAR proteins develop a new asymmetry along the apical-basal axis of cells (<link linkend="bib4">Etemad-Moghadam et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID 8521491 -->; <link linkend="bib5">Guo and Kemphues, 1995</link><!-- PMID 7758115 -->; <link linkend="bib2">Boyd et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8898221 -->; <link linkend="bib6">Hung and Kemphues, 1999</link><!-- PMID 9834192 -->; <link linkend="bib14">Nance and Priess, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11807031 -->; <link linkend="bib13">Nance et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 13129846 -->). During the early four-cell stage, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> is present around the entire cortex of somatic cells in the embryo (<xref linkend="figure2"/>A). By the end of the four-cell stage, when cell  separations that give rise to the blastocoel first become apparent, cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> becomes largely restricted to apical surfaces (<xref linkend="figure2"/>B). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> is localized in a reciprocal pattern at the basolateral cortex (<xref  linkend="figure2"/>C,D). Other PAR proteins that are asymmetrically localized in the zygote and germ-line precursors develop analogous apical-basal asymmetries: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink>, which contains a single PDZ domain, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PKC-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PKC-3</ulink>, an atypical protein kinase C, are enriched on apical surfaces, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-1</ulink>, a serine/threonine kinase, is enriched on basolateral surfaces.</para>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink> exhibit the same asymmetric distributions when ectopic cell contacts are created by combining blastomeres in culture, suggesting that the pattern of cell contacts establishes apical-basal PAR asymmetry (<link linkend="bib14">Nance and Priess, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11807031 -->). In the zygote, the asymmetric localization of PAR proteins is achieved in part by cortical flows generated by an asymmetric anterior contraction of the cortical cytoskeleton (see WormBook chapter: <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html" role="_blank">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>). Analogous apically directed movements of the cytoskeleton occur along the apical-basal axis of early embryonic cells and may function to establish the apical-basal asymmetry  in PAR distribution (<link linkend="bib12">Munro et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15363415 -->).</para>
     
        <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig1" width="5.9in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> Blastocoel formation figure 1</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig1legend;
            </mediaobject>

            <para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink>, but not <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-2</ulink>, is  required for the asymmetric pattern of cell adhesions observed during blastocoel formation. Cells in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-3" role="_blank">par-3</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos develop spaces between their lateral surfaces similar to those found between basal surfaces in wild-type embryos (<link linkend="bib14">Nance and Priess, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11807031 -->). To establish that the role of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> in apical-basal polarity is direct and not a secondary consequence of earlier defects in anterior-posterior polarity, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> was depleted from early embryonic cells by fusion to a protein domain (the ZF1 domain of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PIE-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink>; <link linkend="bib13">Nance et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 13129846 -->). This domain promotes protein degradation beginning at the four-cell stage (<link linkend="bib18">Reese et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10983990 -->; <link linkend="bib13">Nance et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 13129846 -->). Embryos expressing only the hybrid <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> protein (<emphasis>par-3(ZF1)</emphasis> embryos) develop separations between the lateral surfaces of cells indistinguishable from those observed in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=par-3" role="_blank">par-3</ulink></emphasis> mutant embryos. Similar phenotypes are observed in <emphasis>par-6(ZF1)</emphasis> embryos (<xref linkend="figure3"/>). The target molecules that mediate the cell adhesion functions of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> have yet to be identified.</para>
        
            <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> localization figure 2</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig2legend; </mediaobject>
          
            <literallayout></literallayout>
       
        <mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata entityref="fig3" width="5in" align="center"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
            <phrase> Embryos expressing the hybrid <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> protein (<emphasis>par-3</emphasis><emphasis>(ZF1)</emphasis> embryos) figure 3</phrase>
        </textobject> &fig3legend; </mediaobject>
        </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
        <title>Mechanisms of cell ingression</title>
        <para>As <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink> ingress, their apical surfaces move away from the vitelline envelope and are covered by six neighboring cells: three <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink> granddaughters (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MSap;class=Cell" role="_blank">MSap</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MSpa;class=Cell" role="_blank">MSpa</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MSpp;class=Cell" role="_blank">MSpp</ulink>), two <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> progeny (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABplpa;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABplpa</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABplpp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABplpp</ulink>) and P<subscript>4</subscript> (<xref linkend="figure4"/>, <xref linkend="figure9"/>B; <link linkend="bib11">Lee and Goldstein, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12466198 -->). In a lateral view, one <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink> granddaughter (referred to here as MSxx) and P<subscript>4</subscript> can be seen moving toward each other over the apical surfaces of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink>. To examine whether the eggshell and vitelline envelope may provide necessary physical constraints or a necessary microenvironment to the gastrulating embryo, the eggshell and vitelline envelope were removed (<link linkend="bib11">Lee and Goldstein, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12466198 -->). Ingression movements occur in such devitellinized embryos (<xref  linkend="figure5"/>E-H), indicating that these structures do not provide signals or surfaces essential for ingression.</para>
        
        <para>The descendants of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> comprise 16 of the 26 embryonic cells present when gastrulation begins, and several <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> descendants contact <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink> (see <xref linkend="figure9"/>B). To address whether <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> descendants are required for ingression of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink>, the P<subscript>1</subscript> cell was isolated from the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> cell at the two cell stage and was allowed to divide in culture  (<link linkend="bib11">Lee and Goldstein, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12466198 -->). Observation of these P<subscript>1</subscript> isolates revealed that MSxx and P<subscript>4</subscript> movements still occur (<xref linkend="figure5"/>I-P), showing that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> descendants are not necessary for gastrulation-like movements and ruling out a model in which the complete ring of six neighboring cells is necessary to push the E cells internally.</para>
        
        <mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig4" width="5in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> Cell ingression figure 4</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig4legend; </mediaobject>
            
        
        <literallayout></literallayout>
        <mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig5" width="7in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> Cell ingression figure 5</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig5legend; </mediaobject>
            
        <para>The ingressing endodermal cells control the direction of movement of the neighboring cells (<link linkend="bib11">Lee and Goldstein, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12466198 -->). P<subscript>1</subscript> isolates can divide into a linear array of cells where MSxx cells and P<subscript>4</subscript> flank <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink>, respectively (<xref linkend="figure5"/>M-P). In cases where the P<subscript>4</subscript> cell is removed from a P<subscript>1</subscript> isolate, MSxx can still move toward the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink> midline, indicating that the P<subscript>4</subscript> cell does not provide a necessary chemoattractant for MSxx movement. P<subscript>1</subscript> isolates can also be separated into two groups and recombined, effectively rotating the cell groups relative to each other (<xref linkend="figure6"/>). When P<subscript>1</subscript> isolates are separated and recombined at the junction of the endodermal cells and either MSxx or P<subscript>4</subscript>, MSxx and P<subscript>4</subscript> move toward one another over the surfaces of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink>, generally in the same plane, as in unmanipulated P<subscript>1</subscript> isolates. However, when <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink> are separated and recombined, MSxx and P<subscript>4</subscript> still move toward the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink> boundary, but in random axes. Together, these observations show that the polarity of the ingressing endodermal cells determines the direction of movement of neighboring cells, and suggest that neighboring cells may move passively.</para>
        
         <para>Ingressing cells accumulate the non-muscle myosin <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMY-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> at their apical surfaces as they ingress. In <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> embryos, myosin accumulates at the apical surfaces of cells that undergo a morphogenetic change called apical constriction (<link linkend="bib23">Young et al., 1991</link><!-- PMID 1901784 -->). Apical constriction is also observed in many other systems, including gastrulating <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis> bottle cells and ingressing sea urchin primary mesenchyme cells (<link linkend="bib7">Keller, 1981</link><!-- PMID 7288390 -->; <link linkend="bib8">Kimberly and Hardin, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9851856 -->). During apical constriction, the width of the apical surface is decreased, altering the shape of the cell. Although not as dramatic as in some other systems, the width of the apical surface also decreases as cells ingress in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Evidence for apical constriction during  ingression comes from experiments where fluorescent microspheres were used to track cell surface movements (<xref linkend="figure7"/>). Microspheres on the surfaces of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink> in P<subscript>1</subscript> isolates move toward the junction between these cells (<link linkend="bib11">Lee and Goldstein, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12466198 -->). In addition, non-muscle myosin accumulates at these apical surfaces, and myosin activity is required for ingression (<link linkend="bib14">Nance and Priess, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11807031 -->; <link linkend="bib11">Lee and Goldstein, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12466198 -->). These results suggest that an actomyosin-mediated  contraction at the apical surface of ingressing cells causes these surfaces to constrict. The ARP-2/3 complex is also required for ingression, but it is not known whether it plays a role in apical constriction (<link linkend="bib20">Severson et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12498681 -->).</para>
         
         <literallayout></literallayout>
        <mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig6" width="3.7in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> Cell groups figure 6</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig6legend; </mediaobject>
            
            <para>Myosin accumulation in ingressing cells requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink>. As during blastocoel formation, cortical <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> are restricted to the apical surfaces of cells during gastrulation. When these proteins are removed from early embryonic cells by tagging with the ZF1 protein degradation domain (see above), cell ingressions proceed much more slowly than in wild-type and the apical surfaces of ingressing cells do not  do not visibly accumulate more myosin than neighboring, noningressing cells do (<xref linkend="figure8"/>; <link linkend="bib13">Nance et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 13129846 -->). Thus <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> function in ingressing cells to promote an apical accumulation of myosin, although it is not yet clear whether the visible apical myosin enrichment is a prerequisite or result of apical constriction.</para>
 
            <literallayout></literallayout>
            <mediaobject id="figure7" xreflabel="Figure 7">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig7" width="6in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> Evidence for apical constriction figure 7</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig7legend; </mediaobject>
        <para>One surprising finding from studies on embryos depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-3</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PAR-6;class=protein" role="_blank">PAR-6</ulink> (see above) is that ingression can still occur, albeit slowly, despite the lack of apparent myosin accumulation at the apical cortex (<link linkend="bib13">Nance et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 13129846 -->). Whether ingressing cells utilize other mechanims in combination with apical constriction to become internalized is not yet clear. Neither ingressing cells nor spreading neighboring cells appear to use prominent filopodia or lamellipodia to crawl (<link linkend="bib11">Lee and Goldstein, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12466198 -->). One mechanism that could contribute to ingression is a rolling mechanism of neighboring  cells; this is suggested by experiments showing that microspheres coating the apical surface of MSxx cells move toward the endodermal cells (<xref linkend="figure7"/>; <link linkend="bib11">Lee and Goldstein, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12466198 -->). This mechanism might be driven by adhesive differences along surfaces of cells, although no adhesion molecules have yet been implicated in gastrulation.</para>
        
        <mediaobject id="figure8" xreflabel="Figure 8">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig8" width="5in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> Cell ingressions Figure 8</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig8legend; </mediaobject>
        
        <para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EMB-5;class=protein" role="_blank">EMB-5</ulink>, a putative splicing factor (<link linkend="bib19">Schierenberg et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7380087 -->; <link linkend="bib15">Nishiwaki et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID -->), and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GAD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GAD-1</ulink>, a WD repeat protein with some similarity to a transcription initiation factor (<link linkend="bib9">Knight and Wood, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9659931 -->) are required for ingression, but their roles and the genes that they may regulate have not been defined. Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=emb-5" role="_blank">emb-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gad-1" role="_blank">gad-1</ulink></emphasis> shorten the cell cycle of the endodermal cells, which normally ingress during a single prolonged cell cycle (<link linkend="bib19">Schierenberg et al., 1980</link><!-- PMID 7380087 -->; <link linkend="bib9">Knight and Wood, 1998</link><!-- PMID  9659931 -->). Thus <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EMB-5;class=protein" role="_blank">EMB-5</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GAD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GAD-1</ulink> may influence ingression by controlling regulators of the cell cycle.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Patterning cell ingressions</title>
        <para>Ingression of the endodermal cells occurs at approximately 90 minutes after the first cell division of the embryo. After the endodermal cells have completed ingression,  mesodermal cells and germ cells ingress from various positions on the ventral surface over the next 200 minutes (<xref linkend="figure9"/>; <link linkend="bib21">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6684600 -->; <link linkend="bib14">Nance and Priess, 2002</link><!-- PMID  11807031 -->). Although ingressions occur over much of the ventral surface, specific cells ingress at reproducible times and positions. A cleavage-arrested endodermal precursor will even gastrulate at the time that its daughters normally would do so (<link linkend="bib10">Lahl et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 1259034  -->). These observations suggest that the timing of gastrulation is regulated carefully, and this regulation is distinct to each cell or group of cells.</para>
        <para>Several observations suggest that the fate of cells, rather than their ventral position, controls whether they ingress. First, mutations that transform the fates of ingressing cells can prevent the transformed cells from ingressing. For example, genes required for endoderm fate specification are also required for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ea;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ea</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Ep;class=Cell" role="_blank">Ep</ulink> ingression (ex. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=skn-1" role="_blank">skn-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mom-2" role="_blank">mom-2</ulink></emphasis>, genes in the endoderm determining region; <link linkend="bib1">Bowerman et al., 1992</link><!-- PMID 1547503 -->; <link linkend="bib22">Thorpe et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9288749 -->; <link linkend="bib24">Zhu et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9353257 -->). Second, transforming the fates of cells can change the time that the transformed cells ingress. Two populations of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink> descendants ingress at different times and have different fates: a group of cells called wishbone cells ingresses earlier than another group called central cells (<xref linkend="figure9"/>C; <link linkend="bib21">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!-- PMID 6684600 -->; <link linkend="bib14">Nance and Priess, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11807031 -->). Central cells can be induced to ingress at the same time as wishbone cells if their fates are converted to those of wishbone cells (<link linkend="bib14">Nance and Priess, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11807031 -->). However, transformed central cells can only be induced to  ingress earlier when endodermal cells (which normally lie underneath the central cells) are prevented from ingressing, indicating that cell-cell interactions can also play a role in determining ingression behavior.</para>
        <para>After cell ingressions are complete, gastrulation culminates with the epiboly of the  hypodermal (epidermal) cells (see WormBook chapter: <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_epidermalmorphogenesis/epidermalmorphogenesis.html" role="_blank">Epidermal morphogenesis</ulink>). Hypodermal cells are born on the dorsal surface of the embryo and migrate ventrally to encase the embryo in skin.</para>
          <literallayout></literallayout>
        <mediaobject id="figure9" xreflabel="Figure 9">
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata entityref="fig9" width="4in" align="center"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
            <phrase> Two populations of MS descendents figure 9</phrase>
        </textobject> &fig9legend; </mediaobject>
        </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Future prospects</title>
        <para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> gastrulation serves as a model for studying the molecular mechanisms of diverse cell and developmental phenomena (<link linkend="bib3">Dawes-Hoang et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12530957 -->; <link linkend="bib17">Putzke and Rothman, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12646146 -->). Whereas some of the underlying mechanisms of gastrulation have been resolved (see model in <xref linkend="figure10"/>), many questions remain. How does apical-basal PAR polarity control apical myosin accumulation  in ingressing cells? Does cell adhesion play a role in promoting ingression movements? Does the unique cell cycle length in certain ingressing cells play a role in regulating their ingression? How is ingression triggered and coupled to cell fate? Understanding  these issues in this model system may suggest mechanisms by which cells can become repositioned in diverse organisms.</para>
        
        <mediaobject id="figure10" xreflabel="Figure 10">
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata entityref="fig10" width="3in" align="center"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
            <phrase> Gastrulation model figure 10</phrase>
        </textobject> &fig10legend; </mediaobject>
        </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Acknowledgments</title>
        <para>Work on gastrulation by the authors has been supported by Postdoctoral Fellowship Grant PF-02-007-01-DCC from the American Cancer Society (J.N.), funding from the Howard Hughes Medical Institute (J.P.), and a Pew Scholarship in the Biomedical Sciences and NIH R01 grant GM68966 to B.G. (J.-Y.L. and B.G.).</para>
        </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
			<para/>
			&gastrulation_Refs; 
        </sect1>
</article>