<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'hermafig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'hermafig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'hermafig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'hermafig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'hermafig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'hermafig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'hermafig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'hermafig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'hermafig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'hermafig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'hermafig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'hermafig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig7 SYSTEM 'hermafig7.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig7legend SYSTEM 'hermafig7leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig8 SYSTEM 'hermafig8.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig8legend SYSTEM 'hermafig8leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY herma_Refs SYSTEM 'hermarefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>]>
<article id="herma_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title>Hermaphrodite cell-fate specification<footnote>
<para>Edited by: Barbara J. Meyer. Last revised August 18, 2005. Published January 09, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Herman, M. A. Hermaphrodite cell-fate specification (January 09, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.39.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 Michael A. Herman. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
				</footnote>
		</title>
		<author>
		<firstname>Michael A.</firstname>
		<surname>Herman<remark>
					<footnote>
						<para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:mherman@ksu.edu">mherman@ksu.edu</ulink></para>
					</footnote>
					</remark>
		</surname>
		<affiliation>
			<address>Division of Biology, Kansas State University, Manhattan, KS 66506-4901 USA</address>
		</affiliation>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<abstract>
	<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">There are two sexes in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">hermaphrodite and male. While there are many sex-specific differences between males and hermaphrodites that affect most tissues, the basic body plan and many of its structures are identical. However, most structures required for mating or reproduction are sexually dimorphic and are generated by sex-specific cell lineages. Thus to understand cell fate specification in hermaphrodites, one must consider how the body plan, which is specified during embryogenesis, influences the fates individual cells. One possible mechanism may involve the asymmetric distribution of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=POP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink>/Tcf, the sole</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">Tcf homolog, to anterior-posterior sister cells. Another mechanism that functions to specify cell fates along the anterior-posterior body axis in both hermaphrodites and males are the</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Hox</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">genes. Since most of the cell fate specifications that occur in hermaphrodites also occur in males, the focus of this chapter will be on those that only occur in hermaphrodites. This will include the cell fate decisions that affect the HSN neurons, ventral hypodermal P cells, lateral hypodermal cells <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V5;class=Cell" role="_blank">V5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V6;class=Cell" role="_blank">V6</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T;class=Cell" role="_blank">T</ulink>; as well as the mesodermal M, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4</ulink> cells and the intestinal cells. Both cell lineage-based and cell-signaling mechanisms of cell fate specification will be discussed. Only two direct targets of the sex determination pathway that influence cell fate specification to produce hermaphrodite-specific cell fates have been identified. Thus a major challenge will be to learn additional mechanisms by which the sex determination pathway interacts with signaling pathways and other cell fate specification genes to generate hermaphrodite-specific cell fates.</emphasis></para>
	</abstract>
	<sect1>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>There are two sexes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, hermaphrodite and male. Hermaphrodites are basically females that produce a small number of sperm that can fertilize their own oocytes. They are also cross-fertile with males. Males are smaller than hermaphrodites and produce only sperm. There are many sex-specific differences between males and hermaphrodites. Although these differences affect most tissues, the basic body plan and many of its structures are identical (<link linkend="bib67">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib68">Sulston and Horvitz, 1977</link><!--; PMID 838129-->). In fact, about 650 cells seem to be the same in both sexes, out of a total of 959 somatic nuclei in hermaphrodites, and 1031 somatic nuclei in males. Most structures required for mating or reproduction are sexually dimorphic. For example, the hermaphrodite vulva is a reproductive structure that functions to allow eggs to be laid and male sperm to be deposited. Males develop highly specialized reproductive structures in the tail that allow it to find the hermaphrodite vulva and deposit sperm (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). Furthermore, the gonads of each sex have different structures and functions. Finally, sexually dimorphic neurons and muscles develop in each sex to control the movements of these mating structures.</para>
		<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="6.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Each of these structures is generated by sex-specific cell lineages. For example, certain <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P;class=Cell" role="_blank">P</ulink> cells divide to generate the vulva in hermaphrodites, while other <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P;class=Cell" role="_blank">P</ulink> cells divide to generate portions of the mating apparatus of the male tail (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). Other male specific blast cells that do not divide in hermaphrodites generate additional mating structures in the tail. In addition, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M;class=Cell" role="_blank">M</ulink> cell divides in hermaphrodites to generate the vulval muscles that control the movements of the vulva. In males, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M;class=Cell" role="_blank">M</ulink> cell divides to generate sex muscles that control movements of the tail (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). Interestingly, almost all of these sexually dimorphic structures are made during larval development by the sex-specific divisions of just 16 blast cells (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>).</para>
		<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="5.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
		<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="5.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
		<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="6in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 4</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Since most of the cell fate specifications that occur in hermaphrodites also occur in males, the focus of this chapter will be on those that only occur in hermaphrodites. Thus, I will include the cell fate decisions that affect the HSN neurons, ventral hypodermal <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P;class=Cell" role="_blank">P</ulink> cells, lateral hypodermal cells <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V5;class=Cell" role="_blank">V5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V6;class=Cell" role="_blank">V6</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T;class=Cell" role="_blank">T</ulink>; as well as the mesodermal <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M;class=Cell" role="_blank">M</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4</ulink> cells. Even the intestinal cells have sex-specific fates (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>). Aspects of many of these cell fate decisions are covered in more detail in other chapters, which will be referred to where appropriate.</para>
		<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 5</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
</sect1>
<sect1>
	<title>Basic body plan and role of <emphasis>Hox</emphasis> genes</title>
	<para>The basic body plan of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is specified during embryogenesis through both cell interactions and autonomous or cell lineage-based mechanisms (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_gastrulation/gastrulation.html">Gastrulation in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_epidermalmorphogenesis/epidermalmorphogenesis.html">Epidermal morphogenesis</ulink>). The body plan must influence the fates of individual cells, however the mechanisms by which this occurs are not yet clear. One possible mechanism may involve <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=POP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink>/Tcf. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=POP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> is the sole Tcf homolog in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Tcfs are transcription factors that function to activate or repress expression of specific genes in response to Wnt signals (see <ulink url="http://wormbook.org/chapters/www_wntsignaling/wntsignaling.html">Wnt</ulink> chapter). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=POP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> is asymmetrically distributed to anterior-posterior sister cells in many divisions during <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> development (<link linkend="bib24">Herman, 2002</link><!--; PMID 12137732-->; <link linkend="bib28">Herman and Wu, 2004</link><!--; PMID 14977564-->; <link linkend="bib47">Lin et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9458047-->). At most divisions, the nucleus of the anterior daughter has a higher level of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=POP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> than does the posterior daughter. Early in embryogenesis <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=POP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> asymmetry is generated by cell interactions that involve <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MOM-2;class=protein" role="_blank">MOM-2</ulink>/Wnt signals. However later, after the division of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> great-granddaughter cells (AB<superscript>8</superscript>), the generation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=POP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> asymmetry becomes independent of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MOM-2;class=protein" role="_blank">MOM-2</ulink>, yet still requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MOM-5;class=protein" role="_blank">MOM-5</ulink>/Frizzled (<link linkend="bib52">Park and Priess, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12810601-->). Recently, it was shown that prior to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=POP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> being asymmetric at many of these divisions, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MOM-5;class=protein" role="_blank">MOM-5</ulink> is asymmetrically distributed during the division, making this system reminiscent of the <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> and vertebrate planar cell polarity pathways (<link linkend="bib53">Park et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15620652-->). Thus, the asymmetric distribution of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=POP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink>/Tcf might be controlled by a planar cell polarity-like pathway and function as part of a &#x0201C;global patterning system&#x0201D; that may control many cell fates. However, there must be other mechanisms at work as well, since not all cell fates are defective in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pop-1" role="_blank">pop-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib23">Herman, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11171341-->; <link linkend="bib47">Lin et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9458047-->; <link linkend="bib62">Siegfried and Kimble, 2002</link><!--: PMID 11807036-->). Furthermore, this system must function in both hermaphrodites and males.</para>
	<para>Another mechanism that functions to specify cell fates along the anterior-posterior body axis in both hermaphrodites and males is the <emphasis>Hox</emphasis> genes. There are six <emphasis>Hox</emphasis> genes in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome. All are found within 5 Mb on chromosome III: four, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-13" role="_blank">ceh-13</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-5" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-5" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> are found in a loose cluster, whereas two others, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=nob-1" role="_blank">nob-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=php-3" role="_blank">php-3</ulink></emphasis> are located more than 1 Mb away (<link linkend="bib1">Aboobaker and Blaxter, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14638320-->; <link linkend="bib5">Burglin et al., 1989</link><!--; PMID 2571091-->; <link linkend="bib6">Burglin and Ruvkun, 1993</link><!--; PMID 7902148-->; <link linkend="bib7">Burglin et al., 1991</link><!--; PMID 1676487-->; <link linkend="bib56">Ruvkun and Hobert, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9851920-->; <link linkend="bib73">Van Auken et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10781051-->). Interestingly, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-5" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-5" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> are only required for postembryonic development (<link linkend="bib36">Kenyon et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9598363-->). Furthermore, it appears that unlike <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> or vertebrate systems, much of the <emphasis>Hox</emphasis> gene expression pattern in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is dictated by cell lineage (<link linkend="bib12">Cowing and Kenyon, 1996</link><!--; PMID 8684464-->). However, cell signals such as the Wnt signaling pathways control some aspects of <emphasis>Hox</emphasis> gene expression (<link linkend="bib66">Streit et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11820809-->), particularly in the case of vulval development (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_vulvaldev/vulvaldev.html">Vulva development</ulink>; <link linkend="bib16">Eisenmann et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9716532-->). As in other systems, the <emphasis>Hox</emphasis> genes function to specify regions along the anterior-posterior body axis and, with the exception of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-13" role="_blank">ceh-13</ulink></emphasis>, their positions along the chromosome correlate with their regions of expression along the body axis. While <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-5" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-5" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> play large roles in cell fate specification in males (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_maledevelopment/maledevelopment.html">Male development</ulink>), in hermaphrodites, their roles are minimal (see below). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> is a major determinant of vulval cell fates (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_vulvaldev/vulvaldev.html">Vulval development</ulink>). Interestingly, it has been proposed that a tissue polarity or PCP-like mechanism might specify the Hox expression pattern in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib36">Kenyon et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9598363-->). It is possible that the two large-scale patterning mechanisms discussed here may interact to produce different cell fates along the body axis.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
	<title>HSN neuron</title>
	<para>Although programmed cell death plays a large role in shaping the body plan during development, it does not play a large role in shaping the differences between males and hermaphrodites. However, the HSN and CEM neurons are notable exceptions. The two serotonergic hermaphrodite specific neurons (HSNs) innervate the vulval muscles and drive egg-laying in hermaphrodites. The HSNs are not needed in males and die during embryonic development. By contrast, the four CEMs are male-specific head neurons that may be involved in regulating male-specific behaviors. Thus they are not needed in hermaphrodites and die during embryogenesis (<link linkend="bib68">Sulston and Horvitz, 1977</link><!--; PMID 838129-->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_maledevelopment/maledevelopment.html">Male development</ulink>). HSN death in males is controlled by sex-specific expression of the pro-apoptotic gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-1" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> by the terminal sex-determination gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib10">Conradt and Horvitz, 1998</link><!--; PMID 9604928-->). Gain-of-function mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-1" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> that cause inappropriate death of the HSNs in hermaphrodites (<link linkend="bib15">Desai et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID 3200316-->; <link linkend="bib72">Trent et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 11813735-->) map to a TRA-1A binding site, indicating that TRA-1A functions as a sex-specific negative regulator of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-1" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> expression (<link linkend="bib11">Conradt and Horvitz, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10458607-->). Thus, the sex determination pathway directly controls sex-specific HSN fates. This is one of two known examples of control of somatic sexual fates by TRA-1A. The other example involves the control of yolk production in the intestine by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> (see below).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
	<title>Epidermal cell fates</title>
	<para>In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (and other nematodes), the epidermis is referred to as hypodermis. Although the overall organization of the hypodermis in males and hermaphrodites is similar, there are many sex-specific specializations, including the development of the hermaphrodite vulva from the ventral hypodermis and the male sensory rays from the lateral hypodermis. At hatching, there are 85 hypodermal nuclei that are derived from only four blastomeres of the 12-cell embryo. The GATA transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ELT-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ELT-1</ulink> appears to be required for all hypodermal cell fates (<link linkend="bib19">Gilleard and McGhee, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11259601-->; <link linkend="bib51">Page et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9224715-->). Ectopic expression of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ELT-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ELT-1</ulink>, or the related GATA factor, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ELT-3;class=protein" role="_blank">ELT-3</ulink>, in early blastomeres, can activate the expression of hypodermal cell fate markers and cause cells that normally do not produce hypodermis to become hypodermal (<link linkend="bib19">Gilleard and McGhee, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11259601-->). One of these markers is <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-26" role="_blank">lin-26</ulink>,</emphasis> which encodes a zinc finger transcription factor (<link linkend="bib44">Labouesse et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7956818-->) that is expressed in all epithelial cells of the ectoderm as well as in the somatic gonad. In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-26" role="_blank">lin-26</ulink></emphasis> mutants epidermal cells are produced, however they soon degenerate, suggesting that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-26" role="_blank">lin-26</ulink></emphasis> is required for epithelial cell differentiation (<link linkend="bib13">den Boer et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9671593-->; <link linkend="bib43">Labouesse et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8787733-->). Furthermore, ectopic expression of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-26;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-26</ulink> in early embryonic blastomeres activates the expression of several other epithelial markers, suggesting that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-26" role="_blank">lin-26</ulink></emphasis> is a major control gene for epithelial cell fates (<link linkend="bib54">Quintin et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11437447-->). Recent studies of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-26" role="_blank">lin-26</ulink></emphasis> promoter revealed the existence of multiple regulatory elements that controlled expression in cells of the same organ, cells of similar function, or cells that had similar positions along the body axis (<link linkend="bib46">Landmann et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14732406-->). Thus, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-26;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-26</ulink> functions to control epithelial cell differentiation in multiple lineages using modular promoter elements.</para>
	<sect2>
		<title>Lateral hypodermis</title>
		<para>Three major cell types make up the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> epidermis: the hypodermal syncytium that covers much of the body, the seam cells and the P cells, whose nuclei migrate to the ventral nerve cord (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>). The GATA factors ELT-5 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ELT-6;class=protein" role="_blank">ELT-6</ulink> are required for the seam cell fate. In the absence of <emphasis>elt-5</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elt-6" role="_blank">elt-6</ulink></emphasis> function, the seam cells inappropriately fuse with the hypodermal syncytium (<link linkend="bib39">Koh and Rothman, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11532911-->). The seam cells are generated by divisions of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=H;class=Cell" role="_blank">H</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V;class=Cell" role="_blank">V</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T;class=Cell" role="_blank">T</ulink> cells (<link linkend="figure7">Figure 7</link>). At hatching, there are eight seam cells along the each side of the animal, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=H1;class=Cell" role="_blank">H1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=H2;class=Cell" role="_blank">H2</ulink> in the head; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V1;class=Cell" role="_blank">V1</ulink>-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V6;class=Cell" role="_blank">V6</ulink>, along the body; and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T;class=Cell" role="_blank">T</ulink> in the tail. In wild-type hermaphrodites, the anterior <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V1;class=Cell" role="_blank">V1</ulink>-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V4;class=Cell" role="_blank">V4</ulink> cells and the posterior <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V6;class=Cell" role="_blank">V6</ulink> cell all divide asymmetrically in a similar stem cell-like manner throughout larval development; the anterior daughter fuses with the hypodermal syncytium, hyp7, and the posterior daughter becomes a new seam cell. After the last division, all the posterior daughters differentiate into cells that produce the alae, which are cuticular ridges that run the length of the body (<link linkend="bib68">Sulston and Horvitz, 1977</link><!--; PMID 838129-->). The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=H;class=Cell" role="_blank">H</ulink> cells also divide in a stem-like manner, but their division patterns differ from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V1;class=Cell" role="_blank">V1</ulink>-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V4;class=Cell" role="_blank">V4</ulink> and from each other. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V5;class=Cell" role="_blank">V5</ulink> cell also undergoes stem cell-like divisions, but differs from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V1;class=Cell" role="_blank">V1</ulink>-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V4;class=Cell" role="_blank">V4</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V6;class=Cell" role="_blank">V6</ulink> because the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V5;class=Cell" role="_blank">V5</ulink>.pa cell becomes a neuroblast that generates a sensory structure called the postdeirid. When seam cells anterior or posterior to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V5;class=Cell" role="_blank">V5</ulink>.p are killed with a laser microbeam, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V5;class=Cell" role="_blank">V5</ulink>.pa fails to generate a postdeirid, suggesting that physical contact with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V4;class=Cell" role="_blank">V4</ulink>.p and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V6;class=Cell" role="_blank">V6</ulink>.p is required (<link linkend="bib70">Sulston and White, 1980</link><!--; PMID-->). This signaling appears to occur after the first round of seam cell divisions, when contacts between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V5;class=Cell" role="_blank">V5</ulink>.p and its neighbors are reestablished (<link linkend="bib2">Austin and Kenyon, 1994</link><!--; PMID 8149911-->). Wnt signals appear to be responsible for the induction of postdeirid cell fates (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_wntsignaling/wntsignaling.html">Wnt signaling</ulink>). In males, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V5;class=Cell" role="_blank">V5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V6;class=Cell" role="_blank">V6</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T;class=Cell" role="_blank">T</ulink> cells produce sensory rays in a process that involves Wnt signals and the regulation of Hox genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-5" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-5" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink>,</emphasis> as well as several cofactors (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_wntsignaling/wntsignaling.html">Wnt signaling</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_maledevelopment/maledevelopment.html">Male development</ulink>). The asymmetric divisions of two of these cells are also regulated by cell signals. Specifically, mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cam-1" role="_blank">cam-1</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a member of the Ror kinase family causes polarity reversal of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V1;class=Cell" role="_blank">V1</ulink> cell division (<link linkend="bib18">Forrester et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 99404618-->); whereas mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-20" role="_blank">egl-20</ulink>/Wnt</emphasis> cause polarity reversal of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V5;class=Cell" role="_blank">V5</ulink> cell division (<link linkend="bib74">Whangbo et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11023862-->).</para>
		<mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig6" width="6.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 6</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig6legend;</mediaobject>
		<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-22" role="_blank">lin-22</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a homolog of <emphasis>hairy/Enhancer of split</emphasis>, is also involved in specifying <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V;class=Cell" role="_blank">V</ulink> cell fates (<link linkend="bib76">Wrischnik and Kenyon, 1997</link><!--; PMID 9247331-->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-22" role="_blank">lin-22</ulink></emphasis> mutants, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V1;class=Cell" role="_blank">V1</ulink>-<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V4;class=Cell" role="_blank">V4</ulink> adopt the fate of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V5;class=Cell" role="_blank">V5</ulink> (<link linkend="bib17">Fixsen et al., 1985</link><!--; PMID 3868513-->; <link linkend="bib30">Horvitz et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6586368-->; <link linkend="bib76">Wrischnik and Kenyon, 1997</link><!--; PMID 9247331-->). Production of ectopic postdeirids in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-22" role="_blank">lin-22</ulink></emphasis> mutants required the activities of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-5" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink>,</emphasis> the <emphasis>achaete-scute</emphasis> homolog, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-32" role="_blank">lin-32</ulink>,</emphasis> and to some extent <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink>;</emphasis> suggesting that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-22;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-22</ulink> functions to inhibit the functions of these proteins in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=V5;class=Cell" role="_blank">V5</ulink>.pa (<link linkend="bib76">Wrischnik and Kenyon, 1997</link><!--; PMID 9247331-->). It is not yet clear how <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-22;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-22</ulink> function is affected by the Wnt signals that appear to be repressed by cell contacts.</para>
		<mediaobject id="figure7" xreflabel="Figure 7">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig7" width="5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 7</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig7legend;</mediaobject>
		<para>The T cells divide with a different pattern than the V cells and primarily generate neurons and neural support cells, although syncytial and seam cells are also produced. The asymmetric T cell divisions are controlled by a Wnt pathway that involves <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-44" role="_blank">lin-44</ulink>/Wnt, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-17" role="_blank">lin-17</ulink>/Fz, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=wrm-1" role="_blank">wrm-1</ulink>/&#x000DF;-catenin, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lit-1" role="_blank">lit-1</ulink>/NLK</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pop-1" role="_blank">pop-1</ulink>/Tcf</emphasis> (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_wntsignaling/wntsignaling.html">Wnt signaling</ulink> for details; <link linkend="bib23">Herman, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11171341-->; <link linkend="bib26">Herman and Horvitz, 1994</link><!--; PMID 8026318-->; <link linkend="bib27">Herman et al., 1995</link><!--; PMID 7553861-->; <link linkend="bib58">Sawa et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8804313-->). A likely target of this pathway is <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tlp-1" role="_blank">tlp-1</ulink>,</emphasis> which encodes a zinc finger protein expressed in the posterior T cell daughter in a Wnt dependant manner and appears to function to specify neural cell fates (<link linkend="bib80">Zhao et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11880358-->).</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
		<title>Ventral hypodermis</title>
		<para>At hatching, the nuclei of six ventrolateral P cells lie along each side of the animal. About midway through the first larval stage the nuclei migrate into the ventral nerve cord, followed subsequently by the remaining cell body (<link linkend="bib69">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6684600-->). Laser killing experiments demonstrated that cells that lie opposite each other have equivalent cell fates. If one member of the pair is killed, the remaining member takes on the anterior cell fate (<link linkend="bib70">Sulston and White, 1980</link><!--; PMID 7190941-->). Once in the ventral cord, the cells divide producing an anterior Pn.a neuroblast that generates several motorneurons and a posterior hypodermal Pn.p cell. In hermaphrodites, P(1&#x02013;2).p and P(9&#x02013;11).p soon fuse with hyp-7, while P(3&#x02013;8).p remain unfused. In hermaphrodites P(3&#x02013;8).p make-up the vulval precursor cells and participate in vulval development during the third larval stage (see <ulink url="http://wormbook.org/chapters/www_vulvaldev/vulvaldev.html">Vulva development</ulink> chapter for details). In males, P(1&#x02013;2).p and P(7&#x02013;8).p soon fuse with hyp7, while P(3&#x02013;6).p and P(9&#x02013;11).p remain unfused. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P12.p;class=Cell" role="_blank">P12.p</ulink> also remains unfused and divides in the first larval stage with P12.pa generating a rectal hypodermal cell and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P12.pp;class=Cell" role="_blank">P12.pp</ulink> undergoing programmed cell death in both sexes. The pattern of Pn.p fusions, and thus vulval competency in hermaphrodites, appears to be controlled by Hox gene expression and Hox protein activity. In both wild-type hermaphrodites and males, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in P(3&#x02013;8).p and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-5" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in P(7&#x02013;11).p (<link linkend="bib49">Maloof and Kenyon, 1998</link><!--; PMID 9486792-->; <link linkend="bib57">Salser et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8103754-->). However, the activity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-5;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-5</ulink> is inhibited in hermaphrodites, perhaps by the action of the sex determination pathway (<link linkend="bib57">Salser et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8103754-->), although a direct role for TRA-1A has not been shown. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-27" role="_blank">egl-27</ulink>,</emphasis> which encodes a protein similar to the NURD chromatin remodeling complex component MTA1, is also required for the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-5;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-5</ulink> inhibition in hermaphrodites (<link linkend="bib25">Herman et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 9927605-->; <link linkend="bib63">Solari et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10226007-->). In males, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-5;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-5</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-39;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-39</ulink> neutralize each other in a combinatorial interaction that also requires <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-27" role="_blank">egl-27</ulink></emphasis> function, leading to the fusion of P(7&#x02013;8).p with hyp7 (<link linkend="bib8">Ch&apos;ng and Kenyon, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10393110-->).</para>
		<para>The fate of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=P12;class=Cell" role="_blank">P12</ulink> cell is controlled by an interaction of Wnt and Ras pathways that interact to regulate the expression of the Hox gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-5" role="_blank">egl-5</ulink></emphasis> (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_wntsignaling/wntsignaling.html">Wnt signaling</ulink>).</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
		<title>M cell</title>
		<para>Although most of the main body wall muscles are not sexually dimorphic (<link linkend="bib29">Hodgkin, 1988</link><!--; PMID 8709229-->; <link linkend="bib67">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib67">Sulston et al., 1980</link><!--; PMID 7409314-->; <link linkend="bib68">Sulston and Horvitz, 1977</link><!--; PMID 838129-->), the single postembryonic mesoblast, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M;class=Cell" role="_blank">M</ulink>, produces different muscles in hermaphrodites and males. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M;class=Cell" role="_blank">M</ulink>, a descendant of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MS;class=Cell" role="_blank">MS</ulink>.ap, is born in an anterior position on the left side of the embryo. It then migrates to the posterior and makes its way to the right side of the embryo, where it is found after hatching (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>; <link linkend="bib69">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6684600-->). In hermaphrodites, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M;class=Cell" role="_blank">M</ulink> cell produces six cell types: body wall muscles (14), nonmuscle coelomocytes (2) and four classes of sex muscles (4 cells of each class), which are derived from two sex myoblast (SM) cells (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). The SMs are born in the posterior and migrate toward the gonad during the second larval stage where they divide in the third larval stage to generate the uterine (um1 and um2) and vulval (vm1 and vm2) muscles. This migration is controlled by both attractive and repulsive signals from the gonad (<link linkend="bib64">Stern and Horvitz, 1991</link><!--; PMID 1821851-->; <link linkend="bib71">Thomas et al., 1990</link><!--; PMID 2401010-->). The attractive signals involve the expression of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-17;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-17</ulink>/FGF by the somatic gonad and vulva and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EGL-15;class=protein" role="_blank">EGL-15</ulink>/FGFr by the SMs. In the absence of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-15" role="_blank">egl-15</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-17" role="_blank">egl-17</ulink></emphasis> function, a repressive signal from the gonad is revealed. The function and exact source of this signal within the gonad is not yet known (<link linkend="bib3">Branda and Stern, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10993679-->; <link linkend="bib4">Burdine et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9463355-->; Stern<link linkend="bib64"> and Horvitz, 1991</link><!--; PMID 1821851-->).</para>
		<para>Multiple regulatory factors have been shown to be involved in the proliferation and patterning of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M;class=Cell" role="_blank">M</ulink> lineage, as well as for cell fate decisions between body wall muscles, coelomocytes and sex myoblasts. These include <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink>/Notch</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib20">Greenwald et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6616618-->), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-5" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib35">Kenyon, 1986</link><!--; PMID 3731276-->), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hlh-1" role="_blank">hlh-1</ulink>/MyoD</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib21">Harfe et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9609831-->; <link linkend="bib41">Krause et al., 1990</link><!--; PMID 2175254-->), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hlh-8" role="_blank">hlh-8</ulink>/twist</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib22">Harfe et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9716413-->; <link linkend="bib48">Liu and Fire, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11060243-->) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-39" role="_blank">unc-39</ulink>/Six4/5</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib77">Yanowitz et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15282156-->). Hox genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-39" role="_blank">lin-39</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-5" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> play overlapping roles in specifying the various M cell derived fates through the activation of several targets (<link linkend="bib48">Liu and Fire, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11060243-->). One of the main Hox gene targets is <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hlh-8" role="_blank">hlh-8</ulink>/twist</emphasis> which is expressed in undifferentiated M cell descendants. Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hlh-8" role="_blank">hlh-8</ulink></emphasis> cause both the striated and nonstriated <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M;class=Cell" role="_blank">M</ulink>-derived muscles to be misspecified (<link linkend="bib22">Harfe et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9716413-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HLH-8;class=protein" role="_blank">HLH-8</ulink> functions with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HLH-2;class=protein" role="_blank">HLH-2</ulink> to activate additional target genes. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hlh-2" role="_blank">hlh-2</ulink></emphasis> encodes an E/Daughterless homolog and is expressed in a dynamic pattern throughout development, including in the M lineage (<link linkend="bib42">Krause et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9187144-->). After the initial M cell divisions, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hlh-1" role="_blank">hlh-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> function to specify striated muscle, coelomocyte and sex myoblast fates. Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hlh-1" role="_blank">hlh-1</ulink></emphasis> cause the coelomocytes to be transformed into sex myoblasts, while mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> cause the opposite transformation (<link linkend="bib20">Greenwald et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6616618-->; <link linkend="bib22">Harfe et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9716413-->; <link linkend="bib41">Krause et al., 1990</link><!--; PMID 2175254-->).</para>
		<para>A genetic screen for mutations that affected cell fate specification within the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SM;class=Cell" role="_blank">SM</ulink> lineage identified <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mls-1" role="_blank">mls-1</ulink>,</emphasis> which encodes a T-box transcription factor. Uterine muscles are transformed into vulval muscles in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mls-1" role="_blank">mls-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants. Interestingly, overexpression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mls-1" role="_blank">mls-1</ulink></emphasis> in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=M;class=Cell" role="_blank">M</ulink> lineage causes the opposite transformation, indicating that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MLS-1;class=protein" role="_blank">MLS-1</ulink> is a uterine muscle cell fate determinant (<link linkend="bib40">Kostas and Fire, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11799068-->).</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1>
	<title>Somatic gonad</title>
	<para>The gonads of hermaphrodites and males develop sex-specific morphologies from a common primordium. The gonad primordium lies in the center of the animal and contains four cells: two somatic gonadal precursors (SGPs), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4</ulink>, on each end, and two germline precursors, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z2;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z3;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z3</ulink>, in the center. The hermaphrodite gonad develops an anterior and a posterior arm, each of which has its own proximal-distal axis and develops into an ovo-testes (<link linkend="figure8">Figure 8</link>; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_introgermline/introgermline.html">Introduction to the germ line</ulink><!--, PMID 10822256-->). The male gonad develops into a single-armed testis (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_maledevelopment/maledevelopment.html">Male development</ulink>). Thus, the SGPs undergo sex-specific cell lineages (<link linkend="bib37">Kimble and Hirsh, 1979</link><!--; PMID 478167-->). The hermaphrodite SGPs divide along the proximal-distal axis of the gonad with distal cell fates lying at the ends of the primordium and proximal fates lying in the center. The SGPs divide three times in the first larval stage to generate the 12-cell gonad primordium (<link linkend="figure8">Figure 8</link>). Ten of these cells have invariant fates, eight later generate uterine, sheath and spermathecal cells and two become the distal tip cells (DTCs) on each end which lead the elongation of the gonad arms. The remaining two cells, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1.ppp;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1.ppp</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4.aaa;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4.aaa</ulink> have variable cell fates. One will become the anchor cell (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AC;class=Cell" role="_blank">AC</ulink>) and the other will become a ventral uterine precursor (VU). However, which cell becomes the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AC;class=Cell" role="_blank">AC</ulink> and which becomes the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=VU;class=Cell" role="_blank">VU</ulink> varies from animal to animal (<link linkend="bib37">Kimble and Hirsh, 1979</link><!--; PMID 478167-->).</para>
		<mediaobject id="figure8" xreflabel="Figure 8">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig8" width="5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 8</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig8legend;</mediaobject>
	<para>A Wnt signaling pathway controls the asymmetric cell divisions of the SGPs. These asymmetric cell divisions and the resulting tissues are oriented along the proximal-distal axis of the gonad. Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-17" role="_blank">lin-17</ulink>/Fz</emphasis> also cause a loss of asymmetry of the SGP divisions (<link linkend="bib65">Sternberg and Horvitz, 1988</link><!--; PMID-->). In the gonad, this defect is called Sys (for <emphasis>sy</emphasis>mmetric <emphasis>s</emphasis>isters). Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pop-1" role="_blank">pop-1</ulink>/Tcf</emphasis> also cause a Sys defect and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=POP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink> levels appear to be correlated with different proximal and distal cell fates, as the nuclear levels of GFP::POP-1 levels are higher in the proximal <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4</ulink> daughters (<link linkend="bib61">Siegfried et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15020416-->; <link linkend="bib62">Siegfried and Kimble, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11807036-->). The Wnt pathway that controls SGP polarity also includes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mom-1" role="_blank">mom-1</ulink>/Porc, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lit-1" role="_blank">lit-1</ulink>/NLK</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=wrm-1" role="_blank">wrm-1</ulink>/&#x000DF;-catenin.</emphasis> Other recently identified Sys genes include <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sys-1" role="_blank">sys-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sys-3" role="_blank">sys-3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gon-14" role="_blank">gon-14</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gon-1" role="_blank">gon-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gon-16" role="_blank">gon-16</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib61">Siegfried et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15020416-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink> also controls SGP position and polarity, including the nuclear levels of GFP::POP-1 (<link linkend="bib50">Mathies et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15294864-->). However, it is not clear how the sex determination pathway might interact with the Wnt signaling pathway to control SGP polarity. Surprisingly, mutation or interference with each of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Wnts did not cause a Sys defect, thus the Wnt ligand involved in this asymmetric division remains unidentified. It is possible that two or more of the five <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Wnts function redundantly to control SGP polarities, or that a non-ligand mediated mechanism, such as planar cell polarity, may be at work. However, if this is the case, there must be a mechanism by which the gonad can develop a proximal-distal axis of polarity that is different from the anterior-posterior axis of the animal.</para>
	<para>The AC/VU cell fate decision is controlled by cell interactions mediated by the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-12;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-12</ulink>/Notch receptor and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LAG-2;class=protein" role="_blank">LAG-2</ulink>, which is a ligand of the Delta-Serrate-LAG-2 family. Initially, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1.ppp;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1.ppp</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4.aaa;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4.aaa</ulink> express both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lag-2" role="_blank">lag-2</ulink></emphasis>, but a feedback mechanism functions to amplify a small fluctuation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> levels, causing one cell to express higher levels of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> and stop transcribing <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lag-2" role="_blank">lag-2</ulink>,</emphasis> while the other cell begins to express higher levels of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lag-2" role="_blank">lag-2</ulink></emphasis> and stops transcribing <emphasis>lin-12.</emphasis> As a result, the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> expressing<emphasis></emphasis> cell becomes a VU and the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lag-2" role="_blank">lag-2</ulink></emphasis> expressing cell becomes the AC (for details see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_lin12Notch/lin12notch.html">LIN-12/Notch signaling in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>, <link linkend="bib20">Greenwald et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6616618-->; <link linkend="bib45">Lambie and Kimble, 1991</link><!--; PMID 1769331-->; <link linkend="bib59">Seydoux and Greenwald, 1989</link><!--; PMID 2736627-->; <link linkend="bib75">Wilkinson et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 8001154-->). Recently it has been shown that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HLH-2;class=protein" role="_blank">HLH-2</ulink> is required for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lag-2" role="_blank">lag-2</ulink></emphasis> expression during the AC/VU decision (<link linkend="bib33">Karp and Greenwald, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14701877-->) as well as for establishing the competence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z1.ppp;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z1.ppp</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Z4.aaa;class=Cell" role="_blank">Z4.aaa</ulink> to participate in the AC/VU decision (<link linkend="bib34">Karp and Greenwald, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15282161-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
	<title>Intestine</title>
	<para>The hermaphrodite intestine produces yolk proteins, while the male intestine does not. This sex-specific cell fate is controlled by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tra-1" role="_blank">tra-1</ulink></emphasis>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-3;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-3</ulink> is a DM domain containing transcription factor related to <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> Doublesex and mouse Dmrt1 (<link linkend="bib55">Raymond et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9490411-->). Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> cause yolk to be produced in males (<link linkend="bib60">Shen and Hodgkin, 1988</link><!--; PMID 3046751-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-3;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-3</ulink> binds to a site in the promoter of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=vit-2" role="_blank">vit-2</ulink></emphasis> vitellogenin gene in males, repressing <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=vit-2" role="_blank">vit-2</ulink></emphasis> transcription (<link linkend="bib78">Yi et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11003845-->). TRA-1A binds to a site in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> promoter in hermaphrodites, repressing <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> transcription (<link linkend="bib79">Yi and Zarkower, 1999</link><!--; PMID 9927589-->). Thus, the hermaphrodite specific fate of the intestinal cells is controlled directly by the sex determination pathway.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
	<title>Conclusions</title>
	<para>Although there do not appear to be any general genetic or developmental strategies that differentiate hermaphrodite from male development, some trends are evident. Sex-specific differences in the patterns of programmed cell death appear to play a minor role, whereas sex-specific differences in the patterns of cell division play a large role. Specifically, there are few examples of sex-specific programmed cell deaths: the HSNs die in males whereas the CEMs and the progenitors of the CA/P(1&#x02013;6) neurons die in hermaphrodites. Sex-specific divisions of larval blast cells are more common. One result of this is that newly hatched larvae of each sex have virtually identical morphologies whereas adult hermaphrodites and males have unique appearances. In some cases divide blast cells in one sex but not in the other. For example the B and F cells divide in males, but not in hermaphrodites. In other cases blast cells divide in both sexes, but have sex specific cell lineages. For example the Pn.p and Vn.p cells divide differently in hermaphrodites and males. Finally, in some cases, such as the intestine, sex-specific gene expression is important but does not lead to differences in morphology of the tissue. A detailed understanding of how cell fates are differentially specified will go a long way to understanding the control of sex-specific development.</para>
<para>Many <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> papers on cell lineage or cell fate specification that were published in the late 1970s and 1980s emphasized the invariance of the cell lineage (<link linkend="bib14">Deppe et al., 1978</link><!--; PMID 272653-->; <link linkend="bib37">Kimble and Hirsh, 1979</link><!--; PMID 478167-->; <link linkend="bib68">Sulston and Horvitz, 1977</link><!--, PMID 838129-->; <link linkend="bib69">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6684600--> and 97 others), suggesting that cell fates were primarily determined by cell intrinsic or lineage-based mechanisms. However, it was know quite early on that there were many examples of cell fate determination by cell interactions (<link linkend="bib38">Kimble, 1981</link><!--; PMID 7286433-->; <link linkend="bib70">Sulston and White, 1980</link><!--; PMID 7190941-->). Subsequent work has demonstrated that while many cell fates do indeed appear to be specified by lineage-based mechanisms, there is a richness of cell signaling systems also at work. A major future challenge will be to identify and understand the global mechanisms that may function to specify cell positions and cell fates along the body axis. As suggested earlier in this chapter, this may involve a linage-based system involving <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=POP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">POP-1</ulink>/Tcf and the interaction of multiple signaling pathways. A continuing challenge is to understand how lineage-based mechanisms and signaling systems interact to specify cell fates.</para>
<para>An additional challenge will be to understand how sex specific cell fates are specified. How does the pathway described in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_somaticsexdeterm/somaticsexdeterm.html">Somatic sex determination</ulink> chapter interact with the various cell fate determination pathways described here and elsewhere in this book to generate sex specific patterns of cell division, morphology and function? The mechanisms by which the sex determination pathway interacts with signaling pathways such as the Wnt pathway in the control of SGP polarity and fate are not yet clear. To date, only two direct somatic targets of TRA-1A, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-1" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink>,</emphasis> have been identified. In both cases TRA-1A represses transcription of these targets in males. How does TRA-1A control the sex-specific fates in other cells? Genome analysis has revealed four genes in addition to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-3" role="_blank">mab-3</ulink></emphasis> that have three or more TRA-1A upstream binding sties (<link linkend="bib9">Clarke and Berg, 1998</link><!--; PMID 9851917-->). Three of these genes were enriched in expression in males vs. hermaphrodites (<link linkend="bib32">Jiang et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11134517-->). However, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-1" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> only has one TRA-1A binding site, which is located downstream, so it is unclear how many other genes may be directly regulated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TRA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TRA-1</ulink>. Finally, it is likely that other downstream effectors will also interact with cell fate specification genes to control sex specific fates. The mechanisms by which the sex determination pathway interacts with other signaling pathways to control sex-specific cell fates remain to be discovered.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
	<title>Acknowledgements</title>
	<para>Work on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> development in the Herman lab is supported by NIH grant GM56339. This publication was also made possible by NIH grant P20 RR016475 from the INBRE Program of the National Center for Research Resources.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
	<title>References</title>
<para/>
&herma_Refs;</sect1>
</article>