<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 2. Why nematodes might have a long branch.</title>
        <para>It has been claimed that a phenomenon called "long-branch attraction" (LBA) results in an artefactual placement of nematodes near the base of the bilaterian phylogeny, thus appearing to be consistent with the "Coelomata" hypothesis, and obscuring the phylogenetic signal for "Ecdysozoa". However, the branch (lineage) leading to nematodes could be long for different reasons: (1) the rate of nucleotide change is higher in nematodes than in other taxa (e.g., Ecdysozoa could be true and support for Coelomata is artefactual), or (2) the nematodes branched earlier from the tree than the other taxa (i.e., Coelomata is true after all), or (3) both (i.e., Coelomata is true and the rate is higher in nematodes). One legitimate method for testing for significant LBA is to conduct a relative-rate test; one can then discard data (taxa or sequences) which show a significantly higher rate in nematodes than in other taxa. In the relative-rate test, the distance (amount of change, corrected for superimposed substitutions) between one ingroup taxon (like nematodes, N) and an outgroup (O, e.g. diploblastic animals, yeast, etc.) is compared to the distance between another ingroup taxon (e.g., a non-nematode protostome, P<subscript>1</subscript>, like <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>) and the same outgroup. If evolution has occured at equal rates in the different lineages, these distances, NO and P<subscript>1</subscript>O, should be approximately equal, regardless of which hypothesis (Coelomata or Ecdysozoa) is true. The outgroup, O, thus serves as an unbiased "anchor" for these rate comparisons. Any deviation from this equality is a measure of a rate difference. Data showing such a deviation may be discarded to see if their exclusion results in a change in the phylogenetic topology. It is not legitimate, however, to use a potential ingroup as an anchor for the relative-rate test. For example, if human (or other deuterostome taxon, D) were used, the relative rate test would be biased to favor Ecdysozoa. That is, although the distance between N and D should be the same as that between P<subscript>1</subscript> and D if Ecdysozoa were true, ND should be <emphasis>greater than</emphasis> P<subscript>1</subscript>D if Coelomata were true and rates were <emphasis>equal</emphasis>. Eliminating data where ND<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003E;</symbol> P<subscript>1</subscript>D would thus bias the selection of data to favor Ecdysozoa, even if Coelomata were true.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>