<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'cuticlefig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'cuticlefig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'cuticlefig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'cuticlefig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'cuticlefig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'cuticlefig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'cuticlefig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'cuticlefig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'cuticlefig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'cuticlefig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'cuticlefig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'cuticlefig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig7 SYSTEM 'cuticlefig7.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig7legend SYSTEM 'cuticlefig7leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY cuticle_Refs SYSTEM 'cuticlerefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="cuticle_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title>The cuticle<footnote>
			<para>Edited by James M. Kramer and Donald G. Moerman. Last revised January 23, 2007. Published March 19, 2007. This chapter should be cited as: Page, A.P. and Johnstone, I.L. The cuticle (March 19, 2007), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.138.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis>&#x000A9; 2007 Antony P. Page and Iain L. Johnstone. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
		<author>
			<othername>Antony P. Page<superscript>1</superscript><remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:a.page@vet.gla.ac.uk">a.page@vet.gla.ac.uk</ulink> or <ulink url="mailto:i.johnstone@bio.gla.ac.uk">i.johnstone@bio.gla.ac.uk</ulink></para></footnote></remark>, Iain L. Johnstone<superscript>2</superscript><remark><superscript>&#x000A7;</superscript></remark></othername>
			<affiliation>
				<orgname><superscript>1</superscript>Institute of Comparative Medicine, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine</orgname><address>The University of Glasgow, Glasgow G61 1QH Scotland, UK</address></affiliation>
				<affiliation><orgname><superscript>2</superscript>IBLS Division of Molecular Genetics</orgname><address>The University of Glasgow, Glasgow G12 8QQ Scotland, UK</address></affiliation>
	</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">The nematode cuticle is an extremely flexible and resilient exoskeleton that permits locomotion via attachment to muscle, confers environmental protection and allows growth by molting. It is synthesised five times, once in the embryo and subsequently at the end of each larval stage prior to molting. It is a highly structured extra-cellular matrix (ECM), composed predominantly of cross-linked collagens, additional insoluble proteins termed cuticlins, associated glycoproteins and lipids. The cuticle collagens are encoded by a large gene family that are subject to strict patterns of temporal regulation. Cuticle collagen biosynthesis involves numerous co- and post-translational modification, processing, secretion and cross-linking steps that in turn are catalysed by specific enzymes and chaperones. Mutations in individual collagen genes and their biosynthetic pathway components can result in a range of defects from abnormal morphology (dumpy and blister) to embryonic and larval death, confirming an essential role for this structure and highlighting its potential as an ECM experimental model system.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>During post-embryonic development, <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> is enclosed within an exoskeleton called the cuticle (<link linkend="bib9">Cox et al., 1981b</link><!--; PMID 7251677-->; <link linkend="bib10">Cox et al., 1981c</link><!--; PMID 6269931-->; <link linkend="bib26">Kramer, 1994</link><!--; PMID 8143939-->; <link linkend="bib19">Johnstone, 1994</link><!--; PMID 8166670-->; <link linkend="bib27">Kramer, 1997</link><!--; PMID not available-->). The cuticle is a collagenous extracellular matrix (ECM) that is synthesized by an underlying ectodermal cell layer termed the hypodermis that surrounds the body of the animal (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). During synthesis, material is secreted from the apical membranes of the hypodermis, then polymerizes on the outer surface of the membranes where it remains in intimate contact as the mature cuticle.</para>
<para>Synthesis occurs five times during development, once in the embryo, then prior to molting at the end of each larval stage. Thus, with the exception of the first round of synthesis, synthesis occurs underneath an existing cuticle and requires its displacement from the membrane surface prior to, or concurrent with, secretion and polymerization of the new cuticle (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). The old cuticle is removed by molting (<link linkend="bib51">Singh and Sulston, 1978</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1978EU16600007-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Function</title>
<para>The cuticle is a multi-functional exoskeleton. It is a highly impervious barrier between the animal and its environment. It is essential for maintenance of body morphology and integrity, and has a critical role in locomotion via attachments to body-wall muscles (<link linkend="bib25">Kramer et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID 3180220-->; <link linkend="bib55">Von Mende et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID 2846184-->; <link linkend="bib22">Johnstone et al., 1992</link><!--; PMID 1396579-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Structure</title>
<para>The cuticle surrounding the main body of the animal can be sub-divided into the broad dorsal and ventral regions overlying the dorsal and ventral hypodermis and the narrow lateral regions overlying the seam cells where longitudinal ridges termed alae are positioned on the cuticle of the L1 and dauer larvae and of the adult (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1A</link>; <link linkend="bib8">Cox et al., 1981a</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1981LV87300004-->; <link linkend="bib20">Johnstone, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10637627-->). The alae are distinct from the rest of the cuticle both in protein composition and ultrastructure.</para>
<para>The dorsal and ventral cuticle has a gross multilayered ultrastructure, the detail of which varies at different developmental stages (<link linkend="bib10">Cox et al., 1981c</link><!--; PMID: 6269931-->; <link linkend="bib41">Peixoto and Desouza, 1995</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1995TD11800010-->; <link linkend="bib42">Peixoto et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1997XE77200004-->). There are four major layers (epicuticle, cortical, medial and basal), which can be further subdivided (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1B</link>). The outer (cortical) layer of the dorsal and ventral regions is patterned at all developmental stages with circumferential ridges termed annuli (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1A and B</link>). On developmental stages with alae, the annuli of the dorsal and ventral regions are separated by the alae (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1A</link>). On stages without alae, the dorsal and ventral regions (and annuli) meet with an obvious discontinuity above the lateral seam cells. The mechanism by which the pattern of lateral alae is generated (L1 larva, dauer and adult) is unclear; however the lateral seam cells are responsible and may involve the interaction and polymerization of specific cuticulin proteins (<link linkend="bib48">Sapio et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID: 15936343-->). Laser ablation of individual seam cells in the L3 and early L4 results in a corresponding gap in the alae of the adult cuticle, and likewise mutants (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lin-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-5</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e1348;class=Variation" role="_blank">e1348</ulink></emphasis>) that lack individual seam cells also lack alae above the missing seam cells (<link linkend="bib51">Singh and Sulston, 1978</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1978EU16600007-->).</para>
<para>During cuticle synthesis, sub-membranous actin filaments form within the hypodermal cells and are organized circumferentially around the cylindrical body of the worm (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1C</link>), coincident with the furrows that form on the apical surface of the hypodermal cell membrane and subsequently with the furrows that delineate the boundaries of the annuli on the surface of the polymerized cuticle (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1C</link>; <link linkend="bib7">Costa et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1997WX47200015-->). It is therefore probable that the pattern of actin filaments has a definitive role in establishing the annular pattern on the surface of the cuticle.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="5.7in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The presence of the actin filaments and the furrows that they produce on the surface of the hypodermal membrane are transient; they are no longer present when the inner layers of the cuticle, which are not patterned by furrows, polymerize. The furrows remain in the outer layer of the cuticle, indicating that once polymerization has occurred, their presence does not require the continued presence of the cytoskeletal actin bundles. The persistence of the annular furrows in the cuticle does require the function of a specific group of cuticle collagens, discussed in detail below.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Composition</title>
<para>The major component of this extracellular matrix (ECM) is collagen, a protein that represents over 80% of the soluble protein released following its extraction in reducing agents. Collagens are ubiquitous structural proteins with a characteristic Glycine-X-Y tripeptide repeat, where X is frequently proline and Y hydroxyproline. The procollagens are synthesised, modified and trimerize in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER). In addition to collagens, a novel highly cross-linked insoluble class of proteins called cuticlins are associated with the cuticle. The outermost layer, the epicuticle is lipid-rich and this in turn is overlaid by a loosely associated glycoprotein-rich surface coat.</para>
<sect2 id="sec4_1">
<title>Cuticle collagens</title>
<para>The cuticle collagens are encoded by a gene family with over 170 members (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org" role="_blank">WormBase</ulink>). They have a characteristic structure (see <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>) of short interrupted blocks of Gly-X-Y sequence flanked by conserved cysteine residues and can be grouped into families according to homology (<link linkend="bib20">Johnstone, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10637627-->). In comparison to the collagens of vertebrates, in structure and size they are most similar to the fibril-associated collagens with interrupted triple helices (FACIT).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<sect3 id="sec4_1_1">
<title>Cuticle collagen genetics</title>
<para>To date, mutants of 21 of the cuticle collagen genes have been identified that result in a range of informative body morphology defects including phenotypes described as, DumPY (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink>), ROLler (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Rol;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Rol</ulink>), BLIster (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Bli;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Bli</ulink>), SQuaT (<ulink url="http://wormbase.org/db/gene/gene_class?name=sqt;class=Gene_class" role="_blank">Sqt</ulink>), Ray AbnorMal (Ram) and LONg (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Lon;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Lon</ulink>) (see <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link> and <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). As extensive genetic screens have failed to detect mutants of the majority of the ~170 cuticle collagen genes, it is reasonable to assume that mutation of most results in phenotypes too subtle to be readily detected. Additionally, RNAi data may be confusing as there is sufficient sequence homology between many of the cuticle collagen genes that in some cases, RNAi effects could be the result of reduction of mRNA of several genes. Some cuticle collagen genes have been shown to encode components of cuticular sub-structures with specific functions. Mutants of the cuticle collagen genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">7</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">8</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-10;class=Gene" role="_blank">10</ulink></emphasis> are dumpy (short fat worms) and have no cuticular annuli (see <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3B</link>; <link linkend="bib29">McMahon et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID ISI:000182185200011-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DPY-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-7</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DPY-10;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-10</ulink> have been shown to locate to narrow circumferential bands positioned within or beneath the annular furrows (see <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>). It has been proposed that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DPY-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DPY-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DPY-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">8</ulink> are also components of these bands. In mutants of any one of the five "no annuli" <emphasis>dpy</emphasis> genes, the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DPY-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-7</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DPY-10;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-10</ulink> containing bands are absent, and thus all five encoded collagens are believed to be obligate partners required for generation of these annular-furrow band structures. The structures are necessary for the presence/persistence of the annular furrows to which they locate, and hence the annuli that they define.</para>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75%">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1.</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">cuticle collagen genes that have associated phenotypes.</emphasis> Cosmid clone associated with the collagens genes are depicted. Groups 1, 2, 3, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-7</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-2</ulink></emphasis> refer to the structurally related collagen families based on position of conserved cysteines and Gly-X-Y interruptions (<link linkend="bib20">Johnstone 2000</link><!--; PMID 10637627-->). Phenotype listed have been describe for one or more alleles of the listed genes. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink>, Dumpy; RRol, Right-handed roller; LRol, Left-handed Roller; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Lon;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Lon</ulink>, long; Dom, dominant; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Bli;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Bli</ulink>, blister; wDpy, weak Dumpy; DLRol, Dumpy Left-handed roller; Ram, Ray abnormal.</title>
<tgroup cols="4">
<colspec colname="c1" align="center" colwidth="0.8*"/>
<colspec colname="c2" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c3" align="center" colwidth="0.8*"/>
<colspec colname="c4" align="center" colwidth="1.5*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Gene</entry>
<entry>Cosmid</entry>
<entry>Group</entry>
<entry>Phenotypes</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sqt-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">sqt-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B0491.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">B0491.2</ulink></entry>
<entry>1</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink>, RRol, LRol, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Lon;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Lon</ulink>, Dom</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-17;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-17</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F54D8.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">F54D8.1</ulink></entry>
<entry>1</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lon-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">lon-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ZK836.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ZK836.1</ulink></entry>
<entry>1</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Lon;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Lon</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rol-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">rol-6</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T01B7.7;class=Gene" role="_blank">T01B7.7</ulink></entry>
<entry>1</entry>
<entry>RRol, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink>, Dom</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-5</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F27C1.8;class=Gene" role="_blank">F27C1.8</ulink></entry>
<entry>1</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bli-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bli-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C09G5.6;class=Gene" role="_blank">C09G5.6</ulink></entry>
<entry>1</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Bli;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Bli</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-9</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>T21D12.1</entry>
<entry>2</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sqt-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">sqt-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C01B12.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">C01B12.1</ulink></entry>
<entry>2</entry>
<entry>wDpy/ RRol</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rol-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">rol-8</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ZK1290.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">ZK1290.3</ulink></entry>
<entry>2</entry>
<entry>LRol</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bli-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">bli-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F59E12.12;class=Gene" role="_blank">F59E12.12</ulink></entry>
<entry>2</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Bli;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Bli</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EGAP7.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">EGAP7.1</ulink></entry>
<entry>2</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink>, DLRol</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ram-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">ram-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F38A3.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">F38A3.1</ulink></entry>
<entry>2</entry>
<entry>Ram/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rol-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">rol-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y57A10A.11;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y57A10A.11</ulink></entry>
<entry>3</entry>
<entry>LRol/wDpy</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ram-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">ram-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F36A4.10;class=Gene" role="_blank">F36A4.10</ulink></entry>
<entry>3</entry>
<entry>Ram</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sqt-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">sqt-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F23H12.4;class=Gene" role="_blank">F23H12.4</ulink></entry>
<entry>3</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink>, LRol, Dom</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-13;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-13</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F30B5.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">F30B5.1</ulink></entry>
<entry>3</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y41E3.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y41E3.2</ulink></entry>
<entry>3</entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-7</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F46C8.6;class=Gene" role="_blank">F46C8.6</ulink></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-7</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink>, DLRol</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-8</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C31H2.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">C31H2.2</ulink></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-7</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink>, DLRol</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=T14B4.7;class=Gene" role="_blank">T14B4.7</ulink></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink>, DLRol</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-10;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-10</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T14B4.6;class=Gene" role="_blank">T14B4.6</ulink></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink>, DLRol, LRol, Dom</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>Conversely, annuli are present on mutants of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-5</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-13;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-13</ulink></emphasis>, although they are similarly dumpy in phenotype to those with no annuli. However, the annuli are closer together (see <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3B</link>). Consistent with its role in promoting the normal breadth of annuli, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DPY-13;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-13</ulink> locates in a broad circumferential band within each annulus (see <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>). Double mutants between any member of the &#x0201C;no annuli&#x0201D; group of <emphasis>dpy</emphasis> genes and the &#x0201C;narrow annuli&#x0201D; group display a compounded severe dumpy phenotype (see <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3A</link>).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec4_1_2">
<title>Timing of collagen gene expression</title>
<para>The cuticle is synthesized at the end of embryogenesis prior to hatching and then prior to molting at the end of each larval stage. During each cuticle synthetic period, the cuticle collagen genes are expressed in a distinct temporal series, the pattern of which is repeated at each synthetic period (<link linkend="bib21">Johnstone and Barry, 1996</link><!--; PMID 8670866-->). According to their time of expression within this series, the cuticle collagen genes can be described as early, intermediate, or late, corresponding to peaks of mRNA abundance at approximately four hours prior, two hours prior, and concurrent with secretion of each new cuticle, respectively. A comparison of the timing of expression of the early gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-10;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-10</ulink></emphasis> and intermediate <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-5</ulink></emphasis> is given in <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="6in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 4</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 5</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
<para>For the two sets of <emphasis>dpy</emphasis> cuticle collagen genes discussed above, the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-7</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-8</ulink>,</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-10;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-10</ulink></emphasis> genes are all early expressed, whereas the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-13;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-13</ulink></emphasis> genes are intermediate expressed. This is consistent with a model where the individual collagen components of the same cuticle sub-structure are synthesized at the same time and different sub-structures may be synthesized at different times.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_2">
<title>Cuticlins</title>
<para>The cuticlins comprise the insoluble material that remains after extensive ionic detergent and reducing agent extraction of the cuticle. This unusual structural component is highly cross-linked, predominantly via tyrosine, a cross-link that is particularly abundant in the outermost cortical layers and in the dauer cuticle. The cuticlin proteins have cysteine-rich zona pellucida-like domains, are expressed from the hypodermal cells and play stage-specific roles in formation of the seam cell derived cuticular alae. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cut-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cut-1</ulink></emphasis> was the first CUTiclin gene to be identified (<link linkend="bib49">Sebastiano et al., 1991</link><!--; PMID 1864469-->) and together with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cut-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">cut-6</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in the dauer cuticle, underlying and adjacent to the dauer alae, respectively. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CUT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CUT-1</ulink> protein is expressed in the seam cell (<link linkend="bib49">Sebastiano et al., 1991</link><!--; PMID 1864469-->) whereas <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CUT-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">CUT-6</ulink> is expressed at the periphery of the adjacent dorsal and ventral hypodermal cells (<link linkend="bib30">Muriel et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID ISI:000184946000005-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CUT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CUT-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CUT-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">CUT-6</ulink> are involved in dauer alae formation and ultimately maintain the correct radial body morphology in this long-lived stage (<link linkend="bib30">Muriel et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID ISI:000184946000005-->; <link linkend="bib48">Sapio et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15936343-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CUT-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">CUT-3</ulink> is similarly associated with alae formation and body morphology in the L1 larvae, while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CUT-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">CUT-5</ulink> is involved in L1 and dauer alae formation whereas <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CUT-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">CUT-4</ulink> is involved in the adult cuticle formation (<link linkend="bib48">Sapio et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15936343-->). It has been hypothesized that the cuticlins, together with unidentified cuticle components, are enzymatically polymerized to constrict the seam cell-derived cuticle thereby forming the distinctive cuticular alae (<link linkend="bib48">Sapio et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15936343-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_3">
<title>Surface coat</title>
<para>Overlying the nematode cuticle is the lipid-rich epicuticle that is then covered by the glycoprotein-rich negatively charged surface coat. This labile accessory layer is synthesized from the excretory system and gland cells and has been associated with immune evasion in several parasitic nematode species (<link linkend="bib37">Page et al., 1992</link><!--; PMID 1639165-->; <link linkend="bib3">Blaxter et al., 1992</link><!--; PMID 15463630-->). In the natural environment it may function to aid locomotion and prevent predatory microbe adhesion to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. The Srf (SuRFace) class of mutants differ in their stage-specific expression of exposed carbohydrate epitopes (<link linkend="bib45">Politz et al., 1990</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1990CZ29900008-->; <link linkend="bib44">Politz and Philipp, 1992</link><!--; PMID 15463517-->). Of the nine Srf mutants isolated only one has been cloned to date, namely <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=srf-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">srf-3</ulink></emphasis>, and represents a nucleotide sugar transporter UDP-Gal (<link linkend="bib18">Hoflich et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID ISI:000222531900071-->). Null mutants in this excretory cell-synthesised protein have altered surface glycoprotein expression, a weakened cuticle and display altered adherence properties to certain bacterial species (<link linkend="bib18">Hoflich et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID ISI:000222531900071-->). Glycoconjugate analysis of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=srf-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">srf-3</ulink></emphasis> mutants confirmed that, in comparison to wild type nematodes, N and O-linked galactose- containing glycans were significantly depleted, corroborating a role for these surface coat expressed glycans in bacterial adhesion (<link linkend="bib6">Cipollo et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15452127-->). Several <emphasis>srf</emphasis> genes have been re-isolated in mutant screens for nematodes resistant to infection with <emphasis>Microbacterium nematophilium</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib16">Gravato-Nobre et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID ISI:000233967200014-->). Some of the additional Bus (Bacterially UnSwollen) mutants were also found to have weakened cuticles with unusual lectin binding properties and an associated skiddy movement phenotype (<link linkend="bib16">Gravato-Nobre et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID ISI:000233967200014-->). It is expected that other member of the Srf and Bus mutant class will encode components of the glycoprotein biosynthetic pathway or will be essential components of the surface coat. For additional background information regarding carbohydrates and glycosylation see the <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_glycosylation/glycosylation.html" role="_blank">Carbohydrates and glycosylation</ulink> chapter in WormBook.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Molting</title>
<para>The cuticle is synthesized during late embryogenesis, then shed and re-synthesized at each larval stage beneath the existing cuticle, which is subsequently shed by a process called molting (<link linkend="bib51">Singh and Sulston, 1978</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1978EU16600007-->). Molting can be subdivided into lethargus, apolysis and ecdysis. Lethargus is characterised by a gradual decrease in general activity and feeding, followed by the ensuing separation of the old cuticle that defines apolysis. The nematode then rotates rapidly around its longitudinal axis, in so doing loosening the old cuticle. The shedding and emergence from the old cuticle during ecdysis completes the molting process. This complex developmental step involves extensive tissue remodelling and is assisted by numerous proteases (<link linkend="bib11">Davis et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID ISI:000226275700020-->; <link linkend="bib4">Brooks et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID ISI:000187480700044-->). The control factors involved in nematode molting and cuticle synthesis remain to be conclusively defined, however evidence does exist linking cholesterol and steroid hormones to this pathway (<link linkend="bib59">Yochem et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID ISI:000078713700017-->; <link linkend="bib28">Kuervers et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID ISI:000186542500003-->). Furthermore, the involvement of orphan nuclear hormone receptors in the process including, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NHR-23;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-23</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NHR-25;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-25</ulink> is evident (<link linkend="bib24">Kostrouchova et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID ISI:000169456600067-->; <link linkend="bib15">Gissendanner and Sluder, 2000</link><!--; PMID ISI:000086873800020-->). A genome-wide RNAi-based screen has uncovered no fewer that 159 genes that are involved in the molting process; including transcription factors, secreted peptides, transmembrane and extracellular matrix proteins as well as proteases and peroxidases (<link linkend="bib13">Frand et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID ISI:000232404600007-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Collagen biosynthetic pathway</title>
<para>Collagen biosynthesis is a complex multi-step process in vertebrates (<link linkend="bib46">Prockop and Kivirikko, 1995</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1995RH35300015-->; <link linkend="bib32">Myllyharju and Kivirikko, 2004</link><!--; PMID ISI:000188226200006-->). These modifications occur both intra- and extra-cellularly and involve chaperones and numerous modifying, folding and processing enzymes. It is expected that similar steps are involved in nematode collagen biosynthesis (see <link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>) and is supported by the fact that mutations in some of these enzymes result in profound body morphology phenotypes (<link linkend="bib39">Page and Winter, 2003</link><!--; PMID ISI:000186474600002-->).</para>
<?newpage?>
<sect2 id="sec6_1">
<title>Prolyl 4-hydroxylation</title>
<para>The first important co-translational modification of procollagen is prolyl 4-hydroxylation which allows its proper folding into a thermally-stable form (see <link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>). The prolyl 4-hydroxylase enzymes (<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-subunits) associate with the <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-subunit protein disulfide isomerase (PDI) to form active, soluble ER-resident enzyme complexes. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DPY-18;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-18</ulink> encodes a critical <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-subunit of the multi-component enzyme prolyl 4-hydroxylase (<link linkend="bib56">Winter and Page, 2000</link><!--; PMID ISI:000087017100032-->; <link linkend="bib17">Hill et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID ISI:000088056800014-->; <link linkend="bib14">Friedman et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID ISI:000086703000063-->). Null mutants of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-18;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-18</ulink></emphasis> are medium <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink> and the cuticle collagens have a corresponding reduction in their hydroxyproline content (<link linkend="bib56">Winter and Page, 2000</link><!--; PMID ISI:000087017100032-->; <link linkend="bib14">Friedman et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID ISI:000086703000063-->). The combination of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-18;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-18</ulink></emphasis> and RNA interference of a second <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-subunit <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=phy-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">phy-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib56">Winter and Page, 2000</link><!--; PMID ISI:000087017100032-->) or by crossing with a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=phy-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">phy-2</ulink></emphasis> deletion mutant (<link linkend="bib14">Friedman et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID ISI:000086703000063-->), both result in embryonic lethality. Embryonic death was also noted following RNAi of the sole <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pdi-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">pdi-2</ulink></emphasis> <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-subunit-encoding gene (<link linkend="bib56">Winter and Page, 2000</link><!--; PMID ISI:000087017100032-->). Unique active complexes between these three subunits were detected, both <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> and <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>; namely, mixed <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DPY-18;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-18</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PHY-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHY-2</ulink>/(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PDI-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">PDI-2</ulink>)<subscript>2</subscript> tetramers and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DPY-18;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-18</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PDI-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">PDI-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PHY-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHY-2</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PDI-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">PDI-2</ulink> dimers (<link linkend="bib33">Myllyharju et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID ISI:000177342600108-->).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig6" width="6in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 6</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig6legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6_2">
<title>Procollagen registration and trimerization</title>
<para>The next important step in vertebrate collagen folding, that precedes trimer formation is the correct registration of the monomers. Collagen trimerization can be initiated from either N- or C-terminal directions, and may be set up via PDI catalysed disulfide bond formation. The ER-resident enzyme PDI (see <link linkend="figure7">Figure 7</link>) may therefore play multiple independent roles in the proper biosynthesis of collagen (see <link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure7" xreflabel="Figure 7">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig7" width="5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 7</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig7legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> collagens have highly conserved C-terminal cysteine clusters that may be involved in such registration events. The trimerization of imino-rich (25% proline and hydroxyproline) collagen is rate-limited by the slow <emphasis>cis-trans</emphasis> proline isomerization, and requires the assistance of peptidyl prolyl <emphasis>cis-trans</emphasis> isomerase (PPIase) enzymes of the CYclophiliN (CYN) and FK506 Binding protein (FKB) class (<link linkend="bib1">Bachinger, 1987</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1987L332200057-->; <link linkend="bib52">Steinmann et al., 1991</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1991ET17700094-->). These genes constitute large, presumably redundant, families in the worm including several ER-resident isoforms that may perform this function (<link linkend="bib38">Page et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1996UX07700026-->; <link linkend="bib2">Bell et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID ISI:000236787300002-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6_3">
<title>Transit from the ER</title>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SEC-23;class=Protein" role="_blank">SEC-23</ulink> is an integral component of COPII secretory vesicles involved in transport from the ER to golgi apparatus. Loss of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sec-23;class=Gene" role="_blank">sec-23</ulink></emphasis> in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has been shown to cause accumulation of cuticle collagen in the ER suggesting that cuticle collagen secretion occurs through the COPII pathway (<link linkend="bib47">Roberts et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID ISI:000186738300008-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6_4">
<title>Procollagen processing and cross-linking</title>
<para>Prior to collagen multimerization the procollagen trimers must first be processed to remove the N- and C-terminal teleopeptides. These catalytic events alter protein solubility, permit cross-linking and ultimately lead to the formation of the final insoluble matrix (see <link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>). The importance of both N-terminal processing and C-terminal cross-linking has been demonstrated in the cuticle collagen <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SQT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SQT-1</ulink>. RRol phenotypes affecting the subtilisin-like processing site result from a failure to process this site whereas LRol phenotypes, associated with the C-terminal conserved cysteine, interfere with non-reducible cross-linking of this collagen (<link linkend="bib58">Yang and Kramer, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10551833-->).</para>
<sect3 id="sec6_4_1">
<title>N-terminal processing</title>
<para>The Kex2, subtilisin-like serine protease encoding gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bli-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">bli-4</ulink></emphasis> is essential for post-embryonic viability in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib43">Peters et al., 1991</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1991GD51200010-->). All cuticle collagens possess a highly conserved N-terminal cleavage site for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=BLI-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">BLI-4</ulink>, a site that has been experimentally demonstrated to be essential for the proper processing of the collagens <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ROL-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">ROL-6</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SQT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SQT-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib57">Yang and Kramer, 1994</link><!--; PMID-->). Null mutants of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bli-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">bli-4</ulink></emphasis> are embryonically lethal, whereas partial loss-of-function mutants were viable but <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Bli;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Bli</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink> (<link linkend="bib43">Peters et al., 1991</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1991GD51200010-->; <link linkend="bib53">Thacker et al., 1995</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1995QW14400006-->). Furthermore, RNAi screens targeting <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bli-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">bli-4</ulink></emphasis> also described an associated molt defect (<link linkend="bib23">Kamath et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID ISI:000180397600038-->).</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec6_4_2">
<title>C-terminal processing</title>
<para>The C-terminal processing of vertebrate fibrillar collagens is an essential step and is carried out by zinc metalloproteases of the astacin, bone morphogenic protein (BMP) class (<link linkend="bib5">Canty and Kadler, 2005</link><!--; PMID ISI:000228631000005-->; <link linkend="bib40">Pappano et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID ISI:000183848200002-->). The majority of nematode collagens have very short C-terminal non Gly-X-Y domains and until recently this processing step was not considered to be important for their maturation. Isolation and characterization of mutations in the BMP encoding gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-31;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-31</ulink></emphasis> result in temperature sensitive severe <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Emb;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Emb</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Let;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Let</ulink> phenotypes in the worm, demonstrating that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-31;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-31</ulink></emphasis> encodes an essential procollagen C-peptidase (<link linkend="bib34">Novelli et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID ISI:000225767400014-->; <link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>). This enzyme is expressed in the hypodermis and is required for normal cuticle collagen secretion. Extragenic suppressors of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-31;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-31</ulink></emphasis> include alleles of the cuticle collagen genes <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sqt-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">sqt-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-17;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-17</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib35">Novelli et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID ISI:000237225800020-->). Several <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sqt-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">sqt-3</ulink></emphasis> suppressors are themselves cold-sensitive lethal, which is a direct contrast to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sqt-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">sqt-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-31;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-31</ulink></emphasis> nulls, which are temperature sensitive lethal (<link linkend="bib35">Novelli et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID ISI:000237225800020-->). The C-terminal non Gly-X-Y domain of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SQT-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">SQT-3</ulink> is a major substrate for this enzyme, the predicted cleavage site being adjacent to the C-terminal tyrosine cross-linking residues (<link linkend="bib34">Novelli et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID ISI:000225767400014-->; <link linkend="bib35">Novelli et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID ISI:000237225800020-->).</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec6_4_3">
<title>Structural cross-linking</title>
<para>The final steps in collagen maturation and cuticle synthesis involve the structural cross-linking events. The cuticle collagens and cuticlins are covalently cross-linked via unusual di- and tri- tryrosine cross-links. These non-reducible cross-links impart the characteristic strength and integrity to the cuticle (<link linkend="bib36">Page, 2001</link><!--; PMID ISBN0851994237--> ) and differ from the hydroxylysine-derived cross-links of the vertebrate collagens (<link linkend="bib31">Myllyharju and Kivirikko, 2001</link><!--; PMID ISI:000167477100003-->). The major cuticle cross-linking enzyme is a dual oxidase enzyme encoded by the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bli-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">bli-3</ulink></emphasis> locus (<link linkend="bib12">Edens et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID ISI:000170683900019-->; <link linkend="bib50">Simmer et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID ISI:000188834700015-->; <link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>). This large enzyme has a signal peptide, a membrane-bound peroxide generating domain and a functionally-active peroxidase domain (<link linkend="bib12">Edens et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID ISI:000170683900019-->). It is proposed that the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=BLI-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">BLI-3</ulink> enzyme functions in a coupled reaction with the NADPH oxidase portion generating the hydrogen peroxide for the cross-linking reaction, which is then catalysed by the peroxidase portion (<link linkend="bib12">Edens et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID ISI:000170683900019-->). The peroxidase domain does however lack residues considered critical for haem-binding and therefore cannot be considered to be "classical" peroxidases. RNAi (<link linkend="bib12">Edens et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID ISI:000170683900019-->) or single point mutations (<link linkend="bib50">Simmer et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID ISI:000188834700015-->) in this enzyme result in worms with weakened cuticles that lack tyrosine cross-links. The resulting adult worms are devoid of cuticle struts and exhibit <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Dpy;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Dpy</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Bli;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Bli</ulink> phenotypes. This result is consistent with the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=BLI-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">BLI-3</ulink> enzyme having the proposed dual function, but also supports a sole function in generation of hydrogen peroxide that is utilized by an as-yet unidentified Haem peroxidase.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>Perspective</title>
<para>Collagen biogenesis and ECM function play a critical role in organogenesis and body morphology in all metazoans. Defects in these processes result in a variety of debilitating conditions of humans, including osteogenesis imperfecta, Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, Epidermolysis bullosa, several chondrodysplasias and excessive fibrosis associated with wound healing and liver disease. Additionally, the capacity to control and engineer ECM synthesis will play a critical role in any future attempts at organ culture. Although the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> cuticle is a highly specialized ECM with distinct and complex features, its biogenesis involves molecules, mechanisms and pathways that are shared with vertebrates. The extreme genetic tractability makes it an excellent experimental system for the dissection of ECM formation.</para>
</sect1>
<?newpage?>
<sect1>
	<title>References</title>
		&cuticle_Refs;
		<para/>
	</sect1>
</article>