<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'ethanfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'ethanfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'ethanfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'ethanfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'ethanfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'ethanfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY ethan_Refs SYSTEM 'ethanrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>]>
<article id="ethan_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title>Ethanol<footnote>
		<para>Edited by Andres V. Maricq. Last revised October 19, 2006. Published April 29, 2010. This chapter should be cited as: McIntire, S.L. Ethanol (April 29, 2010), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.40.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2010 Steven L. McIntire. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
		</footnote>
	</title>
	<author>
		<firstname>Steven L.</firstname>
		<surname>McIntire<remark>
				<footnote>
					<para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:slm@gallo.ucsf.edu">slm@gallo.ucsf.edu</ulink></para>
				</footnote>
			</remark>
		</surname>
		<affiliation>
			<address>Gallo Research Center, Department of Neurology University of California, San Francisco San Francisco, CA 94143 USA</address>
		</affiliation>
	</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<abstract>
		<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Ethanol is a widely used drug whose mechanism of action, despite intensive study, remains uncertain. Biochemical and electrophysiological experiments have identified receptors and ion channels whose functions are altered at physiological concentrations of ethanol. Yet, the contribution of these potential targets to its intoxicating or behavioral effects is unclear. Unbiased forward genetic screens for resistant or hypersensitive mutants represent an attractive means of identifying the relevant molecular targets or biochemical pathways mediating the behavioral effects of neuroactive compounds.</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">has proven to be a particularly useful system for such studies. The behavioral effects of ethanol occur at equivalent tissue concentrations in mammals and in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">suggesting the existence of conserved drug targets in the nervous system.</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">This chapter reviews the results of studies directed toward determining the mechanisms of action of ethanol. Studies of the neural adaptations that occur with prolonged drug exposure are also discussed. The methods used to characterize the actions of ethanol should be applicable to the characterizations of other compounds that affect the behavior of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans.</emphasis></emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1>
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>Ethanol is a widely used drug that has profound behavioral effects. Nevertheless, the fundamental mechanisms underlying these behavioral responses have remained uncertain. Similar intoxicating effects of ethanol observed in invertebrates and mammals suggest the existence of conserved targets in the nervous system.</para>
<para>Ethanol affects most behaviors of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Its neurodepressive properties have provided the basis for efficient screens for resistant or hypersensitive mutants. Molecular characterization of these mutants has led to the identification of likely drug targets and biochemical pathways mediating the behavioral effects of ethanol.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Behavioral responses of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to ethanol</title>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> exhibits obvious behavioral changes upon acute exposure to ethanol. Exogenous ethanol produces reversible, dose-dependent effects on the body bends responsible for locomotion, speed of movement and frequency of egg laying (<link linkend="bib2">Davies et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14675531-->). Progressive flattening of the body-bend amplitudes becomes apparent at 100&ndash;200mM ethanol and complete flattening occurs at 400&ndash;500 mM exogenous ethanol. The changes in the amplitude of the body bends correlate with a progressive decrease in the speed of movement, as determined by image analysis (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). A similar dose-response curve is observed for egg-laying behavior when animals are maintained on agar plates. Nearly complete inhibition of both locomotion and egg laying occur at an exogenous dose of 400&ndash;500 mM ethanol. This corresponds to an internal or tissue concentration of 22&ndash;29 mM ethanol. Ethanol concentrations can readily be measured in whole animal extracts following a typical acute exposure (22 min). The concentrations are comparable to those causing intoxication in other systems. For instance, 0.1&percnt; ethanol, a common legal drinking limit, corresponds to 21.7 mM blood ethanol. Blood and brain ethanol concentrations are the same in humans. At 400&ndash;500 mM ethanol, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is still capable of movement on plates when stimulated, although the animals are uncoordinated.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="6in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The effect of higher concentrations of ethanol on the movement of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> in liquid has also been studied. (<link linkend="bib6">Morgan and Sedensky, 1995</link><!--: PMID 8749805-->). Animals exhibited a steady state response to ethanol after 5 minutes of exposure. Mobility was scored for 10 sec at each concentration of ethanol after 5 minutes of exposure. EC50s were defined as the concentration in which 50&percnt; of the animals were immobile for greater than 10 sec. Under these conditions, the EC50 of N2 was 1050 &plus;/<symbol role="symbolfont">&minus;</symbol>30 mM exogenous ethanol. Again, the immobility was reversible. This higher concentration required to inhibit movement in liquid may correspond to an anesthetic dose of ethanol in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
</sect1>
<!--<?newpage?>-->
<sect1>
<title>Loss of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> function results in strong resistance to ethanol</title>
<para>Genetic screens for mutants resistant to the behavioral effects of ethanol on locomotion and egg laying led to the isolation of 29 mutants belonging to nine complementation groups (<link linkend="bib2">Davies et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14675531-->). All of the mutants exhibiting strong resistance to the effects of ethanol on these behaviors were found to have mutations in the same gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis>. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> encodes a <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homologue of the mammalian BK potassium channel (<link linkend="bib9">Wang et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 1738032-->). Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> result in uniquely strong resistance to the effects of ethanol on both locomotion and egg laying suggesting a special relationship between BK channels and ethanol sensitivity.</para>
<para>The resistance of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants appears relatively specific. No resistance was found to other compounds that inhibit locomotion including muscimol and serotonin. No differences in the metabolism or internal concentrations of ethanol were found in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants, suggesting that the resistance was not due to diminished penetration of ethanol or increased ethanol metabolism. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> mutations are thought to result in hyperactive neurotransmission, reflected as increased sensitivity to the acetylcholinesterase inhibitor, aldicarb. However, mutants with much stronger aldicarb hypersensitivity, such as <emphasis>goa-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=n363;class=Variation" role="_blank">n363</ulink>)</emphasis> and <emphasis>dgk-1(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nu62;class=Variation" role="_blank">nu62</ulink>)</emphasis>, show no or comparatively little ethanol resistance. Together with the genetic results these findings suggested that the uniquely strong resistance of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> was not an indirect effect.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Ethanol activates the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> channel <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis></title>
<para>Recordings from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> neurons <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> revealed that ethanol causes an increase in a SLO-1-dependent current (see <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). This effect occurs at doses of ethanol that cause intoxication in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as well as in mammalian systems. No effect of ethanol on whole-cell currents was observed in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants. Ethanol increased the frequency of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> channel openings in excised patches, but did not alter the size of the conductance. The ethanol effects on single channel activity occur in the absence of cytosolic factors, consistent with a direct effect of ethanol on the BK channel. Similar effects of ethanol on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> channels can be observed in recordings from multiple different neurons including sensory neurons, interneurons and motorneurons. Activation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> channels should inhibit neuronal excitability and decrease neurotransmitter release, possibly explaining the neurodepressive properties of ethanol.</para>
<para>Analysis of gain-of-function mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> confirmed the role of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> activation in ethanol sensitivity. Recordings from two gain-of-function mutants, <emphasis><ulink url="http://wormbase.org/db/gene/variation?name=ky389;class=Variation" role="_blank">ky389gf</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://wormbase.org/db/gene/variation?name=ky399;class=Variation" role="_blank">ky399gf</ulink></emphasis>, revealed increases in the frequency of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> channel opening, similar in magnitude to that produced by intoxicating concentrations of ethanol. The <emphasis><ulink url="http://wormbase.org/db/gene/variation?name=ky389;class=Variation" role="_blank">ky389gf</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://wormbase.org/db/gene/variation?name=ky399;class=Variation" role="_blank">ky399gf</ulink></emphasis> mutations result in similar depressive behavioral effects as those generated by ethanol, including comparable decreases in speed of locomotion and egg laying frequency. Hence, a selective increase in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> channel activity could recapitulate behavioral effects of ethanol. Although the role of BK channel activation in ethanol intoxication in mammals is not fully understood, similar ethanol-induced increases in the frequency of opening of mammalian BK channels have been observed <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib4">Dopico et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9435186-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Ethanol hypersensitive mutants</title>
<para>Ethanol hypersensitive mutants of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have also been described (<link linkend="bib6">Morgan and Sedensky, 1995</link><!--: PMID 8749805-->). A set of mutants originally identified on the basis of hypersensitivity to volatile anesthetics was tested for altered ethanol sensitivity. At higher doses, ethanol can act as an anesthetic. Testing was completed at the higher concentrations of ethanol required to inhibit movement in liquid. Several of the mutants that were hypersensitive to volatile anesthetics (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_anesthetics/anesthetics.html" role="_blank"><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> volatile anesthetics</ulink>) also showed hypersensitivity to ethanol in this assay. One of these mutants, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis>, was resistant rather than hypersensitive to ethanol. The mechanism of the altered responses to ethanol in this class of mutants is unclear.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="6.4in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=npr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-1</ulink></emphasis> regulation of ethanol tolerance</title>
<para>As in other systems, acute behavioral adaptation (acute tolerance) occurs in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib1">Davies et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15182714-->). Adaptation occurs in most systems provided that tissue concentrations of ethanol remain relatively constant. It is believed that the adaptation to ethanol represents plasticity of the nervous system or a mechanism that compensates for the physiological effects of the drug. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, adaptation to the effect of ethanol on locomotion occurs in the absence of any change in the internal or tissue concentration of ethanol (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). Adaptation occurs more rapidly in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CB4856;class=Strain" role="_blank">CB4856</ulink> (a wild strain isolated in Hawaii) than N2. These differences in the rate of development of acute tolerance were found to be due to allelic variation in a single gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=npr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-1</ulink></emphasis>. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=npr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-1</ulink></emphasis> encodes a NPY-like receptor protein (<link linkend="bib3">de Bono and Bargmann, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9741632-->). Allelic variation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=npr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-1</ulink></emphasis> had previously been shown to account for differences in food-dependent behaviors, including social (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CB4856;class=Strain" role="_blank">CB4856</ulink>) verses solitary (N2) feeding. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CB4856;class=Strain" role="_blank">CB4856</ulink> has a lower function allele of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=npr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-1</ulink></emphasis> than the allele found in the N2 strain. Multiple wild isolates are known to have either the N2 or the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CB4856;class=Strain" role="_blank">CB4856</ulink> allele of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=npr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-1</ulink></emphasis>. When these isolates were tested, the relative rate of adaptation to ethanol was predicted in all cases by the particular allele of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=npr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-1</ulink></emphasis>. More rapid ethanol tolerance was also observed in animals carrying a loss of function allele of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=npr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-1</ulink></emphasis> in an otherwise N2 background. A known suppressor, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ocr-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">ocr-2</ulink>(ok47)</emphasis>, of the food-dependent clumping behavior of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=npr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-1</ulink></emphasis> loss-of-function mutants did not suppress the more rapid adaptation to ethanol suggesting that the functions of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=npr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-1</ulink></emphasis> in ethanol tolerance and food-dependent behavior are separable. Replacing <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=npr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-1</ulink></emphasis> function in different subsets of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=npr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-1</ulink></emphasis>-expressing cells indicated that <emphasis>npr1</emphasis> acts in different neurons or a larger subset of neurons for the modulation of ethanol tolerance compared with those neurons required for social behavior.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Although it is unclear whether <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=npr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-1</ulink></emphasis>-related genes play a role in natural variation in ethanol responses in higher systems, there is evidence for a role of NPY signaling pathways in acute tolerance to ethanol in rodents. Knockout mutants of the NPY-encoding gene and the NPY Y1 receptor-encoding gene each results in more rapid tolerance to ethanol (<link linkend="bib8">Thiele et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9845072-->; <link linkend="bib7">Thiele et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11826154-->)</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Ethanol induced changes in gene expression</title>
<para><link linkend="bib5">Kwon et al. (2004)</link><!-- (PMID 15028283)--> have taken a genomics approach to understanding some of the actions of ethanol and the response of the organism. They used wild-type worms treated with an anesthetic dose of ethanol and collected RNA at various time points during the ethanol treatment. They used that RNA to probe microarrays that represent almost all of the predicted <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> open reading frames to determine where and when changes in gene expression occurs during ethanol treatment. They identified 230 genes that showed altered expression during the treatment, approximately 1&percnt; of the genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib5">Kwon et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15028283-->). Most of these changes were found to occur by the 6 hour time point although some genes were found to respond in as little time as 15 minutes. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=npr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">npr-1</ulink></emphasis> were not identified as genes that showed changes in expression; this suggests that whatever response the worm makes to compensate for the presence of ethanol in its system, it is not through direct changes in expression levels of those two genes that have been shown by mutant analysis to affect ethanol responses.</para>
</sect1>
<!--<?newpage?>-->
<sect1>
<title>Conclusions and prospects</title>
<para>Genetic studies in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have provided a means of understanding the mechanisms of action of ethanol. Despite its profound effects on behavior, the molecular targets of ethanol have remained elusive for decades. Biochemical approaches <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> have suggested that ethanol can affect the activity of a wide variety of neural proteins. It has been unclear whether such effects relate to the behavioral responses to these drugs.</para>
<para>Many of the mechanisms identified in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are likely to contribute to behavioral effects of ethanol in mammalian systems. For instance, it is intriguing that the mammalian BK channel can be modulated by ethanol <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> in the same way that the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> channel is modulated <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>. Further genetic analysis in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> may lead to a more complete understanding of both the acute and chronic effects of ethanol. It may be possible to gain a molecular understanding of not only the acute behavioral responses, but also the more complex adaptations and compensatory mechanisms that are likely to be responsible for drug tolerance, sensitization, withdrawal and dependency.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<para>I thank Andrew Davies and Jonathan Pierce-Shimomura for their comments on the manuscript and assistance with figures.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>References</title>
&ethan_Refs;
<para/>
</sect1>
</article>