<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % local.notation.class '| MOV'>
<!NOTATION MOV SYSTEM 'MOV'>
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'MSPfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'MSPfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'MSPfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'MSPfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'MSPfig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'MSPfig4leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY mov1 SYSTEM 'MSPmov1.mov' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov1legend SYSTEM 'MSPmov1leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY MSP_Refs SYSTEM 'MSPrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="MSP_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Sperm motility and MSP<footnote>
                <para>Edited by Donald G. Moerman and James M. Kramer. Last revised April 21, 2005. Published February 1, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Smith, H. Sperm motility and MSP (February 1, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.68.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 Harold Smith. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
            </footnote>
        </title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 5/19/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory> 
-->
        <author>
            <firstname>Harold</firstname>
            <surname>Smith<remark>
                    <footnote>
                        <para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:smithh@umbi.umd.edu">smithh@umbi.umd.edu</ulink></para>
                    </footnote>
                </remark>
            </surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Center for Advanced Research in Biotechnology, University of Maryland Biotechnology Institute, Rockville, MD 20850 USA</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Form follows function, and this maxim is particularly true for the nematode sperm
            cell. Motility is essential for fertilization, and the process of spermatogenesis
            culminates in the production of a crawling spermatozoon with an extended pseudopod.
            However, the morphological similarity to amoeboid cells of other organisms is not
            conserved at the molecular level. Instead of utilizing the actin cytoskeleton and motor
            proteins, the pseudopod moves via the regulated assembly and disassembly of filaments
            composed of the major sperm protein (MSP). The current work reviews the structure and
            dynamics of MSP filament formation, the critical role of pH in MSP assembly, and the
            recent identification of components that regulate this process. The combination of
            cytological, biochemical, and genetic approaches in this relatively simple system make
            nematode sperm an attractive model for investigating the mechanics of amoeboid cell
            motility.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
    <sect1>
        <title>Spermatogenesis</title>
        <para>A detailed description of sperm development, or spermatogenesis, can be found in the
            WormBook chapter by Steve L'Hernault (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_spermatogenesis/spermatogenesis.html">Spermatogenesis</ulink>); however, a brief summary is included here
            and diagrammed in <xref linkend="figure1"/> to emphasize the particulars of MSP assembly
            and segregation. Spermatogonial stem cells give rise to primary spermatocytes (<link linkend="bib33">Ward et al., 1981</link><!--; PMID 7298721-->). The first meiotic division produces two secondary spermatocytes
            and the second meiosis yields four haploid spermatids. These round, non-motile
            spermatids bud from the surface of the residual body, which contains components that are
            not needed for further development or sperm function. An extracellular signal induces
            the process of activation, or spermiogenesis, and causes pseudopod extension and
            motility that is the hallmark of mature spermatozoa (<xref linkend="figure2"/>).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
        <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig1" align="center" width="5.6in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Spermatogenesis and MSP</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<literallayout></literallayout>
        <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig2" align="center" width="3.4in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Scanning electron micrograph of spermatozoon</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>MSP localization reflects the various stages of spermatogenesis. Monoclonal antibodies
            to MSP first detect the protein in primary spermatocytes within structures termed
            membranous organelles. MSP accumulates in a paracrystalline arrays of filaments, called
            fibrous bodies, to form the associated fibrous body-membranous organelle complexes.
            These complexes segregate into the budding spermatids. Shortly after the spermatids
            separate from the residual body, the fibrous bodies dissociate and MSP is distributed
            throughout the cytoplasm (<link linkend="bib23">Roberts et al., 1986</link><!--; PMID 3517007-->). After activation, MSP
            becomes relocalized to the pseudopod. Ultrastructural analysis (described below in
            greater detail) shows a complex network of MSP filaments and fibers within the
            pseudopod.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Motility and fertilization</title>
        <para>The mechanics of fertilization in the nematode reproductive tract demonstrate the
            importance of sperm motility in this process. Crawling spermatozoa accumulate in the
            sperm storage organ known as the spermatheca, which is the site of fertilization. As
            each oocyte passes through the spermatheca, many spermatozoa are dislodged into the
            uterus but quickly return to the spermatheca. The reproductive period spans several days
            and ~300 progeny are produced during this time. Essentially every spermatozoon is
            successful at fertilizing an oocyte, so sperm motility must be maintained throughout
            this interval (<link linkend="bib35">Ward and Carrel, 1979</link><!--; PMID 499670-->).</para>
        <para>Mutational screens for sperm-specific sterility, the Fer or Spe phenotype, have
            identified a large number of loci necessary for proper sperm function (e.g., see <link linkend="bib1">Argon and Ward, 1980</link><!--; PMID 7196361-->; <link linkend="bib17">L'Hernault et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID 3197956-->). Mutations in several
            of the Spe/Fer genes produce apparently normal spermatids that fail to undergo
            spermiogenesis. These immotile cells initially localize to the spermatheca. However, the
            passage of oocytes rapidly sweeps the mutant sperm into the uterus, where they are
            unable to return to the spermatheca. Motility is not sufficient to insure functionality,
            since mutations in several other Spe/Fer genes permit normal activation but not
            fertilization; however, motility is likely a necessary prerequisite.</para>
        <para>The Spe-8 class of mutations is particularly instructive because sex-specific
            differences in the activation pathway permit the <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>
            manipulation of motility. Mutations of the Spe-8 class, consisting of
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-8" role="_blank">spe-8</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-12" role="_blank">spe-12</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-27" role="_blank">spe-27</ulink></emphasis>,
            and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-29" role="_blank">spe-29</ulink></emphasis>, block activation of spermatids in hermaphrodites but
            not males (<link linkend="bib17">L'Hernault et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID 3197956-->; <link linkend="bib19">Minniti et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8722776-->;
            <link linkend="bib20">Nance et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11102362-->). As a consequence, hermaphrodites are self-sterile
            while males remain cross-fertile. However, Spe-8 class hermaphrodite spermatids can be
            activated by mating, through transfer of a male component of the activation signal.
            These trans-activated sperm become motile and capable of fertilization, indicating the
            importance of motility for sperm cell function.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Motility and MSP</title>
        <para>Video microscopy of crawling sperm (<xref linkend="movie1"/>) reveals the
            critical role of MSP polymerization in cell motility (<link linkend="bib24">Roberts and Ward, 1982</link><!--; PMID 7056796-->; <link linkend="bib27">Sepsenwol et al., 1989</link><!--; PMID 2910878-->). Much of this work is on the large
            sperm from the parasitic nematode <emphasis>Ascaris suum</emphasis>, but the same
            features hold true for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Movement occurs by extension of
            the leading edge of the pseudopod, attachment to the substrate, and retraction of the
            cell body. A meshwork of fibers extends throughout the pseudopod. Assembly of new fibers
            at the leading edge of the pseudopod and disassembly at its base produce a treadmilling
            motion, and the rate of treadmilling correlates precisely with the rate of crawling
            (<link linkend="bib22">Roberts and King, 1991</link><!--; PMID 1773449-->). Manipulation of the rates of assembly and
            disassembly by pH (see following section) clearly demonstrates that the motive force is
            coupled to the combination of these two opposing processes (<link linkend="bib8">Italiano et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10477761-->). In other types of amoeboid cells, motility is based on the actin
            cytoskeleton. However, nematode spermatozoa contain no actin (<link linkend="bib21">Nelson et al., 1982</link><!--; PMID 7199049-->), but instead employ MSP filaments in this role.</para>
        <mediaobject id="movie1" xreflabel="Movie 1">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="mov1" width="2.6in" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Video micrograph of pseudopod treadmilling during motility</phrase>
            </textobject> &mov1legend;</mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>pH regulation</title>
        <para>
            <emphasis>In vitro</emphasis> activation studies reveal a critical role for pH in
            regulating spermiogenesis. Agents that increase the intracellular pH (e.g., the weak base
            TEA or the ionophore monensin at basic pH) induce spermatid activation (<link linkend="bib36">Ward et al.,
            1983</link><!--; PMID 6345236-->). The molecular mechanism of this activation is unknown; however, it
            is likely physiologically relevant, since <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> activation by
            TEA produces mature spermatozoa capable of oocyte fertilization upon artificial
            insemination (<link linkend="bib14">LaMunyon and Ward, 1994</link><!--; PMID 7851766-->). Indeed, initiation of the
            spermiogenesis pathway might culminate in elevated pH, since activation by TEA or
            monensin bypasses the requirement for the Spe-8 class signaling components (<link linkend="bib28">Shakes and Ward, 1989</link><!--; PMID 2731646-->).</para>
        <para>Changes in intracellular pH appear to control not just activation but also MSP
            polymerization throughout spermatogenesis (<link linkend="bib10">King et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 8020106-->). Experiments
            in <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> show that intracellular pH is highest in spermatocytes,
            when MSP is assembled into paracrystalline arrays in fibrous bodies, and lowest in
            spermatids, when MSP disassembles into the cytosol. Spermiogenesis induces an increase
            in pH and the assembly of MSP macrofibers. Remarkably, a pH gradient forms within the
            pseudopod of the spermatozoon; a higher pH is observed at the leading edge, where new
            filaments assemble, than at the base, where disassembly occurs. Decreasing the pH by
            buffer treatment can either slow or halt MSP polymerization at the leading edge of the
            pseudopod without affecting disassembly. A return to physiological buffer rapidly
            restores MSP assembly, pseudopod extension, and motility (<link linkend="bib8">Italiano et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10477761-->). Thus, MSP assembly in all case s is accompanied by an increase in
            intracellular pH. <emphasis>In vitro</emphasis> filament assembly occurs across a wide
            range of pH, so direct regulation of MSP polymerization by pH is unlikely (<link linkend="bib11">King et al., 1992</link><!--; PMID 1527183-->); rather, pH probably alters the activity of membrane components that
            control the assembly and disassembly of MSP filaments.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>MSP assembly and structure</title>
        <para>MSP polymerization occurs through a series of increasingly higher-order interactions
            (<link linkend="bib9">King et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7876359-->). Pairs of MSP monomers produce dimers, dimers assemble
            into helical subfilaments, pairs of subfilaments entwine to form helical filaments, and
            filaments associate into larger structures called fibers, macrofibers, or bundles. MSP
            dimers are extremely stable in solution (K<subscript>d</subscript> &lt; 5 &#x000D7; 10<superscript>-8</superscript>) and exhibit the same structure as in the filamentous
            form (<link linkend="bib6">Haaf et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8764404-->); therefore, the polymerization of MSP is likely
            regulated at the level of subfilament assembly.</para>
        <para>Structural studies have provided insights into the mechanics of MSP assembly that
            generate the motive force. X-ray diffractions of MSP crystals from both <emphasis>A.
            suum</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib3">Bullock et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8913307-->) and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
            (<link linkend="bib2">Baker et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12051923-->) reveal an immunoglobulin-like fold comprised of a
            seven-stranded <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol> sandwich (<xref
                linkend="figure4"/>). MSP forms symmetrical dimers through <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol> strands <emphasis>a<subscript>2</subscript>
            </emphasis> and <emphasis>b</emphasis> plus the penultimate asparagine residue. The
            assembly of dimers into subfilaments occurs through hydrogen bonding between residues
            within strand <emphasis>g</emphasis>. Filament formation between subfilaments is
            mediated through multiple sites of interaction, and the same sites might function in
            filament bundling as well. Mutational and biochemical analyses of recombinant MSP have
            confirmed the importance of residues critical for both the immunoglobulin fold and the
            dimerization interface (<link linkend="bib31">Smith and Ward, 1998</link><!--; PMID 9641981-->).</para>
<para>&#x000A0;</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig4" align="center" width="5in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Structure of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> MSP</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>Purified MSP exists as a dimer under most buffer conditions; however, polymerization
            occurs in the presence of water-miscible alcohols (<link linkend="bib11">King et al., 1992</link><!--; PMID 1527183-->).
            Transmission electron micrographs of these negatively stained filaments are
            indistinguishable from those obtained from fixed spermatozoa, suggesting that filament
            formation is an intrinsic property of MSP even in the absence of additional proteins.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Reconstituted MSP polymerization system</title>
        <para>A crucial advance in our understanding of MSP-based motility has been the development
            of a reconstituted cell-free filament assembly system (<link linkend="bib7">Italiano et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8548814-->). Addition of ATP to lysate from <emphasis>A. suum</emphasis> sperm causes
            the assembly of MSP into fibers. Fractionation of the lysate demonstrates that both
            membrane and cytosolic components, in addition to MSP and ATP, are necessary for fiber
            formation. Phase-contrast video microscopy reveals that each MSP fiber is nucleated by
            a membrane vesicle, and that the vesicle is propelled forward by the growing filament.
            Furthermore, only the subset of vesicles that are derived from the leading edge of the
            pseudopod, the site of MSP polymerization <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>, can promote MSP
            filament assembly <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis>. The maximum observed rate of fiber
            growth is similar to the rate of sperm crawling, suggesting that all of the relevant
            components are present.</para>
        <para>The disassembly of MSP fibers can be promoted in the same cell-free system (<link linkend="bib18">Miao et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14631043-->). Following fiber growth from reconstituted components, removal
            of ATP and addition of a tyrosine phosphatase causes fiber retraction. A bead attached
            to the non-vesicle end of the MSP fiber is drawn toward the vesicle end as the fiber
            shortens. The phosphatase likely controls the activity of a disassembly factor, since
            MSP itself is not phosphorylated. Thus, the reconstituted system exhibits the primary
            hallmarks of <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> motility: the assembly of MSP fibers at the
            leading edge of the pseudopod membrane generates a motive force that propels the
            membrane forward, and disassembly causes fiber retraction at the trailing edge.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Components that control MSP assembly</title>
        <para>Investigators have used the reconstituted system to identify specific proteins that
            regulate the assembly of MSP. One critical component from the vesicle fraction is a
            48kDa integral membrane protein with the unwieldy name major sperm protein
            polymerization organizing protein or, more simply, MPOP (<link linkend="bib16">LeClaire et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12746486-->). Phosphorylation of tyrosine residues appears to regulate the activity of
            MPOP. Immunolabeling of spermatozoa with anti-MPOP antibodies indicates that the protein
            is evenly distributed throughout the sperm plasma membrane, but anti-phosphotyrosine
            labeling of the membrane is restricted to the leading edge of the pseudopod. Purified
            phosphorylated MPOP, when combined with cytosol and ATP, is sufficient to promote MSP
            filament assembly in the absence of other vesicle components. Intriguingly, lowering the
            pH blocks both tyrosine phosphorylation of MPOP and the <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>
            assembly of MSP in a similar manner. This obs ervation suggests an appealing mechanism
            for the regulation of motility by pH, whereby an as-yet-unidentified, pH-sensitive
            tyrosine kinase phosphorylates MPOP at the tip of the pseudopod to nucleate the
            polymerization of MSP fibers.</para>
        <para>Additional proteins have been isolated from the cytosolic fraction as well. MFP1 (for
            MSP fiber protein) is a complex of three related, 15-16 kDa proteins (<symbol
                role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>, <symbol role="symbolfont"
            >&#x03B2;</symbol>, and <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B3;</symbol>) that
            inhibits fiber growth (<link linkend="bib5">Buttery et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14565983-->). Homologs in <emphasis>C.
                elegans</emphasis> comprise a larger gene family called SSP, for sperm-specific
            protein. The crystal structure of one SSP, encoded by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ssp-19" role="_blank">ssp-19</ulink></emphasis>, is
            remarkably similar to MSP despite having less than 20% amino acid sequence identity
            (<link linkend="bib25">Schormann et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15388931-->).</para>
        <para>MFP2 is a 38 kDa protein that appears to be essential for fiber formation (<link linkend="bib5">Buttery et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14565983-->). Anti-MFP2 antibodies abrogate filament assembly in the
            reconstituted system, and addition of purified MFP2 can stimulate assembly. Both
            anti-MFP1 and anti-MFP2 antibodies label MSP fibers <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> and
                <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis>, suggesting that both proteins play fairly direct
            roles in regulating assembly. Neither protein can substitute for the cytosolic fraction
            in the reconstituted system, so additional components remain to be identified.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Evolution of the MSP gene family</title>
        <para>MSP-based sperm motility appears to be conserved among nematodes. Crawling spermatozoa
            are rare among metazoans, but they are a characteristic feature of this phylum. In
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, MSP is encoded by a family of 28 genes (not
            including several additional pseudogenes) that produce isoforms that are 97-100%
            identical (<link linkend="bib4">Burke and Ward, 1983</link><!--; PMID 6315956-->; <link linkend="bib13">Klass et al., 1984</link><!--; PMID 6325882-->; <link linkend="bib34">Ward et
            al., 1988</link><!--; PMID 3351915-->). MSP genes have been identified across widely diverged nematode
            species (e.g., see <link linkend="bib26">Scott et al., 1989</link><!--; PMID 2570394-->) and MSP gene expression is
            restricted to the sperm (<link linkend="bib12">Klass et al., 1982</link><!--; PMID 7128929-->; <link linkend="bib32">Ward, 1987</link><!--; PMID 3445967-->). MSPs
            from all nematodes are greater than 60% identical, with particularly high sequence
            conservation in the dimerization interface as well as <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol> strands <emphasis>f</emphasis> and <emphasis>g</emphasis>
            (the proposed site of subfilament assembly). Missense mutations that abolish MSP-MSP
            interaction in the yeast two-hybrid system map almost exclusively to these regions,
            suggesting functional conservation as well (<link linkend="bib31">Smith and Ward, 1998</link><!--; PMID 9641981-->). However,
            mutant MSPs have not yet been characterized in the reconstituted filament assembly
            system, and conservation might reflect the roles of MSP in oocyte maturation or
            ovulation signaling rather than motility (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_controloocytematuration/controloocytematuration.html" role="_blank">Control of oocyte meiotic maturation and fertilization</ulink>).</para>
        <para>MSP seems to be restricted to nematodes, so how did this unique mechanism of cell
            motility arise? Although homologs have not been found in other phyla, proteins with
            limited sequence similarity have been identified in species from plants to mammals. The
            first of these, VAP-33, was identified from <emphasis>Aplysia californica</emphasis> as
            a VAMP/synaptobrevin-interacting protein involved in neurotransmitter release from
            synaptic vesicles (<link linkend="bib30">Skehel et al., 1995</link><!--; PMID 7667638-->). Subsequent studies in other
            organisms indicate a more general role in vesicle fusion and/or trafficking, and find
            the protein associated with microtubules and the endoplasmic reticulum in addition to
            vesicles (<link linkend="bib29">Skehel et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10655491-->). All of the VAP-33 homologs are predicted
            to share a similar architecture: an amino-terminal MSP-like domain, a central
            coiled-coil region, and a carboxy-terminal transmembrane domain (<link linkend="bib15">Laurent et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10733941-->). In addition to MSP, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome encodes
            several of these VAP-33 homologs. Thus, it appears that the small, cytosolic MSP arose
            from a larger, membrane-tethered vesicle protein.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>Despite the apparent novelty of MSP and sperm motility, the system can offer insights
            into the canonical, actin-based mechanism of cell movement. The generation of force and
            membrane protrusion by protein polymerization is a common feature of both systems. Actin
            is required for multiple cellular processes, which greatly complicates the analysis of
            its role in motility. In contrast, the relative simplicity of sperm motility offers an
            attractive model for investigation, and the combination of genetic and biochemical
            approaches will continue to advance our understanding of the underlying biomechanical
            properties of amoeboid movement.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
		<para/>
		&MSP_Refs;</sect1>
</article>