<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % local.notation.class '| MOV'>
<!NOTATION MOV SYSTEM 'MOV'>
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'biogenomefig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'biogenomefig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'biogenomefig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'biogenomefig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY mov1 SYSTEM 'biogenomemov1.mov' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov1legend SYSTEM 'biogenomemov1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY biogenome_Refs SYSTEM "biogenomerefs.xml">
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="biogenome_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title>The biology and genome of <emphasis>Heterorhabditis bacteriophora</emphasis><footnote>
			<para>Edited by Jonathan Hodgkin and Philip Anderson. Last revised November 22, 2006. Published February 20, 2007. This chapter should be cited as: Ciche, T. The biology and genome of <emphasis>Heterorhabditis bacteriophora</emphasis> (February 20, 2007), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.135.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2007 Todd Ciche. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
		<author>
			<firstname>Todd</firstname>
			<surname>Ciche<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: 405 271-7681. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:ciche@msu.edu">ciche@msu.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></surname>
			<affiliation><address>Department of Microbiology and Molecular Genetics, Michigan State University, East Lansing, MI 48824 USA</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
</articleinfo>
	<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Heterorhabditis bacteriophora</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">is an entomopathogenic nematode (EPN) mutually associated with the enteric bacterium,</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Photorhabdus luminescens</emphasis>,</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">used globally for the biological control of insects. Much of the previous research concerning</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">H. bacteriophora</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">has dealt with applied aspects related to biological control. However,</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">H. bacteriophora</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">is an excellent model to investigate fundamental processes such as parasitism and mutualism in addition to its comparative value to</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Caenorhabditis elegans.</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">In June 2005,</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">H. bacteriophora</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">was targeted by NHGRI for a high quality genome sequence. This chapter summarizes the biology of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">H. bacteriophora</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">in common and distinct from</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">as well as the status of the genome project.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>Much of the interest in <emphasis>Heterorhabditis bacteriophora</emphasis> nematodes relates to its intimate interactions with other organisms. <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> is an insect parasite used for the biological control of insects and an obligate host for symbiotic <emphasis>Photorhabdus luminescens</emphasis> bacteria<emphasis></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib16">Forst et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9343343-->; see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). Transmission of symbiotic bacteria by the infective juvenile (IJ) stage nematodes is essential for the nematode to successfully parasitize insects and to reproduce (<link linkend="bib20">Han and Ehlers, 2000</link><!-- PMID ISI:000085395100009-->). Hence, this association can also be described as an obligate (for nematode and symbiont) vector-borne disease of insects. <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> can also be described as a bacteriovore dependent on symbiotic <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> for growth and reproduction. However, classifying <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> as a bacteriovore ignores the parasitic adaptations such as host finding, buccal tooth used to penetrate the insect exoskeleton (<link linkend="bib5">Bedding and Molyneux, 1982</link><!-- PMID PREV198477035703 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->), regurgitation of intestinal symbionts after sensing host cue(s) (<link linkend="bib10">Ciche and Ensign, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12676661-->), and its symbiotic association with <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> bacteria. <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> is a rhabditid nematode in the eurhabditid clade along with <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and strongylid parasites (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_phylogrhabditids/phylorhab.html" role="_blank">The phylogenetic relationships of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and other rhabditids</ulink>). Thus, unique characteristics such as parasitism, biological control and symbiosis can be studied utilizing the knowledge base and resources of <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis> In June 2005, NHGRI targeted <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> for a high quality draft genome sequence. The knowledge obtained from the genome sequence should rapidly establish this nematode as an animal model for parasitism, symbiosis, vector-born disease and its application for the biological control of insects.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="6in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Discovery and diversity</title>
<para>The insect parasitic (entomopathogenic) nematode, <emphasis>Heterorhabditis bacteriophora,</emphasis> was first described in 1975 as a new genus, species, and family (Heterorhabditidae) of Rhabditida (<link linkend="bib37">Poinar, 1975</link><!-- PMID PREV197661061050 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->). The infective juvenile (IJ) stage, which is similar to the dauer juvenile stage of <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> was found to transmit a specific Gram-negative bacterium in the anterior intestine to the hemocoel of insect hosts (<link linkend="bib38">Poinar et al., 1977</link><!-- PMID PREV197764032992 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->). This bacterium was first described as <emphasis>Xenorhabdus luminescens,</emphasis> along with <emphasis>Xenorhabdus nematophila</emphasis> which is<emphasis></emphasis> associated with the distantly related insect parasitic nematode, <emphasis>Steinernema carpocapsae</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib44">Thomas and Poinar, 1979</link><!-- PMID PREV198069034640 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->). This bacterium is now called <emphasis>Photorhabdus luminescens</emphasis> subspecies <emphasis>luminescens</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib15">Fischer-Le Saux et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID-->). Several <emphasis>Heterorhabditis</emphasis> species have been described (<link linkend="bib1">Adams et al., 2006</link><!-- PMID-->; <link linkend="bib23">Hominick et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9443947-->) and studied for their biological control potential. In 2003, the complete genome sequence of a <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> symbiont, <emphasis>Photorhabdus luminescens</emphasis> subsp. <emphasis>laumondii</emphasis> strain TT01 isolated from Trinidad and Tobago, was published (<link linkend="bib14">Duchaud et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14528314-->). Because of the available symbiont genome sequence, the <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> genome consortium chose <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> for the genome sequence and to use as a model for further studies.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Life-cycle</title>
<para>The non-feeding and developmentally arrested IJ is the only stage of <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> found outside of insect hosts in nature. IJs exist, often in soil, containing a monoculture of symbiotic bacteria in their intestinal lumen while in search for an insect host (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). The IJs sense an insect host, enter the hemocoel and regurgitate symbiotic bacteria into the insect hemocoel (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link> and <link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link>; <link linkend="bib10">Ciche and Ensign, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12676661-->). The bacteria rapidly kill the insect, usually in less than 24 hours. The bacterium is the main cause of insect mortality since the bacterium alone has an LD<subscript>50</subscript> &lt;10 cells when injected the insect hemocoel (<link linkend="bib32">Milstead, 1979</link><!-- PMID PREV198069010037 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->) and axenic IJs do not cause insect mortality nor proliferate without symbiotic bacteria present (<link linkend="bib20">Han and Ehlers, 2000</link><!-- PMID ISI:000085395100009-->). Symbiotic bacteria provide a protected niche for themselves and host nematodes by producing antibiotics (<link linkend="bib3">Akhurst, 1982</link><!-- PMID ISI:A1982QA21700027-->; <link linkend="bib24">Hu and Webster, 2000</link><!--; PMID ISI:000088681500017-->; <link linkend="bib35">Paul et al., 1981</link><!--; PMID ISI:A1981LZ70400011-->; <link linkend="bib41">Richardson et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID PREV198886041631-->), nematicide (<link linkend="bib25">Hu et al., 1999</link><!-- PMID ISI:000084192800002-->) and even compounds which deter scavenging ants (<link linkend="bib47">Zhou et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12450845-->). The nematodes grow and reproduce for 2-3 generations on symbiotic bacteria before generating IJs en masse, most transmitting symbiotic bacteria.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="6.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Parasitism</title>
<para>Entomopathogenic IJs employ different foraging behaviors to infect insect hosts, cruiser and ambusher strategies (<link linkend="bib30">Lewis et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID PREV199598360665 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->). <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> is a cruiser forager meaning that it actively seeks out or hunts its prey. In addition to sensing CO<subscript>2</subscript> and volatile cues (<link linkend="bib34">O&apos;Halloran and Burnell, 2002</link><!-- PMID PREV200200475705 Copyright BIOSIS 2003-->) released by the host, IJs are attracted to (E)-beta-caryophyllene, a terpene released by plant roots upon herbivore damage (<link linkend="bib40">Rasmann et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID 15815622-->). Thus, IJs have evolved chemosensory mechanisms not only to detect insect hosts, but also locations where insect hosts are likely to be present. When in contact with an insect host, the IJs exsheath the previously retained J2 cuticle and enter the hemocoel through the insect mouth, anus or spiracles or by penetrating the exoskeleton using a buccal &#x02018;tooth&#x02019;-like structure (<link linkend="bib5">Bedding and Molyneux, 1982</link><!-- PMID PREV198477035703 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->). Once inside the insect hemocoel, the IJs must contend with the sophisticated innate immune defenses of the insect. Insects defend against large organisms by encapsulation and activation of phenol oxidase cascade, the latter is observed by a black appearance due to melanin production (<link linkend="bib18">Gillespie et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9017902-->). Insects also have Toll-like receptors that detect pathogen associated molecular patterns (PAMPs) which in turn activate antimicrobial peptides (<link linkend="bib29">Lemaitre et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID 9405661-->). <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> and/or associated bacteria either avoid or suppress these immune defenses since IJs are not encapsulated (<link linkend="bib36">Peters et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID PREV199799758430 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->) and infected insects do not turn black.</para>
<para>After IJ entry into insect hemocoel, it releases the symbiotic bacteria. Using GFP-labeled symbionts located in the IJ intestines, it was observed that the IJs regurgitate symbiotic bacteria (<link linkend="bib10">Ciche and Ensign, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12676661-->; see <link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link>). After a 30 minute lag, IJs regurgitate symbiotic bacteria in a pulsatile and staggered manner at an average rate of 1 cell released every 2 minutes. The regurgitation inducing cues were present in all arthropod hemolymph and insect cell culture supernatants tested, but not in vertebrate blood or <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> culture supernatants. The cue(s) was also shown to be heat and protease resistant and less than &gt;5000 Da MW. The nematodes provide the mechanical force for regurgitation because IJs treated with levamisole and ivermectin fail to expel the bacteria and the bacteria are not motile initially after release.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="movie1" xreflabel="Movie 1">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="mov1" width="5.2in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>movie 1</phrase>
			</textobject> &mov1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Like many nematode parasites, <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> infects with a stage analogous to the dauer stage of <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis> Exiting the developmentally arrested IJ during infection is analogous to dauer recovery in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, as exemplified by common muscarinic signaling involved in <emphasis>Ancyclostoma caninum</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> dauer recovery (<link linkend="bib45">Tissenbaum et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10618440-->). <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> provides an excellent model to study parasitism because insect larvae can be used as hosts. Moreover, induction of parasitism can be assayed by monitoring the release of <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> by IJs incubated in insect cell supernatants (<link linkend="bib10">Ciche and Ensign, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12676661-->). Although <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> is the main cause for insect pathogenicity, <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> IJs likely contribute to insect virulence, for example through immune suppression.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Symbiosis</title>
<para>The symbiosis between <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> and <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> is potentially one of the most tractable symbiosis models. <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> shares many attributes with <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> such as, short generation time, high fecundity, hermaphroditic and gonochoristic modes of reproduction, small size, transparency and small genome size. <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> is an enteric <symbol role="symbolfont">&gamma;</symbol>-Proteobacterium that shares many virulence factors with medically relevant pathogens and the complete genome sequence is known (<link linkend="bib14">Duchaud et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14528314-->). Thus genomes will be available for both partners of this symbiosis and genetics are established in <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> and being developed in <emphasis>H. bacteriophora.</emphasis> The most important characteristic of this symbiosis, in my opinion, is that it is obligate in nature. Since <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> and <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> require each other to reproduce in nature, strong selective pressure is likely applied to ensure proper establishment and maintenance of the symbiosis. Two important symbiotic processes are the selective transmission of <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> by IJs and the requirement of <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> for nematode growth and reproduction (<link linkend="bib11">Ciche et al., 2006</link><!-- PMID-->). However, symbiotic bacteria are likely to influence other developmental and physiological processes in <emphasis>H. bacteriophora,</emphasis> e.g., by the production of food signals (<link linkend="bib43">Strauch and Ehlers, 1998</link><!-- PMID PREV199800497213 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->).</para>
<para><emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> must transmit <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> to infect and proliferate inside insects. Axenic nematodes do not cause insect mortality and do not proliferate inside the insect cadavers (limited reproduction occurs generating L1s which fail to develop further; <link linkend="bib20">Han and Ehlers, 2000</link><!-- PMID ISI:000085395100009-->). Thus, <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> IJs selectively transmit symbiotic <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> or related strains (<link linkend="bib17">Gerritsen and Smits, 1993</link><!-- PMID PREV199396097994 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->). Furthermore, when <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> are grown on lawns of the <emphasis>P. temperata</emphasis> symbiont of <emphasis>H. megidis</emphasis>, no <emphasis>P. temperata</emphasis> are transmitted (<link linkend="bib20">Han and Ehlers, 2000</link><!-- PMID ISI:000085395100009-->). However, transmission is not strictly species specific since a <emphasis>P. temperata</emphasis> strain C1 (ATCC 29304) symbiont of <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> nematodes is transmitted by <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> TT01 (Ciche, unpublished).</para>
<para>The processes and molecular mechanisms of symbiont transmission in <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> is not well understood and is a major focus of research in my laboratory (I will update this chapter accordingly as new findings are published). The <emphasis>ngrA</emphasis> gene is required for <emphasis>P. temperata</emphasis> to support <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> growth and development (discussed below) and is unable to compete with wild-type bacteria during IJ colonization, but colonizes normally when grown with <emphasis>P. temperata</emphasis> Meg/1, a strain not transmitted by <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> nematodes (<link linkend="bib9">Ciche et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID PREV200100244598 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->). The <emphasis>ngrA</emphasis> gene encodes a putative 4<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol>-phosphopantetheinyl transferase (PPTase) that is likely required for acyl- and peptidyl- carrier proteins that function for the biosynthesis of fatty acids, polyketides and non-ribosomally synthesized peptides (<link linkend="bib39">Quadri et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9484229-->). Thus, it is the absence of holo-carrier protein(s) and corresponding secondary metabolites that is likely involved in transmission. In another study, a mutant in the <emphasis>pbgPE</emphasis> operon, involved in the synthesis of O-antigen component of lipopolysaccharide, was transmitted 1% compared to wild type and was not transmitted when cocultured with wild-type bacteria (<link linkend="bib6">Bennett and Clarke, 2005</link><!-- PMID-->). A <emphasis>pbgPE</emphasis> mutant is also sensitive to mildly acidic conditions and to the cationic antibiotic polymyxin, suggesting that these stresses might be employed by the nematode to selectively transmit <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> bacteria.</para>
<para>In contrast to more general bacteriovores like <emphasis>C. elegans, H. bacteriophora</emphasis> requires <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> or <emphasis>P. temperata</emphasis> as a substrate for growth and development (<link linkend="bib4">Akhurst et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID 8863433-->) and is very sensitive to contaminating microbes compared to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. In addition, the primary form is required for nematode growth and development. The primary form is isolated from IJs and infected insects and switches to the secondary phase variant upon prolonged subculturing (<link linkend="bib2">Akhurst, 1980</link><!-- PMID ISI: A1980LH09100003-->). The primary form can be distinguished from the secondary variant by differential dye uptake, bioluminescence, colony morphology (mucoid, pigmented and opaque primary form colonies), antibiotic, and exoenzyme production, and production of two intracellular crystalline inclusion proteins, CipA and CipB (<link linkend="bib2">Akhurst, 1980</link><!-- PMID ISI: A1980LH09100003-->; <link linkend="bib8">Bintrim and Ensign, 1998</link><!-- PMID ISI:000072246300031-->).</para>
<para>The Cips can account for as much as 40% of total protein and are unusually high in essential amino acid content (<link linkend="bib8">Bintrim and Ensign, 1998</link><!-- PMID ISI:000072246300031-->). Both <emphasis>cipA</emphasis> and <emphasis>cipB</emphasis> were cloned and disrupted by allelic exchange and neither mutant supported nematode growth and development (<link linkend="bib8">Bintrim and Ensign, 1998</link><!-- PMID ISI:000072246300031-->). The mutant <emphasis>cip</emphasis> strains were phenotypically intermediate between the primary form and the secondary phase. Thus, the inability of the <emphasis>cip</emphasis> mutants to support nematode growth and reproduction might be related to other secondary phase variant characteristics than Cip production.</para>
<para>To determine other genes required for the bacterium to support nematode growth and reproduction, transposon mutants were screened for their inability to support nematode growth and reproduction. Mutant NGR209 was completely defective in supporting nematode growth and reproduction while retaining most primary form characteristics (<link linkend="bib9">Ciche et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID PREV200100244598 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->). The <emphasis>ngrA</emphasis> gene, encoding a putative 4<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol>-phosphopantetheinyl transferase (PPTase), was found to contain a transposon insertion causal for the symbiotic defect of NGR209. As already discussed above, PPTases transfer 4<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol>-phosphopantothenate to serine residues on acyl- or peptidyl carrier proteins involved the biosynthesis of a great variety of secondary metabolites. NGR209 was defective in producing antibiotic and siderophore (microbial compounds that chelate iron) activities. Thus, these metabolites, or another metabolite, likely function to signal directly or indirectly for nematode growth and reproduction (<link linkend="bib9">Ciche et al., 2001</link><!-- PMID PREV200100244598 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->). The production of siderophores was shown not to be necessary for nematode growth and reproduction since a mutant in a peptidyl carrier protein required for the synthesis of photobactin siderophore supported nematode growth and reproduction to the extent of wild type (<link linkend="bib10">Ciche et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID ISI:000184672500048-->). However when a siderophore transport related gene, <emphasis>expD,</emphasis> was disrupted, the mutant bacteria no longer supported nematode growth and reproduction. This defect was complemented by the addition of iron, suggesting a role for iron metabolism for the bacteria to support nematode growth and reproduction (<link linkend="bib46">Watson et al., 2005</link><!-- PMID 15819630-->).</para>
<para>In addition to the production or lack thereof of nematode growth and reproduction activity, some <emphasis>Photorhabdus</emphasis> spp. antagonize non-symbiotic nematodes. This seems to be the case with the <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> subsp. <emphasis>luminescens</emphasis> associated with <emphasis>H. indica</emphasis> nematodes (<link linkend="bib19">Han and Ehlers, 1999</link><!-- PMID ISI:000084583500003-->).</para>
<para>Although most <emphasis>Photorhabdus</emphasis> are toxic to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and other nematodes, some are toxic to <emphasis>Heterorhabditis</emphasis> nematodes. Much remains to be learned regarding nematode growth and reproduction activity of symbiotic <emphasis>Photorhabdus</emphasis> as well as the antagonism towards non-symbiotic nematodes.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Other biology of interest for <emphasis>Heterorhabditis</emphasis></title>
<para>Many biological processes well-known in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> will be of great interest to study in <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> in relation to symbiosis and parasitism. Examples of these are dauer recovery and formation in relation to parasitism and symbiont transmission, and innate immunity in relation to symbiont transmission. Processes such as resistance to stress and desiccation and dauer longevity are also of interest since they may lead to increased efficacy or increased shelf-life of EPNs used for biological control of insects. However, the heterogonic mode of reproduction of <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> is rare in rhabditids (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_phylogrhabditids/phylorhab.html" role="_blank">The phylogenetic relationships of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and other rhabditids</ulink>). <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> IJs develop into hermaphrodites and these in turn can lay eggs that develop into hermaphrodites, females or males. When egg laying ceases, worms develop inside the maternal body cavity by a process called <emphasis>endotokia matricida</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib26">Johnigk and Ehlers, 1999</link><!-- PMID PREV200000105206 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->). Interestingly, worms that develop by <emphasis>endotokia matricida</emphasis> are predominantly hermaphroditic IJs (<link linkend="bib13">Dix et al., 1992</link><!-- PMID PREV199294051880 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->). Thus, it appears that individual worms can change the sex of their offspring. Nothing is known at the molecular level concerning this heterogonic mode of reproduction and the genome sequence should provide sex determination related genes shared and absent in <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> as compared to <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis></para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>Genetics and molecular biology of <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> can be cultivated on agar plates containing the primary form of <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> or <emphasis>P. temperata</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib31">Lunau et al., 1993</link><!-- PMID PREV199396110290 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->). Successful mutagenesis of <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> using EMS similar to the procedure used for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has been published (<link linkend="bib28">Koltai et al., 1994</link><!-- PMID PREV199497221864 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->). Transformation of <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> by microinjection has also been published (<link linkend="bib21">Hashmi et al., 1995</link><!-- PMID PREV199698563977 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->; <link linkend="bib22">Hashmi et al., 1997</link><!-- PMID PREV199799690550 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->). Furthermore, RNAi gene silencing by soaking is successful in <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> (Ciche and Sternberg unpublished). A protocol for the successful cryopreservation of <emphasis>Heterorhabditis</emphasis> species has been developed (<link linkend="bib33">Nugent et al., 1996</link><!-- PMID PREV199698696711 Copyright BIOSIS 2003.-->). Despite these encouraging results, development of genetics and molecular biology in <emphasis>Heterorhabditis</emphasis> is still in the early stages. Few mutants have been published in <emphasis>Heterorhabditis</emphasis> and there is no genetic map. Transformation by microinjection has not been repeated since the initial reports. Along with the high quality draft genome sequence, generation of a physical map is planned for the <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> genome project. The genome and a physical map, along with the development of RNAi and transformation, should facilitate the development and use of genetic and molecular tools in <emphasis>H. bacteriophora.</emphasis></para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>Status and future of the <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> genome project</title>
<para>In June 2005, NHGRI announced that it was targeting <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> for a high quality (i.e., 6X coverage) draft genome sequence. This was partially due to the efforts and white paper produced by the <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> genome consortium initiated at the EPN and associated bacteria meetings in Wooster, Ohio and Eilat, Israel in 2003 (<link linkend="bib11">Ciche et al., 2006</link><!-- PMID-->). <emphasis>Heterorhabditis</emphasis> was chosen over other EPNs because of its relatedness to <emphasis>C. elegans,</emphasis> and <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> strain TTO1 was chosen because the genome sequence of the mutually associated <emphasis>P. luminescens</emphasis> subsp. <emphasis>laumondii</emphasis> bacteria was completed (<link linkend="bib14">Duchaud et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14528314-->). This strain was inbred for 13 generations by self-fertilizing individual IJs and distributed to the EPN community (Ciche and Sternberg unpublished). The genome size was determined to be 111.4 +/- 1.1 Mb by Spencer Johnson using a flow cytometry technique (<link linkend="bib7">Bennett et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID-->; The <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> genome consortium, unpublished). Genomic DNA from the inbred line M31e purified from axenic IJs has been sent to Washington University Genome Sciences Center and is currently undergoing heterozygosity testing (see progress here: <ulink url="http://genome.wustl.edu/genome.cgi?GENOME=Heterorhabditis%20bacteriophora" role="_blank">http://genome.wustl.edu/genome.cgi?GENOME=Heterorhabditis%20 bacteriophora</ulink>). Approximately 4600 sequence traces generated for heterozygosity testing have been deposited in the NCBI Trace Archive (linked to in the website listed above). Construction of a physical map and ESTs are also planned. Recently, an EST dataset (1246 ESTs) from <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> strain GPS11 was analyzed (<link linkend="bib42">Sandhu et al., 2006</link><!-- PMID 16414368-->). From 1072 useful ESTs analyzed, 417 had significant similarities to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and approximately 67% of the ESTs had no significant match in Genbank suggesting the possibility that a significant amount of novel genes expressed by IJ <emphasis>H. bacteriophora.</emphasis> It is evident from this data and initial genome data on the NCBI trace archive, that <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> shares many signaling pathways with <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis> However, the large amount of genome data that will be available in the near future should greatly clarify comparisons to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and other nematodes.<emphasis></emphasis> The high quality draft sequence, ESTs and a physical map will rapidly mature our knowledge of gene content, organization and expression and enable many studies, such as functional genomics to elucidate gene function in <emphasis>H. bacteriophora,</emphasis> for example, as related to parasitic or symbiotic biology.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec9">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<para><emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> is a nematode with applied value for the biological control of insects. <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> also has value as a model to study processes not studied in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, including parasitism, symbiosis and heterogonic sex determination. Information from the genome project, along with comparisons to other nematode genomes, will provide us with a better understanding of what genes make a nematode a parasite and host for symbiotic bacteria.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec10">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>I gratefully acknowledge the National Institutes of Health (NIH), National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI) for targeting <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> for a high quality draft genome sequence and support from the Interagency National Science Foundation (NSF)/ United States Department of Agriculture (USDA)-Cooperative State Research, Education and Extension Service (CSREES) Microbial Genome Sequencing Project (07-165-0709). The energetic support and expertise from Paul Sternberg, consultations from members of Wormbase and John Spieth and Sandra Clifton at Washington University Genome Sciences Center were all critical for the successful funding of the genome project. I gratefully acknowledge Parwinder Grewal for being PI and providing leadership of the genome project, co-PIs Byron Adams, Randy Gaugler and Paul W. Sternberg and all members of the <emphasis>H. bacteriophora</emphasis> genome consortium. The Ciche lab is funded by the CSREES Microbial Genome Sequence Project and from funding though Michigan State University&apos;s Research for Excellence Funds-Center for Microbial Pathogenesis. I also thank two anonymous reviewers for valuable comments and suggestions.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>References</title>
&biogenome_Refs;
<para/>
</sect1>
</article>