<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'transmechfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'transmechfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'transmechfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'transmechfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY transmech_Refs SYSTEM 'transmechrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="transmech_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title>Transcription mechanisms<footnote>
			<para>Edited by Thomas Blumenthal. Last revised July 14, 2006. Published September 5, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Blackwell, T. K. and Walker, A. K. Transcription mechanisms (September 5, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.121.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 T. Keith Blackwell and Amy K. Walker. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
		<author>
		<othername>T. Keith Blackwell<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Phone: 617-919-2769, E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:keith.blackwell@joslin.harvard.edu">keith.blackwell@joslin.harvard.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark> and Amy K. Walker<remark><footnote><para>Present Address: Massachusetts General Hospital Cancer Center, 149-7202 13th Street, Charlestown, MA 02129</para></footnote></remark>
</othername>
		<affiliation><address>Section on Developmental and Stem Cell Biology, Joslin Diabetes Center; Department of Pathology, Harvard Medical School; Harvard Stem Cell Institute; One Joslin Place, Boston, MA 02215, USA</address>
		</affiliation>
	</author>
</articleinfo>
<abstract>
	<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Appropriate regulation of mRNA transcription is central to the differentiation and functions of eukaryotic cells, and to the development of complex organisms. mRNAs are synthesized by the coordinated action of a set of general transcription and mRNA modification factors. These factors and the fundamental mechanisms involved in transcription are conserved among eukaryotes, including</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans.</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">Recent studies in various systems have revealed that this apparatus is not controlled through a simple on/off &#x0201C;switch&#x0201D; at the promoter, and that the factors and mechanisms involved in transcription are instead subject to regulation at a surprising number of different levels. In this chapter we will discuss examples in which regulation involving the general mRNA transcription apparatus or other transcription co-factors plays a central role in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">development, and in which</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">studies have provided new insights into eukaryotic transcription mechanisms. Together, these studies have shown that regulatory mechanisms that involve the general Pol II machinery are a central participant in many aspects of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">biology.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<?newpage?>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>mRNA transcription involves conserved mechanisms, and is regulated at many levels</title>
<para>In this first section we will briefly describe the processes through which eukaryotic mRNAs are synthesized by RNA Polymerase (Pol) II. In general, the findings discussed in this section have been obtained in cellular or <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> studies of <emphasis>S. cerevisiae</emphasis>, <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> embryos, or cultured human cells, but we will also refer to aspects of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> biology where indicated. In subsequent sections of the chapter, we will discuss how analyses of these fundamental mRNA transcription mechanisms or factors have provided important insights into <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> biology, or <emphasis>vice versa</emphasis>. We will not discuss RNA Pol I (ribosomal RNA genes) or Pol III (small nuclear and transfer RNA genes), which have been studied very little in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
<para>Eukaryotic mRNAs are synthesized by Pol II through an intricate multistep process (<link linkend="bib32">Lemon and Tjian, 2000</link><!--: PMID 11040209-->; <link linkend="bib45">Orphanides and Reinberg, 2002</link><!--: PMID 11909516-->). mRNA transcription initiates at a fixed start site that is located adjacent to the promoter (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1A</link>). Transcription then must be maintained during an elongation phase, in which Pol II progresses more distally along the gene. Remarkably, these events are mechanistically coupled to the series of steps that process the transcript into a mature mRNA. Although very few biochemical studies of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> transcription complexes have been performed, it seems almost certain that these basic mRNA transcription mechanisms have been conserved in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Firstly, most of the components of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> general transcription machinery have been identified at the DNA sequence level (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). In addition, as described in the text, <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> studies of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> transcription machinery components have generally yielded results consistent with mechanistic functions that were defined in other systems.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.5in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The first step in eukaryotic mRNA transcription is assembly of a pre-initiation complex (PIC) that consists of Pol II, a set of conserved general transcription factors (GTFs), and Mediator, a large multiprotein complex that communicates directly with many gene-specific regulators (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1A</link>; <link linkend="bib24">Green, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15893723-->; <link linkend="bib29">Kornberg, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15896740-->; <link linkend="bib32">Lemon and Tjian, 2000</link><!--: PMID 11040209-->; <link linkend="bib45">Orphanides and Reinberg, 2002</link><!--: PMID 11909516-->). As described in <link linkend="sec5">Section 5</link>, genetic studies of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Mediator subunits have synergized beautifully with biochemical and functional experiments to link these subunits to specific transcription pathways and biological processes. PIC assembly is directed to the start site by &#x0201C;core&#x0201D; promoter sequences that are recognized primarily by subunits of the GTF TFIID, including the TATA-binding protein (TBP), or by related protein complexes (<link linkend="sec4">Section 4</link>; <link linkend="bib43">Muller and Tora, 2004</link><!--: PMID 14685269-->). This process is driven by upstream gene-specific activators that bind to regulatory sequences within promoters or distal enhancer elements, and recruit PIC components to the promoter through direct interactions (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1A</link>). The complexity involved in PIC assembly makes it possible to integrate many regulatory signals at the promoter, making it possible for an individual gene to be responsive to multiple independent cues.</para>
<para>Recruitment of the PIC by gene-specific activators is the most fundamental mechanism through which transcription is induced, but PIC assembly is also influenced profoundly by the positioning or modification of histones, the basic building block of chromatin. The configuration of chromatin at the promoter region is in turn affected through recruitment of chromatin modification or remodeling factors by gene-specific activators or repressors. Transcription regulation at the chromatin level is an increasingly complex subject that is largely beyond the scope of this chapter, and has been addressed partially in other chapters (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlinechromatin/germlinechromatin.html">Germline chromatin</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_specgermline/specgermline.html">Specification of the germ line</ulink>), but we will briefly describe some examples in which interplays among chromatin remodelers have important functions in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> biology (<link linkend="sec6">Section 6</link>).</para>
<para>In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> numerous promoters that regulate expression of individual genes have been identified and mapped (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transcriptionalregulation/transcriptionalregulation.html">Transcription regulation</ulink>), but little is known about the core promoter elements that direct the Pol II machinery to specific transcription start sites. The basic PIC apparatus that recognizes core promoters is present in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, but approximately 70% of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes are trans-spliced to one of a small number of common leader sequences (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transsplicingoperons/transsplicingoperons.html">Trans-splicing and operons</ulink>), making it almost impossible to identify their transcription start sites precisely. Some predicted <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> core promoters include apparent TATA elements but others do not (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transcriptionalregulation/transcriptionalregulation.html">Transcription regulation</ulink>), as is true in other organisms, but the counterparts to other core promoter elements identified in other systems (<link linkend="bib61">Smale and Kadonaga, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12651739-->) have not been studied in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. At the same time, known core promoter recognition factors are critical for transcription in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="sec4">Section 4</link>), indicating that regulatory principles identified elsewhere are likely to apply. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> upstream regulatory regions are more compact than those of higher eukaryotes (usually &lt;2kb, see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transcriptionalregulation/transcriptionalregulation.html">Transcription regulation</ulink>), and generally do not rely on distant &#x0201C;enhancer&#x0201D; elements, but similarly include clusters of sites for gene-specific regulators. Our understanding of the architecture of gene-specific <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> regulatory regions will continue to increase with expansion of genomics resources for characterizing these elements and identifying proteins that bind to them (<link linkend="bib17">Deplancke et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16777607-->; <link linkend="bib19">Dupuy et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15489340-->).</para>
<para>Elegant mechanistic analyses in other systems have shown that while transcription can begin after assembly of the PIC is complete, subsequent transcription steps depend upon phosphorylation of the Pol II large subunit C-terminal domain (CTD) (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1B</link>; <link linkend="bib3">Bentley, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15901493-->; <link linkend="bib8">Buratowski, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15901494-->; <link linkend="bib39">Meinhart et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15964991-->). The CTD consists of tandem repeats (38 in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, 52 in humans) that are based upon the sequence YSPTSPS. Pol II is recruited with the CTD in an unphosphorylated form, then at the promoter the CTD repeat is phosphorylated on Ser 5 by cyclin-dependent kinase (CDK)-7. This phosphorylation allows Pol II to move away from the promoter region, and results in recruitment of the mRNA capping enzyme (C. E., <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1B</link>). The CTD is then phosphorylated on Ser 2 by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CDK-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDK-9</ulink> (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1B</link>). Ser 2 phosphorylation promotes transcription elongation, and allows mRNA termination and processing factors to be recruited directly to the CTD. One of the most interesting concepts to emerge from the transcription field during the past decade is that the CTD acts as a molecular integrator that physically couples transcription to downstream nuclear events that include mRNA processing, termination, and even nuclear export, and that the cycle of CTD phosphorylation is critical for orchestrating these events. Dephosphorylation of the CTD may occur in competition with the action of CTD kinases (not shown), and is required for Pol II to be recycled for future transcription. As is described below, a number of studies have investigated the regulation of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryonic transcription in part by monitoring CTD phosphorylation (<link linkend="sec3">Sections 3</link> and <link linkend="sec4">4</link>).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Tools for studying transcription in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
<para>Because of its considerable advantages for genetic, phenotypic, and cell biological studies, most analyses of transcription mechanisms in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have involved intact embryos or animals. One of the most important contributions of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to the transcription field is that mutations in PIC genes have been recovered in genetic screens, and have linked regulation that involves these factors to specific biological processes (<link linkend="sec5">Section 5</link> and <link linkend="sec6">6</link>). Another advantage of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is that during early embryonic stages both maternal and zygotic gene expression can be disrupted by RNA interference (RNAi), and viability can be sustained by maternal mRNAs in the absence of transcription. For example, without the Pol II catalytic large subunit <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AMA-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">AMA-1</ulink> embryonic cells continue dividing to form a cluster of approximately 100 undifferentiated cells (<link linkend="bib47">Powell-Coffman et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8812143-->), even though transcription of zygotic genes normally begins much earlier (<link linkend="sec3">Section 3</link>). It has therefore been possible in the early embryo to study functions of GTFs that are otherwise essential for cell viability (<link linkend="sec4">Section 4</link>).</para>
<para>A variety of techniques have been employed to assess mRNA production or occurrence of transcription steps in living or fixed <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. One of the earliest approaches to be adopted was measurement or visualization of labeled UTP incorporation (<link linkend="bib21">Edgar et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID 7512022-->; <link linkend="bib23">Gibert et al., 1984</link><!--: PMID 6234041-->; <link linkend="bib53">Schisa et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11262230-->). This technique provides a rough but direct indicator of mRNA production over time, and has been used to assess when high-level transcription begins during embryogenesis and germ cell development, and to track mRNA localization. A major advance for studying <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> gene regulation was the development of techniques for visualizing the presence of individual mRNAs by <emphasis>in situ</emphasis> hybridization (<link linkend="bib55">Seydoux and Fire, 1994</link><!--: PMID 7607073-->). The most widely used means of assaying gene expression in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is production of transgenic reporter strains in which a coding region or predicted promoter of interest is fused to green fluorescent protein (GFP), or another marker that can be detected in living animals. This approach, and its advantages and potential pitfalls, are described in detail in the <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transcriptionalregulation/transcriptionalregulation.html">Transcription regulation</ulink> chapter. An indirect but valuable technique for studying transcription has been to perform immunostaining or western blotting with well-characterized antibodies that recognize Ser 5- or Ser 2-phosphorylated forms of the CTD repeat (<link linkend="bib3">Bentley, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15901493-->; <link linkend="bib8">Buratowski, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15901494-->), and are refered to here as <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-PSer5 and <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-PSer2. These assays provide approximate indicators of the occurrence of steps associated with the initiation and elongation phases of transcription, respectively (<link linkend="sec4">Section 4</link>).</para>
<para>In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> studies of transcription mechanisms have been performed relatively infrequently, although most biochemical techniques through which transcription has been investigated in other systems are feasible. One of the earliest investigations of transcription in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> involved a series of parallel biochemical and genetic studies of RNA polymerase activity. RNA Pol I, Pol II, and Pol III were partially purified from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, and shown to parallel the corresponding polymerases from other organisms with respect to their relative sensitivies to the mushroom toxin <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-amanitin (<link linkend="bib50">Sanford et al., 1983</link><!--: PMID 6630208-->; <link linkend="bib51">Sanford et al., 1985</link><!--: PMID 3891751-->). At the same time, mutagenesis screens for increased resistance to <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-amanitin identified multiple mutations in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ama-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ama-1</ulink></emphasis> gene that resulted in production of <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-amanitin-resistant Pol II (<link linkend="bib49">Rogalski et al., 1988</link><!--: PMID 3197954-->; <link linkend="bib50">Sanford et al., 1983</link><!--: PMID 6630208-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ama-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ama-1</ulink></emphasis> was then shown to encode the Pol II large subunit based upon its similarity to the corresponding <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> gene (<link linkend="bib4">Bird and Riddle, 1989</link><!--: PMID 2586513-->). Subsequently, a <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Pol II <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> transcription system was developed in which transcription is induced appropriately and specifically by promoter-bound activators (<link linkend="bib33">Lichtsteiner and Tjian, 1993</link><!--: PMID 8415761-->; <link linkend="bib34">Lichtsteiner and Tjian, 1995</link><!--: PMID 7664734-->). This system has not become widely used however, most likely because other organisms are still more advantageous for mechanistic studies since their PIC subunits and other basic transcription machinery components have been characterized more extensively at the biochemical level.</para>
<para>More recently, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> protocols have been developed for studying transcription factor functions through chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP; <link linkend="bib12">Chu et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11937488-->; <link linkend="bib44">Oh et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16380712-->; <link linkend="bib76">Whetstine et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15893731-->), a technique that assays for direct binding of proteins to specific DNA sequences within cells, and is used widely in yeast and mammalian cell studies. In ChIP, transcription factors and bound DNA are crosslinked together in intact cells in the context of chromatin, which is sheared after cell lysis. DNA that is bound by the protein of interest is then identified by co-immunoprecipitation and PCR. With this technique, it is possible to test whether a transcription factor of interest binds directly to specific loci in the genome. A very exciting recent study showed that in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ChIP can be used to identify novel sequences bound by a transcription factor, in this case the regulator of Dauer development and longevity <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-16;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-16</ulink> (<link linkend="bib44">Oh et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16380712-->). As a greater number of antibodies and transgenic tools become available, in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> it will be possible to use ChIP not only for an expanded range of investigative experiments, but potentially to identify new targets of any transcription factor of interest.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Global transcriptional repression in the early embryo</title>
<para>Across diverse species, mRNA transcription is globally shut down during oogenesis then reactivated early during embryonic development (<link linkend="bib16">Davidson, 1986</link>). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, this shutdown occurs as oocytes enter the diakinesis stage of meiotic prophase and begin to undergo maturation, as indicated by dramatic reductions in labeled UTP incorporation and <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-PSer5 staining (<link linkend="bib28">Kelly et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11807039-->; <link linkend="bib53">Schisa et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11262230-->). Transcriptional silence is then maintained until the 4-cell stage of embryonic development (<link linkend="bib54">Seydoux and Dunn, 1997</link><!--: PMID 9187145-->). It is not understood in any species how this transcriptional silencing is established, or is later relieved in the embryo. One rationale for having this period of transcription silence is that it may be advantageous for the earliest stages of embryonic development to be orchestrated entirely through post-translational regulation of "stored" maternal gene products, a strategy that may provide the most rapid and versatile means of modulating gene expression spatially and temporally during this critical period. It is also possible that this transcriptional silencing facilitates the transition between maternal and embryonic transcription programs that are very different from each other (<link linkend="bib2">Baugh et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12538516-->).</para>
<para>In the developing embryo, the onset of new transcription is delayed in the germline relative to somatic blastomeres. Analyses of individual genes and phospho-CTD antibody staining indicate that while transcription begins at the 4-cell stage in somatic lineages, transcriptional silence is maintained in embryonic germ cell precursors until they have been segregated from somatic lineages, after the 100-cell stage (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2A, B</link>; <link linkend="bib40">Mello et al., 1992</link><!--: PMID 1623520-->; <link linkend="bib54">Seydoux and Dunn, 1997</link><!--: PMID 9187145-->). This delay depends upon the germline-specific protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PIE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink>, without which germ cell precursors become transcriptionally active in parallel to their zygotic counterparts, and follow somatic differentiation programs (<link linkend="bib56">Seydoux et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8751441-->).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.5in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PIE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> is a zinc finger protein of an RNA-binding class (<link linkend="bib56">Seydoux et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8751441-->), making it a particularly intriguing question how it might repress transcription. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PIE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> regions potently block transcription when they are tethered to promoters in mammalian cells (<link linkend="bib1">Batchelder et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 9925644-->), and its silencing of embryonic germline transcription depends upon its presence in nuclei (<link linkend="bib65">Tenenhaus et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11316796-->). One <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PIE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> region interferes with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CDK-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDK-9</ulink> function and inhibits elongation, dependent upon a motif that resembles an unphosphorylatable CTD repeat and contributes to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PIE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> function <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib1">Batchelder et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 9925644-->; <link linkend="bib79">Zhang et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12651893-->). Interestingly, transcriptionally silent embryonic germ cell precursors lack detectable <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-PSer2 staining, but contain two <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-PSer5 foci that depend upon presence of transcription initiation factors (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2B</link>; <link linkend="bib54">Seydoux and Dunn, 1997</link><!--: PMID 9187145-->; <link linkend="bib58">Shim et al., 2002a</link><!--: PMID 12089139-->; <link linkend="bib71">Walker et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11566890-->). Taken together, this evidence suggests that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PIE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> may block transcription directly at promoters, after some initiation steps have been completed. Consistent with this model, markers associated with an "active" chromatin configuration are comparably present in early embryonic germline and somatic precursors, suggesting that this silencing of germline transcription is not mediated through global chromatin effects (<link linkend="bib52">Schaner et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14602075-->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlinechromatin/germlinechromatin.html">Germline chromatin</ulink>). It is not known how <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PIE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> is brought to individual genes, but a speculative possibility is that its zinc fingers might bind nascent mRNAs. In addition to this transcriptional silencing role <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PIE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> has additional functions that involve translational regulation, and chromatin modification at germline-specific genes (<link linkend="bib65">Tenenhaus et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11316796-->; <link linkend="bib67">Unhavaithaya et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12507426-->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_specgermline/specgermline.html">Specification of the germ line</ulink>). Genetic and site-directed mutagenesis evidence indicates that each of these latter <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PIE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> functions are mediated through different mechanisms from its transcriptional repressor activity however, and therefore that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PIE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> is involved in multiple distinct germline processes.</para>
<para>It may be advantageous for transcription of embryonic genes to be inhibited at a post-initiation step in germline precursors, because this strategy would presumably allow the transcription block to be reversed very quickly. When embryonic germ cell precursors divide, evidence of new transcription is seen rapidly in each somatic daughter (<link linkend="bib54">Seydoux and Dunn, 1997</link><!--: PMID 9187145-->), suggesting that some genes may have been poised for immediate expression. A <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PIE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> ortholog has not been described outside of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, but in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> embryonic germ cell precursors are also transcriptionally silent and similarly contain foci of Ser 5- but not Ser 2-phosphorylated Pol II (<link linkend="bib54">Seydoux and Dunn, 1997</link><!--: PMID 9187145-->). Post-initiation inhibition of some transcription therefore may be a feature of germ cell precursors in various organisms.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Analyses of GTF functions in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
<para>As indicated in <link linkend="sec2">Section 2</link>, the functions of even essential transcription factors can be investigated in the early <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo because of the presence of maternal gene products. For example, conditional inactivation of the CTD kinase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CDK-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDK-7</ulink> (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1B</link>) essentially abolishes transcription and CTD phosphorylation in living embryonic cells, as predicted by biochemical studies (<link linkend="bib73">Wallenfang and Seydoux, 2002</link><!--: PMID 11960010-->). By showing that most of the Ser 5 phosphorylation detected in early embryos is <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cdk-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">cdk-7</ulink></emphasis>-dependent, this experiment indicated that this CTD phosphorylation is associated with transcription activity and does not derive from other kinases that can phosphorylate the CTD, but are not integral to the transcription process (<link linkend="bib39">Meinhart et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15964991-->). Another question that has been addressed is the importance of phosphorylation of CTD Ser 2 by the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PIE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> target <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CDK-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDK-9</ulink> (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1B</link>). <emphasis>In vitro</emphasis> and cell culture studies had identified <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CDK-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDK-9</ulink> as an enhancer of elongation, particularly during HIV transcription, and had showed that it preferentially phosphorylates CTD Ser 2 (<link linkend="bib48">Price, 2000</link><!--: PMID 10733565-->). Ser 2 can be phosphorylated by other kinases however, and in yeast the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CDK-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDK-9</ulink> counterpart is not essential for viability, raising the question of whether <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CDK-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDK-9</ulink> is needed for most metazoan transcription events. <emphasis>cdk-9(RNAi)</emphasis> embryos are characterized by robust Ser 5 phosphorylation but undetectable Ser 2 phosphorylation, and an apparent absence of new gene expression, indicating that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CDK-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDK-9</ulink> is the major Ser 2 kinase and is needed for most if not all early embryonic transcription (<link linkend="bib59">Shim et al., 2002b</link><!--: PMID 12183367-->). RNAi knockdown of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> mRNA capping enzyme resulted in a similar phenotype, supporting the idea that this mRNA processing event represents an intermediate step between Ser 5 phosphorylation, and Ser 2 phosphorylation and elongation (<link linkend="bib63">Takagi et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12576476-->; <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1B</link>).</para>
<para>Other embryo studies have studied the core promoter recognition factor TFIID (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1A</link>), which includes TBP and a set of TFIID-associated factors (TAF<subscript>II</subscript>s; <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>; <link linkend="bib66">Tora, 2002</link><!--: PMID 11963920-->). Many TAF<subscript>II</subscript>s are also found in alternative complexes that bind mRNA start sites (<link linkend="bib66">Tora, 2002</link><!--: PMID 11963920-->). While TBP is generally required for mRNA transcription, most TAF<subscript>II</subscript>s have specialized functions that involve interactions with core promoter sequences or other transcription factors. The extent to which individual TAF<subscript>II</subscript>s are required for mRNA transcription, as indicated by genetic studies in yeast, has remained controversial (see (<link linkend="bib72">Walker et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14726532-->)). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> a TFIID-specific TAF<subscript>II</subscript> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TAF-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">TAF-1</ulink>) is required at most embryonic genes (<link linkend="bib72">Walker et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14726532-->), in contrast to evidence from yeast that an alternative core promoter complex can substitute at many genes (<link linkend="bib26">Huisinga and Pugh, 2004</link><!--: PMID 14992726-->). This predicts that core promoter elements that interact with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TAF-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">TAF-1</ulink> may be critical at most <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryonic genes. One group of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> TAF<subscript>II</subscript>s (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TAF-5;class=Protein" role="_blank">TAF-5</ulink>, -9, -10) is required broadly for embryonic transcription but is dispensible at most genes that are specific to metazoa, suggesting that the latter genes have diverged in their regulation (<link linkend="bib70">Walker and Blackwell, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12458202-->; <link linkend="bib71">Walker et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11566890-->). In each case, after <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> core promoter elements have been better characterized, it should be possible to understand why these TAF<subscript>II</subscript>s are required for expression of some genes but not others. Surprisingly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TAF-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">TAF-4</ulink> is needed for essentially all early embryonic transcription, making it particularly interesting to elucidate its mechanistic function (<link linkend="bib71">Walker et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11566890-->). Interestingly, the <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-PSer5 and <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>-PSer2 staining patterns of <emphasis>taf-4(RNAi)</emphasis> somatic embryonic cells appear identical to those normally seen in embryonic germ cell precursors (see <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2B</link>; <link linkend="bib71">Walker et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11566890-->), suggesting parallels between how transcription is blocked by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=PIE-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> (<link linkend="sec3">Section 3</link>) and lack of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TAF-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">TAF-4</ulink>. A speculative model is that in each case transcription has been stalled prior to Ser 2 phosphorylation, and that the Ser 5-phosphorylated Pol II that is generated is recycled within the two characteristic foci (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2B</link>).</para>
<para>Given that TFIID and TBP are broadly essential for mRNA transcription, it is intriguing that in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> most early embryonic transcription requires the TBP-related protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TLF-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">TLF-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib15">Dantonel et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 11030350-->; <link linkend="bib27">Kaltenbach et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 11030349-->). Studies in other organisms indicate that TLF does not associate with TAF<subscript>II</subscript>s, or form a TFIID-like complex (<link linkend="bib11">Chong et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15767669-->; <link linkend="bib25">Hochheimer et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12459787-->). TLF is important for some early embryonic transcription in <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis> and Zebrafish but not in mice (<link linkend="bib38">Martianov et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11463376-->; <link linkend="bib42">Muller et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11250159-->; <link linkend="bib68">Veenstra et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 11125147-->), in which it is required specifically for chromatin reorganization during spermatogenesis (<link linkend="bib37">Martianov et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11861477-->). One possible model is that TLF might influence chromatin organization during early stages in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo, when gene expression patterns are changing rapidly (<link linkend="bib2">Baugh et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12538516-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>The many faces of Mediator</title>
<para>Among the various components of the Pol II PIC (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1A</link>), Mediator appears to be the most important integrator of regulatory signals from upstream activators that define specific patterns of gene expression (<link linkend="bib24">Green, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15893723-->; <link linkend="bib29">Kornberg, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15896740-->). Biochemical and genetic studies indicate that the basic features of Mediator are conserved across species, and that Mediator projects many regulatory surfaces that interact with gene-specific activators or repressors (<link linkend="bib5">Bjorklund and Gustafsson, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15896741-->; <link linkend="bib24">Green, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15893723-->; <link linkend="bib36">Malik and Roeder, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15896744-->; <link linkend="bib74">Wang et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15749018-->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> orthologs of 24 of the 33 mammalian Mediator subunits have been identified, primarily through sequence similarities (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>; <link linkend="bib6">Bourbon et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15175151-->; <link linkend="bib31">Kwon et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10611325-->; <link linkend="bib78">Yoda et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15790964-->). The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Mediator complex(es) have not been thoroughly characterized biochemically, but some <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Mediator proteins have been shown to co-fractionate or co-immunoprecipitate with each other (<link linkend="bib31">Kwon et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10611325-->). Mediator subunits have recently been designated as MED proteins in other species, and MDT (MeDiaTor) proteins in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib6">Bourbon et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15175151-->). Here I refer to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Mediator subunits primarily by their original designations, referencing the unified nomenclature in parentheses. Some <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Mediator subunits have pleiotropic functions (<link linkend="bib30">Kwon and Lee, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11688559-->; <link linkend="bib31">Kwon et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10611325-->). For example, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=RGR-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">RGR-1</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-14;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-14</ulink>) appears to be needed for essentially all early embryonic transcription (<link linkend="bib58">Shim et al., 2002a</link><!--: PMID 12089139-->). Significantly however, mutations recovered in genetic screens and protein-protein interaction studies have implicated other Mediator subunits as being central for particular conserved transcription pathways.</para>
<para>Studies of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> MED23 represent a particularly elegant synergy of genetic and biochemical approaches. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> MED23 was initially identified as the novel protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SUR-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUR-2</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-23;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-23</ulink>), through a screen for the <emphasis role="underline">Su</emphasis>ppression of the <emphasis role="underline">R</emphasis>as gain-of-function allele <emphasis>let-60(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=n1046;class=Variation" role="_blank">n1046</ulink>)</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib60">Singh and Han, 1995</link><!--: PMID 7557379-->). Genetic evidence indicated that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sur-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">sur-2</ulink></emphasis> functions downstream of the Ras/Mitogen Activated Protein Kinase (MAPK) signaling pathway that induces the vulval cell fate, and may act at the level of the ETS transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LIN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-1</ulink>, which is regulated by this signaling pathway. The molecular function of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SUR-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUR-2</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-23;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-23</ulink>) remained a mystery however, until this protein was identified in a mammalian biochemical study as a Mediator component (<link linkend="bib7">Boyer et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10353252-->). Mammalian <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SUR-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUR-2</ulink> was then found to be a direct target through which the adenovirus protein E1A recruits Mediator in order to activate transcription of adenovirus genes. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genetics and mammalian biochemistry thus together suggested an exciting model, that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SUR-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUR-2</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-23;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-23</ulink>) might be a specific conduit through which Ras/MAPK-responsive transcription factors communicate with the general transcription machinery. Supporting this idea, mammalian MED23 was found to be required for MAPK-induced transcription, and to be targeted directly by a mammalian Ras/MAPK-activated ETS transcription factor, but not by most other activators (<link linkend="bib7">Boyer et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10353252-->; <link linkend="bib62">Stevens et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11934987-->).</para>
<para>The complexity and specificity of Mediator functions is illustrated further by analyses of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DPY-22;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-22</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-12</ulink>) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LET-19;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-19</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-13;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-13</ulink>). Structural analyses in other systems have shown that these proteins are present in a Mediator submodule that is thought to have mostly inhibitory functions (<link linkend="bib5">Bjorklund and Gustafsson, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15896741-->; <link linkend="bib36">Malik and Roeder, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15896744-->). Accordingly, genetic studies indicate that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DPY-22;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-22</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-12</ulink>) acts antagonistically to Ras signaling during vulval development (<link linkend="bib41">Moghal and Sternberg, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12441291-->), and that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DPY-22;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-22</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-12</ulink>) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LET-19;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-19</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-13;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-13</ulink>) inhibit Wnt-induced gene expression in multiple contexts, supporting the idea that they function together (<link linkend="bib75">Wang et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15073178-->; <link linkend="bib78">Yoda et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15790964-->; <link linkend="bib80">Zhang and Emmons, 2000</link><!--: PMID 10970880-->). The <emphasis>C. elegans MED1</emphasis> ortholog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sop-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">sop-3</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-1.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-1.1</ulink>)</emphasis> has similar genetic properties (<link linkend="bib81">Zhang and Emmons, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11171401-->). This suggests that MED1 may interact functionally with MED12 and MED13 even though it is not in the same Mediator submodule, or may communicate directly with the same regulatory factors. A strong RNAi knockdown of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LET-19;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-19</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-13;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-13</ulink>) prevents expression of some early embryonic genes however, suggesting that this Mediator subunit also has some positive functions (<link linkend="bib75">Wang et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15073178-->). By identifying specific transcription pathways in which <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DPY-22;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-22</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-12</ulink>) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LET-19;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-19</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-13;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-13</ulink>) are important, these studies have made it of particular interest to determine whether the corresponding transcription activators, co-factors, or repressors target these Mediator subunits directly, as is the case for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SUR-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUR-2</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-23;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-23</ulink>).</para>
<para>Two exciting recent studies have further demonstrated the importance of Mediator for coordinating regulation of gene networks, and have shown the value of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> for uncovering regulatory mechanisms that are of direct relevance to human health. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Mediator subunit <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-15;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-15</ulink> (MED15 in mammals) has been identified as a direct target of two transcription factors, the nuclear receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NHR-49;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-49</ulink> and the sterol regulatory element binding protein (SREBP) (<link linkend="bib64">Taubert et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16651656-->; <link linkend="bib77">Yang et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16799563-->). Two-hybrid screening indicated that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-15;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-15</ulink> binds specifically to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NHR-49;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-49</ulink>, which functionally resembles human Peroxisome Proliferator-Activated Receptor-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol>, a regulator of lipid metabolism that is an important target of therapy in diabetes (<link linkend="bib64">Taubert et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16651656-->). It was then determined that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink></emphasis> is required for expression of NHR-49-dependent genes, along with many other lipid metabolism genes. Similar results were obtained in a study of the transcription factor SREBP, a key regulator of cholesterol and lipid homeostasis (<link linkend="bib77">Yang et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16799563-->). It was shown that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-15;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-15</ulink>/MED15 interacts directly and specifically with SREBP, and is required for SREBP-driven transcription in human cells and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, RNAi knockdown of either <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink></emphasis> (<emphasis>SREBP</emphasis>) perturbed fat storage, and resulted in alterations in the levels of specific lipids that were consistent with the accompanying abnormalities in lipid metabolism gene expression (<link linkend="bib64">Taubert et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16651656-->; <link linkend="bib77">Yang et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16799563-->). Remarkably, phenotypes associated with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink></emphasis> RNAi (decreased lifespan and fertility, locomotion impairment, abnormal fat storage) were then partially rescued by dietary supplementation with specific fatty acids. Together, these studies showed that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-15;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-15</ulink>/MED15 integrates specific transcription pathways that regulate lipid and cholesterol homeostasis and that this MED15 function is conserved, a finding that may lead to a more comprehensive understanding of how lipid metabolism is regulated coordinately in humans. Through its interactions with SREBP and nuclear receptors, MED15 may therefore be involved in metabolic abnormalities that include obesity, atherosclerosis, diabetes, and metabolic syndrome.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Chromatin regulation, an emerging field in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
<para>As recently as fifteen years ago, it was thought that they key to understanding transcription regulation lay almost entirely in understanding how activators and repressors acted on the general transcription machinery, but since then it has become apparent that chromatin is a central mechanistic player in the regulation of many if not most eukaryotic genes. The field of chromatin regulation in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has expanded rapidly during recent years, in part through reverse genetic studies of the functions of specific chromatin regulators, but also because protein complexes that modify chromatin structure have appeared in mutagenesis or RNAi screens that involve specific biological processes. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> chromatin modifications are needed to establish some broad transcription programs, particularly with respect to discriminating between germline and somatic gene expression patterns (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlinechromatin/germlinechromatin.html">Germline chromatin</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_specgermline/specgermline.html">Specification of the germ line</ulink>). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> chromatin modification complexes have also been implicated in regulation of a variety of specific biological functions or gene networks, however. This field is now much too broad to be covered comprehensively within the context of this chapter, but here we will describe some specific examples of how interactions among chromatin modifiers play critical roles in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> transcription regulation and development.</para>
<para>The transcription regulators <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CBP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CBP-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HDA-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">HDA-1</ulink> provide an instructive example of how interactions among chromatin modification factors are important for specific biological processes during the life cycle. Acetylation and deacetylation of histone N-terminal tails is usually associated with increased or decreased transcription, respectively (<link linkend="bib45">Orphanides and Reinberg, 2002</link><!--: PMID 11909516-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CBP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CBP-1</ulink> is a conserved histone acetyl transferase (HAT) that in mammals often responds to extracellular signals, and is recruited to genes by upstream activators (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1A</link>; <link linkend="bib10">Chan and La Thangue, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11559745-->). In the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CBP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CBP-1</ulink> is required for differentiation of essentially all cell types except neurons (<link linkend="bib57">Shi and Mello, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9531533-->). Only a minority proportion of embryonic genes depend upon <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cbp-1</ulink></emphasis> for their expression however (<link linkend="bib72">Walker et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14726532-->), presumably because these genes are otherwise repressed through specific chromatin modifications that are counterracted by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CBP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CBP-1</ulink>. For example, the embryonic endoderm specification gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=end-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">end-1</ulink></emphasis> requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CBP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CBP-1</ulink> in order to overcome repression by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HDA-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">HDA-1</ulink>, a histone deacetylase that is recruited by gene-specific repressors (<link linkend="bib9">Calvo et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11742996-->). Inhibition of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=hda-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">hda-1</ulink></emphasis> expression by RNAi allows <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=end-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">end-1</ulink></emphasis> to be expressed independently of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CBP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CBP-1</ulink>, and endodermal cells to be formed independently of either <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CBP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CBP-1</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SKN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SKN-1</ulink>, the transcription factor that initiates endoderm specification in the embryo (<link linkend="bib9">Calvo et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11742996-->; <link linkend="bib57">Shi and Mello, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9531533-->). Like <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CBP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CBP-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HDA-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">HDA-1</ulink> appears to regulate only a limited number of embryonic genes, but usually as a repressor (<link linkend="bib76">Whetstine et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15893731-->). Microarray and ChIP experiments have shown that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HDA-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">HDA-1</ulink> directly inhibits many extracellular matrix genes, a function that is conserved in mammals (<link linkend="bib76">Whetstine et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15893731-->). These <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> studies have thus begun to identify gene regulatory networks that are controlled through particular modifications of histones or other transcription factors, and may have been broadly conserved during evolution.</para>
<para>Much remains to be learned about the functions of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CBP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CBP-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HDA-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">HDA-1</ulink>, but it is clear that they are involved in additional biological and regulatory pathways of major importance. While the above processes appear to involve maternally-provided <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CBP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CBP-1</ulink>, impairment of zygotically-derived <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CBP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CBP-1</ulink> results in embryonic arrest at the beginning of morphogenesis, indicating that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CBP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CBP-1</ulink> is needed for additional developmental processes (<link linkend="bib69">Victor et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11751575-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HDA-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">HDA-1</ulink> has been implicated in additional functions that include vulval development and suppression of inappropriate germline gene expression (<link linkend="bib18">Dufourcq et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11940660-->; <link linkend="bib67">Unhavaithaya et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12507426-->). These <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HDA-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">HDA-1</ulink> functions involve a genetic pathway (SynMuvB) that negatively regulates specification of the vulval cell fate, and includes other conserved chromatin modification factors along with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LIN-35;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-35</ulink>, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog of the retinoblastoma tumor suppressor protein (<link linkend="bib22">Fay and Han, 2000</link><!--: PMID 10748467-->; <link linkend="bib35">Lu and Horvitz, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9875852-->). Genetic and RNAi screening has identified a surprisingly intricate network of additional chromatin modifiers and other regulatory factors that function either to cooperate with or oppose the action of SynMuv pathway components in vulval fate specification (<link linkend="bib14">Cui et al., 2006b</link><!--: PMID 16710447-->; <link linkend="bib46">Poulin et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15990876-->). Further illustrating the complexity of these functional interactions, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CBP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CBP-1</ulink> appears to antagonize vulval fate specification by a mechanism that is independent of the SynMuv pathway (<link linkend="bib20">Eastburn and Han, 2005</link><!--: PMID 16227593-->). Recent work indicates that the SynMuv pathway may function by repressing hypodermal expression of the Epidermal Growth Factor-related protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=LIN-3;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink>, which drives the RAS/MAPK signal that induces vulval cell fate (<link linkend="bib13">Cui et al., 2006a</link><!--: PMID 16678779-->). This last finding may eventually provide an entry point for mechanistic analyses of how particular chromatin modifiers interact functionally with other transcription factors to regulate expression of this key developmental gene. These studies of how chromatin modification machines regulate vulval cell fate illustrate the power of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genetics for discovering functional relationships that can be interpreted in the light of known biochemical functions, and can lead to new insights into regulation of specific biological processes <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<para>Development of an organism depends upon finely-tuned and accurate control of mRNA transcription. Recent studies have identified various biological processes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> that involve direct regulation or specific functions of general transcription machinery components such as Mediator, or transcription co-factors that function in multiple discrete contexts, such as chromatin modification proteins. The list of these processes will continue to grow, as future studies identify additional examples of direct communications between regulatory and general transcription factors, and reveal how promoter groups and gene networks are regulated coordinately through these interactions. Further analyses of these regulatory mechanisms in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> should continue to provide broadly applicable information about their conserved functions <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>, and new insights into the specific biological processes in which they are involved.</para>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="100%">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1.</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">genes that encode major GTFs.</emphasis> These factors are listed according to their names as defined in biochemical or yeast genetic studies, except for TAF<subscript>II</subscript>s and Mediator subunits, for which unified nomenclatures have been agreed upon (<link linkend="bib43">Tora, 2004</link><!--: PMID 14685269-->; <link linkend="bib6">Bourbon et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15175151-->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> TAF<subscript>II</subscript>s were previously named according to an earlier nomenclature (<link linkend="bib71">Walker et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11566890-->). Each of these <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes was identified as the indicated GTF through homology searches performed either in published studies (Worm Base) or by the authors. Blanks in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> column indicate factors for which no ortholog has yet been identified.</title>
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colname="c1" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c2" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c3" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c4" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c5" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Complex</entry>
<entry>Name</entry>
<entry>Former name</entry>
<entry><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> gene</entry>
<entry>ORF</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>RNA Pol II</entry>
<entry>Rpb1</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ama-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ama-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F36A4.7;class=Gene" role="_blank">F36A4.7</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Rpb2</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rpb-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">rpb-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C26E6.4;class=Gene" role="_blank">C26E6.4</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Rpb3</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C36B1.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">C36B1.3</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Rpb4</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F43E2.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">F43E2.2</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Rpb5</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=H27M09.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">H27M09.2</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Rpb6</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C06A1.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">C06A1.5</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Rpb7</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y54E10BR.6;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y54E10BR.6</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Rpb8</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F26F4.11;class=Gene" role="_blank">F26F4.11</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Rpb9</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y97E10AR.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y97E10AR.5</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Rpb10</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y37E3.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y37E3.3</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Rpb11</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=W01G7.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">W01G7.3</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Rpb12</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F23B2.13;class=Gene" role="_blank">F23B2.13</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>TFIIA</entry>
<entry>alpha/beta subunit</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=pqn-51;class=Gene" role="_blank">pqn-51</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=K11D12.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">K11D12.2</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>TFIIA</entry>
<entry>gamma subunit</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y111B2A.13;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y111B2A.13</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>TFIIB</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ttb-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ttb-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=W03F9.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">W03F9.5</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>TFIID</entry>
<entry>TBP</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tbp-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T20B12.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">T20B12.2</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF1</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=W04A8.7;class=Gene" role="_blank">W04A8.7</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF 2</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y37E11B.4;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y37E11B.4</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF 3</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C11G6.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">C11G6.1</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF 4</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-5</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=R119.6;class=Gene" role="_blank">R119.6</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF 5</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-5</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F30F8.8;class=Gene" role="_blank">F30F8.8</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF 6</entry>
<entry><emphasis>taf-3.1</emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-6.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-6.1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=W09B6.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">W09B6.2</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF 6L</entry>
<entry><emphasis>taf-3.2</emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis>taf-6.2</emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y37E11AL.8;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y37E11AL.8</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF 7</entry>
<entry><emphasis>taf-8.1</emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-7.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-7.1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F54F7.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">F54F7.1</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF 7L</entry>
<entry><emphasis>taf-8.2</emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-7.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-7.2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y111B2A.16;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y111B2A.16</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF 8</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-8</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>ZK1320.12</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF 9</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-10;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-10</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-9</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T12D8.7;class=Gene" role="_blank">T12D8.7</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF 10</entry>
<entry><emphasis>taf-11</emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-10;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-10</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>K03B4.3</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF 11</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-7.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-7.1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-11.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-11.1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F48D6.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">F48D6.1</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF 11L</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-7.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-7.2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-11.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-11.2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=K10D3.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">K10D3.3</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF12</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-9</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-12</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y56A3A.4;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y56A3A.4</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF13</entry>
<entry><emphasis>taf-6</emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=taf-13;class=Gene" role="_blank">taf-13</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C14A4.10;class=Gene" role="_blank">C14A4.10</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF14</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>TAF15</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry>TFIIE</entry>
<entry>alpha subunit</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F54D5.11;class=Gene" role="_blank">F54D5.11</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>beta subunit</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry>TFIIF</entry>
<entry>large subunit</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C01F1.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">C01F1.1</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>TFIIF</entry>
<entry>small subunit</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y39B6A.36;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y39B6A.36</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>TFIIH</entry>
<entry>XPB</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y66D12A.15;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y66D12A.15</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>XPD</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y50D7A.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y50D7A.2</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>p62</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=R02D3.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">R02D3.3</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>p52</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>p44</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry>T16h12.4</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>p34</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ZK1128.4;class=Gene" role="_blank">ZK1128.4</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>CDK7</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cdk-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">cdk-7</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y39G10AL.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y39G10AL.3</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>CyclinH</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cyh-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cyh-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y49F6B.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y49F6B.1</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MAT1</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mnat-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">mnat-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>F53g2.7</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Mediator</entry>
<entry>MED1</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sop-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">sop-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-1.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-1.1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>Y71F9B.10</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-1.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-1.2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T23C6.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">T23C6.1</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED2</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED3</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED4</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ZK546.13;class=Gene" role="_blank">ZK546.13</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED5</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED6</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-425;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-425</ulink>/med-6</emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-6</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y57E12AL.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y57E12AL.5</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED7</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-49</ulink>/med-7</emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis>mdt-7</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Y54E5B.3</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED8</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-8</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y62F5A.1b;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y62F5A.1b</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED9</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED10</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-10;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-10</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T09A5.6;class=Gene" role="_blank">T09A5.6</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED11</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-11;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-11</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=R144.9;class=Gene" role="_blank">R144.9</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED12</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=dpy-22;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-22</ulink>/sop-1</emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-12</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F47A4.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">F47A4.2</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED13</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-19</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-13;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-13</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=K08F8.6;class=Gene" role="_blank">K08F8.6</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED14</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=rgr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">rgr-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-14;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-14</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>C38C10.5</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED15</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=R12B2.5b;class=Gene" role="_blank">R12B2.5b</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED16</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED17</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-17;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-17</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y113G7B.18;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y113G7B.18</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED18</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-18;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-18</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C55B7.9;class=Gene" role="_blank">C55B7.9</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED19</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-19;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-19</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y71H2B.6;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y71H2B.6</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED20</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-20;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-20</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=Y104H12D.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">Y104H12D.1</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED21</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-21;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-21</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C24H11.9;class=Gene" role="_blank">C24H11.9</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED22</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-22;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-22</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ZK970.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">ZK970.3</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED23</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sur-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">sur-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-23;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-23</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>F39B2.4</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED24</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED25</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED26</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED27</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-27;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-27</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T18H9.6;class=Gene" role="_blank">T18H9.6</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED28</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-28;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-28</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>W01A8.1</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED29</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-29;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-29</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=K08E3.8;class=Gene" role="_blank">K08E3.8</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED30</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>MED31</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-31;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-31</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F32H2.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">F32H2.2</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>CDK8</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cdk-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">cdk-8</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F39H11.3;class=Gene" role="_blank">F39H11.3</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>CycC</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cic-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cic-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=H14E04.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">H14E04.5</ulink></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>PTEFb</entry>
<entry>CycT</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cit-1.1;class=Gene" role="_blank">cit-1.1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>F44B9.4</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cit-1.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">cit-1.2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>F44B9.3</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>CDK9</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=cdk-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">cdk-9</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>H25P06.2</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Other</entry>
<entry>TLF</entry>
<entry/>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tlf-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tlf-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F39H11.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">F39H11.2</ulink></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>This work was supported by a grant from the National Institute of General Medical Sciences (GM63826).</para>
</sect1>
<?newpage?>
<sect1 id="sec9">
<title>References</title>
&transmech_Refs;
<para/>
</sect1>
</article>