<caption>
	<formalpara>
		<title>Figure 1. Transcription regulatory complexes.</title>
		<para>(A) Partial view of the Pol II pre-initiation complex (<link linkend="bib45">Orphanides and Reinberg, 2002</link><!--: PMID 11909516-->), subunits of which include Mediator and a set of GTFs (TFIIA, TFIIB, TFIID, TFIIE, TFIIH, and others; <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). Most pre-initiation complex factors, including Pol II, consist of multiple subunits. Interactions between pre-initiation complex subunits and core promoter elements localize formation of the pre-initiation complex, which in turn sets the transcription start site (arrow). Pre-initiation complex formation is driven by recruitment of pre-initiation complex components through interactions with DNA-binding activators (see Transcription regulation), which at some genes also recruit chromatin-modifying co-factors such as the HAT <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CBP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">CBP-1</ulink> (see text). (B) The Pol II CTD phosphorylation cycle (<link linkend="bib3">Bentley, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15901493-->; <link linkend="bib8">Buratowski, 2005</link><!--: PMID 15901494-->; <link linkend="bib45">Orphanides and Reinberg, 2002</link><!--: PMID 11909516-->). After Pol II has been recruited into a pre-initiation complex, the CTD repeat is phosphorylated on Ser 5 by the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CDK-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDK-7</ulink> subunit of the GTF TFIIH. This phosphorylation is required for Pol II to transcribe beyond the immediate promoter region (clearance), and for recruitment of the mRNA capping enzyme. Subsequently, phosphorylation of CTD Ser 2 by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CDK-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDK-9</ulink> facilitates elongation and is required for mRNA termination, cleavage, and processing (not shown). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=CDK-9;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDK-9</ulink> is a subunit of the GTF P-TEFb (positive transcription elongation factor b, <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>).</para>
	</formalpara>
</caption>