<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'memiontransport_fig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'memiontransport_fig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'memiontransport_fig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'memiontransport_fig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY movie1 SYSTEM 'memiontransport_movie1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY movie2 SYSTEM 'memiontransport_movie2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'memiontransport_fig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'memiontransport_fig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'memiontransport_fig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'memiontransport_fig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY movie1legend SYSTEM 'memiontransport_movie1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY movie2legend SYSTEM 'memiontransport_movie2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY memiontransport_ref SYSTEM 'memiontransport_ref.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="memiontransport">
<articleinfo>
<title>Membrane ion transport in non-excitable tissues<footnote><para>Edited by: Michel Labousse and Donald G. Moerman. Last Revised 6/30/2014. Published December 23, 2014. This chapter should be cited as: Nehrke K. Membrane ion transport in non-excitable tissues (December 23, 2014), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.174.2, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2014 Keith Nehrke. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para></footnote></title>
<author><othername>Keith Nehrke<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:keith_nehrke@urmc.rochester.edu">keith_nehrke@urmc.rochester.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></othername>
<affiliation><orgname>Departments of Medicine (Nephrology Division) and Pharmacology and Physiology, University of Rochester Medical Center, Rochester NY 14642, USA</orgname></affiliation>
</author></articleinfo>
<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">The facilitated movement of ions across cell membranes can be characterized as occurring through active (ATP-dependent), secondary active (coupled), or passive transport processes. Each of these processes is mediated by a diverse group of membrane proteins. Over the past fifteen years, studies of membrane transport in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have benefited from the fact that worms are anatomically simple, easily and economically cultured, and genetically tractable. These experimental advantages have been instrumental in defining how membrane transport processes contribute to whole organism physiology. The focus of this review is to survey the recent advances in our understanding of membrane transport that have arisen from integrative physiological approaches in the nematode <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>The ability to form and maintain membrane electrochemical gradients is fundamental to life. Electrochemical gradients are created by the regulated distribution of ions by membrane transport proteins that function as molecular gatekeepers to move electrolytes and solutes across lipid bilayers. These proteins are generally classified into three categories: active, secondary active, and passive transporters. Active transporter function is coupled directly to ATP hydrolysis. One of the more well-recognized examples of this class is the Na<superscript>+</superscript>-K<superscript>+</superscript> ATPase, which establishes Na<superscript>+</superscript> and K<superscript>+</superscript> electrochemical gradients across the cell membrane. The movement of Na<superscript>+</superscript> and K<superscript>+</superscript> down their electrochemical gradients can be harnessed by secondary active transporters to energize the movement of other solutes through coupled flux mechanisms against their electrochemical gradients. Unlike transporters that utilize energy directly or through secondary active processes, passive transporters such as ion channels provide a pathway for passive movement of solutes down their electrochemical gradients.</para>
<para>Early studies on membrane transporters measured their activity through biophysical techniques such as patch-clamp electrophysiology and radiolabeled substrate uptake without knowing the identity of the proteins responsible. These approaches were essential for characterizing substrate specificity and protein distribution, and resulted in the identification of a variety of pharmacologic reagents that saw widespread experimental use. Over the course of the &ldquo;molecular revolution&rdquo; many of the genes coding for the underlying transporter proteins were identified. This contributed to a reductionist approach aimed at understanding the function of individual gene products through recombinant expression strategies. Most recently, integrative approaches have focused on the processes through which individual molecular components work together to organize physiologic responses and ultimately to coordinate systemic outputs.</para>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is particularly well suited for defining the integrative biology of membrane transport processes. The worm genome is well defined and powerful forward and reverse genetic tools greatly facilitate the characterization of gene function and the identification of genetic pathways. Development has been well-characterized in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and the animal is anatomically simple, with a limited number of cells of invariant lineage comprising each organ system. In addition, worms exhibit a number of readily observable behaviors that are controlled by membrane transport processes, which provide robust phenotypes to measure in genetic and functional genomic screens.</para>
<para>The apparent simplicity of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> belies a surprising level of conserved physiological sophistication. At their most basic level, membrane ion transporters exhibit a commonality of functions across phyla. This is underscored by the observation that transporter gene families are generally conserved between worms and mammals. While this might be expected for fundamental transporters such as the Na<superscript>+</superscript>-K<superscript>+</superscript> ATPase, it is also true for more specialized families of transporters. For example, there are nine Na<superscript>+</superscript>/H<superscript>+</superscript> exchanger genes in both humans and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Although direct orthology has yet to be established for many of these, both human and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genomes code for paralogs with cell specific expression patterns and others with more global expression. The diversity of transporters in worms, as in mammals, allows them to function in individual tissues, in integrated physiologic processes that require the interaction of multiple organs, and to respond adaptively to environmental pressures.</para>
<para>Despite its many advantages, there are also some disadvantages that must be recognized when choosing to utilize the worm model. Foremost is the difficulty in obtaining access to individual cells in the organism due to what is effectively a pressurized cuticle. This has made traditional electrophysiological approaches difficult, though not impossible (<link linkend="bib39">Goodman et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9581767-->; <link linkend="bib82">Richmond et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10461217-->; <link linkend="bib40">Goodman et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22226532-->). In addition, there are no <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> cell lines available for physiological and molecular studies. Techniques do exist, however, for generating dispersed primary embryonic cells of varying types that are accessible for electrophysiological and imaging approaches (<link linkend="bib20">Christensen et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11856526-->; <link linkend="bib96">Strange et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17446899-->; Culture of embryonic <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> cells for electrophysiological and pharmacological analyses). To some extent, these disadvantages have been circumvented by optogenetic approaches and the use of genetically encoded biosensors (for review, see <link linkend="bib1">Akerboom et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23459413-->). These next generation technologies combined with the optical transparency and small size of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> allow single cell measurements of electrolyte flux in live animals to be combined with optical control of membrane potential and intracellular signaling. Given the existing repertoire of genetic, reverse genetic, and transgenic reagents, these approaches firmly cement <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as a robust model for studying the role of individual membrane transport processes in systems physiology.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Different strokes: the many faces of Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling</title>
<para>Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> is an ubiquitous second messenger whose function as a signaling molecule is specified by spatial and temporal constraints. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, forward and reverse genetic approaches have identified physiologic processes that are linked to Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling, and the transparency of the worm has facilitated in vivo approaches using fluorescent Genetically Encoded Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> Indicator (GECI) proteins to determine how Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> flux is constrained. This section will focus on non-neuronal physiological processes where Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling is fundamental, exploring mechanisms for Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signal initiation, plasma membrane Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> entry, and Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> movement between cells.</para>
<para>Both defecation and fertilization are ultradian rhythmic behaviors that are timed by Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling. Unlike circadian rhythms which occur daily, their periods are on the order of minutes in well-fed animals. These short periods and stereotypical execution are key experimental advantages that have facilitated integrative molecular understanding of the underlying physiological processes. An additional advantage is that both defecation and fertilization are relatively simple behaviors that require the action of just several cells, with Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling required to maintain behavioral fidelity through both cell autonomous and non-autonomous mechanisms.</para>
<sect2 id="sec2-1">
<title>Oscillatory Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling during defecation</title>
<para>The defecation motor program (DMP) occurs with a period of ~ 50s (<link linkend="bib104">Thomas, 1990</link><!--: PMID 2323555-->) and consists of three stereotypical, visible outputs termed the posterior body contraction (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0001641;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">pBoc</ulink>), anterior body contraction (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000204;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">aBoc</ulink>) and expulsion (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>; <link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link>) (For review see <link linkend="bib8">Branicky et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16911844-->). When worms are well-fed, the DMP occurs with little variation (<link linkend="bib104">Thomas, 1990</link><!--: PMID 2323555-->). This basal rhythmicity, coupled with an ability to be entrained by external stimuli and insensitivity to temperature (<link linkend="bib61">Liu et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID 8158250-->), matches the requirements for a &ldquo;biological clock&rdquo;. Seminal work from the Jorgenson laboratory showed that mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002173;class=Gene" role="_blank">itr-1</ulink></emphasis>, which codes for the sole worm inositol 1, 4, 5-trisphosphate receptor (IP3R), slow down or eliminate the cycle (<link linkend="bib25">Dal Santo et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10499793-->). The IP3R is an endoplasmic reticulum (ER) Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> release channel, and overexpression of the IP3R specifically in the intestine caused the cycle to speed up (<link linkend="bib25">Dal Santo et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10499793-->). This observation was consistent with the finding that DMP rhythmicity was controlled independent of specific neuronal input. Based upon these data, cell-autonomous IP3 dependent Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling was proposed to be the molecular pacemaker for defecation.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<mediaobject id="movie1" xreflabel="Movie 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="movie1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>movie 1</phrase>
</textobject> &movie1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Subsequently, it has been discovered that a wave of Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> initiates in the posterior intestinal cells and propagates forward through the intestine concomitant with execution of the DMP (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>; <link linkend="movie2">Movie 2</link>); several parallel approaches that utilized isolated intact intestinal preparations loaded with Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> sensitive dyes or live worms expressing fluorescent GECIs combined with dynamic imaging techniques have corroborated this finding (<link linkend="bib30">Espelt et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16186564-->; <link linkend="bib72">Norman et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16213217-->; <link linkend="bib101">Teramoto et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16780946-->; <link linkend="bib76">Peters et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17825560-->; <link linkend="bib70">Nehrke et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 17942636-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28765;class=Protein" role="_blank">INX-16</ulink>, an innexin gap junction protein, facilitates the propagation of the Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> wave between individual cells of the intestine (<link linkend="bib76">Peters et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17825560-->; <link linkend="bib23">Coburn et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23935448-->). Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> wave dynamics couple the sequential motor steps of the DMP (<link linkend="bib101">Teramoto et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16780946-->), and Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling in the anterior intestinal cells has been suggested to regulate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000204;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">aBoc</ulink> timing independent of the basal pacemaker (<link linkend="bib70">Nehrke et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 17942636-->; <link linkend="bib110">Wang et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23583549-->). Hence, Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> oscillations in the posterior intestinal int9 cell are the pacemaker that defines the DMP period and the speed of Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> wave propagation is likely the defining factor that controls temporal coupling between the first and second motor steps.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<mediaobject id="movie2" xreflabel="Movie 2">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="movie2" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>movie 2</phrase>
</textobject> &movie2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>The supremacy of the posterior-most intestinal cell int9 as the pacemaker cell was recently shown to require an miRNA that regulates fatty acid biosynthesis (<link linkend="bib50">Kemp et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23141108-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00045343;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-786</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in int9, and a defect in timing and execution of the DMP was shown to result from aberrant Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> wave initiation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003334;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-240</ulink>/786</emphasis> mutant worms (<link linkend="bib50">Kemp et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23141108-->). This defect resulted from a loss of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00045343;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-786</ulink></emphasis> suppression of the fatty acid elongase <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001240;class=Gene" role="_blank">elo-2</ulink></emphasis>, and palmitate supplementation was sufficient to suppress the long arrhythmic defecation cycles in the mutants (<link linkend="bib50">Kemp et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23141108-->). The current model suggests that the fatty acid composition in int9 sensitizes this cell such that its oscillatory period is slightly faster than other cells in the intestine, and perhaps the Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signal is stronger, though this has not been tested directly. Since Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> regulates the IP3R through feedback inhibition, normal Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> wave propagation through the intestine would be expected to suppress independent oscillations in Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> that might occur in other cells. Since <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00045343;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-786</ulink></emphasis> acts upstream of the IP3R, which is the central molecular pacemaker for defecation, it is possible that fatty acids directly influence the IP3R&apos;s activity (<link linkend="bib50">Kemp et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23141108-->). Together, these results suggest that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00045343;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-786</ulink></emphasis> is an amplifier of Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling. Since <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00045343;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-786</ulink></emphasis> is expressed from a gene cluster including <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003334;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-240</ulink></emphasis> and both of these genes as well as their positioning are conserved in mammals (where they are termed, &ldquo;miR-193b-365&rdquo;), it will be interesting to see whether the same holds true in higher level eukaryotes.</para>
<para>There are two potential types of ion transport mechanisms that could facilitate plasma membrane Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> entry to support intestinal Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> wave propagation and electrophysiological approaches using a primary culture system (<link linkend="bib20">Christensen et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11856526-->) for functional analysis of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestinal epithelial cells have revealed that both of these exist: store-independent and store-operated Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> entry (SOCE) pathways (<link linkend="bib31">Estevez et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12860924-->). &ldquo;Store-operated&rdquo; refers to the regulatory process through which plasma membrane Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> entry is coupled to ER Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> depletion. IP3R and ER Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> stores are central to the defecation pacemaker (<link linkend="bib25">Dal Santo et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10499793-->). IP3R opening results in Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> depletion from the ER, which can lead to the activation of SOCE pathways into the cell. Over the past several years, the molecular identities of the channels responsible for canonical SOCE and their mechanism of regulation have been discovered. Stim1 is an EF-hand Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> binding protein that resides in the ER and senses store depletion (<link linkend="bib84">Roos et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15866891-->; <link linkend="bib120">Zhang et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16208375-->) while Orai1 is an essential pore-forming subunit whose opening is regulated by Stim1 (<link linkend="bib79">Prakriya et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16921383-->; <link linkend="bib118">Yeromin et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16921385-->). The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021910;class=Gene" role="_blank">stim-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015648;class=Gene" role="_blank">orai-1</ulink></emphasis> gene products are expressed in tissues where regular Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> oscillations occur, such as the pharynx, spermatheca, and intestinal cells (<link linkend="bib98">Strange et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17376526-->). Patch-clamp electrophysiological recordings of co-expressed <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021910;class=Gene" role="_blank">stim-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015648;class=Gene" role="_blank">orai-1</ulink></emphasis> cDNAs recapitulate the biophysical transport properties of native SOCE currents (<link linkend="bib62">Lorin-Nebel et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17218360-->). However, neither <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015648;class=Gene" role="_blank">orai-1</ulink></emphasis> nor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021910;class=Gene" role="_blank">stim-1</ulink></emphasis> appears to play a role in defecation. Their loss compromises the ability to maintain homeostasis under conditions of ER stress, suggesting that they are functional, but has no effect on the DMP behavior or oscillatory Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling in the intestine (<link linkend="bib117">Yan et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16966474-->). So how do intestinal epithelial cells in worms take up Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> during the DMP?</para>
<para>An alternative to OraiI/Stim1 was provided by the observation that a store-independent outward rectifying Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> conductance termed I<subscript>ORCa</subscript> found in primary isolated embryonic intestinal cells oscillates under conditions of low Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> buffering (<link linkend="bib32">Estevez et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15961418-->). The biophysical properties of I<subscript>ORCa</subscript> resembled those of Transient Receptor Potential Melastatin (TRPM) channels, a class of a superfamily of non-selective cation channels that are conserved from worms to humans. Two TRPM homologs, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001651;class=Gene" role="_blank">gon-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001795;class=Gene" role="_blank">gtl-1</ulink></emphasis>, are expressed in the nematode intestine. These two channels have nearly identical biophysical transport properties, are independently required for normal I<subscript>ORCa</subscript>, and help to maintain behavioral rhythmicity during defecation by facilitating the influx of Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> to the cell (<link linkend="bib56">Kwan et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18495023-->; <link linkend="bib115">Xing et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18299395-->). Hence, Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> oscillations in the worm intestine appear to be supported by non-canonical store-independent Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> entry pathways.</para>
<para>However, despite these findings, the specific role of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41002;class=Protein" role="_blank">GON-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33754;class=Protein" role="_blank">GTL-1</ulink> in regulating defecation has been debated and their loss-of-function defecation phenotypes have been suggested to result indirectly from defects in magnesium absorption (<link linkend="bib102">Teramoto et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16054081-->). Supporting this argument is the fact that the orthologous mammalian TRPM6 and TRPM7 channel-kinases govern intestinal magnesium uptake (<link linkend="bib80">Quamme, 2008</link><!--: PMID 18301276-->). However, worm TRPM channels lack the atypical alpha kinase domain (AAKD) found on both TRPM6 and TRPM7 (<link linkend="bib85">Runnels, 2011</link><!--: PMID 20932259-->). AAKDs are widespread amongst vertebrates and form a distinct family with specific substrate preferences. Other members of this family include erukaryotic elongation factor-2 kinase and myosin heavy chain kinase. The extent to which this domain might influence magnesium uptake is currently unknown.</para>
<para>An alternative theory was proposed where coupling of IP3R activity with plasma membrane Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> influx through TRPM channels occurred through co-regulation by phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate (PIP2) in conjunction with Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> itself (<link linkend="bib114">Xing et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 19923421-->). Membrane phosphoinositides play a fundamental role in regulating the activity of many plasma membrane transporters (<link linkend="bib45">Huang, 2007</link><!--: PMID 17928411-->). For example, the IP3R is activated by phospholipase C (PLC)-mediated hydrolysis of PIP2 into diacylglycerol and IP3. And while many ion channel classes bind to and are activated by PIP2, the TRPM channels <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33754;class=Protein" role="_blank">GTL-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41002;class=Protein" role="_blank">GON-2</ulink> are inhibited by PIP2 (<link linkend="bib114">Xing et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 19923421-->). Although this suggests that they may be functional outliers in terms of modulation by PIP2, it does allow for an interesting hypothesis: PIP2 hydrolysis following PLC activation could stimulate both IP3R and TRPM channel activities (model shown in <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). In conjunction, Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> is a positive regulator of PLC activity, a negative regulator of TRPM channel activity, and a biphasic regulator of IP3R: low concentrations of cytoplasmic Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> activate and conversely high concentrations inhibit further Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> release from the ER. As Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> levels increase in the cytoplasm, IP3R and TRPM activity would be predicted to be reduced by feedback inhibition (<link linkend="bib32">Estevez et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15961418-->), which would allow intracellular stores to refill and cytoplasmic Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> to return to baseline levels. As this occurs, TRPM channel feedback inhibition would be relieved, allowing small amounts of Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> to enter the cell, subsequently activating PLC. Increasing PLC activity would then lower PIP2 levels and desuppress TRPM channel activity, resulting in a self-sustaining oscillatory system in the absence of stimulation by extracellular ligands.</para>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> contain six PLC isoforms, and consistent with the above model PLC&gamma; (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004038;class=Gene" role="_blank">plc-3</ulink></emphasis>) regulates the behavioral rhythmicity of the DMP upstream of the IP3R (<link linkend="bib30">Espelt et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16186564-->). Hence, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42905;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLC-3</ulink> activity likely plays the role shown in <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>. PLC&beta; (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004036;class=Gene" role="_blank">plc-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001177;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-8</ulink></emphasis>) activity also contributes to defecation rhythmicity, but unlike PLC&gamma; does not functionally interact with the IP3R (<link linkend="bib30">Espelt et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16186564-->). PLC&beta; has been localized to intestinal cell junctions (<link linkend="bib64">Miller et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10571227-->) and its loss results in abnormal Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> wave propagation (<link linkend="bib70">Nehrke et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 17942636-->), much like that observed following the loss of the gap junction protein innexin <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28765;class=Protein" role="_blank">INX-16</ulink> (<link linkend="bib76">Peters et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17825560-->) or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00045343;class=Gene" role="_blank">mir-786</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib50">Kemp et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23141108-->) This suggests that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42647;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLC-1</ulink> regulates gap junction movement of Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> and is consistent with the idea that wave-driven elevations in Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> suffice to suppress cell autonomous Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> oscillations in cells anterior to int9.</para>
<para>Further evidence for the role of PIP2-IP3 metabolism being central to defecation pacemaking comes from a mutation in the guanidine nucleotide exchange factor (GEF) <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE39333;class=Protein" role="_blank">VAV-1</ulink> that alters several rhythmic behaviors, including defecation (<link linkend="bib72">Norman et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16213217-->). The small GTPases <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000424;class=Gene" role="_blank">ced-10</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003239;class=Gene" role="_blank">mig-2</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004357;class=Gene" role="_blank">rho-1</ulink></emphasis> act redundantly in a pathway with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006887;class=Gene" role="_blank">vav-1</ulink></emphasis> to modulate IP3 levels and may directly regulate <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004087;class=Gene" role="_blank">ppk-1</ulink></emphasis> (PIP5K) activity. GEFs generally function to integrate environmental signals transduced through cell surface receptor activation, but it is as-of-yet unclear what these signals are in worms.</para>
<para>Following defecation, ER Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> stores are replenished through the endoplasmic reticular Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> ATPase (SERCA) <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41682;class=Protein" role="_blank">SCA-1</ulink>. Though a loss-of-function mutation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004736;class=Gene" role="_blank">sca-1</ulink></emphasis> is <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000062;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">lethal</ulink>, mild intestine-restricted RNAi has been used to probe its influence on Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> oscillations during defecation. Surprisingly, mild intestinal knockdown resulted in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000643;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">uncoordinated</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0001641;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">pBoc</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000204;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">aBoc</ulink> (<link linkend="bib70">Nehrke et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 17942636-->). Previously, it had been shown that inhibiting Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> wave propagation through the intestine also dissociated <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0001641;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">pBoc</ulink> from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000204;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">aBoc</ulink> (<link linkend="bib101">Teramoto et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16780946-->). Although <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0001641;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">pBoc</ulink> does not require neural input, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AVL;class=Cell" role="_blank">AVL</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DVB;class=Cell" role="_blank">DVB</ulink> neurons are required for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000204;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">aBoc</ulink> and exp. More recently, the execution of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000204;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">aBoc</ulink> has been attributed to secretion of the neuropeptide-like protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24660;class=Protein" role="_blank">NLP-40</ulink> from the intestine to these neurons (<link linkend="bib110">Wang et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23583549-->). Hence, the <emphasis>sca-1(RNAi)</emphasis> phenotype is consistent with a role for Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> dynamics in the anterior intestine controlling neuropeptide release and intestine-to-neuron signaling.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-2">
<title>Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling during fertilization</title>
<para>Worms typically have 200-300 progeny, with oocytes undergoing fertilization every ~ 23 minutes. Immature oocytes are arrested in the proximal gonad in meiotic prophase I, surrounded by smooth muscle-like myoepithelial sheath cells. Meiosis is resumed just prior to fertilization in a process called meiotic maturation (Control of oocyte meiotic maturation and fertilization). Prior to meiotic maturation, sheath cells contract weakly and intermittently at a basal rate of 7&ndash;8 contractions/minute. However, meiotic maturation of the oocyte increases the force and rate of sheath contractions dramatically. The increased contraction rate is coupled to spermatheca dilation, which allows the mature oocyte to be inserted into the spermatheca for fertilization. This cycle is then repeated, and Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> serves to coordinate somatic and germline cell processes that need to occur in sequence for fertilization to occur properly (for review, see <link linkend="bib93">Singaravelu et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23218668-->).</para>
<para>A key event that times fertilization is the secretion of major sperm protein (MSP), which stimulates parallel responses in both oocytes and the sheath cell. MSP stimulates meiotic maturation in the proximal most oocyte (<link linkend="bib65">Miller et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11251118-->) by functioning as an ephrin-signaling antagonist and by counteracting inhibitory inputs from the somatic gonadal sheath cells (<link linkend="bib41">Govindan et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16824915-->). Genetic analyses have suggested a complex regulatory cascade where the IP3R <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37905;class=Protein" role="_blank">ITR-1</ulink> represses meiotic maturation downstream of the ephrin receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28617;class=Protein" role="_blank">VAB-1</ulink>, and the Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> channel NMDA receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30128;class=Protein" role="_blank">NMR-1</ulink> acts in a parallel pathway to regulate the maturation effector Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> calmodulin kinase type II <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42693;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-43</ulink> (<link linkend="bib24">Corrigan et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16267094-->). Hence, Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling may be important for keeping oocytes arrested in prophase I and for meiotic maturation as well, acting through different outputs (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<para>During meiotic maturation, oocytes secrete the EGF ligand <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49930;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> which binds to its receptor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42891;class=Protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink> on both the spermatheca and the sheath cell surface (<link linkend="bib22">Clandinin et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9491893-->; <link linkend="bib119">Yin et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15194811-->). This triggers PLC&gamma; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42905;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLC-3</ulink>) activity in the sheath cell to produce IP3. Levels of IP3 can be reduced by IP3 kinase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27864;class=Protein" role="_blank">LFE-2</ulink> or type I polyphosphate 5-phosphatase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30857;class=Protein" role="_blank">IPP-5</ulink>, and loss-of-function mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002979;class=Gene" role="_blank">lfe-2</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002146;class=Gene" role="_blank">ipp-5</ulink></emphasis> increase IP3 concentrations, suppressing the ovulation defect caused by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002992;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-3</ulink></emphasis> mutations; this holds true for a gain-of-function mutation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002173;class=Gene" role="_blank">itr-1</ulink></emphasis>, the IP3 receptor, as well (<link linkend="bib22">Clandinin et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9491893-->; <link linkend="bib10">Bui et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12006659-->; <link linkend="bib119">Yin et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15194811-->). A mutant allele of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002146;class=Gene" role="_blank">ipp-5</ulink></emphasis> also exhibits an unusual ovulation phenotype in which the spermatheca hyperextends, thereby ovulating two oocytes per cycle (<link linkend="bib10">Bui et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12006659-->), confirming that the IP3R is central to this cell&apos;s function in fertilization. The final step in fertilization occurs when the oocytes exit the spermatheca, and signaling through this pathway apparently requires PLC&epsi; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42647;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLC-1</ulink>) rather than <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42905;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLC-3</ulink> (<link linkend="bib49">Kariya et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15355798-->). Coordinated constriction of the myoepithelial tube following fertilization is mediated by mechanical stretch via the scaffolding protein filamin (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE20347;class=Protein" role="_blank">FLN-1</ulink>), which times <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42647;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLC-1</ulink> activity, resulting in a distinctive series of IP3-dependent Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> oscillations propagated through the tissue by gap junctions (<link linkend="bib54">Kovacevic et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23671426-->). Together, these results suggest that Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling downstream of IP3R activation is sufficient to time and coordinate fertilization events.</para>
<para>Finally, unlike Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling during defecation, which acts through a non-canonical TRPM dependent pathway (<link linkend="bib56">Kwan et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18495023-->; <link linkend="bib115">Xing et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18299395-->), the increased rate and force of gonadal sheath cell contractions caused by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49930;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-3</ulink> are dependent upon both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021910;class=Gene" role="_blank">stim-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00015648;class=Gene" role="_blank">orai-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib62">Lorin-Nebel et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17218360-->). In a now-routine example of mechanistic convergence between worms and mammals, both Stim1 and Orai have recently been shown to function in oocyte meiotic maturation in mice (<link linkend="bib16">Cheon et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23468522-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-3">
<title>Non-neuronal contributions to the locomotor circuit</title>
<para>Systemic electrolyte homeostasis can influence signaling events that require coordinated action between multiple cells types, likely by altering the environment through which intercellular signaling processes must occur. For example, the TRPM channel <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40563;class=Protein" role="_blank">GTL-2</ulink> was identified through an unbiased genetic screen for suppressors of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000042;class=Gene" role="_blank">acr-2</ulink></emphasis> gain-of-function <emphasis>(gf)</emphasis> epilepsy-like phenotype, where <emphasis>gtl-2</emphasis> loss-of-function restored excitation-inhibition imbalance in an <emphasis>acr-2(gf)</emphasis> strain (<link linkend="bib95">Stawicki et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21549603-->). Cell-specific rescue analysis suggested the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40563;class=Protein" role="_blank">GTL-2</ulink> functions in the hypodermis or excretory cell (<link linkend="bib95">Stawicki et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21549603-->). Like all TRP channels, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40563;class=Protein" role="_blank">GTL-2</ulink> is a non-selective cation channel capable of passing a variety of positively charged electrolytes, and it has been linked to magnesium excretion in the excretory cell (<link linkend="bib103">Teramoto et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20221407-->). However, studies using relatively specific cation chelators suggest that its ability to suppress the <emphasis>acr-2(gf)</emphasis> phenotype may be related more to zinc homeostasis than to that of either Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> or magnesium (<link linkend="bib95">Stawicki et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21549603-->), exemplifying the complexity inherent to an integrated system. It is possible that the relative non-selectivity of TRP channels (such as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40563;class=Protein" role="_blank">GTL-2</ulink>, or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41002;class=Protein" role="_blank">GON-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33754;class=Protein" role="_blank">GTL-1</ulink>) for different cations may diversify their effect on physiologic behaviors, complicating the interpretation of genotype-phenotype approaches.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2-4">
<title>Epidermal wound closure</title>
<para>Lesions to the worm&apos;s &ldquo;skin&rdquo; are repaired in part through a G&alpha;<subscript>q</subscript>-Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling pathway required for actin-dependent wound closure (<link linkend="bib116">Xu et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 22100061-->). Cytoplasmic Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> influx in hypodermal cells following wounding also occurs through <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE40563;class=Protein" role="_blank">GTL-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib116">Xu et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 22100061-->), consistent with a role for this channel in passing a variety of cations. Wounds to a <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> embryo also result in a nearly instantaneous Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> flash, suggesting that this mechanism represents one of the earliest signals in the wound response (<link linkend="bib81">Razzell et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23394834-->). Interestingly, reactive oxygen species (ROS) signaling has been implicated in wound responses in both plants and animals (<link linkend="bib100">Suzuki et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23085520-->) and several of the mammalian TRPM channels are either regulated by ROS (TRPM2) or have been implicated in survival responses to oxidative stress (TRPM7) (<link linkend="bib99">Sumoza-Toledo et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21135052-->; <link linkend="bib15">Chen et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22587440-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>pH Homeostasis: protons at work</title>
<para>Cellular pH homeostasis is well protected by a variety of buffering and acid-base transport mechanisms. Both protons and hydroxyl ions can be transported across cell membranes much like other electrolytes, and the major biological buffer in the cell is bicarbonate which itself is a substrate for membrane transport. Gene families involved in acid-base transport and cell buffering, including sodium-proton exchangers, anion bicarbonate transporters and carbonic anhydrases, are well conserved between worms and mammals (<link linkend="bib71">Nehrke et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12021279-->; <link linkend="bib89">Sherman et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15814591-->; <link linkend="bib9">Bretscher et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21435556-->; <link linkend="bib35">Fasseas et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 20842438-->; <link linkend="bib90">Sherman et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22245567-->).</para>
<sect2 id="sec3-1">
<title>pH fluctuations during defecation</title>
<para>Proton transport processes and pH homeostasis are integral parts of the worm defecation cycle (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>). As in regions of the mammalian gastrointestinal tract such as the stomach, the lumen of the worm&apos;s intestine is relatively acidic with a resting pH &ap; 4.1 (<link linkend="bib77">Pfeiffer et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18291648-->). Recent work has shown that protons or proton equivalents move using an unidentified transport mechanism from the intestinal lumen into the cytoplasm of the cells (which are pH 7.5) in response to Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> oscillations during defecation (<link linkend="bib77">Pfeiffer et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18291648-->). As a consequence, the proton gradient between the lumen and the cytoplasm dissipates. The cytoplasm becomes quite acidic (pH &ap; 7) for a short period of time and the lumen becomes more alkaline (pH > 6). Only after expulsion has occurred are the protons transported back into the lumen. The return of protons from the cell to the lumen is a two-step process, with the first step requiring the activity of the Na<superscript>+</superscript>/H<superscript>+</superscript> exchanger <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE48832;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHX-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib68">Nehrke, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12939266-->). The second step occurs when the resulting proton gradient formed between the cytoplasm and the lumen presumably becomes too great for an electroneutral transporter such as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE48832;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHX-2</ulink> to act against. Further pumping of protons from the cell requires the activity of a V-ATPase on the luminal membrane (<link linkend="bib2">Allman et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19741196-->). Since the cell burns energy to pump protons back out of the intestinal cytoplasm into the lumen every ~ 45s, this process is likely to be quite important, and loss of either <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003730;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhx-2</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006915;class=Gene" role="_blank">vha-6</ulink></emphasis>, a subunit of the intestinal apical V-ATPase, results in cellular acidosis and death (<link linkend="bib68">Nehrke, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12939266-->; <link linkend="bib2">Allman et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19741196-->).</para>
<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>figure 4</phrase>
</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-2">
<title>Proton gradients and nutrient uptake</title>
<para>Although one might predict that overt cellular acidosis is sufficient to cause death, one alternative, which is not mutually exclusive, is that it is instead the luminal protons or the proton gradient between the lumen and the cytoplasm that is essential for viability. Why would gut pH be important for viability? One possibility is suggested by the fact that many nutrient transporters require protons for their activity. There are a variety of nutrient transporters in worms whose activity has been shown to be coupled to proton co-transport or to be activated by protons (<link linkend="bib36">Fei et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9601088-->; <link linkend="bib113">Xiao et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11160871-->; <link linkend="bib68">Nehrke, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12939266-->; <link linkend="bib63">Meissner et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15155758-->). For example, the worm transporters <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE48832;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHX-2</ulink> and OPT-2 together facilitate proton-coupled dipeptide uptake (<link linkend="bib68">Nehrke, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12939266-->; <link linkend="bib63">Meissner et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15155758-->). This functional coupling is conserved in mammals, where Na<superscript>+</superscript>/H<superscript>+</superscript> exchanger isoform 3 drives oligopeptide absorption in the gut via the H<superscript>+</superscript>-dipeptide symporter PEPT1 (<link linkend="bib51">Kennedy et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12397398-->; <link linkend="bib105">Thwaites et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17468205-->). Subsequent dipeptide availability feeds into a variety of signaling pathways that recognize and respond to metabolic changes (for review see <link linkend="bib94">Spanier, 2013</link><!--: PMID 23959672-->). Similarly, the folate transporter <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE47283;class=Protein" role="_blank">FOLT-1</ulink> in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is acid activated (<link linkend="bib5">Balamurugan et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17475669-->) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007388;class=Gene" role="_blank">folt-1</ulink></emphasis> knockouts are <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000688;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">sterile</ulink> (<link linkend="bib4">Austin et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20441590-->). Other possible targets that might be sensitive to luminal pH include SLC36 family members of proton-coupled amino acid transporters (<link linkend="bib106">Thwaites et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21501141-->).</para>
<para>Consistent with this idea, a reduction in either <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003730;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhx-2</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006915;class=Gene" role="_blank">vha-6</ulink></emphasis> expression or activity is associated with reduced <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000542;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">fat</ulink> stores and increased lifespan (<link linkend="bib68">Nehrke, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12939266-->; <link linkend="bib2">Allman et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19741196-->; <link linkend="bib109">Wagner et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21865588-->). This is consistent with the idea that nutrient deprivation extends lifespan but that too much deprivation&mdash;such as might occur in the loss-of-function <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003730;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhx-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006915;class=Gene" role="_blank">vha-6</ulink></emphasis> mutants&mdash;leads to starvation. The observation that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003730;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhx-2</ulink></emphasis> lifespan extension is dependent upon <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15998;class=Protein" role="_blank">PHA-4</ulink>/FOXA (K. Nehrke, unpublished observations), a transcription factor that mediates the effects of caloric restriction on lifespan (<link linkend="bib74">Panowski et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17476212-->), is consistent with this interpretation. One might therefore argue that the main purpose of defecation in worms is not to expulse the contents of the intestinal lumen, since mutant worms that lack expulsion (aex or exp mutants) are <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0000651;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">constipated</ulink> but generally viable, but instead to conserve protons. By moving protons from the lumen into the cytoplasm, they are protected from being expulsed during defection, and in fact the pH of the expulsed waste is estimated to be &ap; 6 (<link linkend="bib77">Pfeiffer et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18291648-->). Subsequently pumping the protons back into the lumen is likely necessary for viability, based upon their role in nutrient uptake.</para>
<para>Recent research into folate metabolism illustrates how integrative physiological research in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> can inform new approaches in higher level eukaryotes. Folate is normally synthesized by bacteria and absorbed in the worm gut through proton-dependent processes. Not surprisingly, a reduction in bacterial folate synthesis can extend worm lifespan (<link linkend="bib108">Virk et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22849329-->). A similar extension of lifespan occurs from metformin (<link linkend="bib73">Onken et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20090912-->), a commonly used drug prescribed to treat type 2 diabetes and metabolic syndrome. The mechanism leading to changes in lifespan of worms treated with metformin has been shown to involve altered microbial folate and methionine metabolism (<link linkend="bib13">Cabreiro et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23540700-->). In mammals, the intestinal microbiome has also been shown to influence host metabolism, including development of metabolic disease. For example, groundbreaking new work has demonstrated &ldquo;diet by microbiota&rdquo; effects of gut microbes from human twins discordant for obesity following transplant into the intestines of germ-free mice (<link linkend="bib83">Ridaura et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 24009397-->). Perhaps there is an underlying change in folate metabolism in the twin&apos;s gut bacteria that transfers to the mice?</para>
<para>Indeed, beyond its direct relevance to nutrient uptake, the pH of the intestinal lumen is also likely to influence the rate at which bacteria proliferate therein (<link linkend="bib78">Portal-Celhay et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22452899-->). Since worms encounter a variety of bacteria that end up in their gut, some of which are pathogenic, and the growth rate of discrete bacterial strains exhibit differing pH sensitivity, luminal proton homeostasis likely feeds into microbial pathogenesis and resulting innate immune responses. Interestingly, the immunologic defenses that mediate pathogen resistance have been shown to involve reactive oxygen species (ROS) formation and oxidative stress signaling (<link linkend="bib14">Chavez et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17483415-->). ROS itself has been shown to cause cellular acidification in worms (<link linkend="bib47">Johnson et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20444981-->) and can regulate the activity of the acid-base transporters such as Na<superscript>+</superscript>/H<superscript>+</superscript> exchangers found in the gut (<link linkend="bib46">Johnson et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22237403-->). Ultimately, we come to the conclusion that pH is a dependent variable whose regulation both affects and is affected by multiple physiologic outputs. A truly integrative understanding of pH will take into account its effects on both host and microbiome.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3-3">
<title>Proton signaling</title>
<para>Historically, pH has been thought to provide &ldquo;a metabolic context within and through which the actions of other effectors are integrated&rdquo; (<link linkend="bib12">Busa et al., 1984</link><!--: PMID 6326601-->). Similarly, the pathway through which information is transmitted between cells has typically been thought to involve neurotransmitter or peptide hormone secretion and receptor binding. Protons are considered as a modulator of ion channel function, if they are considered at all. However, this viewpoint was recently challenged by the finding that the Na<superscript>+</superscript>/H<superscript>+</superscript> exchanger <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31034;class=Protein" role="_blank">PBO-4</ulink> (also known as NHX-7), which resides on the basolateral membrane of the posterior intestinal cells, could extrude protons during defecation (<link linkend="bib6">Beg et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18191228-->; <link linkend="bib77">Pfeiffer et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18291648-->) and that protons could act as a ligand for the Cys-loop nicotinic type receptors <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37284;class=Protein" role="_blank">PBO-5</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42343;class=Protein" role="_blank">PBO-6</ulink> on the membrane of adjacent posterior body wall muscles (<link linkend="bib6">Beg et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18191228-->). Uncaging protons with light induced <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0001641;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">pBoc</ulink> in a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37284;class=Protein" role="_blank">PBO-5</ulink>/6 dependent manner, confirming that proton modification of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37284;class=Protein" role="_blank">PBO-5</ulink>/6 was both necessary and sufficient for signaling (<link linkend="bib6">Beg et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18191228-->).</para>
<para>This novel finding suggested that protons might act as signaling molecules in other contexts, as well. There are certainly scenarios where this type of signaling mechanism could be envisioned to be useful. For example, the balance between respiration and glycolysis can alter the rate of proton production in the cell, and cells could use proton signaling to communicate their metabolic status to their neighbors. In addition, because protons are capable of &ldquo;hopping&rdquo; across water molecules, this new mode of signaling could potentially transmit information between cells faster than the rate of diffusion, modifying how other, slower information is interpreted.</para>
<para>Interestingly, proton signaling appears to be discrete from transport mechanisms that regulate pH homeostasis. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31034;class=Protein" role="_blank">PBO-4</ulink> dependent proton extrusion across the basolateral membrane occurs acutely and transiently, and its loss does not appear to influence the rate at which pH homeostasis is recovered following defecation (<link linkend="bib77">Pfeiffer et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18291648-->). In fact, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31034;class=Protein" role="_blank">PBO-4</ulink> is regulated by Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling through multiple parallel mechanisms such that its robust activity is restricted to a short period (<link linkend="bib3">Allman et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23319594-->). This ensures that most of the protons that enter the cytoplasm during defecation will be shuttled back to the lumen, both reestablishing the proton gradient and reducing the possibility of metabolic acidosis occurring through excess proton secretion into the pseudocoelom. The activity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31034;class=Protein" role="_blank">PBO-4</ulink> has also been shown to require <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27032;class=Protein" role="_blank">PBO-1</ulink>, a calcineurin homolog protein (CHP) ortholog and putative b-subunit that regulates Na<superscript>+</superscript>/H<superscript>+</superscript> exchangers in both worms and mammals (<link linkend="bib76">Peters et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17825560-->). CHP loss of function is not tolerated in mammals, but the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003941;class=Gene" role="_blank">pbo-1</ulink></emphasis> deletion mutant is viable and should provide a valuable resource to decipher its mechanism of action in regulating Na<superscript>+</superscript>/H<superscript>+</superscript> exchangers in worms.</para>
<para>It appears likely that proton signaling is conserved in mammals, as the relevant proteins exist. Protons can be sensed by a class of G-protein coupled receptors including G2A, GPR4, OGR1, and TDAG8, with functions ranging from inflammation to renal acid secretion to osteoclastogenesis (<link linkend="bib107">Tomura et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 16014326-->), as well as by Acid Sensing Ion Channels (ASICs) involved in nociception (<link linkend="bib28">Deval et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20807551-->). The nine member mammalian Na<superscript>+</superscript>/H<superscript>+</superscript> exchanger (NHE) gene family is widely expressed and one or more of these transporters may play an analogous function to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31034;class=Protein" role="_blank">PBO-4</ulink> in signaling. However, to date observations of Na<superscript>+</superscript>/H<superscript>+</superscript> exchanger-dependent proton extrusion as a signaling mechanism have been restricted to worms.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Osmotic balance: the art of adaptation</title>
<para>It&apos;s impossible to consider salt, or in this case ion transport, without also considering water. Systemic fluid and electrolyte balance is exquisitely maintained in all organisms. In general, this balance is regulated by the vectorial transport of ions (i.e. in one direction). Water is osmotically obliged to follow transported ions, often through aquaporins or water channels. As such, the transport of osmotically-active substances across the cell membrane can result in constant challenges to volume homeostasis.</para>
<para>Regulatory volume increase or decrease is a short-term mechanism by which electrolyte transport is triggered in response to cell shrinkage or swelling, as may occur during physiologic processes like fluid secretion or alternatively in response to environmental challenges such as exposure to high salt concentrations. Plasma membrane electrolyte transport processes are a major factor influencing the cell&apos;s and organism&apos;s ability to compensate appropriately to shrinkage or swelling through regulatory volume changes.</para>
<para>Worms have several tissues that contribute significantly to regulating whole-organism osmotic balance. The intestine and hypodermis appear to be particularly important in short term responses to changes in environmental salinity, and signaling pathways that contribute to systemic osmotic homeostasis following acute hypertonic challenge operate in these tissues (<link linkend="bib18">Choe et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17596296-->). The excretory cell functions in long term osmoregulation and water balance, as laser ablation of this cell results in the worms bloating and dying within 24 hours. The regulated movement of salts in response to osmotic challenge occurs through a variety of transport mechanisms. Although the identity of the transporters themselves is of great interest, major contributions of work in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> model have involved defining upstream regulators of ion transport, specific targets of regulation, and downstream effectors of salt stress.</para>
<para>A particularly apt example of this is regulatory cascades that mediate Cl<superscript>-</superscript> transport. In mammals, loss-of-function mutations in the thiazide-sensitive Na<superscript>+</superscript>-Cl<superscript>-</superscript> cotransporter (NCC) cause phenotypes including hypertension, hyperkalemia, hyperchloremia, and metabolic acidosis, all of which depend upon the movement of chloride anion in the distal nephron (<link linkend="bib92">Simon et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8528245-->). Hence, the regulation of NCC is critically important to human health. Shortly thereafter, human disease-causing mutants were identified in With-No-Lysine (K) Kinases WNK1 and WNK4 (<link linkend="bib111">Wilson et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11498583-->) whose pseudohypoaldosteronism phenotypes, a diverse group of electrolyte metabolism disorders, mirrored the phenotypes resulting from loss of NCC. Over the past several years, the WNK signaling pathway has emerged as having a conserved role in regulating electrolyte transport. WNK kinases act upstream of Ste20-like proline/alanine-rich kinase (SPAK) and oxidative stress-responsive 1 (OSR1) kinases and in opposition to protein phosphatase 1 and calcineurin to regulate a variety of plasma membrane electrolyte transport proteins (for review see <link linkend="bib48">Kahle et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20637866-->; <link linkend="bib75">Park et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23026752-->).</para>
<para>The presence of single nematode gene representatives from the WNK subfamily (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49733;class=Protein" role="_blank">WNK-1</ulink>) and the GCK VI subfamily of STE-20 protein kinases to which OSR1 and SPAK belong (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46529;class=Protein" role="_blank">GCK-3</ulink>), has facilitated genetic approaches to determine their function (<link linkend="bib97">Strange et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16443823-->). As regards cell volume regulation, tissue-specific RNAi suggests that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46529;class=Protein" role="_blank">GCK-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49733;class=Protein" role="_blank">WNK-1</ulink> function in a common pathway in the hypodermis and intestine to regulate volume recovery following hypertonic shrinkage (<link linkend="bib18">Choe et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17596296-->). The particular effectors for this process have not yet been identified, but are presumably transporters involved in maintaining systemic fluid and electrolyte balance.</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46529;class=Protein" role="_blank">GCK-3</ulink> was originally identified through an unbiased screen of proteins that interact with the cytosolic C-terminus of CLH-3b (<link linkend="bib27">Denton et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15684092-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27906;class=Protein" role="_blank">CLH-3</ulink> is one of six ClC type Cl<superscript>-</superscript> channel family members in worms (<link linkend="bib88">Schriever et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10567397-->; <link linkend="bib69">Nehrke et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 11078724-->) and CLH-3b is produced from a splice variant that is expressed in oocytes and activated during meiotic maturation (<link linkend="bib86">Rutledge et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11231150-->). Meiotic maturation involves an enormous increase in oocyte volume. Recombinant <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27906;class=Protein" role="_blank">CLH-3</ulink> activity can be triggered by volume changes but the native protein does not appear to be required for normal oocyte volume homeostasis during maturation. Instead, it plays a role in regulating sheath cell contractions through an as-of-yet incompletely understood cell non-autonomous mechanism (<link linkend="bib86">Rutledge et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11231150-->). The net effect of CLH-3b activity is to synchronize oocyte cell cycle progression with ovulation and fertilization. The CLH-3b channel is normally kept inactive by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46529;class=Protein" role="_blank">GCK-3</ulink> dependent phosphorylation of S272 and S274, just downstream of its binding site (<link linkend="bib27">Denton et al., 2005</link><!--: PMID 15684092-->; <link linkend="bib34">Falin et al., 2009</link><!--: PMID 19088383-->). Activation of CLH-3b is a result of dephosphorylation by the type 1 phosphatases <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE20735;class=Protein" role="_blank">GSP-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01319;class=Protein" role="_blank">GSP-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib87">Rutledge et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12163466-->). Extensive structure-function mutagenesis has provided striking insights into how alternative splicing regulates channel activity and how environmental information is transduced by phospho-regulation of its conformation and functional properties (<link linkend="bib26">Denton et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14565992-->; <link linkend="bib43">He et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16500974-->; <link linkend="bib66">Miyazaki et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 22357738-->; <link linkend="bib66">Miyazaki et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23083714-->).</para>
<para>Surprisingly, despite the well documented involvement of WNK kinases in regulating mammalian transporters and its involvement upstream of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46529;class=Protein" role="_blank">GCK-3</ulink> in whole animal osmoregulation in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib18">Choe et al., 2007</link><!--: PMID 17596296-->), CLH-3b regulation by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46529;class=Protein" role="_blank">GCK-3</ulink> during meiotic maturation does not involve <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49733;class=Protein" role="_blank">WNK-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib33">Falin et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21160027-->). Instead, the ERK kinase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01583;class=Protein" role="_blank">MPK-1</ulink> and its upstream regulator <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25437;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEK-2</ulink>, which are known to play important roles in the meiotic cell cycle in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib21">Church et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7671816-->; <link linkend="bib59">Leacock et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 17096596-->) appear to activate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46529;class=Protein" role="_blank">GCK-3</ulink>, keeping CLH-3b basally repressed (<link linkend="bib33">Falin et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21160027-->) (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). Hence, studies in worms have identified a new target transporter regulated by the OSR1/SPAK ortholog <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46529;class=Protein" role="_blank">GCK-3</ulink> and a new kinase that participates in the regulatory cascade. Because of the clear role of WNK kinase in human health, it will be important to determine whether ERK kinases partner with GCK VI kinases in osmoregulatory cascades in mammals, as well.</para>
<para>In addition to its role in meiotic maturation, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00013355;class=Gene" role="_blank">gck-3</ulink></emphasis> is widely expressed in worms and regulates several other developmental processes (<link linkend="bib55">Kupinski et al., 2010</link><!--: PMID 20595048-->). Among these is tubular extension of the excretory canals. The worm excretory cell functions like a kidney, with canals that run along either side of the body being formed by seamless tubule extension from a single cell. Mutants in either <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00013355;class=Gene" role="_blank">gck-3</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006941;class=Gene" role="_blank">wnk-1</ulink></emphasis> result in an excretory cell (exc mutant) phenotype (<link linkend="bib44">Hisamoto et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18049475-->). In these mutants, the apical excretory membrane fails to extend as a result of a defect in triggering peri-apical vesicles to fuse with the lumen (<link linkend="bib53">Kolotuev et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23334499-->). Since lumen expansion can occur in response to osmotic changes and involves the water channel <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE34331;class=Protein" role="_blank">AQP-8</ulink> (<link linkend="bib52">Khan et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23334498-->) and the volume-sensitive Cl<superscript>-</superscript> channel <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27906;class=Protein" role="_blank">CLH-3</ulink> (<link linkend="bib44">Hisamoto et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18049475-->), a role for hydrodynamic force is suggested in the developmental process of tubule extension itself.</para>
<para>In contrast to short-term regulation of volume homeostasis through osmo-sensitive phosphorylation of electrolyte transporters, long-term approaches to surviving &ldquo;salt stress&rdquo; involve the induction of signaling pathways that prevent cell damage. An elegant review on this topic was published recently (<link linkend="bib17">Choe, 2013</link><!--: PMID 23739341-->). Briefly, <emphasis>C elegans</emphasis> accumulate the organic osmolyte glycerol upon hypertonic exposure as a means of adaptation; this is reflected by transcriptional induction of GAPDH, the rate limiting enzyme in the production of glycerol (<link linkend="bib57">Lamitina et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 14644776-->). Reverse genetic screens, either using a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009824;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpdh-1</ulink></emphasis>::GFP transcriptional reporter or scoring directly for hypertonicity resistance, identified proteostasis genes including components of the ubiquitin-proteasome system, endosomal sorting complexes, and lysosomes (<link linkend="bib58">Lamitina et al., 2006</link><!--: PMID 16880390-->; <link linkend="bib19">Choe et al., 2008</link><!--: PMID 18829898-->). In fact hypertonic stress causes rapid and widespread protein damage as measured by hypertonicity-induced aggregation of polyglutamine-YFP (Q35::YFP) (<link linkend="bib11">Burkewitz et al., 2011</link><!--: PMID 21613604-->). The novel finding that inhibiting translation activates <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009824;class=Gene" role="_blank">gpdh-1</ulink></emphasis> gene transcription via <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49733;class=Protein" role="_blank">WNK-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46529;class=Protein" role="_blank">GCK-3</ulink> (<link linkend="bib60">Lee et al., 2012</link><!--: PMID 23076791-->) delivers a direct link between acute and chronic adaptive mechanisms.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<para>The ease of experimental approaches and the wide repertoire of conserved membrane transport proteins contribute to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> value as a genetic model for integrative physiological research. For example, the continuing evolution of fluorescent biosensors will allow sophisticated approaches to simultaneously image dynamic changes in organelle and cytoplasmic electrolyte concentrations. Combined with optogenetic approaches (<link linkend="bib91">Shipley et al., 2014</link><!--: PMID 24715856-->) to manipulate Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> or other second messengers, these reagents are likely to facilitate new avenues toward understanding how membrane ion flux influences systems biology. Exciting questions such as whether mitochondrial Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> buffering integrates oscillatory Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> signaling with metabolism or how cell stress/aging influences membrane transport are ready to be answered using existing molecular and genetic resources. New technologies for precisely manipulating the worm genome (<link linkend="bib29">Dickinson et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23995389-->; <link linkend="bib37">Friedland et al., 2013</link><!--: PMID 23817069-->) will facilitate in vivo structure-function analysis of transport proteins. New reagents such as genetically-caged Ca<superscript>2+</superscript> (<link linkend="bib38">Fukuda et al., 2014</link><!--: PMID 24625002-->) and genetically-encoded photosensitizers that use light to exert spatial and temporal control over ROS production (<link linkend="bib112">Wojtovich et al., 2014</link><!--: PMID 24563855-->) will allow new approaches to be developed. Clearly, the field is expanding rapidly and the contributions of work in this area are certain to advance our understanding of mechanism, regulation, and functional output of electrolyte transporters.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>Dr. Nehrke acknowledges support by USPHS NS064945 and GM087483 and NSF IOS 1352836. Thanks are due to Dr. Paul Brookes, Dr. Andrew Wojtovich and Dr. Andrew Samuelson for critical reading and suggestions.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>References</title>
<para/>
&memiontransport_ref;
</sect1>
</article>