<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 1. Hh encodes a secreted morphogen that activates a signal transduction pathway</title>
        <para>Figure is based on studies from <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> and mammals and is adapted from <link linkend="bib13">Cohen (2003)</link><!--: PMID 14556242-->. A description of genes and abbreviations is provided (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>; for reviews, see <link linkend="bib33">Lee et al., 1992</link><!--: PMID 1394430-->; <link linkend="bib43">Mohler and Vani, 1992</link><!--: PMID 1280560-->; <link linkend="bib57">Tabata et al., 1992</link><!--: PMID 1340474-->; <link linkend="bib60">Tashiro et al., 1993</link><!--: PMID 8166882-->). Left panel: Hh
            is produced, autoprocessed and modified by Ski. N-Hh is released by Disp. Middle panel:
            The N-Hh signal is propagated by the HSPG Dlp, which is modified by transferases such as
            Ttv, Sotv, Botv that add heparan sulphate (HS). Other molecules that can bind Hh signal
            are megalin, Hip and GAS1. N-Hh is an antagonistic ligand that represses the Patched (Ptc)
            receptor, before being internalised, and releases the latent activity of the Smoothened
            (Smo) seven-pass membrane protein, which is related to the Frizzled family of receptors
            (<link linkend="bib2">Alcedo et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8706127-->; <link linkend="bib11">Chen and Struhl, 1998</link><!--: PMID 9811578-->; <link linkend="bib46">Nusse, 2003</link><!--: PMID 14530294-->; <link linkend="bib62">van den Heuvel and Ingham, 1996</link><!--: PMID 8700230-->). In turn, Cos2 is released
            from microtubules and the Cos2/Fu/Su(fu)/Ci complex releases Ci, which can then enter
            the nucleus to activate transcription (<link linkend="bib23">Hooper, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12874118-->; <link linkend="bib27">Jia et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14597665-->; <link linkend="bib37">Lum et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14636583-->; <link linkend="bib48">Ogden et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14614827-->; <link linkend="bib54">Ruel et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14523402-->). Several molecules involved in modifying the
            Cos2//Fu/Su(fu)/Ci complex are not shown. Right panel: In the absence of N-Hh, Ptc
            inhibits Smo, the Cos2/Fu/Su(fu)/Ci complex remains associated with microtubules, Ci is
            phosphorylated and cleaved by Cos2. The Ci fragment now acts as a transcriptional
            repressor. Details of the pathway relevant for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are provided in the text. Grey bar represents microtubules.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>