<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 2. Structural features of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Hh-r proteins </title>
        <para>A) Intramolecular autoprocessing of Hh. The extent of the Hint domain and the sterol
            recognition region (SRR) is underlined beneath Hh-C; in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> the SRR region within
            the Hog domain is called ARR, since it is unknown if it binds cholesterol (<link linkend="bib5">Beachy et
            al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9598352-->). The conserved first residue (cysteine) of the Hint domain is
            highlighted in yellow. The toothed box represents cholesterol. Acids and bases assisting
            in catalysis are not shown (adapted from <link linkend="bib18">Hall et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9335337-->). B) Schematic
            representation of the conserved domains in Hh, WRT, GRD, GRL, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=QUA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">QUA-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HOG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HOG-1</ulink> proteins.
            The yellow box at the N-terminus indicates the signal sequence for secretion and the
            black box represents the Hog domain. The green, red, blue, light blue and orange boxes
            indicate the Hh-N (“Hedge”), Wart, Ground, Ground-like, and Qua domains, respectively.
            The grey regions indicate regions with repetitive sequences of varying lengths. The
            first column on the right indicates the number of members of each family that are
            present in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. The second column shows a tick mark when members of these
            families have been detected in <emphasis>B. malayi</emphasis>, but the precise number has not yet been
            determined. C) Schematic representation of the Hh-N, Qua, Wart, Ground, and Ground-like
            domains. Yellow lines represent conserved cysteine residues. The red bar indicates a
            short conserved motif that often starts with a phenylalanine, followed by an acidic
            residue and two hydrophobic residues; ø stands for a small hydrophobic residue. Black
            solid lines beneath the domains mark predicted disulfide bonds, dashed lines are
            tentative predictions. The cylinders and arrows beneath Hh-N indicate alpha helices and
            beta-sheets, respectively, taken from the solved 3D structure (<link linkend="bib17">Hall et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7477329-->). Cylinders and arrows beneath the Ground and Ground-like domain were produced
            by secondary structure prediction of the multiple aligned sequences (<link linkend="bib3">Asp&#x000F6;ck et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10523520-->).</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>