<caption>
	<formalpara>
		<title>Figure 2. Properties of cultured <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> touch neurons.</title>
<para>(<emphasis role="bold">A</emphasis>) Primary culture of a <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> strain <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bzIs18;class=Transgene" role="_blank">bzIs18</ulink></emphasis> which expresses yellow cameleon 2.12 (yc2.12) in the mechanosensory neurons (<link linkend="bib27">Miyawaki et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9278050-->; <link linkend="bib23">Kerr et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10896155-->; <link linkend="bib37">Suzuki et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12971899-->). All neurons expressing cameleon show neuronal morphology. Scale bar 10 micron. (<emphasis role="bold">B</emphasis>) Example of cultured touch neuron expressing GFP under the touch neuron specific promoter <emphasis><subscript>P</subscript><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-4</ulink></emphasis>. On the bottom, the same neuron was stained with an antibody raised against acetylated-tubulin (Sigma); a unique modification to touch neurons <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib16">Fukushige et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 9885292-->). (<emphasis role="bold">C</emphasis>) <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryonic cells were cultured from <emphasis><subscript>P</subscript><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-4</ulink>::gfp</emphasis> and <emphasis>mec-4(d); <subscript>P</subscript><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mec-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">mec-4</ulink>::gfp</emphasis> nematodes. Cells were plated at the same density (~200,000 cells/cm<superscript>2</superscript>) in individual wells and the number of touch neurons/40x field (identified as expressing GFP) were counted 24 hours and 4 days after plating. Ten fields per sample were counted. (<emphasis role="bold">D</emphasis>) Experiment conducted similarly to panel C for WT and <emphasis>mec-4(d)</emphasis> touch neurons plus and minus genetic modification (calreticulin null mutant <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bz29;class=Variation" role="_blank">bz29</ulink></emphasis>) and pharmacological treatments (10&#x03BC;M dantrolene or 10&#x03BC;M amiloride). The number of touch neurons/40x field was determined 24 hours after plating. Ten fields per sample were counted. Modified from (<link linkend="bib3">Bianchi et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15543143-->).</para>
	</formalpara>
</caption>