<caption>
	<formalpara>
		<title>Figure 3. Whole-cell currents recorded from cultured <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> touch neurons.</title>
		<para>(<emphasis role="bold">A</emphasis>) Example of whole-cell currents recorded from a WT touch neuron perfused with a standard physiological saline. Voltage steps were from <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02212;</symbol>120 to + 100 mV from a holding potential of <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02212;</symbol>50 mV. (<emphasis role="bold">B</emphasis>) Currents elicited in the same neuron by the same voltage protocol as in A after application of 50&#x03BC;M amiloride. Note that the current is not affected by application of amiloride, indicating the lack of activity of amiloride sensitive channels under these experimental conditions. (<emphasis role="bold">C</emphasis>) Perfusion of the same cell with a solution in which NaCl was substituted by NMDG-Cl. Notice the disappearance of the inward component of the current during perfusion with NMDG-Cl indicating that this current is carried mainly by Na<superscript>+</superscript> ions. (<emphasis role="bold">D</emphasis>) Upon washout and reperfusion with NaCl, the inward component reappears. (<emphasis role="bold">E</emphasis>) Current-voltage relationships of currents shown in A and C. (<emphasis role="bold">F</emphasis>) Average current at <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02212;</symbol>120mV recorded from WT and <emphasis>mec-4(null)</emphasis> (<emphasis>mec-4(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=u253;class=Variation" role="_blank">u253</ulink>)</emphasis>) touch neurons. The average inward current is similar in the two genetic backgrounds reinforcing that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MEC-4;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEC-4</ulink> is not active under these experimental conditions. (<emphasis role="bold">G</emphasis>) and (<emphasis role="bold">H</emphasis>) Families of outward currents likely carried by K<superscript>+</superscript> recorded from two WT touch neurons perfused with a physiological saline. Voltage steps were from <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02212;</symbol>80mV to +100mV from a holding potential of <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02212;</symbol>50mV. WT and <emphasis>mec-4(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=u253;class=Variation" role="_blank">u253</ulink>)</emphasis> touch neurons are endowed with K<superscript>+</superscript> currents of similar amplitudes. In most cases the K<superscript>+</superscript> current activated and inactivated rapidly (G) and in a few touch neurons it activated slowly. The nature of this difference is not known at this point. Source: (<link linkend="bib37">Suzuki et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12971899-->).</para>
	</formalpara>
</caption>