<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'pristgenomebiolfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'pristgenomebiolfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'pristgenomebiolfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'pristgenomebiolfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'pristgenomebiolfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'pristgenomebiolfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'pristgenomebiolfig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'pristgenomebiolfig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY pristgenomebiol_Refs SYSTEM 'pristgenomebiolrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="pristgenomebiol_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title><emphasis>Pristionchus pacificus</emphasis><footnote>
			<para>Edited by Jonathan Hodgkin. Last revised May 25, 2006. Published August 14, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Sommer, R.J. <emphasis>Pristionchus pacificus</emphasis> (August 14, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.124.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 Ralf J. Sommer. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
		<author>
			<firstname>Ralf J.</firstname>
			<surname>Sommer<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Phone: ++ 49 7071 601 371, Fax: ++ 49 7071 601 498, E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:ralf.sommer@tuebingen.mpg.de">ralf.sommer@tuebingen.mpg.de</ulink></para></footnote></remark>
			</surname>
			<affiliation><address>Max-Planck Institut f&#x000FC;r Entwicklungsbiologie, Abteilung Evolutionsbiologie, D-72076 T&#x000FC;bingen, Germany</address>
			</affiliation>
	</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<abstract>
		<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">In the last decade, nematodes other than</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">have been studied intensively in evolutionary developmental biology. A few species have been developed as satellite systems for more detailed genetic and molecular studies. One such satellite species is the diplogastrid nematode</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Pristionchus pacificus.</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">Here, I provide an overview about the biology, phylogeny, ecology, genetics and genomics of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">P. pacificus.</emphasis></emphasis></para>
	</abstract>
	<sect1>
		<title>Biology</title>
		<para><emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> was described as a novel species in 1996 and the first isolate PS312 from Pasadena (California) was established as a laboratory strain (<link linkend="bib24">Sommer et al., 1996</link><!--:PMID not available-->; <link linkend="bib25">Sommer and Sternberg, 1996</link><!--:PMID 8805221-->). By now, 15 strains from three different continents (North America, Europe and Asia) are in culture, some of which differ molecularly and developmentally from one another (<link linkend="bib19">Schlak et al., 1997</link><!--:PMID not available-->; <link linkend="bib20">Srinivasan et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID not available-->).</para>
<?newpage?>
		<para>In the last ten years, <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> has been established as a satellite organism in evolutionary developmental biology (<link linkend="bib9">Hong and Sommer, 2006</link>). <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> is a self-fertilizing hermaphrodite, has a 4-day life cycle at 20&#x000B0;C and can be cultured on OP50. <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> is amenable to various cellular, genetic and molecular techniques successfully used in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. In addition to forward genetics, morpholino knockdown and deletion library experiments provide reverse genetic tools (for genetic and genomic methods see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_pristionchuspacificusgeneticprotocols/pristionchus_pacificusgeneticprotocols.html"><emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> genetics</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_Pristionchuspacificusgenomicsfromgeneticstogenomesequence/Pristionchuspacificusgenomicsfromgeneticstogenomesequence.html"><emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> genomics</ulink> chapters in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/toc_wormmethods.html">WormMethods</ulink>; <link linkend="bib28">Zheng et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15696167-->).</para>
		<para>Under laboratory conditions, the life cycle of <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> is nearly as fast as the one of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, but differs in one important feature: <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis>, like all species of the family Diplogastridae, has an embryonic molt. J1 larvae molt to J2 before they hatch from the egg (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>; <link linkend="bib6">F&#x000FC;rst v. Lieven, 2005</link><!--:PMID not available-->). Thus, the J1 stage is not free-living and non-feeding. It has been suggested that the non-feeding J1 stage allows for a complex stoma morphology compared to the basal rhabditid buccal structure. Indeed, some taxa of the Diplogastridae (including <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis>) show an interesting dimorphism of stoma structures (<link linkend="bib5">F&#x000FC;rst von Lieven &amp; Sudhaus, 2000</link><!--:PMID not available-->). The two alternative mouth forms are called eurystomatous and stenostomatous morph, respectively (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>; <link linkend="bib5">F&#x000FC;rst von Lieven &amp; Sudhaus, 2000</link><!--:PMID not available-->). The stenostomatous buccal cavity is narrow, whereas eurystomatous worms have a broad buccal cavity. Among the different tooth-like structures present in the buccal cavity, eurystomatous worms have a claw-like dorsal tooth and a specialized tooth in the right subventral sector acting as antagonist, while stenostomatous worms lack the tooth of the right subventral side, and the dorsal tooth is not claw-like as in eurystomatous worms (<link linkend="figure2">Figrue 2</link>). These differences in buccal morphology are though to be related to different feeding habits (<link linkend="bib5">F&#x000FC;rst von Lieven &amp; Sudhaus, 2000</link><!--:PMID not available-->). Indeed, <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> can feed on various bacteria, fungi and even other nematodes.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="5in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="5in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Developmental biology</title>
		<para>The first developmental process to be studied in great detail in <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> was vulva formation (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_evoldevnematode/evoldevnematode.html">Evolution of development in nematodes related to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). When compared to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, vulva development in <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> involves a set of evolutionary modifications, including i) programmed cell death of non-vulval epidermal cells P(1-4,9-11).p, ii) vulva induction by multiple cells of the somatic gonad and iii) novel cell-cell interactions during vulva formation (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_evoldevnematode/evoldevnematode.html">Evolution of development in nematodes related to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></ulink>). <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> vulva defective mutants have been isolated in large-scale mutagenesis screens and the phenotypes of mutations have helped elucidating the molecular mechanisms of evolutionary change. For example, mutations in <emphasis>Ppa-lin-17</emphasis>/Frizzled result in gonad-independent vulva differentiation and a multivulva phenotype indicating a role of Wnt signaling in a negative signaling process (<link linkend="bib28">Zheng et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15696167-->). Besides vulva formation, gonad development (<link linkend="bib18">Rudel et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15572150-->), sex determination (<link linkend="bib17">Pires-daSilva &amp; Sommer, 2004</link><!--:PMID 1515582-->), mesoderm development (<link linkend="bib16">Photos et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16515780-->), dauer formation, olfaction and other aspects of neurobiology are studied intensively in <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis>.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Phylogeny</title>
		<para><emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> belongs to the family Diplogastridae, which includes about 300 described free-living species in 28 genera (<link linkend="bib5">F&#x000FC;rst v. Lieven &amp; Sudhaus, 2000</link><!--:PMID not available-->; <link linkend="bib26">Sudhaus &amp; F&#x000FC;rst v. Lieven, 2003</link><!--:PMID not available-->). The exact phylogenetic relationship to the Rhabditidae is still debated and several studies suggest that the Diplogastridae are part of the Rhabditidae (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3a</link>; see also Figure 1 in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_phylogrhabditids/phylorhab.html">The phylogenetic relationships of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> and other rhabditids</ulink>). Within the Diplogastridae, the genus <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis> represents a more derived taxon (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3b</link>). However, more molecular studies are necessary to provide a clear picture of the phylogenetic relationship of diplogastrid genera.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="6in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
		<para>Considering that the whole genome sequence comparison between <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> suggests a separation time of 80&#x02013;120 million years for those two species, the separation time of <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is expected to be much older. However, as no fossil record exists for nematodes, no accurate numbers can be given. We are currently working on accurate estimates within the genus <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis> by using detailed molecular phylogenetics (W. Mayer and R. J. Sommer, ongoing studies).</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Ecology</title>
		<para>Little is known about the ecology of many so-called &#x0201C;free-living&#x0201D; nematode species. Only very recently several studies found that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> occurs predominantly in compost heaps (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_naturalvariationgenetics/naturalvariationgenetics.html">Natural variation and population genetics of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis></ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_ecolCaenorhabditis/ecolCaenorhabditis.html">Ecology of <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species</ulink>). In <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis>, recent studies revealed that members of this genus live in close association with scarab beetles and the Colorado potato beetle (<link linkend="bib8">Herrmann et al., 2006</link>). Sampling of beetles in Western Europe in the years 2004 and 2005 resulted in more than 350 isolates that fell into six species. Two hermaphroditic species, <emphasis>P. entomophagus</emphasis> and <emphasis>P. maupasi</emphasis> accounted for 60% of the isolates and occurred on dung beetles and cockchafers, respectively. However, the satellite organism <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> was neither observed on scarab beetles nor on the Colorado potato beetle in Western Europe.</para>
		<para>Similar studies of <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis> species associated with scarab beetles and the Colorado potato beetle in the Eastern United States revealed striking differences in the species composition and mode of reproduction of <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis> species between Europe and North America (Herrmann, Mayer, &amp; Sommer, unpublished). While 60% of the wild isolates from Europe belong to two hermaphroditic species, more than 95% of the American isolates belong to several gonochoristic species. These results establish <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis> as a nematode model system for speciation, biogeography and biodiversity. In total, 15 <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis> species are available in culture and are used for studying microevolution of developmental processes, olfaction and genomics. The phylogenetic relationship of seven of these 15 species is represented in <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
	<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="5.5in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 4</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Genetics</title>
		<sect2>
			<title>Formal genetics and sex determination</title>
			<para><emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> is a self-fertilizing hermaphrodite with the frequent occurrence of males. The sex determination system is of the XX/XO type, similar to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib17">Pires-daSilva &amp; Sommer, 2004</link><!--:PMID 1515582-->). In general, mutagenesis experiments are carried out in the laboratory strain <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> PS312 from California and can be performed using various mutagens, such as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> or TMP/UV. However, RNAi and transformation methods are still being developed. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_pristionchuspacificusgeneticprotocols/pristionchuspacificus geneticprotocols.html"><emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> genetics</ulink> chapter in WormMethods by Pires-daSilva provides detailed protocols for various forward - and reverse genetic approaches in <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis>. For formal genetics, a set of morphological mutants is available (<link linkend="bib11">Kenning et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15493014-->). Most of these mutants have Dumpy-like phenotypes, but mutants with Unc-like phenotypes are available as well.</para>
		</sect2>
<?newpage?>
		<sect2>
			<title>Nomenclature</title>
			<para>In general, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> nomenclature was adopted for <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> by adding the prefix &#x0201C;<emphasis>Ppa</emphasis>&#x0201D; to indicate the species. To prevent confusion between individual gene names in <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> the following rules are used to distinguish phenotypic classes of mutants and orthologous genes: Genetically defined mutants in <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> are described with a prefix and a novel abbreviation, i.e. <emphasis>Ppa-pdl-n</emphasis>, with &#x0201C;<emphasis>pdl</emphasis>&#x0201D; standing for &#x0201C;<emphasis><emphasis role="underline">P</emphasis>ristionchus-<emphasis role="underline">d</emphasis>umpy-<emphasis role="underline">l</emphasis>ike</emphasis>&#x0201D;. This type of nomenclature system is chronological. Generally, mutants are re-named after the molecular lesion of a gene has been identified and was shown to be orthologous to a known <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> gene. On the other hand, molecularly defined orthologs of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genes are described as <emphasis>Ppa-ortholog</emphasis>, i.e. <emphasis>Ppa-lin-39</emphasis> and <emphasis>Ppa-mab-5</emphasis> for the Hox genes (<link linkend="bib4">Eizinger and Sommer, 1997</link><!--:PMID 9334302-->; <link linkend="bib10">Jungblut and Sommer, 1998</link><!--:PMID 9651682-->).</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Genomics</title>
		<para>A genomic initiative in <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> was launched in 2001. An integrated genome map of <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> contains a genetic linkage map of more than 500 molecular markers and a physical map of nearly 10.000 fingerprinted BAC clones (<link linkend="bib21">Srinivasan et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12242228-->, <link linkend="bib22">Srinivasan et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 112884007-->). A whole-genome sequencing project is ongoing (<ulink url="http://www.nhgri.nih.gov/12511858">http://www.nhgri.nih.gov/12511858</ulink>) and should result in a high-coverage draft within 2006.</para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Macrosynteny: chromosome homology and genome size</title>
			<para>The comparison of the genetic linkage maps of <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> revealed that, with one exception, all chromosomes can easily be homologized (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). The <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> chromosomes II, III, IV and X are homologous to the corresponding chromosomes of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> chromosome V corresponds to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> chromosome I and vice versa. However, one arm of <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> chromosome I contains genes that are orthologous to genes of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> X chromosome indicating one major chromosomal translocation after the split of <emphasis>Pristionchus</emphasis> and <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>; <link linkend="bib21">Srinivasan et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 12242228-->).</para>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="100%">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1: Comparisons of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">P. pacificus</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">and</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">chromosomes and their total genetic distances</emphasis>. Reprinted with permission from <link linkend="bib9">Hong and Sommer (2006)</link>, Bioessays &#x000A9; copyright 2006 Wiley Periodicals, Inc.</title>
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colname="c1" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c2" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c3" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c4" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c5" align="center" colwidth="1*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Number of <emphasis>Ppa</emphasis> SNP markers</entry>
<entry><emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> chromosome</entry>
<entry><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> chromosome</entry>
<entry><emphasis>Ppa</emphasis>_chr genetic distances (cM)</entry>
<entry><emphasis>Cel</emphasis>_chr genetic distances (cM)</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>110</entry>
<entry>I</entry>
<entry>V, X</entry>
<entry>215</entry>
<entry>50</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>76</entry>
<entry>II</entry>
<entry>II</entry>
<entry>168</entry>
<entry>50</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>78</entry>
<entry>III</entry>
<entry>III</entry>
<entry>117</entry>
<entry>50</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>78</entry>
<entry>IV</entry>
<entry>IV</entry>
<entry>179</entry>
<entry>50</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>72</entry>
<entry>V</entry>
<entry>I</entry>
<entry>162</entry>
<entry>50</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>65</entry>
<entry>X</entry>
<entry>X</entry>
<entry>185</entry>
<entry>50</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
			<para>Although these data prove the existence of macro-synteny, other genetic and physical properties differ between the <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genomes. Genetically, the strongest difference between the two organisms is the absence of interference in <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis>. Interference describes the genetic phenomenon that the first chiasmata during meiosis at one particular chromosome inhibits the occurrence of another chiasmata along the same chromosome. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> shows nearly complete interference, resulting in one cross-over per chromosome per meiosis. By definition, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> chromosomes are nearly 50 cM in length. In <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> double cross-overs are frequent and most chromosomes are genetically much larger than 50 cM. In total, the <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> genome has a length of 1026 cM with the caveat that the distal-most markers have not been physically linked to the telomeres yet (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>).</para>
			<para>In addition to the larger genetic size of the <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> genome, the physical size also differs from the one in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Fluoremetric measurements indicated a size of 161 Mb (Prof. S. Johnston, pers. Communication), a value that awaits further confirmation by the ongoing sequencing project.</para>
		</sect2>
<?newpage?>
		<sect2>
			<title>Microsynteny</title>
			<para>When genomes of related organisms are compared, the level of conservation of gene order can be expressed as synteny. The term microsynteny indicates that the order of individual genes in considered genomes is exactly conserved. BAC clone sequence analysis, as well as the ongoing whole genome sequencing initiative, revealed that the degree of microsynteny between the genomes of <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is limited (<link linkend="bib14">Lee et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12736304-->). The complete sequence of a BAC clone 7E22 of <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> provided a continuous sequence of 126 kb. It contains a region flanking the <emphasis>caudal</emphasis>-homolog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pal-1" role="_blank">pal-1</ulink></emphasis> of <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> and contains 20 predicted open reading frames (ORFs), 11 of which have putative orthologs in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. 10 of these 11 orthologs are located on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> chromosome III. However, most of these genes are distributed over more than a 12 Mb interval of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome and only three pairs of genes show microsynteny (<link linkend="bib14">Lee et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12736304-->).</para>
			<para>In addition, the comparison between <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> reveals differences in the genetic repertoire of both species. For example, <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> contains a <emphasis>dnmt-2</emphasis>-like DNA methyltransferase gene, whereas <emphasis>dnmt-2</emphasis>-like genes are completely absent from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib7">Gutierrez and Sommer, 2004</link><!--:PMID 15576683-->).</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Trans-splicing</title>
			<para>In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, up to 15% of the genes are organized in operons and polycistronic precursor RNAs are processed by trans-splicing at the 5<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> ends of genes through the addition of a specific trans-spliced leader (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_transsplicingoperons/transsplicingoperons.html">Trans-splicing and operons</ulink>). Among the 10 different spliced leaders known from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, the SL1 leader is most abundant. The SL1 leader is spliced to the 5<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol> ends of monocistronic genes and to upstream genes in operons. Trans-splicing is common among nematodes and was observed in the genera <emphasis>Panagrellus</emphasis>, <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis>, <emphasis>Haemonchus</emphasis>, <emphasis>Anisakis</emphasis> and <emphasis>Brugia</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib2">Bektesh et al., 1988</link><!--:PMID 3203906-->). With regard to operons, the best available information is on <emphasis>Brugia malayi</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib27">Whitton et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15383308-->).</para>
			<para>In <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis>, SL1 trans-splicing occurs commonly and the SL1 leader sequence is identical to the SL1 leader of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib10">Jungblut and Sommer, 1998</link><!--:PMID 9651682-->). In addition, <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> contains operons, downstream genes of which are trans-spliced to SL2 (<link linkend="bib15">Lee and Sommer, 2003</link><!--:PMID 12949121-->). Surprisingly, the operons analyzed so far in <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> are not conserved in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Mapping</title>
			<para>The genetic linkage map with more than 500 molecular markers and the physical map provide useful tools for the mapping and cloning of <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> mutants. For mapping, the laboratory strain <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> PS312 from California is crossed with the mapping strain <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> PS1843 from Washington. These two strains differ in approximately 3% of their sequence and provide large amounts of SNPs. The ongoing sequencing project provides a 1 X coverage of the <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> Washington sequence, which allows the detection of potential polymorphisms by BLAST search.</para>
			<para>Mapping strategies are different from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> protocols given that the available markers are mostly SSCP markers. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_Pristionchuspacificusgenomicsfromgeneticstogenomesequence/Pristionchuspacificusgenomicsfromgeneticstogenomesequence.html"><emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> genomics</ulink> chapter in WormMethods by Srinivasan and Dieterich provides detailed protocols for the mapping procedures and sequence searches. All of this information is available at the <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> database (<ulink url="http://www.pristionchus.org/cgi-bin/index.pl">http://www.pristionchus.org/cgi-bin/index.pl</ulink>).</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Genome sequence</title>
			<para>This paragraph will be added, once a high quality assembly of the <emphasis>P. pacificus</emphasis> genome is available.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
	<title>Acknowledgements</title>
	<para>I thank Metta Riebesell for critically reading this manuscript and the Max-Planck Society for support of our research on <emphasis>Pristionchus pacificus</emphasis>.</para>
	</sect1>
<?newpage?>
	<sect1>
		<title>References</title>
		&pristgenomebiol_Refs;
		<para/>
	</sect1>
</article>