<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % local.notation.class '| MOV'>
<!NOTATION MOV SYSTEM 'MOV'>
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'meioticfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'meioticfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'meioticfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'meioticfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'meioticfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'meioticfig3leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY mov1 SYSTEM 'meioticmov1.mov' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov1legend SYSTEM 'meioticmov1leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY meiotic_Refs SYSTEM 'meioticrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="meiotic_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Control of oocyte meiotic maturation and fertilization<footnote>
                <para>Edited by Judith Kimble and Susan Strome. Last revised March 24, 2005. Published December 28, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Greenstein, D. Control of oocyte meiotic maturation and fertilization (December 28, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.53.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 David Greenstein. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
            </footnote>
       </title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 3/24/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
-->
        <author>
            <firstname>David</firstname>
            <surname>Greenstein<remark>
                    <footnote>
                        <para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:david.greenstein@vanderbilt.edu">david.greenstein@vanderbilt.edu</ulink></para>
                    </footnote>
                </remark>
            </surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Department of Cell and Developmental Biology, Vanderbilt University School of Medicine, Nashville, TN 37232 USA</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Sexual reproduction depends upon meiosis for the generation of haploid gamete nuclei,
            which unite after fertilization to form the diploid zygote. The oocytes of most animal
            species arrest during meiotic prophase, and complete meiosis in response to
            intercellular signaling in a process called meiotic maturation. Oocyte meiotic
            maturation is defined by the transition between diakinesis and metaphase of meiosis I
            and is accompanied by nuclear envelope breakdown, rearrangement of the cortical
            cytoskeleton, and meiotic spindle assembly. Thus, the meiotic maturation process is
            essential for meiosis and prepares the oocyte for fertilization. In</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C.
            elegans,</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">the processes of meiotic maturation, ovulation, and fertilization
            are temporally coupled: sperm utilize the major sperm protein as a hormone to trigger
            oocyte meiotic maturation, and in turn, the maturing oocyte signals its own ovulation
            thereby facilitating fertilization. This chapter highlights recent advances in
            understanding meiotic maturation signaling and gametic interactions required for
            fertilization.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
    <sect1>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>General features of meiotic maturation and fertilization</title>
            <para>Sexual reproduction depends upon meiosis for the generation of haploid gamete
                nuclei, which unite after fertilization to form the diploid zygote. Despite this
                universal requirement, meiosis is regulated differently in oocytes and
                spermatocytes. Whereas spermatocytes proceed through the meiotic divisions uninterrupted, oocytes almost invariably arrest during one, and sometimes two stages
                following premeiotic DNA replication and meiotic recombination, depending on the
                species. This unique characteristic of oocyte meiosis, as well as its close temporal
                association with fertilization, was recognized early by developmental biologists
                (see <link linkend="bib62">Wilson, 1925</link>), who coined the term meiotic maturation for the suite of
                physiological changes occurring in oocytes just before zygote formation. Oocyte
                meiotic maturation is defined by the transition between diakinesis and metaphase of
                meiosis I and is accompanied by nuclear envelope breakdown, rearrangement of the
                cortical cytoskeleton, and meiotic spindle assembly (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>).
                Thus, the meiotic maturation process is essential for meiosis and may prepare the
                oocyte for fertilization.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig1" align="center" width="4in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>figure 1</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
            <para>To ensure successful fertilization, oocyte meiotic maturation must be coordinated
                with other cellular events during oogenesis, including growth, meiotic chromosome
                reorganization, and ovulation. To achieve this coordination, intercellular signals
                regulate oocyte meiotic progression (reviewed by <link linkend="bib13">Ferrell, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10497333-->; <link linkend="bib42">Masui,
                2001</link><!--: PMID 11776390-->). The timing of the meiotic divisions with respect to
                fertilization varies among species, likely reflecting the diversity of reproductive
                strategies observed in nature (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). Despite these differences
                in timing, extensive studies reveal striking conservation in the molecular
                underpinnings of oocyte meiotic maturation among different animals. It was classic
                studies of oocyte meiotic maturation in amphibian oocytes that led to the discovery
                of the Maturation Promoting Factor (MPF; <link linkend="bib44">Masui and Markert, 1971</link><!--: PMID 5106340-->;
                reviewed by <link linkend="bib42">Masui, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11776390-->). Genetic and biochemical analysis of the cell
                cycle, together with MPF purification, subsequently demonstrated that
                cyclin-dependent protein kinases are universal regulators of mitotic and meiotic
                cell cycle progression in eukaryotes (reviewed by <link linkend="bib50">Morgan, 1995</link><!--: PMID 7877684-->).</para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Meiotic maturation and fertilization in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis></title>
            <para>
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is an important system for addressing the
                fundamental events of oocyte meiotic maturation and fertilization, complementing
                studies in vertebrate systems (reviewed by <link linkend="bib25">Hubbard and Greenstein, 2000</link><!--:
                PMID 10822256-->). Oocytes grow and develop in the proximal gonad arm of adult
                hermaphrodites (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2A</link>). Apoptotic cell death of germ cells is a
                conserved feature of oogenesis, occurring in adults near the gonad loop region,
                where the gonad tube bends ventrally. As germline nuclei transit through the loop
                region, they exit pachytene, become more fully enclosed by plasma membrane, and form
                a queue in the proximal gonad arm. The meiotic chromosomes condense as the
                developing oocytes enter diplotene. In diakinesis, six discrete highly condensed
                bivalents, corresponding to the homologous chromosome pairs, are readily visualized
                    (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>B). Oocytes develop in close association with proximal
                gonadal sheath cells (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>), smooth muscle-like cells that
                regulate meiotic maturation and contract to drive ovulation (<link linkend="bib46">McCarter et al., 1997</link><!--:
                PMID 9013925-->; <link linkend="bib19">Hall et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10419689-->; <link linkend="bib49">Miller et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12533508-->).
                Meiotic maturation takes place in an assembly line fashion, such that the most
                proximal oocyte (often referred to as the –1 oocyte) matures, enters the spermatheca
                at ovulation, and is fertilized (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>; <link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link>). In adult
                hermaphrodites, the cycle repeats every ~23 minutes (<link linkend="bib47">McCarter et al., 1999</link><!--:
                PMID 9882501-->).</para>
            <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig2" width="5in" align="center"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase> figure 2</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
    <mediaobject id="movie1" xreflabel="Movie 1">
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata entityref="mov1" width="2in" align="center"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
            <phrase>Movie</phrase>
        </textobject> &mov1legend;</mediaobject>
            <para>In many animals, including many species of sponges, annelids, mollusks, and
                nematodes, sperm promote the resumption of meiosis in arrested oocytes (<link linkend="bib41">Masui, 1985</link>;
                <link linkend="bib47">McCarter et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 9882501-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, sperm
                utilize the major sperm protein (MSP) as a hormone to promote oocyte meiotic
                maturation and gonadal sheath cell contraction at a distance (<link linkend="bib48">Miller et al., 2001</link><!--:
                PMID 11251118-->). MSP is also the key cytoskeletal element required for amoeboid
locomotion of nematode spermatozoa (<link linkend="bib26">Italiano et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8548814-->). MSP
                promotes oocyte meiotic maturation, in part by binding the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-1</ulink> Eph receptor
                protein-tyrosine kinase on oocytes, and in part by antagonizing an inhibitory
                somatic gonadal sheath cell pathway (<link linkend="bib49">Miller et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12533508-->). Since
                hermaphrodites produce only a fixed number of sperm, meiotic maturation rates are
                initially high for the first two days of adulthood, but decline as sperm are used
                for fertilization. In gonochoristic species (e.g., <emphasis>C. remanei</emphasis>),
                oocytes arrest at diakinesis until the female is inseminated during mating.
                Likewise, in sex-determination mutants of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, which
                fully feminize the hermaphrodite gonad, oocytes also arrest until sperm are
                supplied. Thus, the MSP hormone functions as the linchpin of a sperm-sensing
                mechanism linking meiotic maturation and sperm availability, thereby ensuring
                fertilization.</para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Control of oocyte meiotic maturation</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>Oocyte growth, development, and differentiation</title>
            <sect3>
                <title>Pachytene progression and oogenesis</title>
                <para>Progression through pachytene to diplotene requires the mitogen-activated
                    protein kinase (MAPK) signaling pathway in the germ line (<link linkend="bib8">Church et al., 1995</link><!--:
                    PMID 7671816-->). MAPK activation is also involved in meiotic maturation (see
                    below). Mutations in multiple RAS/MAPK pathway components cause a similar
                    phenotype in which germline nuclei arrest in pachytene. The arrested germline
                    nuclei are displaced from the surface of the gonadal tube and clump before the
                    bend (<link linkend="bib8">Church et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7671816-->; <link linkend="bib24">Hsu et al., 2002</link><!--: PMID 11861555-->).</para>
                <para>Whereas the RAS/MAPK pathway is required for fertility in both sexes, the
                        <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=daz-1" role="_blank">daz-1</ulink></emphasis> gene, a homolog of the human Deleted in
                    Azoospermia gene, is specifically required for progression through pachytene
                    during oogenesis (<link linkend="bib33">Karashima et al., 2000</link><!--: PMID 10662646-->). Since
                    <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=daz-1" role="_blank">daz-1</ulink></emphasis> encodes a ribonucleoprotein-type RNA-binding protein,
                    it may regulate translation during female meiotic progression.
                    <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=skr-1" role="_blank">skr-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=skr-2" role="_blank">skr-2</ulink></emphasis>, which encode two of
                    the 21 Skp1-related genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, are also required
                    for progression through pachytene during oogenesis (<link linkend="bib52">Nayak et al., 2002</link><!--:
                    PMID 11864567-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SKP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SKP-1</ulink> and SKP-2 interact with the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CUL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CUL-1</ulink> cullin and are likely to
                    regulate ubiquitin-mediated protein degradation to promote progression through
                    pachytene. The maxi-KH/STAR domain RNA-binding protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLD-1</ulink> is also required
                    for oocyte differentiation (<link linkend="bib15">Francis et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7713419-->; <link linkend="bib29">Jones and Schedl,
                    1995</link><!--: PMID 7601353-->). In the absence of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gld-1" role="_blank">gld-1</ulink></emphasis>, germ cells
                    destined to become oocytes enter meiosis, proceed to pachytene, but then exit
                    meiosis, reentering the mitotic cell cycle to form a germline tumor (<link linkend="bib15">Francis et
                    al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7713419-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLD-1</ulink> functions as a translational repressor protein
                    (<link linkend="bib28">Jan et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 9321409-->; <link linkend="bib38">Lee and Schedl, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11562350-->) that also
                    protects its mRNA targets from nonsense-mediated decay (<link linkend="bib39">Lee and Schedl, 2004</link><!--:
                    PMID 15105376-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLD-1</ulink> protein levels are highest during pachytene, drop sharply
                    as germ cells progress to diplotene, and decrease to undetectable levels in
                    growing oocytes (<link linkend="bib30">Jones et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8948583-->). This observation suggested
                    that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gld-1" role="_blank">gld-1</ulink></emphasis> may prevent the translation of proteins needed for oocyte growth and
                    development in early meiotic prophase. The isolation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLD-1</ulink> mRNA targets by
                    immunoprecipitation identified candidate genes involved in oocyte development or
                    function (<link linkend="bib38">Lee and Schedl, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11562350-->).</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>Oocyte growth</title>
                <para>Oocytes grow in the proximal gonad arm, and accumulate yolk lipoprotein
                    particles. The vitellogenins, protein components of yolk particles, are
                    synthesized in the intestine (<link linkend="bib35">Kimble and Sharrock, 1983</link><!--: PMID 6825952-->) and
                    secreted into the pseudocoelom. Yolk lipoprotein particles appear to pass
                    through the gonadal basal lamina, move through pores in the gonadal sheath cells
                        (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2E</link>), are endocytosed, and stored in
                    membrane-bounded granules within oocytes (<link linkend="bib19">Hall et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10419689-->).
                    Endocytosis, of yolk lipoprotein particles requires the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RME-2;class=protein" role="_blank">RME-2</ulink> yolk receptor, a
                    member of the low-density lipoprotein receptor superfamily (<link linkend="bib16">Grant and Hirsh,
                    1999</link><!--: PMID 10588660-->). The spatial pattern of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rme-2" role="_blank">rme-2</ulink></emphasis>
                    expression is controlled by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gld-1" role="_blank">gld-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib38">Lee and Schedl, 2001</link><!--:
                    PMID 11562350-->) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=atx-2" role="_blank">atx-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib9">Ciosk et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15342467-->).
                    The vitellogenins are cholesterol-binding proteins and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RME-2;class=protein" role="_blank">RME-2</ulink> receptor-mediated
                    endocytosis is required for normal transport of cholesterol into oocytes
                    (<link linkend="bib45">Matyash et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11408580-->). Since adult hermaphrodites turn over the
                    entire volume of the gonad every 6.5 hours, (<link linkend="bib23">Hirsh et al., 1976</link><!--: PMID 943344-->),
                    oocyte growth must be highly regulated. Understanding oocyte growth control is a
                    frontier for the field. Signaling pathways that intersect with meiotic
                    maturation and MAPK pathways appear to be involved (<link linkend="bib18">Gutch et al., 1998</link><!--:
                    PMID 9472025-->; T. Schedl, unpublished results).</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Oocyte meiotic maturation</title>
            <sect3>
                <title>Description of anatomy and timing of events</title>
                <para>Oocyte meiotic maturation can be viewed by time-lapse videomicroscopy of
                    living animals (<link linkend="bib61">Ward and Carrel, 1979</link><!--: PMID 499670-->; <link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link>). The timing of
                    landmark events during meiotic maturation (<link linkend="bib47">McCarter et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 9882501-->)
                    and the ultrastructure of the proximal gonad (<link linkend="bib19">Hall et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10419689-->)
                    have been described. The nuclear envelope of the most proximal oocyte breaks
                    down ~5 min prior to ovulation as it enters meiotic M-phase from prophase
                    (<link linkend="bib47">McCarter et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 9882501-->). During maturation, the oocyte also
                    undergoes a structural change termed cortical rearrangement (<link linkend="bib47">McCarter et al.,
                    1999</link><!--: PMID 9882501-->). These changes within the oocyte coincide with a reproducible
                    sequence of somatic motor events mediated by the contractile proximal sheath
                    cells (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2A</link>, <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2D</link>) and the distal spermatheca resulting in
                    ovulation. The gonadal sheath cells form gap junctions with oocytes (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2D</link>, <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2E</link>) and regulate meiotic
                    maturation and ovulation (<link linkend="bib17">Greenstein et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID 7958868-->; <link linkend="bib46">McCarter et al.,
                    1997</link><!--: PMID 9013925-->; <link linkend="bib56">Rose et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9405097-->; <link linkend="bib49">Miller et al., 2003</link><!--:
                    PMID 12533508-->).</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>The MSP signal</title>
                <para>In a landmark study, <link linkend="bib47">McCarter et al., (1999</link><!--: PMID 9882501-->) showed that a
                    sperm-associated signal promotes oocyte meiotic maturation independent of
                    fertilization. In females (genetically altered XX animals that produce no
                    sperm), oocytes mature and are ovulated at low rates (<symbol role="symbolfont"
                        >&#x003C;</symbol> 0.1 maturations per gonad per hr). Mating to
                    wild-type males, or fertilization incompetent sperm defective
                    (<emphasis>spe</emphasis>) mutants restores the normal rate of oocyte maturation
                    when sperm are plentiful (~2.5 maturations per gonad per hr). Until recently, a
                    key unanswered question in the field concerned the nature of the sperm signal
                    for oocyte meiotic maturation. <link linkend="bib48">Miller et al. (2001</link><!--: PMID 11251118-->) demonstrated
                    that the major sperm protein (MSP), the central cytoskeletal element required
                    for the actin-independent motility of nematode spermatozoa, has a dual role in
                        <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> reproduction, functioning as a hormone for
                    oocyte meiotic maturation and gonadal sheath cell contraction. An <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis>
                    bioassay was developed in which sperm-conditioned medium or sperm lysates were
                    injected into the uterus of unmated <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fog-2" role="_blank">fog-2</ulink></emphasis> female animals,
                    and oocyte meiotic maturation and gonadal sheath cell contraction were monitored
                    by time-lapse videomicroscopy. The bioactive factors were purified to
                    homogeneity with reversed-phase high-performance liquid chromatography and shown
                    to contain only MSP by mass spectrometry. Injection of MSP antibodies into the
                    uterus of hermaphrodites results in a reduction in ovulation rates, consistent
                    with the hypothesis that MSP is an endogenous signal. <emphasis>C.
                    elegans</emphasis> MSP can signal in <emphasis>C. remanei</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib48">Miller et
                    al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11251118-->) and <emphasis>Ascaris</emphasis> MSP can signal in <emphasis>C.
                    elegans</emphasis> (M. Kosinski and D.G., unpublished results), consistent with
                    observations of heterospecific matings in the genus
                    <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib22">Hill and L’Hernault, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11254351-->).</para>
                <para>MAPK activation plays critical roles in regulating meiotic progression
                    (<link linkend="bib13">Ferrell, 1999</link><!--: PMID 10497333-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, the MAPK
                    pathway is required for pachytene progression (<link linkend="bib8">Church et al., 1995</link><!--: PMID 7671816-->)
                    and is important for meiotic maturation (M.-H. Lee and T. Schedl, pers. comm.).
                    Proximal oocytes exhibit MAPK activation in the presence of sperm (<link linkend="bib48">Miller et
                    al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11251118-->; <link linkend="bib54">Page et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID  11463371-->), and MSP was shown to
                    be sufficient to activate MAPK in oocytes (<link linkend="bib48">Miller et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11251118-->).
                    MSP begins as a cytoplasmic protein and does not possess a signal sequence.
                    Recent results suggest that MSP is exported from spermatids and spermatozoa by a
                    vesicle budding mechanism (M. Kosinski, K. McDonald, J. Schwartz, I. Yamamoto,
                    and D. G., unpublished results).</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3>
                <title>MSP signaling and the sperm-sensing mechanism</title>
                <para>The identification of MSP’s signaling role posed the problem of how oocytes
                    and sheath cells sense MSP. A key advance was the identification of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-1</ulink>
                    Eph receptor protein-tyrosine kinase as an MSP receptor (<link linkend="bib49">Miller et al., 2003</link><!--:
                    PMID 12533508-->; reviewed by <link linkend="bib37">Kuwabara, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12533505-->). Recent results show
                    that the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-1</ulink> ectodomain directly binds MSP in vitro (H. Cheng and D. G.,
                    unpublished results). The observation that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=vab-1" role="_blank">vab-1</ulink></emphasis> null mutant oocytes respond to
                    and bind MSP, suggests the involvement of additional MSP receptors.
                        <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=vab-1" role="_blank">vab-1</ulink></emphasis> was shown to function in parallel to a somatic
                    gonadal pathway (<link linkend="bib49">Miller et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12533508-->), defined by the POU-class
                    homeobox gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-18" role="_blank">ceh-18</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib17">Greenstein et al., 1994</link><!--: PMID 7958868-->;
                    <link linkend="bib56">Rose et al., 1997</link><!--: PMID 9405097-->). These parallel pathways negatively regulate
                    oocyte maturation and MAPK activation in hermaphrodite and female gonads.
                    Eliminating <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=vab-1" role="_blank">vab-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-18" role="_blank">ceh-18</ulink> </emphasis>function
                    removes the dependence of meiotic maturation and ovulation on the presence of
                    sperm. Therefore, this meiotic control mechanism resembles a cell cycle
                    checkpoint (<link linkend="bib21">Hartwell and Weinert, 1989</link><!--: PMID 2683079-->) and may confer a selective
                    advantage in hermaphrodite and female species by conserving metabolically costly
                    oocytes when sperm are unavailable for fertilization.</para>
                <para>Positive effectors of oocyte meiotic maturation have been identified in <emphasis>C.
                    elegans</emphasis>, including the cyclin-dependent kinase homolog <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CDK-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CDK-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib4">Boxem et al. 1999</link><!--:
                    PMID 11684669-->) and the polo-like kinase homolog <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PLK-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib7">Chase et al. 2000</link><!--:
                    PMID 10660671-->). The zinc finger domain–containing proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=OMA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">OMA-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=OMA-2;class=protein" role="_blank">OMA-2</ulink> are
                    redundantly required for oocyte maturation and ovulation (<link linkend="bib12">Detwiler et al. 2001</link><!--:
                    PMID 11702779-->). In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=oma-1" role="_blank">oma-1</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=oma-2" role="_blank">oma-2</ulink></emphasis> double mutants, MAPK
                    activation is not sustained and nuclear envelope breakdown does not occur. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=OMA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">OMA-1</ulink>
                    and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=OMA-2;class=protein" role="_blank">OMA-2</ulink> may function upstream of two conserved cell cycle regulators, the
                    MYT1–related kinase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=WEE-1.3;class=protein" role="_blank">WEE-1.3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CDK-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CDK-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib12">Detwiler et al. 2001</link><!--: PMID 11702779-->).
                    Since <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=OMA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">OMA-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=OMA-2;class=protein" role="_blank">OMA-2</ulink> contain zinc finger domains, they could function as
                    regulators of translation or as regulators of proteolysis (<link linkend="bib11">DeRenzo et al., 2003</link><!--:
                    PMID 12894212-->).</para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Control of ovulation</title>
        <para>The ovulatory process represents an attractive physiological model for how
            intercellular signaling affects smooth muscle function. Ovulation involves the
            coordinated function of the gonadal sheath cells, specialized smooth-muscle-like cells
            that surround oocytes (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). During ovulation, the proximal
            gonadal sheath cells contract rapidly, the distal constriction of the spermatheca
            dilates, and sheath cells pull the distal spermatheca over the mature oocyte (<link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link>).
            The maturing oocyte signals its own ovulation in two ways: it modulates sheath
            contractions, which includes an increase in contraction rate and intensity during
            ovulation, and it induces spermathecal dilation during ovulation (<link linkend="bib47">McCarter et al., 1999</link><!--:
            PMID 9882501-->). Spermathecal dilation is regulated by a
            LIN-3(EGF)/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-23;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-23</ulink>(EGF-receptor) signal transduction pathway
            mediating the signal from oocyte to the distal spermatheca (<link linkend="bib10">Clandinin et al., 1998</link><!--:
            PMID 9491893-->; T. Schedl, unpublished results). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-23" role="_blank">let-23</ulink></emphasis> pathway
            required for spermathecal dilation during ovulation is
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-60" role="_blank">let-60</ulink></emphasis><emphasis>(ras)</emphasis>-independent and involves a downstream IP3-mediated
            pathway (<link linkend="bib10">Clandinin et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9491893-->). Dominant gain-of-function mutations in
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-60" role="_blank">let-60</ulink></emphasis>(ras) also perturb ovulation, suggesting that
            ras-dependent pathways are also involved (T. Schedl, unpublished results). Mutations in
            two genes, <emphasis>lfe-1</emphasis>/<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=itr-1" role="_blank">itr-1</ulink></emphasis> and
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lfe-2" role="_blank">lfe-2</ulink></emphasis>, (gain-of-function and loss-of-function, respectively) were
            isolated in a genetic screen for suppressors of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-23" role="_blank">let-23</ulink></emphasis> sterility
            defects. <emphasis>lfe-1</emphasis>/<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=itr-1" role="_blank">itr-1</ulink></emphasis> and
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lfe-2" role="_blank">lfe-2</ulink></emphasis> genes encode an inositol (1, 4, 5) triphosphate receptor and
            an inositol (1, 4, 5) triphosphate-3-kinase, respectively (<link linkend="bib10">Clandinin et al., 1998</link><!--:
            PMID 9491893-->). These results suggest that spermathecal dilation is likely to be dependent
            on calcium release regulated by IP3. Consistent with this possibility, a mutant allele
            of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ipp-5" role="_blank">ipp-5</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a type I 5-phosphatase, predicted to lower
            IP3 levels, exhibits a novel ovulation phenotype in which the spermatheca overextends,
            thereby ovulating two oocytes per cycle (<link linkend="bib5">Bui and Sternberg, 2002</link><!--: PMID 12006659-->).
            Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=plc-1" role="_blank">plc-1</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a phospholipase C epsilon
            homolog, or <emphasis>plc-1(RNAi)</emphasis>, also result in spermathecal entry and exit
            defects (<link linkend="bib34">Kariya et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15355798-->; <link linkend="bib65">Yin et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15194811-->).
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-23" role="_blank">let-23</ulink></emphasis>-mediated IP3 signaling also plays a role in promoting
            the ovulatory gonadal sheath cell contractions (<link linkend="bib65">Yin et al., 2004</link><!--: PMID 15194811-->).</para>
           <para>Mutations that lead to defective ovulation cause an endomitotic oocyte (Emo) phenotype
           (<link linkend="bib27">Iwasaki et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8707849-->). When oocytes are retained in the gonad arm due to
           defective ovulation, they undergo multiple rounds of nuclear envelope breakdown (M-phase
           entry) and S-phase, and become highly polyploid. A large class of genes can mutate to an
            Emo phenotype and these include <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=emo-1" role="_blank">emo-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib27">Iwasaki et al., 1996</link><!--:
            PMID 8707849-->), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mup-2" role="_blank">mup-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib51">Myers et al., 1996</link><!--: PMID 8601585-->),
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mel-11" role="_blank">mel-11</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib63">Wissmann et al., 1999</link><!--: PMID 10208747-->), tropomyosin, and
            troponin C (<link linkend="bib53">Ono and Ono, 2004</link><!--: PMID 15064356-->) as well as genes involved in sheath or
            spermathecal development (<link linkend="bib36">Kostic et al., 2003</link><!--PMID 14597199-->; <link linkend="bib2">Aono et al., 2004</link><!--:
            PMID 1515198-->). In the future, studies of the physiology of ovulation will no doubt
            benefit from the ability to measure calcium concentrations in the gonad (<link linkend="bib58">Samuel et al.,
            2001</link><!--: PMID 11346453-->) and to record oocyte ion channels (<link linkend="bib57">Rutledge et al., 2001</link><!--:
            PMID 11231150-->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Control of fertilization</title>
        <para>Successful fertilization depends on a series of gametic interactions in which
            spermatozoa and oocyte recognize each other, bind, and fuse (reviewed by <link linkend="bib20">Hardy, 2002</link>).
            Egg activation (the process whereby the oocyte completes the meiotic divisions), a block
            to polyspermy, and activation of the embryonic program are dependent on fertilization.
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> provides a promising experimental system for
            examining fertilization because of the availability of fertilization-defective mutants
            (<link linkend="bib40">L’Hernault et al., 1988</link><!--: PMID 3197956-->; reviewed by <link linkend="bib59">Singson, 2001</link><!--: PMID 11161565-->). The
            central finding for the field was the phenotypic characterization and molecular cloning
            of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-9" role="_blank">spe-9</ulink></emphasis>, a gene whose function is required in sperm for
            fertilization (<link linkend="bib60">Singson et al., 1998</link><!--: PMID 9546393-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-9" role="_blank">spe-9</ulink></emphasis>
            spermatozoa are fertilization defective, despite being able to crawl, signal meiotic
            maturation, and contact ovulated oocytes. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-9" role="_blank">spe-9</ulink></emphasis> mutations do not
            affect spermiogenesis, and the mutant spermatozoa have a normal morphology at the EM
            level. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-9" role="_blank">spe-9</ulink></emphasis> encodes a transmembrane protein containing an
            extracellular domain with 10 EGF-like repeats. Based on these results, <link linkend="bib60">Singson et al.
            (1998</link><!--: PMID 9546393-->) proposed that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-9" role="_blank">spe-9</ulink></emphasis> may function as a ligand
            for an oocyte receptor. Analysis of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-9" role="_blank">spe-9</ulink></emphasis>-deletion derivatives
            using a transgenic assay is consistent with this proposal and indicates that the
            EGF-like repeats and the transmembrane segment are required for function (<link linkend="bib55">Putiri et al.,
            2004</link><!--: PMID 15282160-->). By contrast, the cytoplasmic domain was dispensable, ruling out the
            possibility that this region plays a signaling role within spermatozoa.
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-9" role="_blank">spe-9</ulink></emphasis> localizes to the membrane of spermatids, but reorganizes to
            the pseudopod during spermiogenesis (<link linkend="bib66">Zannoni et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 14653860-->; <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). Based on this result, <link linkend="bib66">Zannoni et al. (2003</link><!--: PMID 14653860-->)
            proposed that the spermatozoan interacts with the oocyte cell surface in a “pseudopod
            first” manner. While there are no published ultrastructural observations of
            fertilization events in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, Foor (1968<!--: PMID 5678444-->)
            reported a striking series of EM observations of fertilization in Ascaris lumbricoides,
            which provided evidence for initial contact of the pseudopod with the mature oocyte,
            fusion of cell membranes during fertilization, and first entry of the pseudopodal
            extension. The identification of oocyte cell surface molecules that mediate
            fertilization interactions is an exciting area for future work.</para>
    <mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata entityref="fig3" align="center" width="4in"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
            <phrase> figure 3</phrase>
        </textobject> &fig3legend;
</mediaobject>
        <para>Further studies of fertilization-defective mutations of the
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-9" role="_blank">spe-9</ulink></emphasis> class promise essential information on gametic interactions
            needed for fertilization. These mutations include <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-13" role="_blank">spe-13</ulink></emphasis>,
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-38" role="_blank">spe-38</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-42" role="_blank">spe-42</ulink></emphasis>,
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fer-14" role="_blank">fer-14</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis>trp-3</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib60">Singson et al., 1998</link><!--:
            PMID 9546393-->; <link linkend="bib64">Xu and Sternberg, 2003</link><!--: PMID 12914694-->; A. Singson, T. Kroft, and S.
            L’Hernault, unpublished results). <link linkend="bib64">Xu and Sternberg (2003</link><!--: PMID 12914694-->) reported an
            extensive characterization of <emphasis>trp-3</emphasis> (aka
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spe-41" role="_blank">spe-41</ulink></emphasis>), which encodes a member of the transient receptor potential
            (TRP) superfamily of cation channels. While <emphasis>trp-3</emphasis> plays a critical role in
            fertilization, it is not absolutely essential because hermaphrodites homozygous for
            likely <emphasis>trp-3</emphasis> null mutations have brood sizes that are approximately
            5% of the wild type. TRP-3 displays a dynamic localization during spermiogenesis. TRP-3
            localizes to the MOs in spermatids and translocates to the plasma membrane of the cell
            body and pseudopod during spermiogenesis (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). Calcium imaging
            studies provided evidence that TRP-3 may function as a store-operated calcium entry
            (SOCE) channel in spermatozoa. In addition to SOCE channels, spermatozoa contain
            constitutively active calcium-permeable (CAC) channels. While <emphasis>trp-3</emphasis>
            mutant spermatozoa exhibit lower SOCE channel activity than the wild type, the CAC
            channel activity is normal. These results strongly suggest that TRP cation channel
            activity plays an important role in fertilization. In mammals, TRP channels play roles
            in the acrosome reaction (<link linkend="bib31">Jungnickel et al., 2001</link><!--: PMID 11331878-->) and sperm motility
            (<link linkend="bib6">Castellano et al., 2003</link><!--: PMID 12706821-->). Additional members of this large channel family
            may have conserved functions in fertilization.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>Meiotic maturation and fertilization are fundamental developmental events, which have
            been extensively studied for over a hundred years. Yet, the molecular mechanisms
            underlying these critical processes remain incompletely understood. Many exciting
            biological questions surrounding these events remain. For instance, it is unclear how
            meiotic maturation events actually prepare the oocyte for fertilization. The sequence of
            molecular events needed at fertilization and their interdependencies are
            uncharacterized. How fertilization results in egg activation and triggers the embryonic
            program is largely unknown. Recent progress described here gives confidence that
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> provides a fertile field for answering basic
            questions about the fundamental developmental mechanisms of oocyte meiotic maturation
            and fertilization.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Acknowledgments</title>
        <para>I thank Michael Miller, Tim Schedl, Andy Singson, and Steve L’Hernault for
            communicating unpublished results and for discussions. Thanks to Kent McDonald for
            high-pressure freezing electron microscopy. Thanks to Michael Miller, Sean Xu, and Andy
            Singson for assistance with the figures. Judith Kimble, Mary Kosinski, Steve L’Hernault,
            Tim Schedl, and Susan Strome provided valuable comments on the manuscript. Work in my
            laboratory is supported by grants from the National Institutes of Health (GM57173 and
            GM65115).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
		<para/>
		&meiotic_Refs;</sect1>
</article>