<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'obesfatfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'obesfatfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'obesfatfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'obesfatfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'obesfatfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'obesfatfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'obesfatfig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'obesfatfig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'obesfatfig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'obesfatfig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'obesfatfig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'obesfatfig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY obesfat_Refs SYSTEM "obesfatrefs.xml">
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="obesfat_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title>Obesity and the regulation of fat metabolism<footnote>
			<para>Edited by Andres Villu Maricq and Steven L. McIntire. Last revised November 30, 2006. Published March 9, 2007. This chapter should be cited as: Ashrafi, K. Obesity and the regulation of fat metabolism (March 9, 2007), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.130.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2007 Kaveh Ashrafi. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
		<author>
			<firstname>Kaveh</firstname>
			<surname>Ashrafi<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: 415-514-4102, Fax: 415-514-4242. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:kaveh.ashrafi@ucsf.edu">kaveh.ashrafi@ucsf.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></surname>
			<affiliation><address>Department of Physiology, University of California, San Francisco, San Francisco, CA 94143 USA</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">As in all living organisms, survival in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">requires adequate management of energy supplies. Genetic screens have revealed that</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">fat regulation involves a complex network of genes with known or likely functions in food sensation, neuroendocrine signaling, uptake, transport, storage and utilization of fats. Core fat and sugar metabolic pathways are conserved in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans.</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">Flux through these pathways is modulated by cellular energy sensors that operate via transcriptional and translational regulatory mechanisms. In turn, neuroendocrine mechanisms couple sensory and metabolic pathways while neuromodulatory pathways influence both metabolic and food seeking/consumption pathways. The shared ancestry of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">and mammalian fat regulatory pathways extends to developmental programs that underlie fat storage capacity, despite lack of dedicated adipocytes, and genes whose human homologs are implicated in obesity. This suggests that many of the newly identified</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">fat regulatory pathways play similar roles in mammals.</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">is ideally suited for the integrated study of mechanisms that operate in multiple tissues and elicit feedback responses that affect processes as diverse as metabolism and behavior.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Obesity: an overview</title>
<para>Obesity is a significant risk factor for major diseases including Type II diabetes, coronary heart disease, hypertension and certain forms of cancer (<link linkend="bib9">Barsh et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10766251-->; <link linkend="bib53">Kopelman, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10766250-->; <link linkend="bib65">Luchsinger, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16807483-->). Obesity arises when energy intake, principally stored as triglycerides, exceeds energy expenditure (<link linkend="bib28">Flier, 2004</link><!--; PMID 14744442-->; <link linkend="bib95">Spiegelman and Flier, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11239410-->). Obesity is a complex trait influenced by diet, developmental stage, age, physical activity and genes (<link linkend="bib14">Brockmann and Bevova, 2002</link><!--; PMID 12127777-->; <link linkend="bib32">Friedman, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12574619-->).</para>
<para>Genetic predisposition is a key contributing factor in obesity as demonstrated by familial aggregation, twin and adoption studies (<link linkend="bib1">Allison et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8639146-->; <link linkend="bib32">Friedman, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12574619-->; <link linkend="bib96">Stunkard et al., 1990</link><!--; PMID 2336075-->). Estimates for the genetic basis of phenotypic variations in obesity range from approximately 40 to 70&#x00025;. This matches or exceeds the accepted genetic contribution to height (<link linkend="bib32">Friedman, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12574619-->). The idea that genetic loci alter body fat content has been substantiated by identification of mutations that cause low- or high-fat phenotypes in rodents and humans (<link linkend="bib14">Brockmann and Bevova, 2002</link><!--; PMID 12127777-->; <link linkend="bib23">Delrue and Michaud, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15253756-->).</para>
<para>There is convincing experimental evidence showing that the balance between energy intake (food consumption) and energy expenditure (basal metabolic rate, i.e. biochemical processes required to maintain cellular viability, physical activity and adaptive thermogenesis) is tightly regulated. A homeostatic network maintains energy stores through a complex interplay between the feeding regulatory centers in the central nervous system (CNS), particularly in the hypothalamus and the regulated storage and mobilization of fat stores (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>; <link linkend="bib21">Cone, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15856065-->; <link linkend="bib30">Friedman, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10766249-->, <link linkend="bib28">Flier, 2004</link><!-- #101-->; <link linkend="bib88">Sainsbury et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12468411-->; <link linkend="bib95">Spiegelman and Flier, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11239410-->). Thus, genes that encode the molecular components of this system may underlie obesity and related disorders.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>In mammals, white adipose tissue functions as the main depot for fuel storage. In the past decade, identification of myriad lipid and protein signals secreted from this tissue has led to its recognition as a major endocrine organ (<link linkend="bib86">Rondinone, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16622295-->; <link linkend="bib100">Trayhurn and Bing, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16815801-->). This was principally based on the discovery of leptin, a cytokine-like hormone secreted from white adipose tissue in proportion to fat mass (<link linkend="bib33">Friedman and Halaas, 1998</link><!--; PMID 9796811-->). Activation of hypothalamic leptin receptors suppresses food intake and promotes energy expenditure pathways (<link linkend="bib31">Friedman, 2002</link><!--; PMID 12403078-->; <link linkend="bib82">Porte et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12403080-->).</para>
<para>Insulin is another key afferent signal to the CNS that controls energy balance. Insulin is secreted from the endocrine pancreas in proportion to fat mass and exerts potent effects on peripheral nutrient storage. Similar to leptin, insulin causes long-term inhibitory effects on energy intake. There is cross talk between insulin and leptin signaling in a common set of hypothalamic neurons. Moreover, a series of neuropeptides (e.g., the melanocortin system, neuropeptide Y) and neurotransmitters (e.g., serotonin, dopamine and noradrenaline) function in the hypothalamus to coordinate behavioral, physiological and metabolic responses. Together, these responses maintain energy balance via both intake and expenditure pathways (<link linkend="bib21">Cone, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15856065-->; <link linkend="bib82">Porte et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12403080-->; <link linkend="bib88">Sainsbury et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12468411-->).</para>
<para>In addition to these long-term adiposity signals, short-term meal-related signals are transmitted to the CNS through afferent nerves or gut-secreted peptides (e.g., cholecystokinin, ghrelin; <link linkend="bib8">Badman and Flier, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15790843-->). Finally, neurons in the CNS also directly sense carbohydrate and fats (<link linkend="bib24">Demuro and Obici, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16898570-->; <link linkend="bib55">Lam et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15856066-->).</para>
<para>Because energy balance involves this complex interplay between multiple tissues and signaling pathways, an integrated view of feeding behavior, neuroendocrine signaling, nutrient uptake, transport, storage and utilization is required for understanding fat regulation. Moreover, developmental programs that underlie fat storage capacity are fundamental to understanding fat regulation. A wealth of genetic and behavioral tools makes <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> an excellent system for unraveling these complex pathways. Thus, in the past few years, the study of fat in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has emerged as an exciting field that is yielding new insights in the regulation of energy balance at the level of the whole organism.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> fat</title>
<sect2 id="sec2_1">
<title>Fat composition</title>
<para>Several groups have biochemically determined the composition of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> fat content. This is accomplished by extraction of total lipids from whole animals, fractionation to phospholipids and neutral lipid moieties, and further analysis by column and thin-layer chromatography as well as gas-chromatography/mass spectrometry (GC/MS; <link linkend="bib51">Kniazeva et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12586704-->; <link linkend="bib90">Satouchi et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8231660-->; <link linkend="bib108">Watts and Browse, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11972048-->). Triacylglyceride fat stores make up approximately 40&#x02013;55&#x00025; of total lipids depending on diet and growth stage (<link linkend="bib4">Ashrafi, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16581000-->). Phospholipids pools are composed of approximately 55&#x00025; ethanolamine glycerophospholipid, 32&#x00025; choline glycerophospholipid, 8&#x00025; sphingomyelin. Cardiolipin, inositol glycerophospholipids and lyso-cholineglycero- phospholipids account for the remaining 5&#x00025;. Relative abundance of these phospholipid constituents changes with growth temperature (<link linkend="bib90">Satouchi et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8231660-->; <link linkend="bib98">Tanaka et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8934450-->).</para>
<para>Similar to mammals, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> contains a wide range of saturated, monounsaturated and polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs) including arachidonic (20:4n-6) and eicosapentaenoic acid (20:5n-3) as well as monomethyl branched chain fatty acids (mmBCFAs; <link linkend="bib50">Kniazeva et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15340492-->; <link linkend="bib90">Satouchi et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 8231660-->; <link linkend="bib108">Watts and Browse, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11972048-->). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> combines the full range of desaturase and PUFA elongase activities that are found separately in plants and animals, abrogating the requirement for dietary supply of linoleic acid (18:2n6) and linolenic acid (18:3n3), which are essential fatty acids in mammalian diets (<link linkend="bib13">Brock et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839188-->; <link linkend="bib106">Wallis et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12217522-->; <link linkend="bib108">Watts and Browse, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11972048-->). Inactivation of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> desaturase and elongase family members, encoded by <emphasis>fat</emphasis> and <emphasis>elo</emphasis> genes, respectively, causes imbalances in fatty acid composition and is associated with metabolic, physiological and behavioral phenotypes. These include altered total fat levels, growth retardation, slowed movement, reduction in body size, germ cell maintenance and reproductive defects, aberrations in rhythmic behavior, defects in sensory signaling, defects in neurotransmission and reduced adult lifespan (<link linkend="bib13">Brock et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839188-->; <link linkend="bib48">Kahn-Kirby et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15607983-->; <link linkend="bib50">Kniazeva et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15340492-->; <link linkend="bib51">Kniazeva et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12586704-->; <link linkend="bib60">Lesa et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14625390-->; <link linkend="bib101">Van Gilst et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15719061-->; <link linkend="bib109">Watts and Browse, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16487504-->; <link linkend="bib110">Watts et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12618397-->). Some of the reported phenotypes may be indirect consequences of global alterations in fat levels and membrane composition.</para>
<para>Finally, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are cholesterol auxotrophs requiring dietary supply of this sterol. Given the small quantities of cholesterol needed for viability, it has been postulated that cholesterol functions as a precursor for sterol-derived hormones rather than playing a structural role in membrane composition and fluidity (<link linkend="bib54">Kurzchalia and Ward, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12894170-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec2_2">
<title>Visualization of fat droplets</title>
<para>Whereas mammals have dedicated adipocytes, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> store fat in droplets in their intestinal cells and in their hypodermal cells (see <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). Because <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have transparent bodies, these fat stores can be directly visualized in intact animals. A classic method is to stain fixed animals with the fat-soluble dye Sudan Black B (see <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2F and G</link>; <link linkend="bib49">Kimura et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9252323-->), which produces a blue-black stain visible under a standard dissection microscope.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="6in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Intestinal lipid droplets can also be visualized by supplementing the normal laboratory diet of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> with Nile Red or BODIPY-labeled fatty acids (4,4-difluoro-5-methyl-4-bora-3a,4a-diaza-s-indacene-3-dodecanoic acid and 4,4-difluoro-5-octoyl-4-bora-3a,4a-diaza-s-indacene-3-pentanoic acid; <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2C&#x02013;E</link>; <link linkend="bib5">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529643-->). These dyes have greatly facilitated the genetic analysis of fat regulation as they allow for easy visualization of lipids in living nematodes. These compounds are brightly fluorescent and, have been used to visualize lipid droplets in cultured mammalian cells. These vital dyes do not produce any adverse effects on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> growth rate, brood-size, pharyngeal pumping, dauer (a larval hibernation state) formation and recovery or lifespan. One limitation is that Nile Red and BODIPY-labeled fatty acid staining methods do not distinguish between animals with reduced fat levels and animals that fail to uptake these compounds. In such cases, Sudan Black B staining is the preferred method.</para>
<para>Fat visualization as well as direct examination of fat composition by GC/MS have formed the basis of genetic screens for identifying <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> fat regulatory pathways (<link linkend="bib5">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529643-->; <link linkend="bib72">McKay et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12530969-->; <link linkend="bib108">Watts and Browse, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11972048-->). Unlike the GC/MS method, Sudan Black B., Nile Red and BODIPY-labeled fatty acids do not distinguish between different lipid compositions as these dyes have a general preference for hydrophobic moieties.</para>
</sect2>
<?newpage?>
<sect2 id="sec2_3">
<title>Genetic analysis of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> fat regulation</title>
<para>Targeted gene deletions, mutagenesis screens and a genome-scale RNA interference (RNAi) screen have identified approximately 300 gene inactivations that cause fat reduction and approximately 100 gene inactivations that cause fat accumulation without significant effects on growth and viability (<link linkend="bib5">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529643-->; <link linkend="bib45">Jia et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15253933-->; <link linkend="bib50">Kniazeva et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15340492-->; <link linkend="bib51">Kniazeva et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12586704-->; <link linkend="bib66">Ludewig et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15314028-->; <link linkend="bib68">Mak et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16462744-->; <link linkend="bib72">McKay et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12530969-->; <link linkend="bib75">Mukhopadhyay et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16054097-->; <link linkend="bib99">Taubert et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16651656-->; <link linkend="bib101">Van Gilst et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15719061-->; <link linkend="bib104">Vellai et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14668850-->; <link linkend="bib108">Watts and Browse, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11972048-->; <link linkend="bib112">Yang et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16799563-->). Another approximately 250 gene inactivations cause dramatic fat reductions concomitant with defects ranging from sterility to growth arrest and lethality. Because of these pleiotropies, it is difficult to assign specific fat regulatory functions to such genes although they include some well-known components of metabolism.</para>
<para>The analysis of the genes identified through these screens is still in its infancy; however, recent reports demonstrate that they regulate fat content through diverse physiological processes. The shared ancestry of the mammalian and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> fat regulatory pathways is highlighted in the sections below.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Metabolic pathways</title>
<para>Intricate metabolic networks tightly coordinate the flow of sugars and fats through synthesis, storage, and breakdown pathways. These pathways are summarized in <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="6in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<sect2 id="sec3_1">
<title>Breakdown pathways</title>
<para>In general, cells break down carbohydrates, amino acids and fats to generate ATP, the universal energy resource of cells (<link linkend="bib89">Salway, 2004</link><!--; PMID-->). Carbohydrates are broken down via glycolytic enzymes to pyruvate and further to acetylCoA which powers generation of NADH and FADH<subscript>2</subscript> through the tricarboxylic acid cycle (TCA) cycle. In turn, NADH and FADH<subscript>2</subscript> are used to generate ATP via oxidative phosphorylation and ATP synthesis. Mobilization of stored triacylglycerides is initiated by lipolytic enzymes such as hormone-sensitive lipase. Liberated fatty acids are then activated to their respective acyl-CoA derivates by acyl-CoA synthases/ligases. Breakdown of fatty acyl-CoAs to acetyl-CoA occurs in peroxisomes or mitochondria via <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation enzymes (<link linkend="bib89">Salway, 2004</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3_2">
<title>Synthesis and storage pathways</title>
<para>Acetyl-CoA is the key substrate for synthesis of fatty acids. Acetyl-CoA is carboxylated by acetyl-CoA carboxylase (ACC) to form malonyl-CoA, which is then elongated by fatty acid synthase (FAS) in a step-wise fashion to generate fatty acids of different lengths, mainly C16:0. Products of FAS are then acted upon by fatty acid desaturases to generate unsaturated fatty acids (see <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link> and <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>). Storage of fatty acids involves the step-wise conversion of fatty acyl-CoAs derived from exogenous or endogenous sources to phosphotidic acid, diacylglycerol and ultimately triacylglycerols (see <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>; <link linkend="bib89">Salway, 2004</link><!--; PMID-->).</para>
<para>Glucose is synthesized by gluconeogenic enzymes. One substrate for gluconeogenesis is glycerol, which can be derived from breakdown of triacylglycerides. Depending on tissue, excess carbohydrates may be stored as glycogen. Alternatively, they are broken down to acetyl-CoA by glycolysis, and then converted to and stored as fats. Moreover, the glyoxylate pathway allows the interconversion of carbohydrates and fats through components of the TCA cycle.</para>
<para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome encodes proteins with sequence homology to conserved components of carbohydrate and lipid synthesis and breakdown. Annotations of metabolic pathways are found at <ulink url="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/pathway.html" role="_blank">KEGG</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.reactome.org/" role="_blank">Reactome</ulink> databases. A partial list is presented in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>.</para>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="100%">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1. Partial listing of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">metabolic pathways deduced from the genome sequence.</emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c2" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><emphasis role="bold">Carbohydrate metabolism</emphasis></entry>
<entry><emphasis role="bold">Lipid metabolism</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Glycolysis/Gluconeogenesis</entry>
<entry>Lipolysis (hormone sensitive lipase)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Glycogen synthesis/Glyogen breakdown</entry>
<entry>Carnitine shuttle (fatty acid uptake)</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Trehalose synthesis/Trehalose breakdown</entry>
<entry>Mitochondrial <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Galactose metabolism</entry>
<entry>Peroxisomal <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Fructose and mannose metabolism</entry>
<entry>Glycerol catabolism</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Glyoxylate pathway</entry>
<entry>Fatty acid synthesis</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Citric acid (TCA) cycle</entry>
<entry>Fatty acid elongation and desaturation</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry/>
<entry>Triacylglyceride synthesis</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis role="bold">Energy metabolism</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Phospholipids biosynthesis</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>Oxidative phosphorylation</entry>
<entry>Synthesis and utilization of ketone bodies</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>ATP synthesis</entry>
<entry>Sphingolipid and ceramide synthesis</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> metabolic pathways have been examined most extensively in the context of insulin signaling. This is because down-regulation of insulin signaling confers an extended adult lifespan as well as promoting dauer formation, the larval hibernation stage (see aging and dauer chapters in Post-embryonic development section of WormBook). Increased fat accumulation and altered metabolism are hallmarks of the long-lived, stress resistant dauers. Similarly, loss of function of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis>, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> insulin-receptor, causes fat accumulation in adults (see <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>). Measurements of metabolic rate, as assessed by CO<subscript>2</subscript> release, biochemical activity assessment of several key enzymes, microarray and serial analysis of gene expression, have all indicated global shifts in metabolic pathways associated with dauer larvae and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> mutant adults (<link linkend="bib12">Braeckman et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12882336-->; <link linkend="bib15">Burnell et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16221538-->; <link linkend="bib34">Gems, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10469585-->; <link linkend="bib36">Halaschek-Wiener et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15837805-->; <link linkend="bib40">Holt and Riddle, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12875742-->; <link linkend="bib46">Jones et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11483575-->; <link linkend="bib57">Larsen et al., 1995</link><!--; PMID 7789761-->; <link linkend="bib59">Lee et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12690206-->; <link linkend="bib67">Lund et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12372248-->; <link linkend="bib70">McElwee et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15308663-->; <link linkend="bib71">McElwee et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16522328-->; <link linkend="bib76">Murphy et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12845331-->; <link linkend="bib103">Van Voorhies and Ward, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10500188-->; <link linkend="bib105">Wadsworth and Riddle, 1989</link><!--; PMID 2917691-->; <link linkend="bib107">Wang and Kim, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12620986-->). In general, these shifts are reminiscent of metabolic adjustments observed in nutrient deprived or fasting mammals. These adjustments favor energy conservation, fat storage, and utilization of stored reservoirs. One complexity in interpreting these studies is that they analyze mRNAs and proteins extracted from whole animals. Since different tissues play different roles in energy balance, it is likely that identical metabolic pathways are modulated differentially in separate tissues.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 4</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Genetic alterations of metabolic enzymes profoundly impact fat levels in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. For example, RNAi inactivation of key glycolic and gluconeogenic genes such as GAPDH, an insulin-regulated glycolytic enzyme, and PEPCK, a regulated enzyme of gluconeogenesis and glyceroneogenesis, cause fat reduction (<link linkend="bib5">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529643-->). Similarly, inactivations of fatty acid synthesis (e.g., acetylCoA carboxylate and fatty acid synthase), phospholipid synthesis (e.g., serine palmitoyltransferase, choline/ethanoloaminephosphotransferase) and triglyceride synthesis (e.g., glycerol-3-phosphate acyltransferase) pathways cause reductions in lipid accumulation and, in some cases, are associated with growth arrest (see <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link> and <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>; <link linkend="bib5">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529643-->). Inactivation of fatty acid oxidation genes causes either decreased or increased fat levels (<link linkend="bib5">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529643-->; <link linkend="bib68">Mak et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16462744-->; <link linkend="bib101">Van Gilst et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15719061-->). The basis for this paradoxical result is not yet clear but likely reflects compensatory and homeostatic mechanisms. Not surprisingly, inactivation of oxidative phosphorylation and ATP synthesis components is generally associated with profound reductions in fat levels concomitant with growth defects (K. Ashrafi, unpublished observations).</para>
<para>Inhibition of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> genes encoding delta-9 fatty acid desaturation enzymes is associated with reduced fat levels. Interestingly, RNAi inactivation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> causes fat reduction and shortened lifespan, phenotypes not seen in a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> deletion mutation (<link linkend="bib13">Brock et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839188-->; <link linkend="bib101">Van Gilst et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15719061-->). This discrepancy may be explained by the observation that loss of function mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink></emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> cause compensatory transcriptional responses in the remaining delta-9 desaturase genes. Accordingly, triple <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis> are embryonic lethal (<link linkend="bib13">Brock et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839188-->).</para>
<para>Mammalian delta-9 stearoyl-CoA desaturase-1 (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SCD-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SCD-1</ulink>) has emerged as a therapeutic target for obesity and metabolic disorders. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SCD-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SCD-1</ulink> is a target of leptin signaling. Significantly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SCD-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SCD-1</ulink> knock-out mice display dramatic reductions in adiposity on otherwise wild-type or leptin deficient (<emphasis>ob/ob</emphasis>) backgrounds (<link linkend="bib19">Cohen and Friedman, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15333742-->; <link linkend="bib20">Cohen et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14683458-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SCD-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SCD-1</ulink> deficiency promotes <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation pathways and decreases lipogenesis in liver and skeletal muscle. One proposed mechanism is that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SCD-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SCD-1</ulink> inhibition results in accumulation of saturated fatty acylCoAs which cause feedback inhibition of acyl-CoA carboxylase (ACC), the rate-limiting enzyme of fatty acid synthesis. ACC inhibition results in reduced accumulation of its product, malonylCoA, which in turn, relieves inhibition of carnitine-palmityol-transferase (CPT) shuttle. This allows for transport of fats into mitochondria for breakdown via <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation (see <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>; <link linkend="bib19">Cohen and Friedman, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15333742-->; <link linkend="bib20">Cohen et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14683458-->). Whether similar mechanisms account for fat reduction of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> deficient in desaturase activity is not known. However, as in mammals, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> delta-9 fatty acid desaturases are transcriptionally regulated by sterol response element binding protein and nuclear hormone receptors (see <link linkend="sec4_1">sections 4.1</link> and <link linkend="sec4_2">4.2</link> below; <link linkend="bib13">Brock et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839188-->; <link linkend="bib99">Taubert et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16651656-->; <link linkend="bib101">Van Gilst et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15719061-->)</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 5</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Metabolic sensors and coordinated regulation of metabolic pathways</title>
<para>The capacity to coordinately adjust energy flux through various catabolic and anabolic pathways in response to changing nutritional status is critical for cellular and organismal survival. Metabolic sensing mechanisms are thought to coordinate these responses (<link linkend="bib61">Lindsley and Rutter, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15581787-->). How alterations in energy status are sensed is a vibrant field of research. On a cellular level, metabolic sensors respond to altered concentrations of macronutrients, e.g., glucose, amino acids and fatty acids, metabolites derived from these macronutrients and energy resources such as ATP and NADH. In multicellular organisms, energetic status of different tissues is further coordinated through hormonal signals (<link linkend="bib61">Lindsley and Rutter, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15581787-->; <link linkend="bib89">Salway, 2004</link><!--; PMID-->). Recent studies in mammals indicate that some of these cellular metabolic sensors also function in the nervous system to regulate behavioral responses (<link linkend="bib74">Minokoshi et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15058305-->; <link linkend="bib83">Porte et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15855309-->). Several such <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> pathways are highlighted below:</para>
<sect2 id="sec4_1">
<title><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink></emphasis></title>
<para>Sterol response element binding protein (SREBP) is a key transcriptional regulator of fat and sterol synthesis pathways in mammals (<link linkend="bib25">Eberle et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15589694-->; <link linkend="bib84">Rawson, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12923525-->). RNAi inhibition and loss of function mutations in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> SREBP, Y47D38.7/<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink>/lpd-1</emphasis>, cause dramatic reductions in fat content and biogenesis of intestinal lipid droplets (<link linkend="bib4">Ashrafi, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16581000-->; <link linkend="bib72">McKay et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12530969-->; <link linkend="bib112">Yang et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16799563-->). Thus far, analysis of candidate <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink></emphasis> targets in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has been reported for malic enzyme (ME), and ATP citrate-lyase (ACL), acyl-CoA carboxylase (ACC), fatty acid synthase (FAS), stearoyl-CoA desaturases (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=FAT-6;class=Protein" role="_blank">FAT-6</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=FAT-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">FAT-7</ulink>), and glycerol 3-phosphate acyltransferase (G3PA; <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>; <link linkend="bib72">McKay et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12530969-->; <link linkend="bib112">Yang et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16799563-->). The mammalian homologs of each of these lipogenic genes are direct SREBP targets. Additionally, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink></emphasis> regulates expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elo-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">elo-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=elo-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">elo-6</ulink></emphasis>, two fatty acid elongation enzymes required for synthesis of monomethyl branched chain fatty acids (<link linkend="bib50">Kniazeva et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15340492-->).</para>
<para>Further conservation of function for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink></emphasis> has emerged from studies in which <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink></emphasis> stimulated transcription of mammalian SREBP targets in a human cell line. Moreover, in both mammalian cells and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, SREBP function requires physical interaction with a transcriptional co-activator, ARC105/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-15;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-15</ulink> (<link linkend="bib112">Yang et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16799563-->; see <link linkend="sec4_2">section 4.2</link>).</para>
<para>Given that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are cholesterol auxotrophs, it remains to be determined whether any sterol metabolic pathways are regulated by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink></emphasis>. One function of cholesterol in mammalian cells is to regulate membrane fluidity. Interestingly, <emphasis>Drosophila melanogaster</emphasis>, also a cholesterol auxotroph, regulates its membrane fluidity through an SREBP-mediated transcriptional program that produces phosphotidylethanolamine (<link linkend="bib92">Seegmiller et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11832248-->). It is likely that a similar mechanism regulates membrane fluidity in <emphasis>C. elegans.</emphasis> Also, it remains to be determined if, as in mammals, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> insulin signaling regulates <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink></emphasis> function.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_2">
<title><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink></emphasis></title>
<para>In mammals, several nuclear hormone receptors (NHRs) function as metabolic sensors and master regulators of energy balance (<link linkend="bib17">Chawla et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11729302-->; <link linkend="bib26">Evans et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15057233-->; <link linkend="bib77">Nakamura et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15726822-->). The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome contains a remarkable number of NHRs yet none display sequence homology to the Peroxisome Proliferator-Activated Receptor (PPAR) family, which are key regulators of fat, cholesterol and glucose homeostasis (<link linkend="bib35">Gissendanner et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14738886-->; <link linkend="bib94">Sluder and Maina, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11275326-->). Instead, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NHR-49;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHR-49</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-15;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-15</ulink> system serves a parallel function to mammalian PPAR<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> and its co-activator, PGC-1.</para>
<para>A deletion mutation in the HNF-4<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> family member <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> mimics the high fat phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> RNAi (<link linkend="bib5">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529643-->; <link linkend="bib101">Van Gilst et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15719061-->). Analysis of genes in fat metabolic pathways (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>) by quantitative RT-PCR revealed that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> causes down-regulation of three genes encoding mitochondrial <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation enzymes and concomitant up-regulation of three genes that encode peroxisomal <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation enzymes (<link linkend="bib101">Van Gilst et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15719061-->). Down-regulation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=acs-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-2</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ech-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ech-1</ulink></emphasis>, two of the three affected mitochondrial <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation genes, causes fat accumulation, and over-expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=acs-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">acs-2</ulink></emphasis> suppresses the high fat phenotype of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib101">Van Gilst et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15719061-->). This suggests that down-regulation of mitochondrial <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation underlies excess fat levels of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> inactivation. Similar to mammalian PPAR<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> also regulates expression of fatty acid desaturation and lipid binding proteins. Interestingly, changes in expression patterns of fat metabolic genes caused by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> inactivation overlap with expression changes noted after 12 hours of food deprivation (<link linkend="bib101">Van Gilst et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15719061-->; <link linkend="bib102">Van Gilst et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16157872-->). Thus, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> responds to nutrient signals and functions as a regulatory node of metabolic gene expression.</para>
<para>The transcriptional co-activator, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink>/arc105</emphasis>, was found to interact with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> in a yeast two-hybrid assay (<link linkend="bib99">Taubert et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16651656-->). Many of the metabolic gene expression changes noted for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> are similarly altered in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink>/arc105</emphasis> knock-down animals. Although overlapping, the full complement of expression changes caused by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink>/arc105</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis> are not identical, raising the possibility that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink>/arc105</emphasis> functions as a co-activator for other transcription factors. Indeed, several other NHRs bind <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MDT-15;class=Protein" role="_blank">MDT-15</ulink>/ARC105 in yeast two-hybrid experiments (<link linkend="bib99">Taubert et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16651656-->). Interestingly, MDT15/ARC105 was recently characterized as a co-activator of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SBP-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SBP-1</ulink>/SREBP in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and mammals (<link linkend="bib112">Yang et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16799563-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mdt-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">mdt-15</ulink>/arc105, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-49;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-49</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhr-80;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhr-80</ulink></emphasis> control expression of delta-9 fatty acid desaturase genes (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-6;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-6</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=fat-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">fat-7</ulink></emphasis>) illustrating complex regulatory mechanisms of fat metabolic pathways (<link linkend="bib13">Brock et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16839188-->; <link linkend="bib99">Taubert et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16651656-->; <link linkend="bib101">Van Gilst et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15719061-->).</para>
<para>Several other NHRs, whose mechanisms of function are unknown, are also required for wild type intestinal fat deposits (<link linkend="bib5">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529643-->). Finally, another NHR, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-12;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-12</ulink></emphasis>, and its co-factor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=din-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">din-1</ulink></emphasis> are components of a steroid-based hormonal signaling pathway that controls entry into the high fat dauer state; however, the relationship of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-12;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-12</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DIN-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">DIN-1</ulink> complex to metabolic pathways is not yet clear (<link linkend="bib2">Antebi et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10859169-->; <link linkend="bib66">Ludewig et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15314028-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4_3">
<title>TOR, AMPK, and hexosamine pathways</title>
<para>TOR (target of rapamyacin) is an evolutionarily conserved phosphatidylinositol kinase related family member that couples cell size and proliferation to nutrient levels, particularly amino acids and hormonal signals such as insulin (<link linkend="bib43">Inoki and Guan, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16516475-->; <link linkend="bib61">Lindsley and Rutter, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15581787-->). In <emphasis>Saccharomyces cerevisiae, Drosopholia melanogaster</emphasis> and mammalian cells, TOR activity promotes translation through direct activation of translational machinery. The precise nature of the nutrient signal that elicits TOR activity remains elusive. Loss of function mutations as well as RNAi inactivation of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> TOR (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=let-363;class=Gene" role="_blank">let-363</ulink></emphasis>/<ulink url="http://wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=B0261.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">B0261.2</ulink>) and its partner Raptor (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-15</ulink></emphasis>/C10C5.6) cause developmental arrest and fat accumulation (<link linkend="bib45">Jia et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15253933-->; <link linkend="bib104">Vellai et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14668850-->). Genetic analysis places raptor/<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-15;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-15</ulink></emphasis> downstream of insulin signaling and upstream of the eIF-4G and eIF-2 subunits of translational machinery (<link linkend="bib45">Jia et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15253933-->). In <emphasis>Drosophila melanogaster</emphasis> and mammals, the TSC tumor suppressor complex provides a mechanism of cross talk between the insulin and TOR signaling pathways. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome lacks sequence identifiable TSC complex components, TSC-1 and TSC-2. Thus, despite differences in cross talk mechanisms, insulin and TOR pathways interact in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to couple nutrient availability to growth and metabolism (<link linkend="bib62">Long et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14560955-->; <link linkend="bib63">Long et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12225660-->).</para>
<para>The AMP-activated kinase (AMPK) is a major cellular fuel gauge as its activity is responsive to cellular AMP:ATP ratio as well as upstream kinase cascades (<link linkend="bib47">Kahn et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16054041-->; <link linkend="bib61">Lindsley and Rutter, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15581787-->). AMPK activation causes numerous cellular changes, that together down-regulate energy-consumptive pathways and up-regulate energy-generating pathways. There is extensive cross talk between insulin, AMPK and TOR signaling pathways. In mammals, neuronal AMPK also functions downstream of leptin and insulin signaling to modulate food intake (<link linkend="bib47">Kahn et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16054041-->; <link linkend="bib61">Lindsley and Rutter, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15581787-->). Thus, AMPK is a major target of therapeutic intervention for metabolic syndromes such as type II diabetes.</para>
<para>Genes corresponding to catalytic <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> and regulatory <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol> and <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B3;</symbol> subunits of AMPK are conserved in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and kinase activity for one of the two catalytic <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B1;</symbol> subunits has been demonstrated (<link linkend="bib3">Apfeld et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15574588-->; <link linkend="bib22">Curtis et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16626391-->; <link linkend="bib78">Narbonne and Roy, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16407400-->). Genetic analysis has linked the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> AMPK cascade to insulin and mitochondrial pathways. These studies have focused on adult lifespan as a read-out. Direct investigation of the effect of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> AMPK on fat regulatory pathways has not yet been reported.</para>
<para>O-linked <emphasis>N</emphasis>-acetylglucosamine (<emphasis>O</emphasis>-GlcNAc) is thought to function as a dynamic posttranslational modification of many proteins (<link linkend="bib61">Lindsley and Rutter, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15581787-->; <link linkend="bib64">Love and Hanover, 2005</link><!--; PMID 16317114-->). Production of uridine 5<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x02032;</symbol>-diphospho-<emphasis>N</emphasis>-GlcNAc (UDP-GlcNAc), the <emphasis>O</emphasis>-GlcNAc donor, occurs through the hexosamine biosynthetic pathway. O-GlcNAC transferase (OGT) and O-GlcNAC glycosidase (OGA) add and remove <emphasis>O</emphasis>-GlcNAc from target proteins. Flux through the hexosamine pathway is tuned to cellular energy levels. This allows for global alterations in functions of <emphasis>O-GlcNAC</emphasis> modified target proteins. Defects in this pathway are associated with numerous diseases including Type II diabetes. Deletions in <emphasis>C. elegans <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ogt-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ogt-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=oga-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">oga-1</ulink></emphasis> have been reported to increase glycogen and trehalose levels while decreasing fat levels. Moreover, insulin mediated dauer pathways are affected in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ogt-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ogt-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=oga-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">oga-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant animals (<link linkend="bib29">Forsythe et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16882729-->; <link linkend="bib37">Hanover et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16051707-->; <link linkend="bib64">Love and Hanover, 2005</link><!--; PMID 16317114-->).</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Development of fat storage capacity</title>
<para>During mammalian adipogenesis, hormonal cues initiate transcriptional programs that guide the differentiation of multipotent mesenchymal stem cells into mature adipocytes. Members of bZIP CCAAT/enhancer binding protein (C/EBP) transcription factor family and PPAR<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B3;</symbol> are key components of these transcriptional cascades (<link linkend="bib87">Rosen, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15936931-->). SREBP is also required for lipogenic programs of differentiating adipocytes. Despite the fact that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestinal cells, the major site of fat deposition, are endodermal derivatives, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> counterpart of C/EBP (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=C48E7.11;class=Gene" role="_blank">C48E7.11</ulink>) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink></emphasis> are expressed in intestinal cells and are required for fat storage (<link linkend="bib72">McKay et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12530969-->). Electron microscopic examination of a deletion mutation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lpd-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">lpd-1</ulink>(gf1)</emphasis>, revealed that, intestinal cells of these animals maintain overall normal ultrastructural appearance including intact microvilli (<link linkend="bib72">McKay et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12530969-->). This suggests that fat storage capacity of intestinal cells is distinct from developmental program of these cells as enterocytes.</para>
<para>McKay and colleagues also found that RNAi inactivation of each of eight genes (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lpd-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">lpd-3</ulink></emphasis> though <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lpd-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">lpd-9</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mac-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">mac-1</ulink></emphasis>) causes morphological and fat phenotypes reminiscent of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=sbp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">sbp-1</ulink></emphasis> and C/EBP inactivation. <emphasis><ulink url="http://wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lpd-4;class=Gene" role="_blank">lpd-4</ulink></emphasis> (F26E9.4) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lpd-5;class=Gene" role="_blank">lpd-5</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ZK973.10;class=Gene" role="_blank">ZK973.10</ulink>) encode components of complex IV and complex I of the mitochondrial respiratory chain, respectively. Chemical inhibition of complex I and complex IV by rotenone and NaN<subscript>3</subscript> causes reduction of lipid accumulation in 3T3-L1 cells, a murine tissue culture adipocyte model system. Moreover, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lpd-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">lpd-3</ulink></emphasis> encodes a novel but conserved gene expressed in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> intestinal cells. The mammalian counterpart of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lpd-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">lpd-3</ulink></emphasis> is strongly expressed in brain, testis and embryonic fat tissues. Inactivation of mammalian <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=lpd-3;class=Gene" role="_blank">lpd-3</ulink></emphasis> by shRNA in 3T3-L1 cells that had been induced to undergo adipogenesis prevented lipid accumulation despite appearance of adipocyte differentiation markers (<link linkend="bib72">McKay et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12530969-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Lipid uptake/transport</title>
<para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome encodes proteins with sequence homology to fatty acid translocase (FAT/CD36), fatty acid transport protein (FATP), fatty acid binding proteins (FABPs), acyl-CoA binding proteins (ACBPs), carnitine-palmitoyl transferases (CPTs) and ATP-binding-cassette (ABC) transporter proteins. Mammalian homologs of these genes mediate fatty acid transport across various lipid bilayers and intracellular shuttling of fatty acylCoAs. In mammals, altered expression of putative fatty acid transport proteins is associated with obesity and insulin resistant states (<link linkend="bib17">Chawla et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11729302-->; <link linkend="bib52">Koonen et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16198626-->; <link linkend="bib69">Mashek and Coleman, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16680032-->).</para>
<para>Loss of function mutations and RNAi inactivation of specific members of FABP, ACBP, CPT and ABC transporters cause increased or decreased intestinal fat levels as visualized by Nile Red staining (<link linkend="bib5">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529643-->). Loss of function of a FATP-like transporter causes a reduced fat phenotype only in the context of mutations that confer increased fat storage (K. Ashrafi, unpublished results). Additionally, RNAi inactivations of specific family members of OCT-type transporters, a lysosomal transporter, an amino-acid permease and glucose transporters cause altered fat accumulation (<link linkend="bib5">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529643-->). Mechanisms of function underlying these phenotypes are not known.</para>
<para>Similarly, inactivation of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=opt-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">opt-2</ulink>/pep-2</emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nhx-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">nhx-2</ulink></emphasis> transporters cause reduced fat accumulation (<link linkend="bib5">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529643-->; <link linkend="bib73">Meissner et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15155758-->; <link linkend="bib79">Nehrke, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12939266-->). GFP-reporter fusions for each of these genes are exclusively expressed along the apical membrane of intestinal epithelia. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=OPT-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">OPT-2</ulink> is a transporter of di- and tripeptides and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NHX-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">NHX-2</ulink> is a Na<superscript>+</superscript>/H<superscript>+</superscript> exchanger. These functions are required for appropriate acidification of intestinal cells, which in turn, powers a variety of proton-coupled nutrient uptake systems.</para>
<para>The best characterized lipid uptake and transport system in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has been delivery of nutrients from intestinal cells to developing embryos (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_intracellulartrafficking/intracellulartrafficking.html" role="_blank">Intracellular trafficking</ulink>). A mixture of fats and cholesterol are loaded onto vitellogenins, yolk proteins with functional and structural similarities to LDL-type proteins. Vitellogenins are secreted from the intestinal cells into the pseudocoelum and then taken up by developing embryos via receptor-mediated endocytosis (<link linkend="bib27">Fares and Grant, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11872138-->). Finally, a conserved, transmembrane ACBP, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=maa-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">maa-1</ulink></emphasis>, is associated with Golgi and endosomal membranes. This ACBP modulates vesicular transport in the intestine, hypodermis and oocytes and, when inactivated, impairs receptor-mediated endocytosis (<link linkend="bib56">Larsen et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16870706-->).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>Neuroendocrine fat and feeding regulatory pathways</title>
<para>In mammals, the nervous system functions as a central coordinator of both metabolic pathways and behaviors associated with food consumption. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> nervous system also regulates fat storage both in conjunction with and independent of feeding pathways.</para>
<sect2 id="sec7_1">
<title>Insulin and TGF-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol></title>
<para>Signaling cascades through insulin, transforming growth factor (TGF-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>) and cyclic nucleotide regulated pathways control whether <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> larvae grow to adults or fat-storing dauers. Molecular components of these pathways are extensively covered elsewhere. Down-regulating either insulin or TGF-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol> pathway components promotes fat accumulation in adults. A clear example of neuronal regulation of fat levels is provided by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=DAF-7;class=Protein" role="_blank">DAF-7</ulink>, a TGF-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol> ligand. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-7</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in one pair of ciliated sensory neurons (ASI) and its transcription is modulated by daumone, a constitutively secreted pheromone that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> use to assess population density (<link linkend="bib44">Jeong et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15690045-->; <link linkend="bib85">Ren et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8910282-->). Thus, this pathway responds to environmental conditions and function as a central regulator of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homeostasis.</para>
<para>Similarly, many of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> insulins are expressed in neurons and have been postulated to relay changes in food availability, although direct evidence for this is lacking (<link linkend="bib81">Pierce et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11274053-->). In mammals, insulin signaling has both peripheral and central actions on fat homeostasis (see <link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>). Importantly, tissue-specific knockouts or reconstitution of the insulin receptor in mice has begun to reveal contributions of different tissues to glucose and fat homeostasis. For instance, neuronal insulin receptor knockout and muscle insulin receptor knockout mice are obese while fat cell insulin receptor knockout mice are lean and resistant to diet induced obesity (<link linkend="bib11">Biddinger and Kahn, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16460269-->). Similarly, insulin signaling in different <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> tissues contributes differentially to fat content. For instance, reconstitution of the insulin receptor in neurons but not in muscle partially rescues the increased fat content of insulin receptor knockout animals (<link linkend="bib111">Wolkow et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11021802-->).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
		<mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata entityref="fig6" width="6.5in" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>figure 6</phrase>
			</textobject> &fig6legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec7_2">
<title>Serotonin, dopamine and glutamate pathways</title>
<para>Classical neurotransmitters have dramatic effects on fat regulation in nemotodes and in mammals. Deleting <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tph-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tph-1</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes the enzyme tryptophan hydroxylase, causes <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to lack serotonin (<link linkend="bib97">Sze et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10676966-->). Serotonin production is largely confined to ADF, a head sensory neuron, NSM, a pharyngeal neuron, HSN, a hermaphrodite-specific neuron that innervates the vulva, and sensory neurons innervating the male tail. Serotonin-deficient animals are viable but have excess fat accumulation, reduced feeding rate (see <link linkend="sec7_4">section 7.4</link>) and reduced rate of progeny production (<link linkend="bib97">Sze et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10676966-->). Genetic analysis suggests interactions between serotonin, insulin and TGF-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol> pathways (<link linkend="bib97">Sze et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10676966-->).</para>
<para>Additionally, inactivating specific dopaminergic and glutamergic receptors alters fat deposits without adversely affecting growth rate or viability (<link linkend="bib5">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529643-->). Mammalian counterparts of these neuromodulatory pathways have also been implicated energy balance (<link linkend="bib18">Clifton and Kennett, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16787230-->; <link linkend="bib88">Sainsbury et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12468411-->).</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec7_3">
<title><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tub-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tub-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bbs-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bbs-1</ulink></emphasis></title>
<para>Mutations in rodent <emphasis>tubby</emphasis> cause progressive degeneration in retinal and cochlear sensory receptor cells, infertility and adult-onset obesity with insulin resistance (<link linkend="bib16">Carroll et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14708010-->). <emphasis>Tubby</emphasis> is broadly expressed in the central nervous system including the hypothalamus. Molecular mechanisms of <emphasis>Tubby</emphasis> function are unclear although several models have been proposed (<link linkend="bib16">Carroll et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14708010-->). Loss of function in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tub-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tub-1</ulink></emphasis>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=F10B5.5;class=Gene" role="_blank">F10B5.5</ulink>, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> ortholog of <emphasis>Tubby</emphasis>, causes fat accumulation (<link linkend="bib5">Ashrafi et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529643-->; <link linkend="bib68">Mak et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16462744-->). A functional <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TUB-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">TUB-1</ulink>::GFP fusion localizes to all ciliated sensory neurons in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib68">Mak et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16462744-->; <link linkend="bib75">Mukhopadhyay et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16054097-->). In a yeast two-hybrid assay, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TUB-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">TUB-1</ulink> was found to interact with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=B0393.2;class=Gene" role="_blank">B0393.2</ulink>, a predicted RabGTPase-activating protein (RabGAP) postulated to function in vesicular transport (<link linkend="bib75">Mukhopadhyay et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16054097-->). This RabGAP is expressed in the amphid and phasmid subset of ciliated sensory neurons. RNAi inactivation of this RabGAP causes only a minor reduction in fat content of wild-type animals but suppresses the excess fat of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tub-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tub-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant animals (<link linkend="bib75">Mukhopadhyay et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16054097-->). This suggests a surprisingly specific role for vesicular transport in accumulation of excess fat in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tub-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tub-1</ulink></emphasis> deficient animals. Moreover, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tub-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tub-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant animals have extended lifespan. This lifespan extension requires insulin signaling but appears to be independent of the TUB-RabGAP fat pathway (<link linkend="bib75">Mukhopadhyay et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16054097-->).</para>
<para>Neuronal <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tub-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tub-1</ulink></emphasis> has been reported to act synergistically in fat accumulation with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=kat-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">kat-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=T02G5.8;class=Gene" role="_blank">T02G5.8</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes a non-neuronal <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B2;</symbol>-oxidation enzyme, 3-ketoacyl-coA thiolase (<link linkend="bib68">Mak et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16462744-->). The synergistic nature of the excess fat accumulation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tub-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tub-1</ulink>;kat-1</emphasis> double mutants suggests that defects in neuronal <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tub-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tub-1</ulink></emphasis> are normally compensated by <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=kat-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">kat-1</ulink></emphasis> mediated fat oxidation in non-neuronal tissues. Loss of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=kat-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">kat-1</ulink></emphasis> abrogates this multi-tissue compensatory mechanism.</para>
<para>The molecular nature of compensatory mechanisms that couple <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tub-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tub-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=kat-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">kat-1</ulink></emphasis> are not yet known; however, genetic analysis of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=kat-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">kat-1</ulink></emphasis> led to identification of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bbs-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bbs-1</ulink></emphasis> as another modifier of intestinal fat storage that, like <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tub-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tub-1</ulink></emphasis>, functions in ciliated neurons (<link linkend="bib68">Mak et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16462744-->). Mutations in human ortholog of <emphasis>bbs</emphasis> genes including <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bbs-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bbs-1</ulink></emphasis> underlie Bardet-Biedl syndrome, a pleiotropic syndrome associated with obesity (<link linkend="bib10">Beales, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15917208-->). Many human <emphasis>BBS</emphasis> genes, which are implicated in ciliogenesis and intraflagellar transport (IFT), have <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homologs (<link linkend="bib42">Inglis et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16860433-->). Similar to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tub-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tub-1</ulink></emphasis>, loss of function mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bbs-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bbs-1</ulink></emphasis> cause modest increases in fat accumulation that are exacerbated by loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=KAT-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">KAT-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib68">Mak et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16462744-->; <link linkend="bib75">Mukhopadhyay et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16054097-->). Moreover, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tub-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tub-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants have defects in chemotaxis, a function mediated by a subset of ciliated sensory neurons, and there is evidence that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=TUB-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">TUB-1</ulink> undergoes IFT (<link linkend="bib68">Mak et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16462744-->; <link linkend="bib75">Mukhopadhyay et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 16054097-->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_chemosensation/chemosensation.html" role="_blank">Chemosensation</ulink>). Together, these findings suggest that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tub-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tub-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bbs-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bbs-1</ulink></emphasis> function in the same fat regulatory pathway.</para>
<para>The provocative hypothesis that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=bbs-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">bbs-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tub-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tub-1</ulink></emphasis> form a neuroendocrine axis with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=kat-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">kat-1</ulink></emphasis> is based on the synergistic rather than additive fat content of double mutants as assessed by Nile Red fluorescence. The potential insights offered by such genetic interactions highlight the need for standard methods to accurately quantify fluorescence intensity.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec7_4">
<title>Feeding behavior and fat pathways</title>
<para><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> feed by pumping and concentrating food using a neuromuscular organ known as the pharynx (<link linkend="bib7">Avery and Shtonda, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12796460-->; <link linkend="bib93">Shtonda and Avery, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15914661-->). The grinder, a teeth-like structure located at the junction of the pharynx and the intestine, breaks food particles that are then pushed into the lumen of the intestine by the peristaltic pumping action of the pharynx. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> pump in the presence and absence of food; however, pumping rate is modulated by food availability (<link linkend="bib6">Avery and Horvitz, 1990</link><!--; PMID 2181052-->). Animals that have experienced starvation will pump faster when re-exposed to food than well-fed animals. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> also forage for food. Rates and patterns of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> movement are different compared on or off food. These locomotory rates and patterns are also modulated by starvation (<link linkend="bib38">Hills et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14762140-->; <link linkend="bib91">Sawin et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10896158-->).</para>
<para>Serotonin modulates pumping rate. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tph-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tph-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant animals display reduced pumping rate while animals exposed to excess serotonin or imipramine, a serotonin uptake inhibitor, display increased pumping (<link linkend="bib6">Avery and Horvitz, 1990</link><!--; PMID 2181052-->; <link linkend="bib41">Horvitz et al., 1982</link><!--; PMID 6805073-->). Pumping stimulatory effects of serotonin are abrogated by mutations in each of two serotonergic receptors <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ser-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">ser-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ser-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">ser-7</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib39">Hobson et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16204223-->). Additionally, serotonin, dopamine and glutamate signaling pathways are implicated in different foraging strategies of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib38">Hills et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14762140-->; <link linkend="bib91">Sawin et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10896158-->). These neuronal signaling mechanisms also modulate mammalian feeding behavior (<link linkend="bib18">Clifton and Kennett, 2006</link><!--; PMID 16787230-->; <link linkend="bib88">Sainsbury et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12468411-->).</para>
<para>Together, these results indicate an overlap between neuronal feeding and foraging behavior pathways and central fat regulatory mechanisms; however, the nature of these relationships is not yet clear. For instance, there is an inverse correlation between fat content and pumping rate for serotonin deficient animals. In other cases, such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=tub-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">tub-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants, animals display wild-type pumping rates despite increased fat levels.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>Perspectives</title>
<para>Our understanding of body fat regulation as a homeostatic, organismal process has flourished in the past decade. Although many of the core metabolic pathways were biochemically defined long ago, integration and coordination of these pathways across multiple tissues is a vibrant field of integrative biology. This is because understanding fat regulation requires multiple layers of investigation spanning from metabolism, transcription and signaling to neuronal development and behavior. Deciphering neuronal circuits that coordinate behavior, physiology, and metabolism is a major challenge in understanding fat regulation. Similarly, compensatory mechanisms that operate at organismal level to maintain energy homeostasis are just being elucidated.</para>
<para>The genetic tractability of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has already revealed that mechanisms of energy balance in this organism range from neuronal sensation and endocrine signals to nutrient uptake, transport and storage/utilization mechanisms. Importantly, amenability of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> to multiple rounds of suppressor/enhancer screening is critical and provides a unique advantage for understanding homeostatic feedback regulatory mechanisms. Examining fat regulatory pathways under different environmental conditions holds the potential to reveal how physiological pathways are coordinately modulated in response to environmental perturbation. Similarly, how developmental stage, age, experience and diet perturb and possibly rewire the fat networks can be addressed in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> at a molecular level. Finally, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is well suited for deciphering developmental programs that underlie fat storage capacity and cell biological determinants of lipid droplet biogenesis.</para>
<para>Many of the adverse health effects of excess fat accumulation in humans are unlikely to occur in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. Nevertheless, the limited number of studies reported thus far already reveal remarkable similarities between molecular components of mammalian and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> fat pathways that extend to disease-associated genes. Many of the fat genes identified in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have mammalian homologs whose roles in energy balance have not yet been examined. Given that energy balance is fundamental for viability, it is likely that many of the newly identified <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> fat regulatory networks are functionally conserved in mammals.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec9">
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<para>Work in the Ashrafi laboratory is supported by a Career Award in Biomedical Sciences from Burroughs Welcome Fund, and grants from the NIH, Searle Scholars Program, ADA/Smith Family Foundation and The UCSF Sandler Program in Basic Sciences. I am indebted to members of the Ashrafi lab and Jennifer Watts for discussions.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Bibliography</title>
&obesfat_Refs;
<para/>
</sect1>
</article>