<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'germlinegenomicsfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'germlinegenomicsfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'germlinegenomicsfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'germlinegenomicsfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'germlinegenomicsfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'germlinegenomicsfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'germlinegenomicsfig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'germlinegenomicsfig4leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY germlinegenomics_Refs SYSTEM 'germlinegenomicsrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="Germlinegenomics_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Germline genomics<remark>
                <footnote>
                    <para>Edited by Judith Kimble and Susan Strome. Last revised March 18, 2005. Published January 20, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Reinke, V. Germline genomics (January 20, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.74.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 Valerie Reinke. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
                </footnote>
            </remark>
        </title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 3/18/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
-->
        <author>
            <firstname>Valerie</firstname>
            <surname>Reinke<remark>
                    <footnote>
                        <para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:valerie.reinke@yale.edu">valerie.reinke@yale.edu</ulink></para>
                    </footnote>
                </remark>
            </surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Department of Genetics, Yale University, New Haven, CT 06520 USA</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The completion of the</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">genome sequence permits the
            comprehensive examination of the expression and function of genes. Annotation of
            virtually every encoded gene in the genome allows systematic analysis of those genes
            using high-throughput assays, such as microarrays and RNAi. This chapter will center on
            the use of microarrays to comprehensively identify genes with enriched expression in the
            germ line during development. This knowledge provides a database for further studies
            that focus on gene function during germline development or early embryogenesis.
            Additionally, a comprehensive overview of germline gene expression can uncover striking
            biases in how genes expressed in the germ line are distributed in the genome, leading to
            new discoveries of global regulatory mechanisms in the germ line.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
    <sect1>
        <title>Regulatory mechanisms of germline gene expression</title>
        <para>Regulation of gene expression at both transcriptional and post-transcriptional levels
            is crucial for the proper specification, proliferation and differentiation of germ
            cells. At the transcriptional level, certain genes are effectively silenced while
            other genes are expressed (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_specgermline/specgermline.html" role="_blank">Specification of the germ line</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlinechromatin/germlinechromatin.html" role="_blank">Germline chromatin</ulink>). After transcript production, complex networks of RNA regulatory proteins
            modulate either the stability and/or translation of mRNAs. These processes combine to effectively control, both spatially and
            temporally, the levels of germline-expressed gene products. Our understanding of these
            mechanisms in the germ line is still murky. How are genes selected for silencing or
            expression? How does germline gene expression influence the organization of genes in the
            genome, and vice versa? How are the dramatic structural changes of meiotic chromosomes
            coordinated with continued gene expression? What mechanisms control spatial and temporal
            expression within the germ line?</para>
        <para>For those wishing to understand these aspects of germline development, one goal is to
            identify every germline-expressed gene. With such information in hand, it is possible to
            analyze gene functions by RNAi and decipher regulatory mechanisms by a combination of
            bioinformatics and molecular genetics. Such genome-wide studies reveal global trends,
            and also identify individual genes that might function to control germ cell fate decisions or
            terminal differentiation of gametes, making them candidates for future functional study.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Gene expression profiling of the germ line</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>DNA microarray technology</title>
            <para>DNA microarray technology is frequently used to monitor changes in gene expression
                for thousands of genes simultaneously (reviewed in <link linkend="bib7">Duggan et al., 1999</link><!-- [PMID 9915494]-->). Typically, DNA microarrays are common laboratory glass slides upon which
                is printed a series of discrete spots of DNA. Each spot corresponds to some portion
                of a known gene or predicted open reading frame. For each experiment, a comparison
                is made between two different populations of transcripts that have been
                reverse-transcribed to cDNA, each in the presence of a distinct fluorescent label.
                At each spot, competitive hybridization between the two populations occurs. The
                relative intensity of the two fluorescent labels at each spot measures the relative
                abundance of a given gene transcript between the two populations (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). When used in this manner, microarrays provide information
                about the steady state levels of mRNAs; they do not directly address the rate at
                which a transcript is synthesized or degraded. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
                DNA microarrays that primarily have been used to investigate germline gene
                expression contain over 18,000 spots and represent about 90<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of the currently annotated genes in the
                genome (<link linkend="bib12">Jiang et al., 2001</link><!-- [PMID 11134517]-->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_DNAmicroarrays/DNAmicroarrays.html">DNA microarrays</ulink>).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
            <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig1" align="center" width="4in"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase> Example of microarray hybridization figure 1</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
        </sect2>
<?newpage?>
        <sect2>
            <title>Identification of germline-enriched genes in adult hermaphrodites</title>
            <para>The comprehensive identification of germline-expressed genes will comprise a
                molecular definition of germline components, and provide the framework to identify
                individual genes involved in specific germline functions. Microarrays are an
                excellent platform to achieve such a goal because the expression of all genes in the
                genome can be examined simultaneously. Microarray analysis of mutants that perturb
                specific aspects of germline development has been very useful in defining sets of
                genes with germline-enriched expression. Discussed below are three sets of genes
                that have been identified to date: genes with enriched expression in the germline
                relative to the soma, genes with enriched expression during spermatogenesis, and
                genes with enriched expression during oogenesis.</para>
            <para>One of the most straightforward comparisons identified genes with
                germline-enriched expression relative to somatic tissues (<link linkend="bib20">Reinke et al., 2000</link><!--[PMID 11030340]-->; <link linkend="bib19">Reinke et al., 2004</link><!-- [PMID 14668411])-->). A temperature-sensitive
                mutation, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-4" role="_blank">glp-4</ulink>(bn2)</emphasis>, causes severe defects in germ cell
                proliferation, resulting in gonads with <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x223C;</symbol>100-fold fewer germ cells than wild type
                (<link linkend="bib4">Beanan and Strome, 1992</link><!-- [PMID 1289064]-->). Microarray comparison of either L4 or
                young adult wild type hermaphrodites to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-4" role="_blank">glp-4(ts)</ulink></emphasis>
                hermaphrodites of the corresponding stage identified 3144 genes with
                germline-enriched expression relative to somatic tissues in hermaphrodites (<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003E;</symbol>2x, p<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003C;</symbol>0.01). When a similar comparison was done
                with wild-type and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-4(ts)</ulink></emphasis> males, 1092 genes showed
                significantly enriched expression in the germ line. Previous single-gene analyses
                had identified <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x223C;</symbol>70 genes that are
                expressed and/or function in the hermaphrodite germline. Essentially every one of
                these genes was correctly identified as germline-enriched in the microarray
                experiments, demonstrating the accuracy and comprehensiveness of the microarray
                approach. However, it is important to note that a gene with equivalent expression in
                both samples, even if expressed in the germline, will not be identified as a
                “germline gene”. Thus, these studies are limited to identification of genes with
                <emphasis>enriched</emphasis> expression in the germ line relative to the soma.</para>
            <para>While the identification of genes with germline-enriched expression in the two
                sexes is informative, the number of genes identified is formidably large. Further
                microarray experiments using mutants that affect gametogenesis helped to group these
                genes into distinct categories. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-1" role="_blank">fem-1</ulink>(lf)</emphasis> mutant hermaphrodites
                are defective in initiation of spermatogenesis and consequently produce only oocytes
                (<link linkend="bib15">Nelson et al., 1978</link><!-- [PMID 700253]-->), while <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-3" role="_blank">fem-3</ulink>(gf)</emphasis> mutants
                are defective in switching from spermatogenesis to oogenesis and consequently
                produce only sperm (<link linkend="bib1">Barton et al. 1987</link><!-- [PMID 3557107]-->). Direct comparison of the
                genes differentially expressed between <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-1" role="_blank">fem-1</ulink>(lf)</emphasis> and
                    <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-3" role="_blank">fem-3</ulink>(gf)</emphasis> populations defined two sets of genes: those
                expressed during spermatogenesis (1343) and those expressed during oogenesis (1652)
                    (<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003E;</symbol>2x, p<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003C;</symbol>0.01). Genes with high expression during
                spermatogenesis are likely to be involved in spermatocyte specification and
                differentiation. Genes with high expression during oogenesis are expected to encode
                proteins required for oocyte differentiation as well as maternally provided factors
                necessary for proper development of the early embryo.</para>
            <para>Combination of the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-4" role="_blank">glp-4</ulink>(ts)</emphasis> vs wild type comparison and the
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-1" role="_blank">fem-1</ulink>(lf)</emphasis> vs <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-3" role="_blank">fem-3</ulink>(gf)</emphasis> comparison
                identifies 4245 genes with expression in the germ line and/or gametes –
                approximately 20<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> of all the genes in
                the genome (<xref linkend="figure2"/>). These genes can be divided into three
                groups, spermatogenesis (genes in the green circle), oogenesis (genes in the orange
                circle), and intrinsic, which includes germline genes not differentially expressed
                during gametogenesis (genes in the blue circle but not in the green or orange
                circles). Most of the spermatogenesis-enriched genes identified in hermaphrodites
                were also enriched in males, as expected.</para>
            <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig2" align="center" width="4.2in"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase> Germline gene sets figure 2</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
        </sect2>
		<sect2>
        <title>Analysis of germline gene expression during development</title>
        <para>In addition to expression profiles of mutants, temporal expression profiles gathered
            from wild type animals can also reveal sets of co-regulated genes. Microarrays have been
            probed with RNAs prepared at consecutive times of development from wild type animals.
            This timecourse provides high temporal resolution (every 3 hours for 36 hours) of gene
            expression from mid-L3 through adulthood (<link linkend="bib19">Reinke et al., 2004</link><!-- [PMID 14668411]-->). During
            this period, major germline events include entry into meiosis, spermatogenesis,
            oogenesis and embryogenesis. Because intact animals were used for the timecourse
            analysis, fluctuations in expression of somatic genes would also be detected. Among the
            major developmental events in the soma during this period are gonadogenesis (i.e.,
            generation of uterus, spermathecae and sheath cells) and vulval development. Statistical
            analysis using ANOVA identified 5083 genes with a significant fluctuation in expression
            level during the timecourse (p<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003C;</symbol>0.01);
            among these, 2426 genes had also been identified as germline-regulated genes.</para>
        <para>To identify sets of co-regulated genes, gene expression data can be grouped together
            by similarity of expression profiles. One method for grouping genes is hierarchical
            clustering using the Pearson correlation coefficient to determine relatedness of
            expression (<link linkend="bib8">Eisen et al., 1998</link><!-- [PMID 9843981]-->). In <xref linkend="figure3"/>,
            hierarchical clustering was performed on the data from the timecourse microarrays. Not
            surprisingly, some of these clusters based on common temporal regulation contain
            particular classes of germline genes, as defined by the analysis of mutants (Clusters D-F in <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig3" align="center" width="5in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> Gene expression analysis in larvae and adults figure 3</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>One prominent cluster identified from the timecourse microarrays contains a set of
            genes with sharp onset of expression in late L3s and abrupt decline in late L4 (cluster
            D in the temporal clustergram at left in <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). Examination of this set of genes in
            the microarray analysis performed on mutants (right side of <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>) showed that 99<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol> are associated with
            spermatogenesis. Thus, the spermatogenesis genes are regulated in a fashion that is
            distinct from the oogenesis and intrinsic genes, and the timing of their expression
            coincides with the duration of spermatogenesis in late L3/L4 larvae. Additionally,
            spermatogenesis genes encode different classes of proteins, with more signaling
            molecules and fewer DNA and RNA metabolism factors (<xref linkend="figure4"/>). Thus,
            genes with spermatogenesis-enriched expression are clearly distinct from other
            germline-enriched genes.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig4" align="center" width="4.5in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> Classification of germline enriched genes figure 4</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>Unlike the spermatogenesis-enriched genes, expression of other germline-enriched genes
            (in clusters E and F) increased over time without any significant decline. Overall, the
            temporal regulation of these germline genes was very similar, but minor differences
            sub-divided them into two groups. Expression of cluster F genes gradually increases in
            L3 or L4, while expression of cluster E genes has a more abrupt onset at adulthood. The
            cluster E expression profile is consistent with oogenesis, which initiates in the adult.
            However, genes in the intrinsic and oogenesis sets are fairly evenly distributed between
            cluster E and cluster F. Furthermore, the classes of protein functions are also
            proportioned similarly in the two clusters (<xref linkend="figure4"/>). Thus, separation
            of germline genes into “intrinsic” and “oogenesis” categories is not supported by the
            temporal analysis, and it is difficult at this point to separate genes specifically
            required in immature germ cells versus maturing oocytes (see <link linkend="bib19">Reinke et al., 2004</link><!-- [PMID 14668411]--> for discussion of possible reasons).</para>
    </sect2>
	</sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Chromosome bias for genes with germline-enriched expression</title>
        <para>Genome-scale views can provide much more than gene lists. A prime example is the
            discovery of a chromosomal bias in the genomic location of germline-enriched genes,
            which arose from the microarray studies described above. The germline genes are
            primarily located on the autosomes; very few reside on the X chromosome (<link linkend="bib20">Reinke et al., 2000</link><!-- [PMID 11030340]-->; <link linkend="bib19">Reinke et al., 2004</link><!-- [PMID 14668411]-->). This bias is particularly
            strong for spermatogenesis genes, and though less marked for other germline genes, the
            bias is quite significant.</para>
        <para>The biased location of germline-enriched genes, in combination with electron
            microscopic images of germ cell nuclei in males, led to the hypothesis that the X
            chromosome might be transcriptionally silent in the germ line. By EM analysis of male
            germlines, the unpaired X chromosome appears condensed (Goldstein, 1992<!--[PMID 7075356]-->),
            a morphology now thought to be similar to the condensed, transcriptionally inactive sex
            chromosome body observed during meiosis in organisms with single or non-equivalent sex
            chromosomes (<link linkend="bib14">McKee and Handel, 1993</link><!-- [PMID 8432196]-->). If the X chromosome is essentially
            transcriptionally inactive in the male germline, then it would be an inhospitable
            environment for genes needed in that tissue. Thus, genes expressed in the germline would
            ultimately be under-represented on the X chromosome. Alternatively, some unknown force
            could prevent germline genes from residing on the X, and consequently, their absence
            from the X triggers its apparent transcriptional silencing.</para>
        <para>Subsequent experiments have supported and extended the hypothesis that the X is
            silenced in the germline. In the male germline, the unpaired X chromosome is decorated
            with histone modifications that correlate with transcriptional silencing, and is devoid
            of modifications that correlate with active gene expression (<link linkend="bib13">Kelly et al., 2002</link><!-- [PMID 11807039]-->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlinechromatin/germlinechromatin.html" role="_blank">Germline chromatin</ulink>). Unexpectedly, the synapsed X chromosomes
            in hermaphrodites are also apparently silenced throughout most of the germ line, as they
            largely lack detectable activating modifications (<link linkend="bib13">Kelly et al., 2002</link><!-- [PMID 11807039]-->;
            see ). However, silencing modifications are not seen on the hermaphrodite Xs as they are
            in the male (<link linkend="bib3">Bean et al., 2004</link><!-- [PMID 14702046]-->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlinechromatin/germlinechromatin.html" role="_blank">Germline
            chromatin</ulink>). This milder silencing correlates well with the extent of gene bias
            against the X chromosome, which is less severe for genes expressed primarily in the
            hermaphrodite germline (oogenesis genes) compared to those shared with the male germline
            (spermatogenesis genes). The silencing of the Xs in hermaphrodites was subsequently
            shown to require the activity of the MES proteins (<link linkend="bib9">Fong et al., 2002</link><!-- [PMID 12077420]-->).
            Mutations in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mes-2" role="_blank">mes-2</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mes-3" role="_blank">mes-3</ulink></emphasis>, and
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mes-6" role="_blank">mes-6</ulink> </emphasis>genes causes the X to inappropriately acquire marks of
            active chromatin, suggesting that transcriptional control of the X chromosome is
            disrupted (<link linkend="bib9">Fong et al., 2002</link><!-- [PMID 12077420]-->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_specgermline/specgermline.html" role="_blank">Specification of the germ line</ulink>).</para>
        <para>The remarkable insight that an entire chromosome is silenced in a major tissue such as
            the germ line would have been difficult to achieve if the germ line had been studied
            only on a gene-by-gene basis. As each individual germline-enriched gene was identified,
            its location on an autosome would not have been surprising. By examining the expression
            profiles of many germline genes in parallel, the bias against the X chromosome became
            obvious, and could be further examined through additional experiments. This example
            provides an important instance of how emergent properties become apparent from
            comprehensive molecular depictions.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Integration of germline functional genomic data</title>
        <para>In addition to the microarray approach described above, other large-scale methods of
            examining gene expression have been undertaken. An <emphasis>in situ</emphasis> hybridization project
            performed under the direction of Dr. Yuji Kohara examined the expression pattern of
            several thousand genes at multiple stages of development, from embryos to young adults,
            specifically in hermaphrodites. Because <emphasis>in situ</emphasis> hybridization analysis reveals both
            location and timing of transcript accumulation, it complements the quantitative data
            provided by microarrays. Together, these two methods provide insights into spatial,
            temporal, and condition-dependent control of gene expression. The whole-mount <emphasis>in situ</emphasis>
            studies have successfully identified many genes with germline-enriched expression,
            perhaps because the germ line has a relatively high rate of mRNA production and/or
            because the germ line is one of the largest organs in the adult. The spatial aspect of
            <emphasis>in situ</emphasis> hybridization data is particularly informative. For instance, accumulation of
            oogenesis transcripts from X-linked germline genes is restricted to the proximal germ
            line, consistent with silencing of the X chromosome in the distal germ line (<link linkend="bib13">Kelly et al., 2002</link><!-- [PMID 11807039]-->, see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlinechromatin/germlinechromatin.html" role="_blank">Germline chromatin</ulink>).</para>
        <para>The identification of germline-expressed genes provides an excellent starting point
            for analysis of gene function during oogenesis and early embryogenesis. Indeed such
            studies have begun. Based on an early version of the germline gene set (<link linkend="bib20">Reinke et al., 2000</link><!-- [PMID 11030340]-->), several RNAi screens have been performed, including ones focused
            on identification of genes required for early embryogenesis (<link linkend="bib17">Piano et al., 2002</link><!-- [PMID 12445391]-->), genes required for correct localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PIE-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PIE-1</ulink> in the early embryo
            (<link linkend="bib16">Pellettieri et al., 2003</link><!-- [PMID 12967564]-->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_specgermline/specgermline.html" role="_blank">Specification of the germline</ulink>), and genes required for
            chromosome morphogenesis during meiosis (<link linkend="bib6">Colai&#x000E1;covo et al., 2003</link><!-- [PMID 12242227]-->). A
            separate study identifying genes expressed during meiosis was followed by RNAi analysis
            of candidate genes for roles in germline development (<link linkend="bib11">Hanazawa et al., 2001</link><!-- [PMID 1447255]-->). Additionally, protein partners are being identified by systematic yeast
            two-hybrid analysis (<link linkend="bib22">Walhout et al., 2002</link><!-- [PMID 12445390]-->). Therefore, a tremendous data
            set is emerging for germline genes, which includes their temporal and spatial
            expression, biological functions, and protein partners. As this data set becomes more
            comprehensive, the data will provide a remarkably complete overview of the function and
            interaction of critical factors and can be used to assemble the genetic regulatory
            networks underlying germline and embryonic development.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Future directions</title>
        <para>Many questions about germline development and function remain that will benefit from
            genomic analyses. Below, some questions are listed along with approaches for answering
            those questions using DNA microarrays.</para>
        <para>How does gene expression differ between different stages of germ cell development?
            Many additional mutants exist that can be used to further distinguish genes that are
            expressed in different germ cell types. For instance, a gain-of-function mutation in the
            GLP-1(Notch) receptor causes excess germline stem cells (<link linkend="bib5">Berry et al., 1997</link><!-- [PMID 9043073]-->; see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlineprolifcontrol/germlineprolifcontrol.html" role="_blank">Germline proliferation and its control</ulink>). Use of this mutant in
            microarray experiments will identify genes expressed primarily in the distal
            proliferating stem cells and better separate these genes from those that are expressed
            and act in oogenesis.</para>
        <para>How many germline-expressed genes still remain to be identified? Because the current
            microarray studies used intact animals, somatic gene expression has likely masked the
            germline expression of certain genes. In the future, the use of dissected gonads in
            microarray experiments will greatly improve the sensitivity with which
            germline-expressed genes can be identified. Dissected gonads are composed almost
            entirely of germ cells; with careful dissection, the only somatic cells included are the
            distal tip cell and sheath cells. Improvements to linear RNA amplification techniques
            permit the use of very small amounts of RNA (<link linkend="bib2">Baugh et al., 2001</link><!--; [PMID 11222780]-->), and
            it has been possible to perform microarray experiments with RNA derived from ~50
            dissected adult gonads. Use of dissected gonads will also improve detection of gene
            expression changes in mutants with only subtle germline defects.</para>
        <para>How do post-transcriptional mechanisms control target mRNAs? Current germline
            microarray analyses have identified many RNA-binding proteins that are likely to act in
            the germ line to regulate mRNA translation and/or stability. The RNA targets bound by
            these proteins can be identified using microarrays. In this experiment, an antibody
            specific to the RNA binding protein is used to immunoprecipitate the protein and its
            associated RNAs. These RNAs can then be isolated, labeled and hybridized to a
            microarray. This approach has worked well for one germline RNA binding protein, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLD-1</ulink>
            (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_RNAbindingproteins/RNAbindingproteins.html" role="_blank">RNA-binding
            proteins</ulink>; M.H. Lee, V. Reinke, and T.
            Schedl, unpublished data). Over 100 candidate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GLD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">GLD-1</ulink> mRNA targets have been identified,
            the vast majority of which have germline-enriched expression.</para>
        <para>How do DNA- and chromatin-binding proteins affect germline gene expression? The
            initial germline microarray experiments described above have identified many candidate
            transcriptional regulators that likely function in the germ line. RNAi or a genetic
            deletion of the transcriptional regulator will presumably result in changes in the
            levels of its transcriptional targets that can be assessed by DNA microarray analysis.
            These expression data can be correlated with the binding locations of these proteins in
            the genome. Approaches such as chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) or DNA adenine
            methylase identification (DamID), which identify or mark DNA sequences bound by specific
            transcriptional regulators, can be combined with DNA microarray technology to map the
            bound DNA sequences genome-wide (<link linkend="bib18">Pollack and Iyer, 2002</link><!-- [PMID 12454647]-->; <link linkend="bib21">van Steensel and Henikoff, 2003</link><!-- [PMID 12951776]-->). Because most DNA-binding proteins bind in
            non-coding, regulatory sequences that flank genes, a microarray that contains intergenic
            sequences is required for this analysis. Such arrays are currently being built by Jason
            Lieb at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</para>
        <para>Global genome studies will help to further determine the gene regulatory networks that
            govern germline function. In addition to microarray-based approaches, systematic RNAi
            analysis of germline-expressed genes will shed significant light on their roles in
            germline development (see for example <link linkend="bib6">Colai&#x000E1;covo et al., 2003</link><!-- [PMID 12242227]-->).
            Proteomic approaches, such as systematic yeast two-hybrid, mass spectrometry analysis of
            TAP-immunoprecipitated proteins, and systematic structural analysis (for review, see <link linkend="bib23">Zhu et al., 2003</link><!-- [PMID 14527327]-->), will also play important roles in deciphering the
            functional relationships among germline gene products. When data from these different
            functional approaches are combined for germline-expressed genes, we will be
            well-launched on a comprehensive understanding of germline function.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Useful links for germline genomics</title>
        <para>
            <ulink url="http://wormgermline.yale.edu">http://wormgermline.yale.edu</ulink> (data generated in mutant and timecourse
            microarray studies can be searched and downloaded).
            <ulink url="http://nematode.lab.nig.ac.jp">http://nematode.lab.nig.ac.jp</ulink> (Kohara lab <emphasis>in situ</emphasis> database “NExtDB”)
            <ulink url="http://www.RNAi.org">http://www.RNAi.org</ulink> (database of RNAi experiments including germline gene
            set) <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org">http://www.wormbase.org</ulink> (database of the genomic sequence and useful tools for database mining).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
		<para/>
		&germlinegenomics_Refs;</sect1>
</article>