<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 3. Analysis of gene expression in larvae and adults </title>
        <para>The top diagram shows germline development during the various stages that were
            examined. Black = somatic gonad; orange = proliferating germ cells;
            pink = meiotic germ cells; red = differentiating spermatocytes; blue = differentiating
            oocytes. The clustergrams below show all genes whose expression changed over the
            timecourse examined. Each row represents a gene, and, in the clustergram on the left,
            each column represents a different timepoint in the analysis. The clustergram on the
            right shows the expression levels of the same genes (in the same order) in wild type,
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-4" role="_blank">glp-4</ulink>(ts)</emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-1" role="_blank">fem-1</ulink>(lf)</emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-3" role="_blank">fem-3</ulink>(gf)</emphasis> hermaphrodites, as well as in wild type and
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-4" role="_blank">glp-4</ulink>(ts)</emphasis> males. Above the clustergrams, small and large "+" indicate small and large
            germ line, "–" indicates diminished germ line in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-4" role="_blank">glp-4</ulink>(ts)</emphasis> mutants, and “fem” indicates
            the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-3" role="_blank">fem-3</ulink>(lf)</emphasis> vs <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-3" role="_blank">fem-3</ulink>(gf)</emphasis> experiment. Yellow indicates higher expression in staged wild
            type, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-4" role="_blank">glp-4</ulink>(ts)</emphasis>, or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-3" role="_blank">fem-3</ulink>(gf)</emphasis> samples; blue indicates higher expression in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fem-1" role="_blank">fem-1</ulink>(lf)</emphasis>, or
            a reference sample that was used for the timecourse. Clusters of genes with distinct
            temporal expression profiles are marked by letters. Cluster D contains almost
            exclusively spermatogenesis genes, while intrinsic and oogenesis genes are distributed
            among clusters E and F. Clusters A-C primarily contain somatic genes whose expression
            varies over time. Reprinted with permission from <link linkend="bib19">Reinke et al., 2004</link><!-- [PMID 14668411]-->.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>