<caption>
<formalpara>
<title>Figure 6. Model of how the initial left-right asymmetry of the Q neuroblasts may dictate which Wnt signaling pathway is activated.</title>
<para>Initial Q cell migration (top left side) is independent of Wnt signaling. In wild type, at the end of initial migration, canonical Wnt/&beta;-catenin signaling is activated in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=QL;class=Cell" role="_blank">QL</ulink> resulting in expression of the Hox gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003102;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> (red), while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=QR;class=Cell" role="_blank">QR</ulink> activates non-canonical Wnt signaling and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003102;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> expression is not upregulated (green). This is necessary for correct migration of the Q.x (right side), as canonical Wnt/&beta;-catenin signaling drives posterior migration of the QL.x (red arrow) and non-canonical Wnt signaling drives anterior migration of the QR.x (green arrow, the panels on the right show the final positions of Q.paa and Q.pap). In mutants that affect the initial polarization of the Q neuroblasts, the direction of polarization and migration is random. In the bottom left side, different possible states of Q cell polarization in initial Q polarity mutants are depicted. In these mutants, the degree of posterior polarization correlates with activation of the canonical Wnt/&beta;-catenin signaling pathway and high <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003102;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> expression (red). Anterior polarization correlates with activation of a non-canonical Wnt signaling response characterized by low <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003102;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> expression (green). Intermediate polarization states will result in intermediate levels of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003102;class=Gene" role="_blank">mab-5</ulink></emphasis> expression (lower left panel, yellow). Depending on the degree of polarization, a tug of war between canonical and non-canonical Wnt signaling (middle right panels) may decide the direction and extent of Q.x migration.</para>
</formalpara>
</caption>