<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % local.notation.class '| MOV'>
<!NOTATION MOV SYSTEM 'MOV'>
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'morphofig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'morphofig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'morphofig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'morphofig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'morphofig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'morphofig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'morphofig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'morphofig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'morphofig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'morphofig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'morphofig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'morphofig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig7 SYSTEM 'morphofig7.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig7legend SYSTEM 'morphofig7leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY mov1 SYSTEM 'morphofig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY mov1legend SYSTEM 'morphomov1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY mov2 SYSTEM 'morphofig5.jpg' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov2legend SYSTEM 'morphomov2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY mov3 SYSTEM 'morphofig5.jpg' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov3legend SYSTEM 'morphomov3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY mov4 SYSTEM 'morphofig5.jpg' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov4legend SYSTEM 'morphomov4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY mov5 SYSTEM 'morphofig5.jpg' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov5legend SYSTEM 'morphomov5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY mov6 SYSTEM 'morphofig5.jpg' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov6legend SYSTEM 'morphomov6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY mov7 SYSTEM 'morphofig5.jpg' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov7legend SYSTEM 'morphomov7leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY mov8 SYSTEM 'morphofig5.jpg' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov8legend SYSTEM 'morphomov8leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY mov9 SYSTEM 'morphofig5.jpg' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov9legend SYSTEM 'morphomov9leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY morpho_Refs SYSTEM 'morphorefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="morpho_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Epidermal morphogenesis<footnote>
		<para>Edited by James R. Priess and Geraldine Seydoux. Last revised May 19, 2005
				. Published December 01, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Chisholm, A.D. and Hardin, J. Epidermal morphogenesis (December 01, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. 
				elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.35.1
				, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
				<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 Andrew D. Chisholm and Jeff Hardin. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
				</footnote>
       </title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 5/19/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory> 
-->
        <author>
            <firstname>Andrew D.</firstname>
            <surname>Chisholm</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <orgname>Department of Molecular, Cellular and Developmental Biology, University of
                    California, Santa Cruz</orgname>
                <address> Santa Cruz, CA 95064 USA</address>
           </affiliation>
       </author>
        <author>
            <firstname>Jeff</firstname>
            <surname>Hardin <remark>
                    <footnote>
                        <para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:jdhardin@wisc.edu">jdhardin@wisc.edu</ulink>
                       </para>
                   </footnote>
               </remark>
           </surname>
            <affiliation>
                <orgname>Department of Zoology, University of Wisconsin, Madison</orgname>
                <address> Madison, WI 53706 USA</address>
           </affiliation>
       </author>
   </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The morphogenesis of the</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold-italic">C. elegans</emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">embryo is largely controlled
            by the development of the epidermis, also known as the hypodermis, a single epithelial
            layer that surrounds the animal. Morphogenesis of the epidermis involves cell-cell
            interactions with internal tissues, such as the developing nervous system and
            musculature. Genetic analysis of mutants with aberrant epidermal morphology has defined
            multiple steps in epidermal morphogenesis. In the wild type, epidermal cells are
            generated on the dorsal side of the embryo among the progeny of four early embryonic
            blastomeres. Specification of epidermal fate is regulated by a hierarchy of
            transcription factors. After specification, dorsal epidermal cells rearrange, a process
            known as dorsal intercalation. Most epidermal cells fuse to generate multinucleate
            syncytia. The dorsally located epidermal sheet undergoes epiboly to enclose the rest of
            the embryo in a process known as ventral enclosure; this movement requires both an
            intact epidermal layer and substrate neuroblasts. At least three distinct types of
            cellular behavior underlie the enclosure of different regions of the epidermis.
            Following enclosure, the epidermis elongates, a process driven by coordinated cell shape
            changes. Epidermal actin microfilaments, microtubules, and intermediate filaments all
            play roles in elongation, as do body wall muscles. The final shape of the epidermis is
            maintained by the collagenous exoskeleton, secreted by the apical surface of the epidermis.</emphasis></para>
   </abstract>
    <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>Morphogenesis is the development of form, of tissues, of organs, and of organisms.
            This chapter describes the major morphogenetic processes of the mid-to-late <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> embryo, focusing on the epidermis and its interactions with
            underlying neurons and muscle. The morphogenetic movements of early gastrulation are
            described in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_gastrulation/gastrulation.html"
                role="_blank">Gastrulation in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
           </ulink>. Morphogenesis of post-embryonic organs such as the gonad, vulva, and male
            tail, is described in the Sex determination section of WormBook.</para>
        <para>Our description of embryonic morphogenesis centers on the epidermis, as this tissue
            plays the major role in determining the shape of the animal. (&#x0201C;Epidermis&#x0201D; refers to the
            outer cellular layer of the organism. In older literature and in WormAtlas the epidermis
            is named hypodermis, although the terms are synonymous in <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis>. To avoid needless worm-specific terminology we will use
            &#x0201C;epidermis&#x0201D;). Morphogenesis of the epidermis involves both autonomously generated
            changes in epidermal cell shape and position, and interactions with internal tissues,
            including the developing nervous system and body wall muscles. Molecules required for
            epidermal morphogenesis thus include components of the epidermal cytoskeleton, epidermal
            cellular junctions, cell signaling pathways operating between the epidermal cells and
            underlying tissues, and of the extracellular matrix. More detailed accounts of these
            molecules can be found in the Cell biology section of WormBook.</para>
        <para>At the time of hatching, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> epidermis is almost
            entirely composed of syncytia formed by fusions of epidermal cells. The process and
            mechanism of cell fusion is described by Podbilewicz (see <ulink
                url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_cellfusion/cellfusion.html" role="_blank">Cell fusions</ulink>).
            Mutants defective in cell fusion, such as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=eff-1" role="_blank">eff-1</ulink></emphasis>, display aberrant
            elongation of the epidermis (<link linkend="bib43">Mohler et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11879640-->), indicating that cell
            fusion is required for normal epidermal morphogenesis; the mechanistic basis for this
            requirement has not been fully elucidated.</para>
        <para>In this review we follow the development of the epidermis during embryogenesis,
            focusing on processes and tissue interactions required for its morphogenesis. Our
            discussion of genes or molecules involved in these developmental processes is selective,
            and focuses on pathways whose role in the morphogenetic process has been analyzed in
            most detail. We begin with the specification of the major epidermal fates, then describe
            the morphogenetic processes of epidermal enclosure, dorsal intercalation, and
            elongation. Both enclosure and elongation exemplify organogenesis processes in that they
            involve interaction with underlying tissues: ventral neuroblasts are required for
            epidermal enclosure, whereas body muscles are required for epidermal elongation. We
            conclude with the role of the extracellular matrix, including the cuticle, in embryonic
            epidermal development.</para>
   </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Formation and specification of epidermal cells</title>
        <para>The anatomy of the mature epidermis is described by Hall (see the Anatomy
            section of WormBook). In this chapter we focus on the morphogenesis of the major
            epidermal cells, as defined by Gendreau et al. (<link linkend="bib18">Gendreau et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7813794-->) and
            modified by Page et al. (<link linkend="bib48">Page et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9224715-->). The 71 major epidermal cells
            form most of the epidermis; an additional 11 minor epidermal cells form epidermal
            syncytia at the extreme head and tail.</para>
        <para>The major epidermal cells are large cells that are generated after the
            9<superscript>th</superscript> round of embryonic cell divisions, 220-240 minutes after
            first cleavage; at this stage the embryo is composed of ~365 cells. The major epidermal
            cells are derived from four of the 12-cell stage blastomeres: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABarp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABarp</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABpla;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABpla</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABpra;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABpra</ulink>, and
            C. These blastomeres also give rise to other cell types: the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> blastomeres generate
            neuronal cells and C gives rise to body muscle. In general, epidermal cells arise
            piecemeal within these lineages; only at the 7<superscript>th</superscript> round of
            cleavages do exclusively epidermal precursors arise. The major epidermal precursors are
            located on the dorsal surface of the early embryo, and thus the major epidermal cells
            arise as a group on this surface. The minor epidermal cells are smaller and born later,
            after the 10<superscript>th</superscript> round of division. Once the terminal divisions
            that produce the epidermis occur, three major groups of cells are evident within the
            epidermis: (1) dorsal epidermal cells arise as two rows of ten cells each along the
            anterior-posterior axis, straddling the dorsal midline; (2) two more lateral rows of
            “seam” epidermal cells flanking the dorsal cells; and (3) ventral epidermal cells lying
            at the extreme lateral edges of the epidermis, ultimately migrating to meet at the
            ventral midline.</para>
        <para>Soon after their birth, the major epidermal cells express and begin to localize
            epithelial markers, such as the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AJM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">AJM-1</ulink> protein. Formation of an epidermal sheet thus
            begins within a few minutes of the birth of the major epidermal cells (<link linkend="bib42">McMahon et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11493666-->). The initial specification of epidermis requires the GATA family
            Zinc finger transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ELT-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ELT-1</ulink>. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elt-1" role="_blank">elt-1</ulink></emphasis> null mutants completely fail to undergo
            morphogenesis and contain excess neurons and muscles instead of epidermis. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ELT-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ELT-1</ulink> is
            expressed from about the 28-cell stage in cells that will give rise to, among other
            things, the major epidermal cells (<link linkend="bib48">Page et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9224715-->). It is likely that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ELT-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ELT-1</ulink>
            directly activates the transcription of at least two other transcription factors, the
            zinc finger protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-26;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-26</ulink> and the GATA family protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ELT-3;class=protein" role="_blank">ELT-3</ulink>.</para>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-26;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-26</ulink> expression begins at the 100-cell stage in precursors of major epidermal cells;
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-26;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-26</ulink> expression is continuous in these lineages. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-26;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-26</ulink> acts to maintain epithelial
            aspects of the epidermal fate; in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-26" role="_blank">lin-26</ulink></emphasis> null mutants epidermal
            fates are specified but abnormal; for example, epidermal cells fail to develop a normal
            apical-basal polarity. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-26" role="_blank">lin-26</ulink></emphasis> mutants display variable failures in
            morphogenesis, including defects in epidermal enclosure and elongation. Epidermal cells
            in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-26" role="_blank">lin-26</ulink></emphasis> mutants eventually become necrotic (<link linkend="bib37">Labouesse et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7956818-->).</para>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ELT-3;class=protein" role="_blank">ELT-3</ulink> is activated in all post-mitotic epidermis, except the seam cells, until the
            2.5-fold stage; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ELT-3;class=protein" role="_blank">ELT-3</ulink> expression then declines until it is reactivated in a second phase
            in the valve cells at either end of the gut (<link linkend="bib21">Gilleard et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10191044-->). An
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elt-3" role="_blank">elt-3</ulink></emphasis> null mutation does not cause detectable effects on
            embryogenesis, suggesting that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ELT-3;class=protein" role="_blank">ELT-3</ulink> functions redundantly with other epidermal regulators
            (<link linkend="bib20">Gilleard and McGhee, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11259601-->).</para>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-26;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-26</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ELT-3;class=protein" role="_blank">ELT-3</ulink>, and perhaps other proteins, likely regulate genes required for the
            expression of epidermal fates. Such genes must include those required generally in all
            epithelial cells, and those required specifically in the epidermis, such as cuticle
            components. Ectopic expression of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-26;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-26</ulink> induces expression of the general epithelial
            markers <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AJM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">AJM-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DLG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CHE-14;class=protein" role="_blank">CHE-14</ulink>, but not of genes specific to epidermal cells (<link linkend="bib58">Quintin et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11437447-->). However, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AJM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">AJM-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CHE-14;class=protein" role="_blank">CHE-14</ulink> expression is normal in
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-26" role="_blank">lin-26</ulink></emphasis> null mutant epidermal cells. Thus, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIN-26;class=protein" role="_blank">LIN-26</ulink> is sufficient, but
            not necessary, for expression of these epithelial markers, suggesting that multiple
            factors act combinatorially to completely specify the epidermal fate.</para>
   </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Movements of ventral neuroblasts</title>
        <para>Ventral neuroblasts form the substrate for later enclosure movements of the epidermis,
            and so their development is considered here. Ventral neuroblasts themselves undergo
            morphogenetic movements together known as ventral cleft closure (<xref
            linkend="movie1"/>). During gastrulation precursors of the gut, pharynx, and body
            muscles ingress on the ventral surface of the developing embryo (see <ulink
                url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_gastrulation/gastrulation.html" role="_blank">Gastrulation
                in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
           </ulink>). These ingression movements create a depression on the ventral surface, known
            as the ventral cleft (<xref linkend="figure1"/> and <xref linkend="figure2"/>; <link linkend="bib73">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6684600-->). The ventral cleft is surrounded by neuroblasts derived
            from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABplp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABplp</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABprp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABprp</ulink> in the posterior and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABalp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABalp</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=ABarp;class=Cell" role="_blank">ABarp</ulink> in the anterior. These ventral
            neuroblasts move <emphasis>en masse</emphasis> from more lateral positions towards the ventral midline
            between 230 and 290 minutes, causing the ventral cleft to disappear by about 290
            minutes, roughly an hour before epidermal enclosure begins. Ventral neuroblast movements
            begin at the posterior cleft and progress towards the anterior. The rate and timing of
            individual neuroblast movements have not been examined in detail, nor is it yet known if
            specific cells or cell groups play different roles in the movement. The ventral
            neuroblasts undergo their last major round of divisions between 250 and 310 minutes.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig1" align="center"/>
           </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 1</phrase>
           </textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
        <mediaobject id="movie1" xreflabel="Movie 1">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="mov1" align="center"/>
           </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Movie 1</phrase>
           </textobject> &mov1legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>Defects in the movement of ventral neuroblasts are seen in animals defective in any of
            several cell signaling pathways, including Eph receptor/ephrin, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PTP-3;class=protein" role="_blank">PTP-3</ulink>/LAR RPTP
            (Leukocyte Common Antigen Related Receptor Protein Tyrosine Phosphatase), and
            semaphorin-2A/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-20;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-20</ulink> (<link linkend="bib8">Chin-Sang et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10619431-->; <link linkend="bib9">Chin-Sang et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12403719-->; <link linkend="bib19">George et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9506518-->; <link linkend="bib26">Harrington et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11959824-->; <link linkend="bib62">Roy et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10648234-->; <link linkend="bib76">Wang et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10635316-->). Such
            defects result in an enlarged or persistent ventral cleft; if the ventral cleft is not
            closed by the time of epidermal enclosure, enclosure movements can be blocked. The
            cellular defects of the neuroblasts in these mutants have not yet been elucidated. Loss
            of function in the SCAR/WAVE gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=wve-1" role="_blank">wve-1</ulink></emphasis> causes drastic defects in
            ventral neuroblast organization (<link linkend="bib84">Withee et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15280232-->), suggesting that
            actin-based motility may be important for ventral neuroblast movement. However,
            abnormalities in actin distribution in ventral neuroblasts have not yet been observed in
            such mutants, possibly reflecting the limited resolution of available reagents. Ventral
            cleft closure is also defective in some neuronal cell fate mutants such as
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-62" role="_blank">unc-62</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pal-1" role="_blank">pal-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib75">Van Auken et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12399316-->). Mutations in the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pha-4" role="_blank">pha-4</ulink></emphasis> gene, which block pharynx specification, cause failure
            of ingression of pharyngeal precursors and later defects in epidermal enclosure and
            elongation, presumably reflecting a defective substrate (<link linkend="bib39">Mango et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7607089-->).</para>
        <para>Interestingly, null mutations in several genes cause slight delays in neuroblast
            migration, detectable by 4-D timelapse microscopy, that result in low penetrance
            epidermal enclosure defects. Such genes include the atypical ephrin
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=efn-4" role="_blank">efn-4</ulink></emphasis>, the Wiskott-Aldrich Syndrome Protein ortholog
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=wsp-1" role="_blank">wsp-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib84">Withee et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15280232-->), and the <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> Kallmann syndrome ortholog <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=kal-1" role="_blank">kal-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib64">Rugarli et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11874923-->; M.L. Hudson and A.D.C., unpublished results). These subliminal
            defects in neuroblast migration nevertheless appear to sensitize the embryo to loss of
            function in other pathways acting in neuroblast movement, as illustrated by the extreme
            synergistic effects of loss of function mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=efn-4" role="_blank">efn-4</ulink></emphasis> and
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=vab-1" role="_blank">vab-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib9">Chin-Sang et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12403719-->).</para>
        <para>The nature of the interaction between migrating epidermal cells and the neuronal
            substrate remains poorly understood. Epidermal enclosure may require a uniform
            substratum of cells; if this substrate is disrupted by a persistent ventral cleft,
            epidermal cells may be physically unable to enclose the embryo. Although it is possible
            that specific substrate cells may play instructive roles in guiding the movement of the
            overlying epidermis, laser killing experiments did not reveal individual cells that
            could play such roles (<link linkend="bib81">Williams-Masson et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9247332-->).</para>
   </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Intercalation of dorsal epidermal cells</title>
        <para>The preceding sections described the processes that lead to a dorsal sheet of
            epidermal cells and a ventral surface of substrate neuroblasts. Before epidermal
            enclosure begins, two rows of dorsal epidermal cells engage in a striking rearrangement,
            known as dorsal intercalation (<xref linkend="movie2"/> and <xref linkend="movie3"/>),
            to form a single row across the dorsal midline; intercalation begins approximately 10
            minutes after the terminal divisions of epidermal precursors. During the first stages of
            intercalation, dorsal cells become wedge shaped, with their pointed tips oriented toward
            the dorsal midline. Dorsal cells then interdigitate between their contralateral
            neighbors, eventually elongating until their extending edges make contacts with seam
            cells on the opposite side of the embryo (<link linkend="bib73">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6684600-->;
            <link linkend="bib78">Williams-Masson et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9851858-->; <xref linkend="figure3"/>). The nuclei of
            intercalating cells also migrate contralaterally (<link linkend="bib73">Sulston et al., 1983</link><!--; PMID 6684600-->;
            <link linkend="bib78">Williams-Masson et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9851858-->); however, nuclear migration is not required
            for successful intercalation (<link linkend="bib71">Starr et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11748140-->).</para>
<para>&#x000A0;</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig2" align="center" width="5.5in" depth="7.205in"/>
           </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 2</phrase>
           </textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>&#x000A0;</para>
        <mediaobject id="movie2" xreflabel="Movie 2">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="mov2" align="center"/>
           </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Movie 2</phrase>
           </textobject> &mov2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>&#x000A0;</para>
        <mediaobject id="movie3" xreflabel="Movie 3">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="mov3" align="center"/>
           </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Movie 3</phrase>
           </textobject> &mov3legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>The mechanisms by which dorsal cells rearrange is not well understood. Pharmacological
            studies indicate that both actin microfilaments and microtubules are required
            (<link linkend="bib78">Williams-Masson et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9851858-->), but the precise role each cytoskeletal
            system plays is unclear. Based on serial reconstructions of TEM thin sections
            (<link linkend="bib78">Williams-Masson et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9851858-->) and on dynamic imaging of a cytoplasmic
            GFP reporter (<link linkend="bib27">Heid et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11456452-->), dorsal cells extend basolateral
            membrane protrusions in the direction of rearrangement. After an initial period of
            protrusive activity at both their lateral and medial borders, dorsal cells extend highly
            polarized protrusions that extend far beyond the position of the overlying apical
            junctions (<xref linkend="figure5"/>a-c; <xref linkend="movie4"/>). Such activity is
            similar to the "monopolar" activity of some rearranging cells in the <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis> neural
            plate (<link linkend="bib14">Elul and Keller, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10898957-->) and the ascidian notochord (<link linkend="bib45">Munro and Odell, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11782397-->), and presumably allows dorsal epidermal cells to change
            position. What molecules are required for the extension of these basolateral
            protrusions, and what, if any, force they exert is unknown. Regardless of the mechanism,
            several lines of evidence suggest that an individual dorsal cell may be able to effect
            the cell-shape changes required for intercalation in a cell-autonomous fashion. Removal
            of the posterior portion of the dorsal epidermal array by ablation of the C blastomere,
            neighboring seam cells, or underlying muscle does not disrupt intercalation of the
            remaining cells (<link linkend="bib27">Heid et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11456452-->; <link linkend="bib78">Williams-Masson et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9851858-->).</para>
        <para>Little is known about the molecular control of dorsal intercalation. The C2H2 Zinc
            finger transcription factor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DIE-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DIE-1</ulink> is required for completion of intercalation, but not
            for the initial polarization of intercalating cells towards the dorsal midline (<link linkend="bib27">Heid et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11456452-->). Mosaic loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DIE-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DIE-1</ulink> in dorsal cells results in cell
            autonomous failure to complete intercalation, suggesting that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DIE-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DIE-1</ulink> is required in all
            intercalating cells (<link linkend="bib27">Heid et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11456452-->). Transcriptional targets of
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DIE-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DIE-1</ulink> have not yet been identified. Other genes are likely required for the correct
            patterning of the dorsal epidermis. These include the functionally redundant T box
            proteins, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TBX-8;class=protein" role="_blank">TBX-8</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TBX-9;class=protein" role="_blank">TBX-9</ulink>. Loss of function in either <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tbx-8" role="_blank">tbx-8</ulink></emphasis> or
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tbx-9" role="_blank">tbx-9</ulink></emphasis> results in occasional defects in the positioning of some
            dorsal cells, whereas <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tbx-8" role="_blank">tbx-8</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tbx-9" role="_blank">tbx-9</ulink></emphasis> double mutants or double RNAi
            embryos display severe disruption of the positioning and/or morphogenesis of the dorsal
            epidermis (<link linkend="bib1">Andachi, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15066124-->; <link linkend="bib54">Pocock et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15102704-->). Whereas
            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=die-1" role="_blank">die-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant dorsal cells appear correctly patterned and in the
            correct positions but fail to complete intercalation, dorsal cells in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tbx-8" role="_blank">tbx-8</ulink>
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tbx-9" role="_blank">tbx-9</ulink></emphasis> double mutants can complete intercalation even when they initiate it
            from an incorrect position (<link linkend="bib54">Pocock et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15102704-->), suggesting that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DIE-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DIE-1</ulink>
            and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TBX-8;class=protein" role="_blank">TBX-8</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TBX-9;class=protein" role="_blank">TBX-9</ulink> regulate different phases of the process.</para>
<para>&#x000A0;</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig3" align="center"/>
           </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 3</phrase>
           </textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
        <mediaobject id="movie4" xreflabel="Movie 4">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="mov4" align="center"/>
           </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Movie 4</phrase>
           </textobject> &mov4legend;</mediaobject>
<para>&#x000A0;</para>
        <mediaobject id="movie5" xreflabel="Movie 5">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="mov5" align="center"/>
           </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Movie 5</phrase>
           </textobject> &mov5legend;</mediaobject>
        <mediaobject id="movie6" xreflabel="Movie 6">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="mov6" align="center"/>
           </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Movie 6</phrase>
           </textobject> &mov6legend;</mediaobject>
   </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Ventral enclosure</title>
        <para>Ventral enclosure (<xref linkend="movie5"/>, <xref linkend="movie6"/> and <xref
            linkend="movie7"/>; <xref linkend="figure4"/>), the process by which ventral epidermal cells migrate toward the
            ventral midline to encase underlying cells in an epithelial monolayer, ensues shortly
            after dorsal intercalation begins (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). Based on 4-D Nomarski and
            multiphoton imaging, ventral enclosure occurs in two phases. First, two pairs of
            anterior, or ‘leading’ cells extend large protrusions as they migrate towards the
            ventral midline (<xref linkend="figure5"/>d-f; <xref linkend="movie6"/>). The anterior
            pair of leading cells are the two ventral cells that will later fuse to the hyp6
            syncytium; the posterior pair will eventually become part of hyp7. The migratory
            activity of these cells is essential for enclosure, since ventral enclosure can be
            completely blocked by the laser inactivation of these two pairs of cells
            (<link linkend="bib81">Williams-Masson et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9247332-->). In these experiments the leading cells
            were irradiated with laser power sufficient to prevent their movement, but not
            sufficient to kill them. In the second step, posterior ventral cells become wedge
            shaped and elongate toward the ventral midline, lining a ‘pocket’ at the ventral midline
                (<xref linkend="figure4"/>). Laser inactivation of a significant fraction of the
            ventral pocket cells also results in failure of enclosure; the elastic recoil of the
            leading edge in such experiments further suggests that the pocket is under mechanical
            tension. Ultimately, ventral epidermal cells make bilaterally symmetric contacts,
            thereby establishing new junctional connections at the ventral midline. The extreme
            anterior epidermis then completes the enclosure of the embryo by a sheet of epidermis
                (<xref linkend="figure4"/>).</para>
<para>&#x000A0;</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig4" align="center" width="5.451in" depth="5in"/>
           </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 4</phrase>
           </textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
<para>&#x000A0;</para>
        <mediaobject id="movie7" xreflabel="Movie 7">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="mov7" align="center"/>
           </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Movie 7</phrase>
           </textobject> &mov7legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>Pharmacological studies indicate that both the actin and microtubule cytoskeletal
            systems are required for enclosure (<link linkend="bib81">Williams-Masson et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9247332-->). The
            requirement for the latter is consistent with enclosure defects observed in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=evl-20" role="_blank">evl-20</ulink></emphasis>/ARL2
            mutants, which also show defects in microtubule organization (<link linkend="bib2">Antoshechkin and Han, 2002</link><!--; PMID 12015966-->).</para>
<para>&#x000A0;</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig5" align="center"/>
           </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 5</phrase>
           </textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
        <sect2>
            <title>Migration of the leading cells</title>
            <para>Several permissive requirements for leading cell migration and adhesion have been
                identified. First, Rac-dependent modulation of the actin cytoskeleton, presumably
                operating through the Arp2/3 complex, is required for the onset of migration.
                Progeny of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ced-10" role="_blank">ced-10</ulink></emphasis>/Rac mutant mothers (<link linkend="bib70">Soto et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11877381-->; <link linkend="bib38">Lundquist et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11714673-->), as well as embryos depleted of
                components of the Arp2/3 complex (<link linkend="bib65">Sawa et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12640035-->; <link linkend="bib67">Severson et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12498681-->), and the Rac interacting proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GEX-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GEX-2</ulink>/Sra-1 and
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GEX-3;class=protein" role="_blank">GEX-3</ulink>/HEM2/NAP1/KETTE (Gex <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003D;</symbol> <emphasis role="underline">g</emphasis>ut on
                the <emphasis role="underline">ex</emphasis>terior) display a highly disorganized epidermis that is largely unable to
                undergo ventral migration (<link linkend="bib70">Soto et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11877381-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CED-10;class=protein" role="_blank">CED-10</ulink> (<link linkend="bib6">Chen et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8824291-->), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GEX-2;class=protein" role="_blank">GEX-2</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=GEX-3;class=protein" role="_blank">GEX-3</ulink> (<link linkend="bib70">Soto et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11877381-->) all
                localize to the periphery of epidermal cells near apical junctions, suggesting that
                they are important for maintaining epidermal cell shape and protrusive activity. The
                Scar/Wave protein GEX-1/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=WVE-1;class=protein" role="_blank">WVE-1</ulink> likely acts as a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CED-10;class=protein" role="_blank">CED-10</ulink> effector in this pathway to
                activate the Arp2/3 complex, based on similarity of phenotype (M. Soto, personal
                communication; M. Sheffield and J. Hardin, unpublished). This same pathway may also
                be required for successful dorsal intercalation, although further analysis will be
                required to confirm this (M. Sheffield and J. Hardin, unpublished).</para>
            <para>Once leading cell migration is underway, regulation of leading cell protrusive
                activity is important for continued migration. The WASP family protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=WSP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">WSP-1</ulink> and the
                Ena/VASP family protein, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-34;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-34</ulink>, are likely to be important during this process:
                tissue-specific knockdown of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=wsp-1" role="_blank">wsp-1</ulink></emphasis> function in epidermal cells
                (<link linkend="bib65">Sawa et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12640035-->) or simultaneous depletion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-34;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-34</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=WSP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">WSP-1</ulink>
                (<link linkend="bib84">Withee et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15280232-->) results in enclosure defects. Since both WASP
                and Ena/VASP family proteins regulate activation of the Arp2/3 complex and filament
                dynamics at the plus ends of actin filaments, respectively, these likely exert their
                effects on enclosure by regulating the polymerization of actin at the free edges of
                the enclosing epidermis. Cell signaling, in part mediated via inositol trisphosphate
                (IP<subscript>3</subscript>), also appears to regulate leading cell migration. Offspring of hermaphrodites
                carrying a weak mutation in the single <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> IP<subscript>3</subscript> receptor
                gene, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=itr-1" role="_blank">itr-1</ulink></emphasis>, display reduced protrusive activity at the leading
                edge and a variety of enclosure defects (<link linkend="bib74">Thomas-Virnig et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15498499-->).</para>
            <para>Another requirement for successful leading cell function is the cadherin/catenin
                junctional complex. Leading cells in embryos lacking both maternal and zygotic
                contributions of any of the components of the cadherin/catenin complex
                (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HMR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HMR-1</ulink>A/cadherin, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HMP-2;class=protein" role="_blank">HMP-2</ulink>/<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-catenin, or
                    <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HMP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HMP-1</ulink>/<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>-catenin; see <ulink
                    url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_cadherinsuperfam/cadherinsuperfam.html" role="_blank">The
                    cadherin superfamily</ulink> and <ulink
                    url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_epithelialjunctionsattach/epithelialjunctionsattach.html"
                    role="_blank">Epithelial junctions and attachments</ulink> for further
                information) can extend protrusions, but these protrusions fail to make stable
                adhesive contacts at the ventral midline (<xref linkend="movie8"/>). Analysis of
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HMP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HMP-1</ulink>::GFP distribution in living embryos indicates that leading cell protrusions
                accumulate cytoplasmic <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HMP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HMP-1</ulink>, which is rapidly recruited to nascent junctions upon
                their contact at the midline, a process that has been termed "filopodial priming"
                (<link linkend="bib59">Raich et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10531027-->).</para>
            <mediaobject id="movie8" xreflabel="Movie 8">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="mov8" align="center"/>
               </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase>Movie 8</phrase>
               </textobject> &mov8legend;</mediaobject>
       </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Movement of epidermal cells in the ventral pocket</title>
            <para>Whereas the migratory behavior of leading cells clearly leads to their ventral
                migration, how the ventral pocket closes is less certain. Actin is concentrated at
                the ventral tips of pocket cells, which suggests that the ventral pocket may close
                via a multicellular purse-string mechanism (<link linkend="bib81">Williams-Masson et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9247332-->). However, multiphoton imaging has shown that pocket cells also extend short
                protrusions towards the ventral midline as they migrate (<link linkend="bib74">Thomas-Virnig et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15498499-->). Both filopodial protrusions and a robust actin cable have been
                observed during <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> dorsal closure; the former are
                presumed to aid bilateral cell-cell matching and the latter contributes forces for
                closure (<link linkend="bib33">Jacinto et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12110163-->). Similar mechanisms may operate during
                ventral pocket closure in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. That regulation of
                protrusive contacts between pocket cells is important during pocket closure is
                suggested by defects in mutants for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-20" role="_blank">mab-20</ulink>/Ce-sema-2a</emphasis>, which
                encodes a secreted Semaphorin. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-20" role="_blank">mab-20</ulink></emphasis> mutants display ectopic
                contacts between adjacent pocket cells during enclosure (<link linkend="bib62">Roy et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10648234-->). Semaphorins typically mediate repulsive guidance cues in other contexts
                (<link linkend="bib49">Pasterkamp and Kolodkin, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12593985-->); <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-20;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-20</ulink> may limit adhesion between
                adjacent pocket cells as they migrate by preventing ectopic protrusive activity.</para>
       </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Enclosure of the head</title>
            <para>The enclosure of the head epidermis (defined as the syncytia hyp1-5) has not been
                extensively characterized. Correct specification of head epidermal cells is likely
                necessary for head enclosure, as loss of function in the homeobox genes
                    <emphasis>ceh-13/labial</emphasis> or <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ceh-43" role="_blank">ceh-43</ulink>/Distal-less</emphasis>
                results in ruptures of head epidermis (<link linkend="bib3">Aspock and Burglin, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11747075-->;
                <link linkend="bib5">Brunschwig et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10068646-->). Based on SEM, multiphoton and spinning disk
                confocal imaging, the extreme anterior epidermal cells do not produce long,
                anterior-directed protrusions, although some epidermal cells that contribute to the
                hyp3 and hyp4 syncytia display long protrusions as they migrate (J. Hardin,
                unpublished observations). As with ventral epidermal cells in the trunk,
                semaphorin-mediated signaling may regulate contacts between adjacent ventral cells.
                In this case, the transmembrane semaphorin, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SMP-1</ulink>/Ce-sema-1a, may be redundant with
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MAB-20;class=protein" role="_blank">MAB-20</ulink>. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=smp-1" role="_blank">smp-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants display a "displaced mouth" phenotype,
                indicative of defects in the morphogenesis of hyp3; these defects are exacerbated in
                    <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mab-20" role="_blank">mab-20</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=smp-1" role="_blank">smp-1</ulink></emphasis> double mutants (<link linkend="bib22">Ginzburg et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11959817-->).</para>
       </sect2>
   </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Embryonic elongation</title>
        <para>Immediately after the epidermis is enclosed, elongation converts the bean-shaped
            embryo into the elongated shape of the worm (<xref linkend="movie9"/>). In our
            discussion of elongation we focus on the epidermis, as this tissue is thought to provide
            the driving force for the elongation movement. Based on analysis of pharyngeal
            specification mutants (<link linkend="bib39">Mango et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 7607089-->) and laser killing experiments
            (<link linkend="bib34">Junkersdorf and Scheierenberg, 1992</link><!--; PMID-->), the pharynx and intestine may not be
            required for the embryo to elongate. However, at least one internal tissue (body muscle)
            is essential for full elongation of the epidermis.</para>
<para>&#x000A0;</para>
        <mediaobject id="movie9" xreflabel="Movie 9">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="mov9" align="center"/>
           </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase>Movie 9</phrase>
           </textobject> &mov9legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>Epidermal elongation begins ~350 minutes after first cleavage and is largely complete
            by 600 minutes (<xref linkend="figure1"/>). During elongation, the embryo reduces its
            circumference by a factor of three and increases in length by a factor of four.
            Elongation after the 1.5-fold stage (430 minutes) proceeds at ~50 <symbol
            role="symbolfont">&#x03BC;</symbol>m/hour until ~600 minutes (<link linkend="bib40">McKeown et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9570773-->). The rate of elongation is highly reproducible and late
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos are developmentally staged by their extent
            of elongation (<xref linkend="figure1"/>).</para>
        <para>Elongation of the embryo reflects the elongation of epidermal cells along the
            anterior-posterior axis (<link linkend="bib57">Priess and Hirsh, 1986</link><!--; PMID 3743895-->). The apical surfaces of
            epidermal cells shorten around the animal’s circumference while elongating in the
            orthogonal direction, along the anterior-posterior axis. Laser killing experiments have
            demonstrated that the integrity of the epidermal sheet is essential for elongation
            (<link linkend="bib57">Priess and Hirsh, 1986</link><!--; PMID 3743895-->). An essential role for underlying muscle cells
            in later elongation has been shown by genetic analysis (see below).</para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Early elongation (between comma and two-fold stages)</title>
            <para>The onset of elongation involves several processes. First, both actin
                microfilaments and microtubules within dorsal and ventral epidermal cells become
                highly organized in a striking circumferential pattern, in association with the
                apical plasma membrane (<link linkend="bib10">Costa et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9133443-->; <link linkend="bib11">Costa et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9531567-->; <link linkend="bib57">Priess and Hirsh, 1986</link><!--; PMID 3743895-->; <link linkend="bib81">Williams-Masson et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9247332-->). Both filament systems are required for elongation: treatment with the
                microfilament inhibitor cytochalasin D prevents elongation entirely, and treatment
                with the microtubule inhibitor nocodazole results in disorganized elongation.
                Remarkably, the effects of cytochalasin are reversible (<link linkend="bib57">Priess and Hirsh, 1986</link><!--; PMID 3743895-->). Although the mechanisms by which circumferential actin filament
                bundles (CFBs) form in such an ordered fashion is unknown, their assembly is
                transient; actin filaments do not align until near the end of ventral enclosure, and
                they do not persist after elongation is complete (<link linkend="bib10">Costa et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9133443-->;
                <link linkend="bib81">Williams-Masson et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9247332-->).</para>
            <para>Genetic analysis has demonstrated that actomyosin-based contraction of epidermal
                cells is crucial for elongation. Loss of function of the <emphasis>C.
                elegans</emphasis> homologue of Rho-binding kinase (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-502;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-502</ulink>) results in reduced
                elongation; conversely, loss of function of the myosin phosphatase, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEL-11;class=protein" role="_blank">MEL-11</ulink>, results
                in "hypercontraction", as local regions of excessive constriction occur. Null
                mutants for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-502" role="_blank">let-502</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mel-11" role="_blank">mel-11</ulink></emphasis> suppress
                one another, indicating that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-502;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-502</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEL-11;class=protein" role="_blank">MEL-11</ulink> act antagonistically during
                elongation. The relatively normal elongation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-502" role="_blank">let-502</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mel-11" role="_blank">mel-11</ulink></emphasis>
                double mutants indicates that this pathway is redundant with additional pathways in
                regulating elongation; components of such parallel pathways include the phosphatase
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=FEM-2;class=protein" role="_blank">FEM-2</ulink>, better known for its function in sex determination (see the Sex determination
                section of WormBook; <link linkend="bib53">Piekny et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11102366-->; <link linkend="bib82">Wissmann et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10208747-->; <link linkend="bib83">Wissmann et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9042856-->).</para>
            <para>Based on the expression patterns of these regulatory proteins (see below), it is
                thought that the actomyosin-based contractile machinery is predominantly active in
                the lateral seam cells. Seam cells may transmit contractile forces to dorsal and
                ventral cells via CFBs and cadherin-catenin junctions; the dorsal and ventral cells
                may not actively constrict, but may passively respond to seam-generated forces.
                However, components of dorsal and ventral epidermal cell cytoskeleton become
                essential for epidermal elongation after the two fold stage; although this
                requirement is not fully understood, it suggests that dorsal and ventral cells may
                actively reorganize their cytoskeleton in later elongation.</para>
            <para>Both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-502;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-502</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEL-11;class=protein" role="_blank">MEL-11</ulink> are expressed at high levels in the cytoplasm of seam
                cells; when elongation starts, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEL-11;class=protein" role="_blank">MEL-11</ulink> becomes confined to cell-cell junctions where
                it can no longer inhibit the contractile apparatus (<link linkend="bib52">Piekny et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14522875-->). Moreover, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-502;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-502</ulink> is coextensive with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MLC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink>, a myosin regulatory light
                chain that is expressed at high levels in seam cells (<link linkend="bib68">Shelton et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10427096-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mlc-4" role="_blank">mlc-4</ulink></emphasis> is required zygotically for elongation
                (<link linkend="bib68">Shelton et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10427096-->), making <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MLC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink> a likely target of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-502;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-502</ulink>.
                Together, these data suggest that by acting on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MLC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-502;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-502</ulink> promotes
                actomyosin-mediated contraction, whereas <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEL-11;class=protein" role="_blank">MEL-11</ulink> mediates relaxation: in seam cells,
                contractile forces predominate and the cells elongate. Two non-muscle myosin heavy
                chains, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMY-1;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMY-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> have partially redundant roles in elongation and are
                presumably both regulated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MLC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink> (<link linkend="bib52">Piekny et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14522875-->).</para>
            <para>The linkage of CFBs to adherens junctions is critical for converting the forces of
                contraction into coordinated elongation across the entire epidermis. Mutations in
                genes encoding core proteins of the cadherin-catenin complex
                (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hmp-1" role="_blank">hmp-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hmp-2" role="_blank">hmp-2</ulink></emphasis>, and
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hmr-1" role="_blank">hmr-1</ulink></emphasis>) or associated proteins result in elongation failure or
                abnormalities due to detachment of CFBs. Whereas absence of maternally and
                zygotically contributed cadherin-catenin complex proteins result in enclosure
                failure (often the Hammerhead (Hmr) phenotype; see above), zygotic
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hmp-1" role="_blank">hmp-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hmp-2" role="_blank">hmp-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants display a milder
                Humpback (Hmp) phenotype, in which embryos enclose but form abnormal bulges when
                they attempt to elongate (<link linkend="bib11">Costa et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9531567-->). In Hmp mutants CFBs
                visibly detach from junctions. Based on its genetic interactions with a weak loss of
                function allele of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hmp-1" role="_blank">hmp-1</ulink>(fe4)</emphasis>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=JAC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">JAC-1</ulink>/p120ctn positively
                modulates cadherin-catenin function in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> but is not
                itself essential (<link linkend="bib50">Pettitt et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12847081-->). The claudin-like putative
                four-pass transmembrane protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-9;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-9</ulink> also localizes to the adherens junctional
                domain and requires HMR 1 for its localization (<link linkend="bib69">Simske et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12819787-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=vab-9" role="_blank">vab-9</ulink></emphasis> null mutants have elongation and body-shape abnormalities
                and perturbed CFB organization (<link linkend="bib69">Simske et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12819787-->; <xref linkend="figure6"/>).</para>
            <para>The epidermal spectrin cytoskeleton is essential for epidermal elongation. Loss of
                function in the sole <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
                <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>-spectrin, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SPC-1</ulink>, causes embryos to
                arrest in mid-elongation (<link linkend="bib46">Norman and Moerman, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11994313-->). <emphasis>C.
                elegans</emphasis> expresses two <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol>-spectrins, the conventional <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol><subscript>G</subscript>-spectrin <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-70;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-70</ulink> (<link linkend="bib24">Hammarlund et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10811832-->; <link linkend="bib44">Moorthy et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10811831-->) and the <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B2;</symbol><subscript>H</subscript>-spectrin <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SMA-1</ulink>. Null mutants in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sma-1" role="_blank">sma-1</ulink></emphasis> (for <emphasis role="underline">Sma</emphasis>ll) display
                slower elongation (<link linkend="bib40">McKeown et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9570773-->) and variable defects in the
                organization of actin in seam cells (<link linkend="bib55">Praitis et al., 2005</link>). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-70;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-70</ulink> does not appear to be required individually for elongation
                but may account for the residual elongation of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sma-1" role="_blank">sma-1</ulink></emphasis> null
                mutants (<link linkend="bib44">Moorthy et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10811831-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SMA-1</ulink> is associated with the apical
                membrane in dorsal and lateral epidermis (<link linkend="bib55">Praitis et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15890334-->), and
                the organization of CFBs is mildly abnormal in both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sma-1" role="_blank">sma-1</ulink></emphasis> and
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spc-1" role="_blank">spc-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib40">McKeown et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9570773-->; <link linkend="bib46">Norman and Moerman, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11994313-->). This suggests that a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMA-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SMA-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SPC-1</ulink> complex could
                stabilize actin filaments at the apical surface of epidermal cells, particularly in
                seam cells as they contract.</para>
       </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Late elongation</title>
            <para>Elongation beyond the two-fold stage appears to require additional molecular
                mechanisms in addition to the components described above (<link linkend="bib13">Ding et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15501449-->). The first evidence that later stages of elongation may differ
                mechanistically from the earlier stages came from analysis of mutants affecting
                muscle function. Mutations causing complete absence of muscle function result in
                failure to elongate beyond the two-fold stage (the Pat, paralyzed arrest at
                two-fold, phenotype; <link linkend="bib77">Williams and Waterston, 1994</link><!--; PMID 8106547-->). In such mutants
                elongation appears to proceed at a normal rate until the two-fold stage when it ceases.</para>
            <para> The mechanism by which muscle function promotes epidermal cell shape change is
                not known. It is known that muscles induce and localize hemidesmosome-containing
                trans-epidermal attachment structures (‘fibrous organelles’) within the epidermal
                cytoskeleton (<link linkend="bib17">Francis and Waterston, 1991</link><!--; PMID 1860880-->; <link linkend="bib31">Hresko et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 8106548-->); for a detailed description of the molecules of attachment structures, see
                    <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_epithelialjunctionsattach/epithelialjunctionsattach.html"
                    role="_blank">Epithelial junctions and attachments</ulink>. Attachment structures
                can be regarded as analogous to tendons, transmitting the force of muscle
                contraction to the cuticular exoskeleton. Components of these attachment structures,
                such as Myotactin/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-805;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-805</ulink> (<link linkend="bib30">Hresko et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10444073-->), Plectin/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-10;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-10</ulink>A
                (<link linkend="bib4">Bosher et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12756232-->), Intermediate filament (IF) proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=IFB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">IFB-1</ulink> and
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=IFA-3;class=protein" role="_blank">IFA-3</ulink> (<link linkend="bib85">Woo et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14975728-->), and the novel cytoplasmic adaptor protein
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=VAB-19;class=protein" role="_blank">VAB-19</ulink> (<link linkend="bib12">Ding et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14534136-->), are essential for epidermal elongation
                past the two-fold stage. At present there is no evidence that IFs function in
                earlier elongation or morphogenesis, although this conclusion is qualified by the
                lack of data on the function of most <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> IFs.</para>
            <para>Unlike &#x0201C;strong Pat&#x0201D; mutants, which are completely paralyzed, mutants defective in
                epidermal attachment structures display initially normal muscle contractions from
                the 1.75-fold stage, prior to detachment of muscles from the epidermis. The
                interdependence of muscles and epidermal attachment structures confounds efforts to
                determine whether the role of muscles in elongation reflects their function in
                formation of trans-epidermal attachments, or whether attachment structures, by
                allowing muscle force transduction to the epidermis, promote some additional
                muscle-dependent function. If the role of muscles is to induce and organize
                attachment structures, this begs the question of why trans-epidermal attachments
                (which are only found in dorsal and ventral epidermis) are required for elongation.
                Attachment structures likely interact with other components of the epidermal
                cytoskeleton, such as circumferential actin and microtubule bundles or the apical
                spectrin cytoskeleton. Abnormalities in the trans-epidermal attachment structures
                may in turn result in defects of the cytoskeletal structures required for
                elongation. The molecular basis for such interactions is not yet known.</para>
            <para>The extracellular matrix basement membrane (bm) secreted by the epidermis is
                essential for normal elongation, although the requirements for bm components can
                vary. Lack of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-52;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-52</ulink>/Perlecan causes elongation to be blocked at the two-fold stage,
                the ‘severe Pat’ phenotype, reflecting an essential role for perlecan in
                integrin-mediated assembly of the myofilament lattice in body wall muscles (<link linkend="bib31">Hresko et al., 1994</link><!--; PMID 8106548-->). In contrast, lack of the <symbol
                role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>(IV) basement membrane collagens <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EMB-9;class=protein" role="_blank">EMB-9</ulink> or
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-2;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-2</ulink> causes progressive muscle detachment and a late block in elongation at the
                three-fold stage (<link linkend="bib23">Gupta et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9166417-->) (the ‘Lat’ phenotype described
                by <link linkend="bib31">Williams and Waterston, 1994</link>). Because <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EMB-9;class=protein" role="_blank">EMB-9</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-2;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-2</ulink> only localize to the
                regions of bm between muscle and epidermis, the requirement for bm collagens again
                reflects the requirement for muscle-epidermal interaction for normal epidermal
                elongation. Mutations affecting laminin <symbol
                role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol> result in pleiotropic effects on epidermal
                morphogenesis that may reflect both failure to maintain epidermal apical-basal
                polarity and specific defects in muscle-epidermal attachment (<link linkend="bib32">Huang et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12783803-->).</para>
            <para>During elongation the shape of the epidermis is actively regulated by the
                epidermal actin cytoskeleton. At their apical surface epidermal cells secrete the
                extracellular embryonic sheath, whose function is not well understood. After
                elongation is complete, the epidermis begins to secrete the cuticle of the first
                stage larva. The cuticle now takes over the role of holding the epidermal cells in
                place. Animals lacking the cuticle collagen <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SQT-3;class=protein" role="_blank">SQT-3</ulink> elongate normally but then fail to
                maintain the elongated form and retract (<link linkend="bib57">Priess and Hirsh, 1986</link><!--; PMID 3743895-->).
                Similar late defects in epidermal morphogenesis result from loss of function in
                other collagens or in enzymes required for collagen processing such as the protease
                <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DPY-31;class=protein" role="_blank">DPY-31</ulink> (<link linkend="bib47">Novelli et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15579684-->). Defects in cuticle secretion also
                result in late-onset defects in elongation (<link linkend="bib61">Roberts et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14551256-->).</para>
<para>&#x000A0;</para>
            <mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig6" align="center"/>
               </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase> figure 6</phrase>
               </textobject> &fig6legend;</mediaobject>
       </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Summary and prospects</title>
            <para>
                <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryonic morphogenesis comprises a rich array of
                developmental and cell biological processes that are becoming increasingly
                tractable. Many of the processes of embryonic morphogenesis exemplify morphogenetic
                processes found in other organisms (epiboly, cell intercalation, constriction of the
                apical cytoskeleton). Almost all the molecular pathways so far defined are shared
                with other organisms, making <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> morphogenesis a model
                for many cellular and developmental phenomena.</para>
            <para>As morphogenesis by its nature is a dynamic process, timelapse analysis has been
                essential to form an accurate picture of morphogenetic processes and defects.
                Advanced microscopy methods that allow dynamic analysis of subcellular structures
                will increasingly be needed to explore these processes. Computer aided
                reconstructions of the cellular dynamics of morphogenetic movements are labor
                intensive, but likely will become increasingly important in understanding the
                cellular movements in embryos (<link linkend="bib29">Heid et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11977985-->; <link linkend="bib66">Schnabel et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9133433-->). A major future goal will be to test roles for specific cells or
                subcellular structures by laser microsurgery combined with timelapse recording.</para>
            <para>Although genetic and RNA interference analysis has provided insights into many of
                the processes of epidermal morphogenesis, we are clearly still far from a detailed
                mechanistic understanding of most morphogenetic movements. As morphogenesis is an
                essential process, very large scale screens for morphogenetic mutants are labor
                intensive; with the possible exception of the Hmr or Pat phenotypes, forward screens
                for morphogenetic defects have not been saturated. With the advent of RNAi
                hypersensitive strain backgrounds, a more comprehensive picture of the genetic
                requirements for embryonic morphogenesis should be within reach. Finally, an
                emerging theme is that many interesting pathways in morphogenesis display a high
                degree of redundancy: roles of such pathways can only be revealed by quantitative
                timelapse studies or by use of sensitized genetic backgrounds.</para>
<para>&#x000A0;</para>
            <mediaobject id="figure7" xreflabel="Figure 7">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig7" align="center" width="5.5in" depth="3.772in"/>
               </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase> figure 7</phrase>
               </textobject> &fig7legend;</mediaobject>
       </sect2>
   </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Acknowledgements</title>
        <para>We thank the co-workers mentioned in the Figure and Movie legends for images and 4D
            movies. Work on <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> morphogenesis in our laboratories is
            supported by NIH grants GM54657 (A.D.C.) and GM58038 (J.H.) and NSF grant IBN0112803 (J.H.).</para>
   </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title>
<para/>
&morpho_Refs;</sect1>
</article>
