<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 5. Protrusive activity during morphogenesis</title>
<para>Both dorsal (top row, A-C) and ventral (bottom row, D-F) epidermal cells display protrusive activity as they migrate. (A) A schematic of cell wedging during dorsal intercalation, corresponding to <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3B</link>. (B) An embryo expressing an <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lbp-1" role="_blank">lbp-1</ulink>::gfp</emphasis> transcription reporter to mark epidermal cells (<link linkend="bib27">Heid et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11456452-->), imaged using spinning disk confocal microscopy (courtesy of R. King; see also <xref linkend="movie4"/>). Mosaicism has resulted in expression only in the righthand cohort of posterior dorsal epidermal cells. Rearranging cells extend long protrusions in the direction of migration (arrow). (C) A schematic showing the relationship between such basolateral protrusions and rearrangement of dorsal cells (here and in F, anterior at the top). Protrusions lie basal to the apical junctional domain (pink). In addition, although it is not understood, wedging must presumably remodel junctional proteins as they rearrange (red; see <link linkend="bib25">Hardin and Walston (2004</link><!--; PMID 15261656-->) for detailed discussion). (D) A schematic of leading cell migration during ventral enclosure, corresponding to <link linkend="figure4">Figure 4B</link>. (E) An embryo expressing a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dlg-1" role="_blank">dlg-1</ulink>::gfp</emphasis> transcriptional reporter (<link linkend="bib15">Firestein and Rongo, 2001a</link><!--; PMID 11694581-->) visualized using spinning disk confocal microscopy (courtesy of M. Sheffield; see also <xref linkend="movie7"/>). Migrating leading cells extend long protrusions in the direction of migration (arrows); in time-lapse sequences, pocket cells can also be observed with shorter protrusions. Scale bar = 5 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03BC;</symbol>m. (F) A schematic showing the relationship between leading cell protrusions and the underlying cellular substratum of neuroblasts (anterior at the top). Protrusions make contact via cadherin/catenin complex proteins on their surfaces (green). F-actin is abundant within the cytoplasm of extending protrusions and may connect to cadherin complex proteins (&#x0201C;filopodial priming&#x0201D;; <link linkend="bib59">Raich et al., 1999a</link><!--; PMID 10531027-->).</para>
   </formalpara>
</caption>




