<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 6. Requirements for cadherin-based adhesion during morphogenesis</title>
        <para>The cadherin/catenin complex and associated proteins are required for ventral
            enclosure and elongation. Left column (A-C), Nomarski images; right column (D-F),
            phalloidin staining of F-actin imaged using confocal microscopy. (A) Wild-type embryo at
            approximately the three-fold stage. (B) A <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hmp-1" role="_blank">hmp-1</ulink>(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=zu278;class=Variation" role="_blank">zu278</ulink>)</emphasis> homozygote from a heterozygous mother, displaying the Hmp (<emphasis role="underline">H</emphasis>u<emphasis role="underline">mp</emphasis>back) phenotype. Prominent dorsal bulges in the epidermis are visible (arrows). (C) An embryo from a
                <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hmp-1" role="_blank">hmp-1</ulink>(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=zu278;class=Variation" role="_blank">zu278</ulink>)</emphasis> germline mosaic mother, which therefore lacks both
            maternal and zygotic <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HMP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HMP-1</ulink>, displaying the more severe Hmr (<emphasis role="underline"
                >H</emphasis>a<emphasis>m</emphasis>me<emphasis role="underline">r</emphasis>head)
            phenotype. Enclosure failure in the anterior results in rupture of the embryo and
            ejection of internal cells through the opening in the epidermis. For a multiphoton movie
            of such enclosure failure, see <xref linkend="movie8"/>. (D) Phalloidin staining of a
            wild-type embryo at approximately the three-fold stage of elongation. Circumferential
            filament bundles (CFBs) are clearly visible; the bright staining is one of the four
            muscle quadrants. (E) A <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hmp-1" role="_blank">hmp-1</ulink>(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=zu278;class=Variation" role="_blank">zu278</ulink>)</emphasis> homozygote stained with
            phalloidin. CFBs have detached from cell-cell junctions (arrows). (F) A <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=vab-9" role="_blank">vab-9</ulink>(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=e2016;class=Variation" role="_blank">e2016</ulink>)</emphasis> embryo. CFBs aggregate into abnormally large bundles (arrow).
            Images in (A, B, D, E) courtesy of M. Costa; (C) courtesy of W. B. Raich, from (<link linkend="bib11">Costa et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9531567-->); used by permission of Rockefeller Press. (F) is courtesy of J.
            Simske, from (<link linkend="bib69">Simske et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12819787-->); used by permission of Nature
            Publishing Group. Scale bar <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003D;</symbol> 5 <symbol
                role="symbolfont">&#x03BC;</symbol>m.</para>
   </formalpara>
</caption>
