<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 7. Embryonic elongation</title>
        <para>Nomarski images (A-C, left column; lateral view; see also <xref linkend="movie9"/>)
            and corresponding <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=DLG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">DLG-1</ulink>::GFP images, highlighting epidermal cell boundaries (middle
            column; D-F), of embryonic elongation. (G, H) Schematic representations of a section of
            the trunk epidermis corresponding to the boxed regions in panels D and E, respectively.
            (G, H) are adapted from (<link linkend="bib7">Chin-Sang and Chisholm, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11102704-->), with permission
            of Elsevier Publishing. Ventral cells are shown in pink, seam cells in yellow, and
            dorsal cells in teal. Contractile forces are produced predominantly by seam epidermal
            cells (arrows pointing toward one another), and transmitted to dorsal and ventral cells
            via adherens junctions (black ovals), which anchor circumferential actin filaments
            bundles (CFBs) in dorsal and ventral cells (black lines and arrows within dorsal and
            ventral cells). CFBs are thought to transmit and distribute the forces of contraction
            evenly throughout the epidermis. In seam cells, the activity of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-502;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-502</ulink>/Rho kinase is
            high, leading to myosin-dependent contraction; conversely, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEL-11;class=protein" role="_blank">MEL-11</ulink>/myosin phosphatase
            activity is low in seam cells and presumed high in non-seam cells. (I) Phalloidin
            staining of a wild-type embryo at approximately the two-fold stage of elongation (dorsal
            view). CFBs are clearly visible. The bright staining is one of the four muscle quadrants
            (image courtesy of E. William-Masson). Scale bar <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003D;</symbol> 5 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03BC;</symbol>m.</para>
   </formalpara>
</caption>
