<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 7. Proteins required for cytokinesis can grouped based on their depletion phenotypes</title>
        <para>Proteins that localize to the cortical contractile ring in <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> are shown in green. Rho has not been localized in <emphasis>C.
                elegans</emphasis> but activated Rho localizes to the furrow in other systems. Proteins that
            localize to the spindle midzone/midbody in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> are shown in
            red. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-21;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-21</ulink> (yellow) has not been localized in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, but is
            reported to localize to both the contractile ring and the spindle midzone/midbody in
            other systems. In embryos depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-21;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-21</ulink> or the contractile ring components <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMY-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink>,
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MLC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CYK-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CYK-1</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RHO-1;class=protein" role="_blank">RHO-1</ulink>, a normal spindle midzone forms between the separating chromosomes
            but furrow formation is inhibited and ingression often fails. In embryos depleted of the
            spindle midzone/midbody components <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CYK-4;class=protein" role="_blank">CYK-4</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZEN-4;class=protein" role="_blank">ZEN-4</ulink> or the chromosomal passenger proteins
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AIR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=BIR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">BIR-1</ulink>, INCENP and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CSC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CSC-1</ulink>, a normal spindle midzone fails to form. Cleavage furrows
            form and ingress, but cytokinesis fails to complete and the furrow ultimately regresses.
            In embryos depleted of the spindle midzone/midbody component, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-1</ulink>, the first
            cytokinesis succeeds despite defects in the structure of the spindle
        midzone/midbody.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>