<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'celldivisionfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'celldivisionfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'celldivisionfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'celldivisionfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'celldivisionfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'celldivisionfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'celldivisionfig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'celldivisionfig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'celldivisionfig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'celldivisionfig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'celldivisionfig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'celldivisionfig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig7 SYSTEM 'celldivisionfig7.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig7legend SYSTEM 'celldivisionfig7leg.xml'>

<!ENTITY celldivision_Refs SYSTEM 'celldivisionrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="celldivision_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <title>Cell division<footnote>
                <para>Edited by James M. Kramer and Donald G. Moerman. Last revised May 4, 2005. Published January 19, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Oegema, K. and Hyman, A. A. Cell division (January 19, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.72.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 Karen Oegema and Anthony A. Hyman. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
            </footnote>
        </title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 5/4/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
-->
        <author>
            <firstname>Karen</firstname>
            <surname>Oegema<remark>
                    <footnote>
                        <para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:koegema@ucsd.edu">koegema@ucsd.edu</ulink> or <ulink url="mailto:hyman@mpi-cbg.de">hyman@mpi-cbg.de</ulink></para>
                    </footnote>
                </remark>
            </surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Ludwig Institute for Cancer Research, Department of Cellular and Molecular Medicine, University of California, San Diego, La Jolla, CA 92093 USA</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
        <author>
            <firstname>Anthony A.</firstname>
            <surname>Hyman</surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Max Planck Institute for Molecular Cell Biology and Genetics (MPI-CBG), Dresden 01307, Germany</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">embryo is a powerful model system for studying the mechanics of
            metazoan cell division. Its primary advantage is that the architecture of the syncytial
            gonad makes it possible to use RNAi to generate oocytes whose cytoplasm is reproducibly
            (typically <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003E;</symbol>95%) depleted of targeted
            essential gene products via a process that does not depend exclusively on intrinsic
            protein turnover. The depleted oocytes can then be analyzed as they attempt their first
            mitotic division following fertilization. Here we outline the characteristics that
            contribute to the usefulness of the</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">embryo for cell division studies. We
            provide a timeline for the first embryonic mitosis and highlight some of its key
            features. We also summarize some of the recent discoveries made using this system,
            particularly in the areas of nuclear envelope assembly/ dissassembly, centrosome
            dynamics, formation of the mitotic spindle, kinetochore assembly, chromosome
            segregation, and cytokinesis.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
    <sect1>
        <title>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo as a system to study cell division</title>
        <para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo is a powerful model system for studying the mechanics of
            metazoan cell division. Its primary advantage is that the syncytial gonad makes it
            possible to use RNA interference (RNAi) to generate oocytes whose cytoplasm is
            reproducibly (<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003E;</symbol>95%) depleted of targeted
            essential gene products.
            Introduction of dsRNA rapidly catalyzes the destruction of the corresponding mRNA in
            many different systems. However, depletion of pre-existing protein is generally a slow
            process that depends on the half-life of the targeted protein. In contrast, in the <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> gonad, the protein present when the dsRNA is introduced is depleted by the
            continual packaging of maternal cytoplasm into oocytes (<xref linkend="figure1"/>).
            Since depletion relies on the rate of embryo production instead of protein half-life,
            the kinetics tend to be similar for different targets. By 36-48 hours after introduction
            of the dsRNA, newly formed oocytes are typically <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003E;</symbol>95% depleted of the target protein.</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig1" align="center" width="3.8in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 1</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>Several additional advantages contribute to the usefulness of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo as
            a model system. Of particular importance is their rapid and highly stereotypical mitotic
            divisions; the time between the onset of DNA condensation and the
            completion of furrow ingression during cytokinesis is approximately 14 minutes. The
            invariant nature of the first few divisions also facilitates the development of methods to
            assess the consequences of molecular perturbations. Quantitative methods
            have already been developed to monitor pronuclear migration (<xref linkend="figure4"/>;
            see also <link linkend="bib1">Albertson, 1984</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib100">O'Connell, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11005028-->), cortical flows (for
            examples see <link linkend="bib15">Cheeks et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15186741-->; <link linkend="bib55">Hird and White, 1993</link><!--; PMID 8509454-->;
            <link linkend="bib96">Munro et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15363415-->), chromosome segregation and spindle elongation during
            anaphase (for examples see <link linkend="bib17">Cheeseman et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15371340-->; <link linkend="bib45">Grill et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11214323-->; <link linkend="bib71">Labbe et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15492042-->), and the asymmetric positioning of the
            spindle within the embryo (for examples see <link linkend="bib22">Colombo et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12750478-->; <link linkend="bib71">Labbe et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15492042-->; <link linkend="bib149">Tsou et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12223405-->). Assay development has
            been accelerated by the emergence of microparticle bombardment mediated transformation
            (<link linkend="bib116">Praitis et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11238406-->) and the availability of vectors containing
            regulatory sequences that direct efficient germline expression (<link linkend="bib144">Strome et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11408582-->), which together have led to the generation of a large number of strains
            expressing fluorescent fusion proteins in the early embryo. Analysis of the mechanical
            consequences of depleting essential cell division proteins is also facilitated by the
            relatively weak DNA damage (<link linkend="bib10">Brauchle et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12747829-->) and spindle
            checkpoints (<link linkend="bib32">Encalada et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15616189-->), which allow the embryo to proceed
            through the cell cycle despite dramatic defects in nuclear structure, spindle assembly,
            chromosome segregation and centrosome function.</para>
        <para>Genetic and RNAi-based approaches have identified a large number of loci important for
            cell division. Mutants in proteins required for cell division have been uncovered in
            screens of collections of nonconditional maternal effect and temperature sensitive
            mutations that result in embryonic lethality (for some examples see <link linkend="bib31">Encalada et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11112326-->; <link linkend="bib40">Golden et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11134076-->; <link linkend="bib44">G&#x000F6;nczy et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10085292-->; <link linkend="bib65">Kemphues et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID 3224814-->; <link linkend="bib102">O'Connell et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9649522-->).
            The ability to reproducibly deplete oocytes of target proteins by RNAi, which can be
            performed by feeding, soaking or injection of hermaphrodites (see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_introreversegenetics/introreversegenetics.html" role="_blank">Reverse genetics</ulink>), has also led to a series of genome-wide screens that identified a
            set of ~2100 genes required for embryonic viability (<link linkend="bib33">Fernandez et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15687288-->; <link linkend="bib35">Fraser et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11099033-->; <link linkend="bib42">G&#x000F6;nczy et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11099034-->; <link linkend="bib63">Kamath et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12529635-->; <link linkend="bib84">Maeda et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11231151-->; <link linkend="bib112">Piano et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11137018-->; <link linkend="bib123">Rual et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15489339-->; <link linkend="bib134">Simmer et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14551910-->; <link linkend="bib136">S&#x000F5;nnichsen et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15791247-->). Filming of embryos depleted of each of these
            2100 gene products using differential interference contrast (DIC) microscopy has defined
            a set of 660 genes whose inhibition results in detectable defects during the first two
            cell divisions (<link linkend="bib42">G&#x000F6;nczy et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11099034-->; <link linkend="bib112">Piano et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11137018-->;
            <link linkend="bib136">S&#x000F5;nnichsen et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15791247-->; <link linkend="bib157">Zipperlen et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11483502-->). Roughly
            half of these genes are specifically required for cell division processes such as
            chromosome segregation or cytokinesis, whereas the other half contributes to cell
            maintenance, via roles in processes such as translation and mitochondrial function
            (<link linkend="bib136">S&#x000F5;nnichsen et al., 2005</link>). The embryonic lethality resulting from RNAi of some of the
            1440 genes for which no DIC defect was observed may be due to cell division defects that
            remain undetected, either due to incomplete penetrance of the RNAi or failure to score
            the resulting defects by DIC (for example subtle defects in chromosome segregation are
            very difficult to detect using this assay). Alternatively, depletion of many of these
            gene products may cause embryonic lethality due to developmental defects that preclude
            hatching.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>A timeline of events during the first mitotic division of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo</title>
        <para>Due to its accessibility to RNAi-based molecular perturbation, the first embryonic
            division that ensues following fertilization has been the most intensively studied. In
            this section, we provide a brief timeline for the events between fertilization and the
            completion of the first cytokinesis (outlined schematically in <xref linkend="figure2"/>; for reviews see <link linkend="bib23">Cowan and Hyman, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15473847-->; <link linkend="bib110">Pelletier et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID-->;
            <link linkend="bib127">Schneider and Bowerman, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14616061-->).</para>
        <para>Prior to fertilization, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> oocytes are arrested in meiotic prophase with
            nuclei containing two copies of the diploid genome packaged into recombined bivalent
            chromosomes. The two rounds
            of meiotic chromosome segregation that generate the haploid oocyte pronucleus are
            completed in the zygote after the oocytes are fertilized. During each meiotic division,
            chromosome segregation is accomplished by a small acentriolar meiotic spindle that forms
            in the embryo anterior. During anaphase of meiosis I and again in meiosis II, the
            meiotic spindle associates with the cortex in an end-on fashion, and a highly asymmetric
            cytokinesis-like event extrudes a polar body (<xref linkend="figure2"/>; <link linkend="bib2">Albertson and Thomson, 1993</link><!--; PMID 8143084-->; <link linkend="bib19">Clark-Maguire and Mains, 1994</link><!--; PMID 8027178-->; <link linkend="bib155">Yang et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12885567-->). In addition to the haploid pronucleus, the sperm brings a pair of
            centrioles into the oocyte, which lacks centrioles due to their degradation during
            oogenesis. As meiosis completes, the haploid oocyte and sperm-derived pronuclei, located
            at opposite ends of the embryo increase in size, becoming visible by DIC microscopy.
            After entering the oocyte, the sperm-derived centriole pair recruits pericentriolar
            material and acquires the ability to nucleate microtubules (<link linkend="bib100">O'Connell, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11005028-->; <link linkend="bib110">Pelletier et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID-->). Subsequently, the two sperm-derived centrioles
            separate, forming two centrosomes positioned on either side of the paternal pronucleus.
            Coincident with chromosome condensation during mitotic prophase, the pronuclei migrate
            towards each other. After the pronuclei meet, the nuclear-centrosome complex moves to
            the center of the embryo and rotates to align with the long axis of the embryo
            (<link linkend="bib1">Albertson, 1984</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib58">Hyman and White, 1987</link><!--; PMID 3680373-->). The miotitc spindle begins
            to move towards the embryo posterior during metaphase (<link linkend="bib71">Labbe et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15492042-->; <link linkend="bib105">Oegema et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11402065-->), and asymmetric elongation during anaphase
            contributes to its posterior displacement (<link linkend="bib1">Albertson, 1984</link>; <link linkend="bib45">Grill et al., 2001</link>). Since
            the cleavage furrow bisects the mitotic spindle, this displacement results in an
            asymmetric first cleavage (For more on the mechanisms that generate this asymmetry see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_asymcelldiv/asymcelldiv.html">Asymmetric cell division and axis formation in the embryo</ulink>).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig2" align="center" width="5.7in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 2</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Nuclear envelope structure and dynamics</title>
        <para>The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> nuclear envelope is structurally similar to that of vertebrates,
            consisting of two concentric membranes (outer and inner) enclosing a lumenal space,
            nuclear pore complexes that mediate bidirectional transport between the cytoplasm and
            the nucleus, and an underlying laminar network (<xref linkend="figure3"/>; <link linkend="bib21">Cohen et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12490171-->). The molecular composition of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> inner nuclear
            membrane/lamina also resembles that in vertebrates (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> expresses a
            single B-type lamin (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LMN-1;class=protein" role="_blank">LMN-1</ulink>; <link linkend="bib80">Liu et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11071918-->; <link linkend="bib120">Riemer et al., 1993</link><!--; PMID 7925480-->), that forms a meshwork of intermediate filaments beneath the inner nuclear
            membrane (reviewed in <link linkend="bib47">Gruenbaum et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15688064-->). The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> inner
            nuclear membrane/lamina also contains three proteins, Ce-emerin, CeMAN-1, and CeLem2,
            that contain a LEM domain, a defining 40 amino acid motif shared by a family of nuclear
            envelope proteins (<link linkend="bib46">Gruenbaum et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11870211-->; <link linkend="bib73">Lee et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10982402-->; <link linkend="bib79">Lin et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10671519-->; <link linkend="bib81">Liu et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12684533-->). LEM family
            proteins all bind to lamins (reviewed in <link linkend="bib75">Lee and Wilson, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15565891-->) and to the
            small inner nuclear membrane associated protein BAF (<link linkend="bib130">Segura-Totten and Wilson, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15130582-->; <link linkend="bib156">Zheng et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10908652-->). Depletion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LMN-1;class=protein" role="_blank">LMN-1</ulink>, Ce-BAF, or
            simultaneous depletion of the LEM family proteins Ce-Emerin and Ce-MAN-1, results in a
            similar spectrum of defects in nuclear structure, chromosome condensation, and
            chromosome segregation (<link linkend="bib80">Liu et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11071918-->; <link linkend="bib81">Liu et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12684533-->; <link linkend="bib87">Margalit et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15728376-->; <link linkend="bib156">Zheng et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10908652-->).</para>
<table id="table1" frame="all">
<title>Table 1. Nuclear envelope proteins</title>
				<tgroup cols="7">
				<colspec colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c2" align="left" colwidth="1.1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c3" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c4" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c5" align="left" colwidth="0.9*"/>
				<colspec colname="c6" align="left" colwidth="2.5*"/>
				<colspec colname="c7" align="left" colwidth="1.5*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> protein</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> gene</entry>
                        <entry>Required for embryonic viability?</entry>
                        <entry>Vertebrate orthologue</entry>
                        <entry>TMR</entry>
                        <entry>Summary of localization and functional analysis</entry>
                        <entry>Selected references</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Ce-lamin (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LMN-1;class=protein" role="_blank">LMN-1</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lmn-1" role="_blank">lmn-1</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=DY3.2;class=CDS" role="_blank">DY3.2</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Lamin-B</entry>
                        <entry>NO</entry>
                        <entry>B-type lamin expressed in all cell types; localizes to the nuclear
                            side of the nuclear envelope; required for nuclear morphology, nuclear
                            pore complex distribution, chromosome segregation and the localization
                            of Ce-emerin.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib80">Liu, 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib46">Gruenbaum, 2002</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Ce-emerin (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=EMR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">EMR-1</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=emr-1" role="_blank">emr-1</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=M01D7.6;class=CDS" role="_blank">M01D7.6</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>NO</entry>
                        <entry>Emerin</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Integral component of the inner nuclear membrane; contains a LEM
                            domain and interacts with Ce-Lamin; co-depletion with Ce-MAN-1 results
                            in 100% embryonic lethality, chromosome condensation and segregation
                            defects and mislocalization of Ce-BAF.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib46">Gruenbaum, 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib81">Liu, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Ce-MAN1 (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LEM-2;class=protein" role="_blank">LEM-2</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lem-2" role="_blank">lem-2</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=W01G7.5;class=CDS" role="_blank">W01G7.5</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>PARTIAL Depletion gives 15% lethality</entry>
                        <entry>LEM2 and MAN1</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Integral component of the inner nuclear membrane; contains a LEM
                            domain and interacts with Ce-Lamin and Ce-BAF <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis>. May require
                            Ce-Lamin for its localization.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib81">Liu, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Ce-BAF</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=baf-1" role="_blank">baf-1</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=B0464.7;class=CDS" role="_blank">B0464.7</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>BAF</entry>
                        <entry>NO</entry>
                        <entry>10kDa soluble protein highly conserved among metazoans; localization
                            to the NE requires emerin and MAN1; interacts with Ce-MAN1 <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis>;
                            required for the proper organization of Ce-lamin, Ce-emerin and Ce-MAN1
							on the nuclear envelope.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib81">Liu, 2003</link>; <link linkend="bib87">Margalit, 2005</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Matefin <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SUN-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>mtf-1 <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sun-1" role="_blank">sun-1</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F57B1.2;class=CDS" role="_blank">F57 B1.2</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>None</entry>
                        <entry>NO</entry>
                        <entry>Interacts with lamin, but its Localization to the nuclear envelope
                            does not require lamin; expressed in all embryonic cells until
                            mid-embryogenesis and thereafter only in germline cells; required for
                            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZYG-12;class=protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink> localization and the attachment of centrosomes to nuclei.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib36">Fridkin, 2004</link>; <link linkend="bib86">Malone, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZYG-12;class=protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=zyg-12" role="_blank">zyg-12</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ZK546.1;class=CDS" role="_blank">ZK546.1</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>SYNE</entry>
                        <entry>YES/NO&#x0002A;</entry>
                        <entry>Member of the Hook family of proteins; localizes to the nuclear
                            envelope and accumulates around the centrosomes; required for the
                            attachment of centrosomes to nuclei; &#x0002A; TMR present in some isoforms.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib86">Malone, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-83;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-83</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-83" role="_blank">unc-83</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=W01A11.3;class=CDS" role="_blank">W01A11.3</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>NO</entry>
                        <entry>?</entry>
                        <entry>NO</entry>
                        <entry>Requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-84;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-84</ulink> for its localization to the nuclear envelope;
                            mutations disrupt nuclear migration in migrating P cells, hyp7
                            precursors, and the intestinal primordium.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib140">Starr, 2001</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-84;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-84</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-84" role="_blank">unc-84</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F54B11.3;class=CDS" role="_blank">F54B11.3</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>NO</entry>
                        <entry>UNC84</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Integral nuclear envelope protein required for nuclear migration and
                            anchorage; expressed after the 26-cell stage; localization requires
                            lamin; required to target <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-83;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-83</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ANC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ANC-1</ulink>, which function in nuclear
                            migration and positioning, respectively, to the nuclear membrane; during
                            nuclear positioning, may form a bridging complex with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ANC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ANC-1</ulink> that spans
                            the perinuclear space to connect the NE to actin cytoskeleton.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib140">Starr, 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib85">Malone, 1999</link>; <link linkend="bib74">Lee, 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib139">Starr, 2002</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ANC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ANC-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=anc-1" role="_blank">anc-1</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ZK973.6;class=CDS" role="_blank">ZK973.6</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>NO</entry>
                        <entry>Nesprin/ Nuance</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>955kDa protein orthologous to vertebrate NUANCE proteins; connects
                            the nuclear envelope to the actin cytoskeleton during nuclear
                            positioning in a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-84;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-84</ulink>-dependent manner.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib139">Starr, 2002</link></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
				</tgroup>
            </table>
        <para>The dynamics of nuclear envelope disassembly and reassembly during the first mitotic
            division of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo are illustrated in <xref linkend="figure3"/>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LMN-1;class=protein" role="_blank">LMN-1</ulink>
            leaves the nuclear envelope during prometaphase (<link linkend="bib73">Lee et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10982402-->; <link linkend="bib80">Liu et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11071918-->). In contrast, inner nuclear membranes containing Ce-emerin and
            Ce-MAN-1 remain largely intact and surround the mitotic spindle everywhere except near
            spindle poles during metaphase and early anaphase, disassembling fully only during
            mid to late anaphase (<xref linkend="figure3"/>; <link linkend="bib73">Lee et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10982402-->; <link linkend="bib74">Lee et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11907270-->; V. Galy, P. Askjaer and I.W. Mattaj, personal communication).
            As the remnants of the old nuclear envelopes disperse, the formation of new nuclear
            envelopes around the segregated chromatin is detected beginning about 1 minute after
            anaphase onset (<xref linkend="figure3"/>; V. Galy, P. Askjaer and I.W. Mattaj, personal
            communication).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig3" align="center" width="6.5in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 3</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>The molecular composition of the nuclear pore complexes (NPCs) is also similar to that
            in vertebrates. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> orthologs of at least one component of each vertebrate NPC
            sub-complex have been identified (<link linkend="bib38">Galy et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12937276-->; <link linkend="bib70">Kuznetsov et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12424524-->). 17 genes encoding 19 nucleoporins are essential for embryonic
            viability. Depletion of 14 of these proteins results in defects in nuclear morphology
            and, in some cases, to reduced nuclear size consistent with a defect in
            nucleo-cytoplasmic transport (<link linkend="bib38">Galy et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12937276-->). Nuclear envelope
            assembly also requires the small GTPase, Ran and the nuclear transport receptor
            importin-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B3;</symbol> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=IMB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">IMB-1</ulink>; <link linkend="bib3">Askjaer et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12475958-->; <link linkend="bib4">Bamba et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11909538-->; <link linkend="bib153">Walther et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12894213-->). High concentrations of RanGTP in the
            vicinity of chromatin are thought to promote the dissociation of importin-<symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B3;</symbol>  from
            nucleoporins to trigger NPC assembly on the chromatin surface.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Pronuclear migration</title>
        <para>The site of sperm entry defines the embryo posterior (<link linkend="bib41">Goldstein and Hird, 1996</link><!--; PMID 8625834-->). As the pronuclei become visible by DIC, the sperm-derived pronucleus and its
            associated centrosome(s) sit on the posterior cortex. The oocyte-derived pronucleus
            forms following two rounds of meiotic chromosome segregation, typically in the embryo
            anterior. The two pronuclei migrate towards each other coincident with chromosome
            condensation during the first mitotic prophase. Pronuclear migration consists of
            movement of the oocyte pronucleus towards the sperm pronucleus and movement of the sperm
            pronucleus away from the cortex towards the embryo center (<link linkend="bib1">Albertson, 1984</link><!--; PMID-->;
            <link linkend="bib103">O'Connell et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10885746-->). Initially, the oocyte pronucleus moves ~ 12 &#x003BC;m
            towards the posterior at a slow rate (~ 3.5 &#x003BC;m/min). As it approaches the sperm
            pronucleus, the oocyte pronucleus accelerates, moving an additional 10 &#x003BC;m at ~5-10 times
            its initial rate (<xref linkend="figure4"/>; <link linkend="bib1">Albertson, 1984</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib103">O'Connell et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10885746-->). The sperm pronucleus begins its migration later than its female
            counterpart and travels at a slow rate of ~ 3.5 &#x003BC;m/min till it meets the oocyte
            pronucleus near the embryo center (~7 &#x003BC;m).</para>
			<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata entityref="fig4" align="center" width="3.5in"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                    <phrase> figure 4</phrase>
                </textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>Rapid movement of the oocyte pronucleus towards the sperm pronucleus and pronuclear
            meeting, both require an intact microtubule cytoskeleton (<link linkend="bib145">Strome and Wood, 1983</link><!--; PMID 6684994-->). Two nuclear envelope proteins, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZYG-12;class=protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SUN-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> recruit dynein to pronuclei,
            and are required for centrosomes to maintain their association with nuclei (<link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>;
            <link linkend="bib86">Malone et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14697201-->). The centrosomes separate around the sperm
            pronucleus in a dynein dependent manner (<link linkend="bib43">G&#x000F6;nczy et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10508861-->). As the
            pronuclei move towards each other, dynein on the oocyte pronucleus is thought to come
            into contact with microtubules emanating from the centrosomal asters associated with the
            sperm pronucleus. The fast phase of pronuclear migration and pronuclear meeting is thus
            mediated by nuclear envelope associated dynein pulling on the two centrosomal
            microtubule asters (<link linkend="bib24">Cowan and Hyman, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15343338-->; <link linkend="bib43">G&#x000F6;nczy et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10508861-->; <link linkend="bib51">Hamill et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12431374-->; <link linkend="bib86">Malone et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14697201-->;
            <link linkend="bib103">O'Connell et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10885746-->; <link linkend="bib125">Schmidt et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15616192-->).</para>
        <para>In addition to the migration of the female pronucleus towards the male pronucleus, the
            migration and centration of the male pronucleus within the embryo has also been analyzed
            to distinguish between two possible models: (1) a “pushing mechanism,” in which the male
            pronucleus is pushed away from the cortex by the polymerization of astral microtubules
            and, (2) a “pulling mechanism” in which the male pronucleus is pulled by
            minus-end-directed motors anchored throughout the cytoplasm. Comparisons between
            simulations and actual migration indicate that the second “pulling” model is the primary
            mechanism (<link linkend="bib67">Kimura and Onami, 2005</link>). Although microtubule-based mechanisms for pronuclear
            movement are the best characterized, some slow pronuclear movement is still observed in
            embryos in which the microtubule cytoskeleton is compromised, or which lack centrosomes
            or fail to recruit dynein to nuclei (<link linkend="bib24">Cowan and Hyman, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15343338-->; <link linkend="bib43">G&#x000F6;nczy et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10508861-->; <link linkend="bib51">Hamill et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12431374-->; <link linkend="bib86">Malone et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14697201-->; <link linkend="bib103">O'Connell et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10885746-->; <link linkend="bib125">Schmidt et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15616192-->).
            Consistent with these observations, correlative evidence suggests that cortical flows
            may also contribute to the slow phase of pronuclear migration (<link linkend="bib55">Hird and White, 1993</link><!--; PMID 8509454-->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Centrosome assembly and duplication</title>
        <para>Centrosomes consist of a single centriole or centriole pair surrounded by
            pericentriolar material that nucleates and anchors microtubules. Like the centrioles in
           <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> embryos (<link linkend="bib12">Callaini and Riparbelli, 1990</link><!--; PMID 2127418-->), <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> centrioles
            are composed of nine singlet microtubules symmetrically positioned around a central tube
                (<xref linkend="figure5"/>B; <link linkend="bib1">Albertson, 1984</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib68">Kirkham et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12600319-->; <link linkend="bib101">O'Connell et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID-->; <link linkend="bib154">Wolf et al., 1978</link><!--; PMID 671581-->). Each
            cylindrical centriole is approximately 200– 250 nm in length and 175 nm in diameter. In
            contrast, vertebrate centrioles typically have nine triplet microtubules (<link linkend="bib88">Marshall, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11448793-->; <link linkend="bib117">Preble et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11005020-->). Consistent with this
            structural difference, the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome lacks homologs of delta- and
            epsilon-tubulin, two tubulin family members required for the formation of triplet
            microtubules (<link linkend="bib30">Dutcher, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14662361-->).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig5" align="center" width="3.4in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 5</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>During fertilization, the amoeboid sperm brings a pair of centrioles into the egg.
            After entering the egg, the centrioles recruit pericentriolar material and separate
            around the sperm-derived nucleus, forming two centrosomal microtubule asters (<xref linkend="figure5"/>; <link linkend="bib100">O'Connell, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11005028-->; <link linkend="bib110">Pelletier et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID-->).
            After they separate, a new daughter centriole begins to form adjacent to each sperm
            centriole. The centrosomes recruit additional pericentriolar material as the embryo
            enters mitosis in a process called centrosome maturation, increasing about 5 fold in
            size and nucleating capacity by metaphase (<link linkend="bib52">Hannak et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11748251-->).
            Coincident with the recruitment of additional PCM, the daughter centrioles elongate,
            reaching full length by metaphase. In late anaphase/telophase the centriole pairs split.
            Concurrent with cytokinesis, the mitotic PCM disassembles, releasing two small
            centrosomes into each daughter cell.</para>
        <para>Pericentriolar material is thought to consist of a proteinacious matrix, called the
            “centromatrix”, that recruits other PCM components (<link linkend="bib9">Bornens, 2002</link><!--; PMID 11792541-->;
            <link linkend="bib108">Palazzo et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11005031-->). Three centrosomal proteins, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AIR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">AIR-1</ulink>
            (Aurora-A kinase), are required for the assembly of pericentriolar material (see <link linkend="table2">Table 2</link>
            for a list of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> centrosome/centriole components). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-5</ulink> is a coiled-coil
            protein thought to be a component of the centromatrix. In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spd-5" role="_blank">spd-5</ulink></emphasis> embryos, no PCM forms
            around the centrioles, and no centrosomal microtubule asters are observed (<link linkend="bib51">Hamill et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12431374-->). Severe defects in PCM assembly are also observed when <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-2</ulink>
            or the aurora A kinase homolog <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AIR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">AIR-1</ulink> are inhibited (<link linkend="bib52">Hannak et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11748251-->;
            <link linkend="bib64">Kemp et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15068791-->; <link linkend="bib103">O'Connell et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10885746-->; <link linkend="bib110">Pelletier et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15186742-->; <link linkend="bib129">Schumacher et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9778499-->). In these embryos,
            centrosomal microtubule asters form, but are very small, and additional PCM fails to
            accumulate around the centrioles during mitotic entry.</para>
            <table id="table2" frame="all">
                <title>Table 2. Centrosome proteins</title>
                <tgroup cols="6">
				<colspec colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c2" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c3" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c4" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c5" align="left" colwidth="2.5*"/>
				<colspec colname="c6" align="left" colwidth="1.5*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> protein</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> gene</entry>
                        <entry>Required for embryonic viability?</entry>
                        <entry>Vertebrate orthologue</entry>
                        <entry>Summary of localization and functional analysis</entry>
                        <entry>Selected references</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-4</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sas-4" role="_blank">sas-4</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F10E9.8;class=CDS" role="_blank">F10E9.8</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>CPAP</entry>
                        <entry>Centriole protein required for centriole assembly; incorporated into
                            centrioles during their assembly and does not subsequently exchange with
                            the cytoplasmic pool; partial depletion leads to the formation of
                            defective centrioles that recruit less than wild-type levels of PCM.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib68">Kirkham, 2003</link>; <link linkend="bib77">Leidel, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-5</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sas-5" role="_blank">sas-5</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F35B12.5;class=CDS" role="_blank">F35B12.5</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>?</entry>
                        <entry>Centriole protein required for centriole assembly; physically
                            interacts with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-6;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-6</ulink>; centriolar <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-5</ulink> shuttles continuously between
                            centrioles and the cytoplasm; requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZYG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ZYG-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-6;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-6</ulink>, but not <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-4</ulink> to
                            localize to centrioles; required for the localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-4</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-6;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-6</ulink>
                            to centrioles. Like <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-4</ulink>, partial depletion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-5</ulink> leads to the
                            formation of defective centrioles that recruit less than wild-type
                            levels of PCM.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib27">Delattre, 2004</link>; <link linkend="bib25">Dammermann, 2004</link>; <link linkend="bib76">Leidel, 2005</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-6;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-6</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=sas-6" role="_blank">sas-6</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y45F10D.9;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y45F10D.9</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>HsSAS-6; DKFZP761 A078</entry>
                        <entry>Centriole protein required for centriole assembly; like <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-4</ulink>, is
                            recruited to centrioles once per cell cycle and does not subsequently
                            exchange; physically interacts with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-5</ulink>; requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZYG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ZYG-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-5</ulink>, but
                            not <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-4</ulink> to be recruited to centrioles; required for the localization
                            of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-4</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-5</ulink>. Like <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-4</ulink>, partial depletion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-5</ulink> leads to the
                            formation of defective centrioles that recruit less than wild-type
                            levels of PCM. The human homolog of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-6;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-6</ulink> localizes to centrioles and is
                            required for centriole duplication.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib25">Dammermann, 2004</link>; <link linkend="bib76">Leidel, 2005</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZYG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ZYG-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=zyg-1" role="_blank">zyg-1</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F59E12.2;class=CDS" role="_blank">F59E12.2</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>?</entry>
                        <entry>Centriole protein required for centriole assembly; localizes to
                            centrioles throughout the cell cycle, but in contrast to SAS-4-6 is not
                            detected on centrioles in sperm; required to target <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-4</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-5</ulink> and
                            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-6;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-6</ulink> to centrioles; atypical protein kinase that autophosphorylates in
                            vitro, but <emphasis>in vivo</emphasis> substrates remain unknown; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=zyg-1" role="_blank">zyg-1</ulink></emphasis> mutation interacts
                            genetically with a mutation in spd-2.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib101">O&apos;Connell, 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib64">Kemp, 2004</link>; <link linkend="bib27">Delattre, 2004</link>; <link linkend="bib25">Dammermann, 2004</link>
                       </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-2</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spd-2" role="_blank">spd-2</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F32H2.3;class=CDS" role="_blank">F32H2.3</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>FLJ10352</entry>
                        <entry>Bi-functional protein required for new centriole formation and for
                            the assembly of the PCM around the centrioles; localizes to both
                            centrioles and the PCM; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spd-2" role="_blank">spd-2</ulink></emphasis> mutation interacts genetically with
                            mutations in both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=zyg-1" role="_blank">zyg-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spd-5" role="_blank">spd-5</ulink></emphasis>; the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-2</ulink> domain shares homology to
                            the ASP protein family.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib100">O'Connell, 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib64">Kemp, 2004</link>; <link linkend="bib110">Pelletier, 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-5</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spd-5" role="_blank">spd-5</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F56A3.4;class=CDS" role="_blank">F56A3.4</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry>PCM component required for PCM assembly; required to recruit all
                            tested PCM proteins; in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-5</ulink> depleted embryos centrosomal microtubule
                            asters are absent and spindle assembly fails; depleted embryos also
                            exhibit a severe defect in new centriole assembly, possibly due to
                            failure to recruit gamma-tubulin to promote the formation of centriolar
                            microtubules; a <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spd-5" role="_blank">spd-5</ulink></emphasis> mutation interacts genetically with mutations in
                            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spd-2" role="_blank">spd-2</ulink></emphasis> and dynein heavy chain.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib51">Hamill, 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib64">Kemp, 2004</link>; <link linkend="bib25">Dammermann, 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AIR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">AIR-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=air-1" role="_blank">air-1</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=K07C11.2;class=CDS" role="_blank">K07C11.2</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Aurora A</entry>
                        <entry>PCM component required for PCM assembly; localization appears more
                            peripheral than that of gamma-tubulin, extending out along centrosomal
                            microtubules; required to recruit additional PCM during centrosome
                            maturation; in depleted embryos centrosomes remain small and spindle
                            assembly fails.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib129">Schumacher, 1998</link>; <link linkend="bib52">Hannak, 2001</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>gamma- tubulin</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tbg-1" role="_blank">tbg-1</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F58A4.8;class=CDS" role="_blank">F58A4.8</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>gamma- tubulin</entry>
                        <entry>Normal levels of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-5</ulink> are observed in depleted embryos indicating
                            that it is not required for PCM formation; in depleted embryos,
                            centrosomal microtubule asters fail to form during interphase, but
                            robust asters assemble as embryos enter mitosis; although unknown
                            mechanisms support partial assembly of mitotic centrosomal asters, the
                            rate of centrosomal microtubule nucleation is severely compromised in
                            depleted embryos indicating that the kinetically dominant pathway for
                            the nucleation of centrosomal microtubules is gamma-tubulin dependent;
                            depleted embryos also exhibit a severe defect in new centriole assembly.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib8">Bobbinec, 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib144">Strome, 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib53">Hannak, 2002</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>CeGrip-1</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gip-1" role="_blank">gip-1</ulink></emphasis> (H04J21.3)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>GCP3</entry>
                        <entry>PCM component; orthologues form a heterotrimeric complex with
                            gamma-tubulin in <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis>, <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>, and <emphasis>S. cerevisiae</emphasis>; depletion
                            prevents recruitment of gamma-tubulin to centrosomes; depletion
                            phenotype is essentially identical to that observed in gamma tubulin
                            depleted embryos.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib53">Hannak, 2002</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>CeGrip-2</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=gip-2" role="_blank">gip-2</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=C45G3.3;class=CDS" role="_blank">C45G3.3</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>GCP2</entry>
                        <entry>PCM component; orthologues form a heterotrimeric complex with
                            gamma-tubulin in <emphasis>Xenopus</emphasis>, <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>, and <emphasis>S. cerevisiae</emphasis>; depletion
                            prevents recruitment of gamma-tubulin to centrosomes; depletion
                            phenotype is essentially identical to that observed in gamma tubulin
                            depleted embryos.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib53">Hannak, 2002</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZYG-9;class=protein" role="_blank">ZYG-9</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=zyg-9" role="_blank">zyg-9</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F22B5.7;class=CDS" role="_blank">F22B5.7</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>XMAP-215</entry>
                        <entry>PCM component; physically interacts with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TAC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TAC-1</ulink>; this interaction is
                            required for the efficient localization of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZYG-9;class=protein" role="_blank">ZYG-9</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TAC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TAC-1</ulink> complex to
                            centrosomes; important regulator of microtubule dynamics; depletion
                            phenotype is similar to that resulting from treatment of embryos with
                            low doses of nocodozole which destabilize microtubules, pronuclear
                            migration fails and a short spindle forms in the embryo posterior.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib89">Matthews, 1998</link>; <link linkend="bib72">Le Bot, 2003</link>; <link linkend="bib138">Srayko, 2003</link>; <link linkend="bib5">Bellanger, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TAC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TAC-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tac-1" role="_blank">tac-1</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y54E2A.3;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y54E2A.3</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>TACC-1, 2, 3</entry>
                        <entry>PCM component; physically interacts with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZYG-9;class=protein" role="_blank">ZYG-9</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TAC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TAC-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZYG-9;class=protein" role="_blank">ZYG-9</ulink> are
                            dependent on each another for their localization to the centrosome.
                            Depletion phenotype is similar to that resulting from treatment of
                            embryos with low doses of nocodozole which destabilize microtubules,
                            pronuclear migration fails and a short spindle forms in the embryo
                            posterior.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib72">Le Bot, 2003</link>; <link linkend="bib138">Srayko, 2003</link>; <link linkend="bib5">Bellanger, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
				</tgroup>
            </table>
        <para>Several PCM proteins are required for the activity rather than the assembly of the
            PCM. The microtubule nucleating activity of the pericentriolar material requires the
            centrosomal tubulin isoform gamma-tubulin, and two gamma-tubulin associated proteins,
            CeGrip-1 and CeGrip-2. Embryos depleted of any of these proteins fail to form
            centrosomal microtubule asters during interphase (<link linkend="bib53">Hannak et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12011109-->).
            As depleted embryos enter mitosis, relatively robust microtubule asters form around the
            centrosomes, suggesting that a gamma-tubulin independent pathway contributes to their
            assembly (<link linkend="bib144">Strome et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11408582-->). However, chill and rewarm experiments
            reveal that the rate of centrosomal microtubule nucleation is highly compromised in
            gamma-tubulin depleted embryos and spindle assembly fails (<link linkend="bib53">Hannak et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12011109-->; <link linkend="bib144">Strome et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11408582-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZYG-9;class=protein" role="_blank">ZYG-9</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TAC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TAC-1</ulink> are two conserved PCM
            proteins that associate to form a complex that promotes microtubule growth. Embryos
            depleted of either protein exhibit defects in pronuclear migration, presumably because
            centrosomal microtubules are too short to capture the oocyte pronucleus, and small
            spindles form around the sperm chromatin in the embryo posterior (<link linkend="bib5">Bellanger and G&#x000F6;nczy, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12956950-->; <link linkend="bib72">Le Bot et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12956951-->; <link linkend="bib89">Matthews et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9606208-->; <link linkend="bib138">Srayko et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12956952-->).</para>
        <para>Seven <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> proteins have been shown to contribute to new centriole assembly.
            Four of these, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-4</ulink> (<link linkend="bib68">Kirkham et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12600319-->; <link linkend="bib77">Leidel and G&#x000F6;nczy, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12636923-->), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-5</ulink> (<link linkend="bib25">Dammermann et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15572125-->; <link linkend="bib27">Delattre et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15232593-->; <link linkend="bib126">Schmutz and Spang, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15724817-->), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAS-6;class=protein" role="_blank">SAS-6</ulink> (<link linkend="bib25">Dammermann et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15572125-->; <link linkend="bib76">Leidel et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15665853-->), and the atypical protein kinase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZYG-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ZYG-1</ulink>
            (<link linkend="bib101">O'Connell et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID-->), localize to centrioles and are specifically required for
            centriole formation. Depletion of any of these proteins by RNAi results in specific
            failure of centrosome duplication. In this characteristic phenotype (<link linkend="bib101">O'Connell et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID-->), the two sperm centrioles separate after fertilization (as in wild-type) and
            organize the two centrosomes that form the poles of an apparently normal spindle during
            the first mitotic division. However, since daughter centrioles fail to form adjacent to
            each of the sperm centrioles, only one centriole instead of the normal two are released
            into each daughter cell when the centrosomes break down in telophase. Since each
            daughter cell contains only one centriole, it can form only one centrosome, and
            monopolar spindles are observed in both cells at the two-cell stage. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-2;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-2</ulink> is a
            bi-functional protein that localizes to centrioles as well as the PCM and is required
            for centriole assembly in addition to its role in PCM recruitment (<link linkend="bib64">Kemp et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15068791-->; <link linkend="bib110">Pelletier et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15186742-->). Embryos depleted of two
            pericentriolar material proteins, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-5;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-5</ulink> and gamma-tubulin, also exhibit severe defects
            in centriole assembly, leading to the idea that the PCM contributes to centriole
            assembly by recruiting gamma-tubulin, which may promote the assembly of the microtubules
            that make up the centriolar cylinders, as well as those nucleated by the PCM (<link linkend="bib25">Dammermann et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15572125-->).</para>
    </sect1>
<?newpage?>
    <sect1>
        <title>Formation of mitotic chromosomes</title>
        <para>The formation of mitotic chromosomes begins when cohesin is loaded onto chromosomes
            and establishes cohesion between the duplicated chromosomes (sister chromatids) during
            DNA replication in S phase. Proteolytic cleavage of one of the cohesin subunits later in
            the cell cycle is thought to release the linkage between the sister chromatids to allow
            their segregation during anaphase (<link linkend="bib49">Haering and Nasmyth, 2003</link><!--; PMID 14635253-->). The
            components of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> cohesin complex have been identified and depletion has
            revealed roles in mitotic chromosome segregation and the pairing of homologous
            chromosomes during meiosis (<link linkend="table3">Table 3</link>; <link linkend="bib13">Chan et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12827206-->; <link linkend="bib92">Mito et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12808038-->; <link linkend="bib109">Pasierbek et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14499625-->).</para>
            <table id="table3" frame="all">
                <title>Table 3. Mitotic chromosome proteins</title>
                <tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c2" align="left" colwidth="1.1*"/>
<colspec colname="c3" align="left" colwidth="0.9*"/>
<colspec colname="c4" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c5" align="left" colwidth="2.5*"/>
<colspec colname="c6" align="left" colwidth="1.5*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> protein</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> gene</entry>
                        <entry>Required for embryonic viability?</entry>
                        <entry>Vertebrate orthologue</entry>
                        <entry>Summary of localization and functional analysis</entry>
                        <entry>Selected references</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HIM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HIM-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=him-1" role="_blank">him-1</ulink></emphasis>; <emphasis>smc-1</emphasis>; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F28B3.7;class=CDS" role="_blank">F28B3.7</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>SMC-1</entry>
                        <entry>Component of the cohesin complex; concentrated in the nucleus during
                            interphase; by the metaphase to anaphase transition levels in the vicinity
                            of the chromatin are reduced and protein appears excluded from the
                            compacted chromatin.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib13">Chan, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMC-3;class=protein" role="_blank">SMC-3</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=smc-3" role="_blank">smc-3</ulink></emphasis>; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y47D3A.26;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y47D3A.26</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMC-3;class=protein" role="_blank">SMC-3</ulink></entry>
                        <entry>Component of the cohesin complex; concentrated in the nucleus during
                            interphase; by the metaphase to anaphase transition levels in the vicinity
                            of the chromatin are reduced and protein appears excluded from the
                            compacted chromatin.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib13">Chan, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SCC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SCC-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=scc-1" role="_blank">scc-1</ulink></emphasis>; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F10G7.4;class=CDS" role="_blank">F10G7.4</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SCC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SCC-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry>Component of the cohesin complex; concentrated in the nucleus during
                            interphase; by the metaphase to anaphase transition levels in the vicinity
                            of the chromatin are reduced and protein appears to be excluded from the
                            compacted chromatin; depletion results in a defect in mitotic chromosome
                            segregation; the severity of the chromosome segregation defects is
                            enhanced by simultaneous RNAi of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=him-1" role="_blank">him-1</ulink></emphasis>.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib13">Chan, 2003</link>; <link linkend="bib92">Mito, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SCC-3;class=protein" role="_blank">SCC-3</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=scc-3" role="_blank">scc-3</ulink></emphasis>; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F18E2.3;class=CDS" role="_blank">F18E2.3</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SCC-3;class=protein" role="_blank">SCC-3</ulink></entry>
                        <entry>Component of the cohesin complex; concentrated in the nucleus during
                            interphase; by the metaphase to anaphase transition levels in the vicinity
                            of the chromatin are reduced and protein appears to be excluded from the
                            compacted chromatin; depletion results in defects in chromosome
                            segregation during mitosis and homologous pairing during meiosis.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib13">Chan, 2003</link>; <link linkend="bib109">Pasierbek, 2003</link>; <link linkend="bib95">Moore, 2005</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=TIM-1;class=protein" role="_blank">TIM-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tim-1" role="_blank">tim-1</ulink></emphasis>; <emphasis>csg-5</emphasis>; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y75B8A.22;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y75B8A.22</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>mTim1</entry>
                        <entry>Component of the cohesin complex; concentrated in the nucleus during
                            interphase; by the metaphase to anaphase transition levels in the vicinity
                            of the chromatin are reduced and protein appears excluded from the
                            compacted chromatin; RNAi of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tim-1" role="_blank">tim-1</ulink></emphasis> in conjunction with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=him-1" role="_blank">him-1</ulink></emphasis> results in
                            more severe defects in chromosome segregation than either alone;
                            required to recruit non-SMC cohesin subunits to chromatin before or
                            during pre-meiotic S phase and to stabilize homologous chromosome
                            associations during synapsis and sister chromatid cohesion in
                            diplotene/ diakinesis.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib13">Chan, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MIX-1;class=protein" role="_blank">MIX-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mix-1" role="_blank">mix-1</ulink></emphasis>; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=M106.1;class=CDS" role="_blank">M106.1</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>SMC-2</entry>
                        <entry>Component of the condensin complex; required for mitotic chromosome
                            condensation; chromosomal localization does not require kinetochore
                            assembly; depletion results in severe chromatin bridging during
                            anaphase; required for X-chromosome dosage compensation (repression).</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib78">Lieb, 1998</link>; <link linkend="bib50">Hagstrom, 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib62">Kaitna, 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib14">Chan, 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SMC-4</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=smc-4" role="_blank">smc-4</ulink></emphasis>; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F35G12.8;class=CDS" role="_blank">F35G12.8</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SMC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SMC-4</ulink></entry>
                        <entry>Component of the condensin complex; required for mitotic chromosome
                            condensation; chromosomal localization does not require kinetochore
                            assembly; depletion leads to severe chromatin bridging during anaphase.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib50">Hagstrom, 2002</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HCP-6;class=protein" role="_blank">HCP-6</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hcp-6" role="_blank">hcp-6</ulink></emphasis>; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y110A7A.1;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y110A7A.1</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>CAP-D3, Heat (IIA)</entry>
                        <entry>Component of the condensin complex; required for mitotic chromosome
                            condensation; chromosomal localization requires kinetochore assembly
                            (fails to localize in CeCENP-C RNAi); required for mitotic chromosome
                            condensation; depletion leads to severe chromatin bridging during
                            anaphase.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib142">Stear and Roth, 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib14">Chan, 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F55C5.4;class=CDS" role="_blank">F55C5.4</ulink></entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>CAP-G2; Heat (IIB)</entry>
                        <entry>Predicted component of the condensin complex based on sequence
                            homology; no published localization or detailed depletion data.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib106">Ono, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>KLE-2</entry>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=C29E4.2;class=CDS" role="_blank">C29E4.2</ulink></entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>CAP-H2; Kleisin <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003B3;</symbol>  (IIC)</entry>
                        <entry>Component of the condensin complex; required for mitotic chromosome
                            condensation; depletion leads to severe chromatin bridging during
                            anaphase.</entry>
                        <entry>Schleiffer, 2003</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AIR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=air-2" role="_blank">air-2</ulink></emphasis>; <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-603" role="_blank">let-603</ulink></emphasis>; <emphasis>stu-7</emphasis>; <emphasis>cyk-6</emphasis>; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=B0207.4;class=CDS" role="_blank">B0207.4</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Aurora B</entry>
                        <entry>Aurora/Ip11- related serine/threonine protein kinase; chromosomal
                            passenger protein, localizes to chromosomes between prophase and
                            telophase and to microtubule bundles in the spindle midzone between
                            anaphase and telophase; forms a complex with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=BIR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">BIR-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ICP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ICP-1</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CSC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CSC-1</ulink> and
                            requires all three to localize to chromosomes; required for histone H3
                            phosphorylation, chromosome alignment and segregation, formation of the
                            spindle midzone and cytokinesis.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib129">Schumacher, 1998</link>; <link linkend="bib57">Hsu et al., 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib61">Kaitna, 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib132">Severson, 2000</link>;
                            <link linkend="bib105">Oegema, 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib121">Rogers 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib62">Kaitna, 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib122">Romano, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ICP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ICP-1</ulink>, CeINCENP</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=icp-1" role="_blank">icp-1</ulink></emphasis>; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y39G10AR.13;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y39G10A R.13</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>INCENP</entry>
                        <entry>Chromosomal passenger protein, localizes to chromosomes between
                            prophase and telophase and microtubule bundles in the spindle midzone
                            between anaphase and telophase; required for chromosome alignment and
                            segregation, formation of the spindle midzone and cytokinesis;
                            chromosomal localization requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=BIR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">BIR-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CSC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CSC-1</ulink>, but not AIR-2.
                            Kinetochore assembly does not require <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ICP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ICP-1</ulink> and inhibiting kinetochore
                            assembly by depletion of CENP-A (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HCP-3;class=protein" role="_blank">HCP-3</ulink>) does not
                            block the recruitment of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ICP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ICP-1</ulink> to chromosomes.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib61">Kaitna, 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib62">Kaitna, 2002</link>; <link linkend="bib105">Oegema, 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib122">Romano, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=BIR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">BIR-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=bir-1" role="_blank">bir-1</ulink></emphasis>; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=T27F2.3;class=CDS" role="_blank">T27F2.3</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Survivin</entry>
                        <entry>Chromosomal passenger protein, localizes to chromosomes between
                            prophase and telophase and microtubule bundles in the spindle midzone
                            between anaphase and telophase; chromosomal localization requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CSC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CSC-1</ulink>
                            and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ICP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ICP-1</ulink>, but not <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AIR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink>; required for chromosome alignment and
                            segregation, formation of the spindle midzone and cytokinesis.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib34">Fraser, 1999</link>; <link linkend="bib61">Kaitna, 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib137">Speliotes, 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib105">Oegema, 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib122">Romano, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KLP-19;class=protein" role="_blank">KLP-19</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=klp-19" role="_blank">klp-19</ulink></emphasis></entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>kinesin-4; Kif4</entry>
                        <entry>Localizes to the chromatin between the kinetochores; depletion
                            results in aberrant chromosome motions during prometaphase, chromosome
                            misalignment and the formation of multiple chromatin bridges during
                            anaphase; thought to reduce the frequency with which individual diffuse
                            kinetochores become attached to microtubules emanating from both spindle
                            poles (merotelic attachment) by interacting with microtubules to
                            stabilize an orientation in which the two kinetochores directly face the
                            spindle poles.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib115">Powers, 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
				</tgroup>
            </table>
        <para>Two additional protein complexes, condensin and the chromosomal passenger complex,
            also have critical roles in the formation and segregation of mitotic chromosomes. In
            contrast to vertebrates, which have two complexes, condensins I and II, that mediate
            spatially distinct aspects of condensation (<link linkend="bib54">Hirano, 2004</link><!--; PMID 14657659-->), <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has
            only condensin II (<link linkend="table3">Table 3</link>, <link linkend="bib50">Hagstrom et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11914278-->; <link linkend="bib106">Ono et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14532007-->). Chromosome condensation is delayed in condensin depleted embryos, but DNA
            compaction is ultimately achieved, indicating the existence of condensin-independent
            mechanisms that can compact mitotic chromatin. However, sister chromatid pairs formed in
            the absence of condensin are structurally defective and cannot be efficiently separated
            from each other by the mitotic spindle (<link linkend="bib50">Hagstrom et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11914278-->; <link linkend="bib62">Kaitna et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12015116-->; <link linkend="bib14">Chan et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15557118-->). Concurrent with, but
            largely independent of condensation, kinetochores assemble to create chromosomal
            attachment sites for spindle microtubules (described in greater detail below). Like
            condensin, the chromosomal passenger protein complex (including the aurora B kinase,
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AIR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=BIR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">BIR-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ICP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ICP-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CSC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CSC-1</ulink>) is recruited to mitotic chromosomes as they form and is
            required for their proper segregation, (<link linkend="bib128">Schumacher et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9852156-->; <link linkend="bib132">Severson et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11050384-->; <link linkend="bib61">Kaitna, 2000</link><!--; PMID 11050385-->; <link linkend="bib105">Oegema, 2001</link><!--; 11402065-->; <link linkend="bib62">Kaitna et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12015116-->; <link linkend="bib121">Rogers 2002</link><!--; PMID; 11940606-->; Romano 2004<!--; PMID12707312-->;
            <link linkend="bib57">Hsu et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10975519-->). Although it does not appear to be required for
            kinetochore assembly in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, the passenger complex plays important roles in
            chromosome structure and likely functions to correct aberrant kinetochore-microtubule
            attachments (reviewed in <link linkend="bib150">Vagnarelli and Earnshaw, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15351889-->).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Kinetochore assembly</title>
        <para>Eukaryotes can be divided into two groups based on the architecture of their mitotic
            chromosomes. Monocentric organisms assemble kinetochores on a single localized
            chromosomal site defined by the presence of dedicated centromeric chromatin. In
            contrast, holocentric organisms, including <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, assemble diffuse kinetochores
            along the entire poleward face of each sister chromatid (<xref linkend="figure6"/>A).
            Holocentric chromosome architecture is present in widely divergent and highly successful
            metazoan lineages (including nematodes, hemipteran insects, and lower plants) that
            constitute a large part of the earth’s biomass, and <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has emerged as an
            important model system for studying holocentric chromosome architecture (reviewed in
            <link linkend="bib28">Dernburg, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11402076-->; <link linkend="bib83">Maddox et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15289669-->).</para>
        <para>Despite differences in the extent of the chromosomal length occupied by the
            kinetochore, the molecular composition of kinetochores in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and monocentric
            organisms is very similar (<link linkend="table4">Table 4</link>). Importantly, mitotic kinetochores in both
            monocentric and holocentric organisms assemble on a base of specialized centromeric
            chromatin defined by the presence of nucleosomes containing the histone H3 variant
            CENP-A (<link linkend="bib11">Buchwitz et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10524621-->; <link linkend="bib146">Sullivan, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11250142-->). Depletion
            of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of CENP-A leads to a characteristic “kinetochore-null”
            phenotype in which chromosomes fail to distribute over the spindle equator and to
            segregate (<link linkend="bib105">Oegema et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11402065-->). This defect results from the failure to
            assemble kinetochores that can interact with spindle microtubules. To date only 4
            proteins have been identified whose depletion gives a kinetochore-null defect:
                CENP-A<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HCP-3;class=protein" role="_blank"><superscript>HCP-3</superscript></ulink>, CENP-C<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HCP-4;class=protein" role="_blank"><superscript>HCP-4</superscript></ulink>,
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-3;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>, which can be placed in a linear assembly hierarchy (<xref linkend="figure6"/>B) with CENP-A<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HCP-3;class=protein" role="_blank"><superscript>HCP-3</superscript></ulink> at the top (<link linkend="bib94">Moore and Roth, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11402064-->; <link linkend="bib105">Oegema et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11402065-->; <link linkend="bib29">Desai et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14522947-->; <link linkend="bib17">Cheeseman et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15371340-->). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-3;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink> are components of
            a 10-protein complex that is critical to forming the outer domains of the kinetochore
            that interact with spindle microtubules (<xref linkend="figure6"/>B; <link linkend="bib17">Cheeseman et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15371340-->; <link linkend="bib29">Desai et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14522947-->). A number of other kinetochore
            proteins have been identified whose depletion results in less severe chromosome
            segregation defects (for examples see <link linkend="bib56">Howe et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11402066-->; <link linkend="bib93">Moore et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10545493-->; for a detailed summary see <link linkend="table4">Table 4</link>). The reproducible phenotypes
            obtained following protein depletion have been useful in grouping proteins that function
            together in the context of the kinetochore (<xref linkend="figure6"/>B; <link linkend="bib17">Cheeseman et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15371340-->).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig6" align="center" width="5.8in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 6</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig6legend;</mediaobject>
            <table id="table4" frame="all">
                <title>Table 4. Kinetochore proteins</title>
                <tgroup cols="6">
				<colspec colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c2" align="left" colwidth="1.1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c3" align="left" colwidth="0.9*"/>
				<colspec colname="c4" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c5" align="left" colwidth="2.5*"/>
				<colspec colname="c6" align="left" colwidth="1.5*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> protein</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> gene</entry>
                        <entry>Required for embryonic viability?</entry>
                        <entry>Vertebrate orthologue</entry>
                        <entry>Summary of localization and functional analysis</entry>
                        <entry>Selected references</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>CeCENP-A, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HCP-3;class=protein" role="_blank">HCP-3</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hcp-3" role="_blank">hcp-3</ulink></emphasis>; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F58A4.3;class=CDS" role="_blank">F58A4.3</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>CENP-A</entry>
                        <entry>Histone H3-variant; thought to localize to chromatin throughout the
                            cell cycle; found in nuclear foci during interphase and concentrated on
                            the chromatin in a stripe that runs along the poleward face of each
                            sister chromatid during mitosis; CeCENP-A is required for the
                            localization of all other kinetochore components that have been tested;
                            depletion results in failure to align and segregate mitotic chromosomes
                            and premature spindle elongation due to the inability of the
                            kinetochores to attach to spindle microtubules; a highly homologous gene
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F54C8.2;class=CDS" role="_blank">F54C8.2</ulink>) is likely also targeted by dsRNAs generated against CeCENP-A.
                            The relative abundance of CeCENP-A versus <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F54C8.2;class=CDS" role="_blank">F54C8.2</ulink> is not known. <emphasis>C.
                            briggsae</emphasis> does not have 2 genes encoding CENP-A like proteins, suggesting
                            that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F54C8.2;class=CDS" role="_blank">F54C8.2</ulink> may have arisen from a recent duplication.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib11">Buchwitz, 1999</link>; <link linkend="bib105">Oegema, 2001</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row><entry>CeCENP-C, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HCP-4;class=protein" role="_blank">HCP-4</ulink></entry> <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hcp-4" role="_blank">hcp-4</ulink></emphasis>; (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=T03F1.9;class=CDS" role="_blank">T03F1.9</ulink>)</entry> <entry>YES</entry> <entry>CENP-C</entry> <entry>Kinetochore localization
                        (prophase to telophase) requires CeCENP-A; CeCENP-C is required for the
                        localization of all kinetochore proteins except CeCENP-A; associates with
                        the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>/3 complex and may act as an adaptor to connect centromeric
                        chromatin to the outer kinetochore; plays a role in the resolution of
                        CeCENP-A chromatin into two paired “lines” on the replicated chromosome;
                        depletion results in failure to align and segregate mitotic chromosomes and
                        premature spindle elongation.</entry> <entry><link linkend="bib94">Moore, 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib105">Oegema, 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib29">Desai, 2003</link>;
                            <link linkend="bib17">Cheeseman, 2004</link></entry> </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-3;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-3</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=knl-3" role="_blank">knl-3</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=T10B5.6;class=CDS" role="_blank">T10B5.6</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>?</entry>
                        <entry>Kinetochore localization (prophase to telophase) requires CeCENP-A and CeCENP-C; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-3;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-3</ulink> levels at the kinetochore are reduced in embryos depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MIS-12;class=protein" role="_blank">MIS-12</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KBP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KBP-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KBP-2;class=protein" role="_blank">KBP-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>; depletion results in failure to align and segregate mitotic chromosomes and premature spindle elongation; component of the 10-protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>/3 complex required to assemble an outer kinetochore that can make microtubule attachments.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib17">Cheeseman, 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=knl-1" role="_blank">knl-1</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=C02F5.1;class=CDS" role="_blank">C02F5.1</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>AF15q14</entry>
                        <entry>Kinetochore localization (prophase to telophase) requires CeCENP-A, CeCENP-C and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-3;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-3</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink> levels at the kinetochores are reduced in embryos depleted of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NDC-80;class=protein" role="_blank">NDC-80</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HIM-10;class=protein" role="_blank">HIM-10</ulink>; depletion results in failure to align and segregate mitotic chromosomes and premature spindle elongation. Component of the 10-protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>/3 complex required to assemble an outer kinetochore that can make microtubule attachments.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib29">Desai, 2003</link>
                            <link linkend="bib17">Cheeseman, 2004</link>
                       </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MIS-12;class=protein" role="_blank">MIS-12</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mis-12" role="_blank">mis-12</ulink></emphasis>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y47G6A.24;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y47G6A.24</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Mis12</entry>
                        <entry>Kinetochore localization (prophase to telophase) requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-3;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-3</ulink> but not <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>; relatively weak chromosome missegregation phenotype seen in depleted embryos consistent with a delay in the formation of chromosome- spindle attachments; identified by sequence homology to human and fission yeast Mis12 and as a component of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>/3 complex.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib17">Cheeseman, 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KBP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KBP-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=kbp-1" role="_blank">kbp-1</ulink></emphasis>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=R13F6.1;class=CDS" role="_blank">R13F6.1</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>?</entry>
                        <entry>Localizes to kinetochores from prophase to telophase; relatively weak chromosome missegregation phenotype seen in depleted embryos consistent with a delay in the formation of chromosome- spindle attachments; identified as a component of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>/3 complex.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib17">Cheeseman, 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KBP-2;class=protein" role="_blank">KBP-2</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=kbp-2" role="_blank">kbp-2</ulink></emphasis>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F26F4.13;class=CDS" role="_blank">F26F4.13</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>?</entry>
                        <entry>Localizes to kinetochores from prophase to telophase; relatively weak chromosome missegregation phenotype seen in depleted embryos consistent with a delay in the formation of chromosome- spindle attachments; identified as a component of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>/3 complex.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib17">Cheeseman, 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NDC-80;class=protein" role="_blank">NDC-80</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ndc-80" role="_blank">ndc-80</ulink></emphasis>
                            (W01B6.9.1)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Ndc80/
                            HEC
                       </entry>
                        <entry>Localizes to kinetochores from prophase to telophase; kinetochore localization requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HIM-10;class=protein" role="_blank">HIM-10</ulink> in addition to chromatin- proximal components; depletion results in chromosome missegregation and premature spindle elongation; phenotype is less severe than a kinetochore-null but more severe than that of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MIS-12;class=protein" role="_blank">MIS-12</ulink>, suggests defect in the ability to form microtubule attachments that can withstand tension; member of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NDC-80;class=protein" role="_blank">NDC-80</ulink> subcomplex, which is part of the larger <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>/3 complex.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib29">Desai, 2003</link>
                            <link linkend="bib17">Cheeseman, 2004</link>
                       </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HIM-10;class=protein" role="_blank">HIM-10</ulink>
                            Nuf2<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HIM-10;class=protein" role="_blank"><superscript>HIM-10</superscript></ulink>
                       </entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=him-10" role="_blank">him-10</ulink></emphasis>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=R12B2.4;class=CDS" role="_blank">R12B2.4</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Nuf2</entry>
                        <entry>Localizes to kinetochores from prophase to telophase; kinetochore localization requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NDC-80;class=protein" role="_blank">NDC-80</ulink>, in addition to chromatin- proximal components.  Depletion disrupts kinetochore ultrastructure, resulting in chromosome missegregation and premature spindle elongation; phenotype is less severe than a kinetochore-null but more severe than that of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MIS-12;class=protein" role="_blank">MIS-12</ulink>, suggests defect in the ability to form microtubule attachments that can withstand tension; member of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NDC-80;class=protein" role="_blank">NDC-80</ulink> subcomplex, which is part of the larger <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>/3 complex.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib56">Howe, 2001</link>
                            <link linkend="bib29">Desai, 2003</link>
                            <link linkend="bib17">Cheeseman, 2004</link>
                       </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KBP-3;class=protein" role="_blank">KBP-3</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=kbp-3" role="_blank">kbp-3</ulink></emphasis>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F26H11.1;class=CDS" role="_blank">F26H11.1</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Spc25</entry>
                        <entry>Localizes to kinetochores from prophase to telophase; depletion results in chromosome missegregation and premature spindle elongation; phenotype is less severe than a kinetochore-null but more severe than that of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MIS-12;class=protein" role="_blank">MIS-12</ulink>, suggests defect in the ability to form microtubule attachments that can withstand tension; member of the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NDC-80;class=protein" role="_blank">NDC-80</ulink> subcomplex, which is part of the larger <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>/3 complex.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib17">Cheeseman, 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KBP-4;class=protein" role="_blank">KBP-4</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=kbp-4" role="_blank">kbp-4</ulink></emphasis>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y92C3B.1;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y92C3B.1</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>?</entry>
                        <entry>Localizes to kinetochores from prophase to telophase. Depletion results in chromosome missegregation and premature spindle elongation; phenotype is less severe than a kinetochore-null but more severe than that of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MIS-12;class=protein" role="_blank">MIS-12</ulink>, suggests defect in the ability to form microtubule attachments that can withstand tension; identified as a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>/3-associated protein.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib17">Cheeseman, 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KBP-5;class=protein" role="_blank">KBP-5</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=kbp-5" role="_blank">kbp-5</ulink></emphasis>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=C34B2.2;class=CDS" role="_blank">C34B2.2</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>NO</entry>
                        <entry>?</entry>
                        <entry>Localizes to kinetochores from prophase to telophase. Identified as a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>/3-associated protein.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib17">Cheeseman, 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HCP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HCP-1</ulink>
                            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HCP-2;class=protein" role="_blank">HCP-2</ulink>
                       </entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hcp-1" role="_blank">hcp-1</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ZK1055.1;class=CDS" role="_blank">ZK1055.1</ulink>)
                            <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=hcp-2" role="_blank">hcp-2</ulink></emphasis>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=T06E4.1;class=CDS" role="_blank">T06E4.1</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES&#x0002A; &#x0002A;When co-depleted</entry>
                        <entry>CENP-F?</entry>
                        <entry>Functionally redundant proteins that localize to the region of the mitotic spindle and to kinetochores between late prometaphase and early anaphase; kinetochore localization requires CeCENP-A/C, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=BUB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">BUB-1</ulink>, but not the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NDC-80;class=protein" role="_blank">NDC-80</ulink> subcomplex; depletion perturbs chromosome alignment and segregation. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HCP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HCP-1</ulink> and 2 physically associate with CLASP<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CLS-2;class=protein" role="_blank"><superscript>CLS-2</superscript></ulink>.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib93">Moore, 1999</link>;
                            <link linkend="bib29">Desai, 2003</link>;
                            <link linkend="bib143">Stear, 2004</link>;
                            <link linkend="bib32">Encalada, 2004</link>;
                            <link linkend="bib16">Cheeseman, 2005</link>
                       </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>CLASP<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cls-2" role="_blank"><superscript>cls-2</superscript></ulink>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CLS-2;class=protein" role="_blank">CLS-2</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cls-2" role="_blank">cls-2</ulink></emphasis>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=R107.6;class=CDS" role="_blank">R107.6</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>CLASP</entry>
                        <entry>Microtubule- associated protein that localizes to spindle poles, the region of the miotic spindle and kinetochores; prominent kinetochore localization is seen at metaphase. Kinetochore localization requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HCP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HCP-1</ulink>/2, but not the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NDC-80;class=protein" role="_blank">NDC-80</ulink> subcomplex. Depletion perturbs chromosome alignment and segregation. CLASP<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CLS-2;class=protein" role="_blank"><superscript>CLS-2</superscript></ulink> associates with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=HCP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">HCP-1</ulink>/2.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib29">Desai, 2003</link>;
                            <link linkend="bib16">Cheeseman, 2005</link>
                       </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>CeMCAK
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KLP-7;class=protein" role="_blank">KLP-7</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=klp-7" role="_blank">klp-7</ulink></emphasis>
                            (K11D9.1)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>MCAK</entry>
                        <entry>Kinesin-13 microtubule depolymerase that localizes to kinetochores between early prometaphase and telophase, and to spindle poles throughout mitosis; kinetochore localization requires CeCENP-A and CeCENP-C, but not <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-3;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-3</ulink>; depletion results in snapping of the anaphase spindle, suggesting excessive astral pulling forces or a defect in spindle midzone formation/ stability.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib105">Oegema, 2001</link>;
                            <link linkend="bib45">Grill, 2001</link>;
                            <link linkend="bib29">Desai, 2003</link>;
                            <link linkend="bib115">Powers, 2004</link>
                       </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LIS-1;class=protein" role="_blank">LIS-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lis-1" role="_blank">lis-1</ulink></emphasis>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=T03F6.5;class=CDS" role="_blank">T03F6.5</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>LIS1</entry>
                        <entry>Microtubule associated protein that localizes to the cell cortex, nuclear periphery, kinetochores, and microtubule asters; kinetochore localization requires CeCENP-C, but not dynein; depletion results in multiple defects in spindle positioning, pronuclear migration, and centrosome separation, leading to gross missegregation of chromosomes.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib20">Cockell, 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CZW-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CZW-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=czw-1" role="_blank">czw-1</ulink></emphasis>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F20D12.4;class=CDS" role="_blank">F20D12.4</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Zw10</entry>
                        <entry>Predicted kinetochore protein based on sequence homology; partial depletion results in chromosome missegregation; penetrant depletion results in sterility</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib141">Starr, 1998</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ROD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ROD-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rod-1" role="_blank">rod-1</ulink></emphasis>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F55G1.4;class=CDS" role="_blank">F55G1.4</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Rod</entry>
                        <entry>Predicted kinetochore protein based on sequence homology; depletion results in chromosome missegregation.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib124">Scaerou, 2001</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=BUB-1;class=protein" role="_blank">BUB-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=bub-1" role="_blank">bub-1</ulink></emphasis>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=R06C7.8;class=CDS" role="_blank">R06C7.8</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Bub1</entry>
                        <entry>Mitotic checkpoint pathway serine/threonine protein kinase; kinetochore localization (prophase to metaphase) requires CeCENP-A, CeCENP-C, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KNL-1;class=protein" role="_blank">KNL-1</ulink>; depletion results in misalignment and missegregation of chromosomes.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib105">Oegema, 2001</link>;
                            <link linkend="bib29">Desai, 2003</link>;
                            <link linkend="bib32">Encalada, 2004</link>
                       </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>BUB-3</entry>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y54G9A.6;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y54G9A.6</ulink></entry>
                        <entry>NO</entry>
                        <entry>Bub3</entry>
                        <entry>Predicted mitotic checkpoint pathway protein based on sequence homology.</entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MDF-1;class=protein" role="_blank">MDF-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mdf-1" role="_blank">mdf-1</ulink></emphasis>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=C50F4.11;class=CDS" role="_blank">C50F4.11</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>NO</entry>
                        <entry>Mad1</entry>
                        <entry>Mitotic checkpoint pathway protein based on sequence homology; mutant worms fail to thrive due to accumulated chromosomal abnormalities; required to delay the embryonic cell cycle in response to spindle defects.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib69">Kitagawa, 1999</link>;
                            <link linkend="bib32">Encalada, 2004</link>
                       </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MDF-2;class=protein" role="_blank">MDF-2</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mdf-2" role="_blank">mdf-2</ulink></emphasis> (Y69A2AR. 30)</entry>
                        <entry>NO</entry>
                        <entry>Mad2</entry>
                        <entry>Mitotic checkpoint pathway protein with similar functions as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MDF-1;class=protein" role="_blank">MDF-1</ulink>; depletion of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MDF-2;class=protein" role="_blank">MDF-2</ulink> also overrides the mitotic arrest induced by anoxia, suggesting that survival under very low oxygen levels is promoted by activation of the mitotic checkpoint.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib69">Kitagawa, 1999</link>;
                            <link linkend="bib98">Nystul, 2003</link>;
                            <link linkend="bib32">Encalada, 2004</link>
                       </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAN-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SAN-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=san-1" role="_blank">san-1</ulink></emphasis>
                            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ZC328.4;class=CDS" role="_blank">ZC328.4</ulink>)
                       </entry>
                        <entry>NO</entry>
                        <entry>BubR1</entry>
                        <entry>Mitotic checkpoint pathway protein that localizes to kinetochores after nuclear envelope breakdown. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAN-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SAN-1</ulink> is the homologue of budding yeast MAD3 protein (their vertebrate orthologue, BubR1, has a serine/threonine kinase domain fused to the Mad3 homology region). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SAN-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SAN-1</ulink> was identified in a genetic screen for anoxia-sensitive mutants, highlighting a link between survival under very low oxygen levels and mitotic arrest mediated by the mitotic checkpoint pathway.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib99">Nystul, 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
				</tgroup>
            </table>
        <para>In addition to its role in directing kinetochore assembly, CENP-C has also been
            implicated in sister kinetochore resolution, the process by which the kinetochores on
            the two sister chromatids resolve from one another, coming to rest on opposite sides of
            the mitotic chromosome (<link linkend="bib94">Moore and Roth, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11402064-->). Defects in sister
            kinetochore resolution in CENP-C depleted embryos can be suppressed by RNAi or mutation
            of cohesin subunits suggesting that resolution of the sister kinetochores during the
            assembly of mitotic chromosomes is normally facilitated by loss of cohesion between the
            sister centromeres (<link linkend="bib95">Moore et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15767665-->). In addition to
            kinetochore-localized proteins, the chromokinesin <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KLP-19;class=protein" role="_blank">KLP-19</ulink>, which localizes to the
            chromatin between the diffuse kinetochores, is also critical for chromosome segregation.
            Interactions between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=KLP-19;class=protein" role="_blank">KLP-19</ulink> and spindle microtubules are postulated to generate a
            pushing force that rotates chromosomes to orient the sister kinetochores to face
            opposite spindle poles (<link linkend="table3">Table 3</link>; <link linkend="bib115">Powers et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15452142-->), thereby reducing
            the possibility that a single kinetochore will become incorrectly attached to
            microtubules coming from both spindle poles.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Assembly of the mitotic spindle</title>
        <para>In vertebrates and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>, spindle assembly results from the superposition of two
            distinct mechanisms: (1) an inside out chromatin-based mechanism in which Ran-GTP
            produced in proximity to chromatin activates factors that promote the assembly and
            self-organization of microtubules to form a bipolar spindle, and (2) an outside in
            mechanism in which centrosomal microtubule asters reinforce spindle bipolarity and
            position the spindle within the cell (<link linkend="bib37">Gadde and Heald, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15380094-->). In
            contrast, <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> appears to lack a significant inside out pathway and primarily
            utilizes an outside in centrosome-based mechanism to form its spindles. Consistent with
            this idea, Eg5, a mitotic kinesin that promotes anti-parallel microtubule sliding and
            plays an essential role in the chromatin-based pathway in vertebrates and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis>, is
            not required for spindle assembly in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib6">Bishop et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15548597-->).
            Conversely, whereas centrosomes are not essential for spindle assembly in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> or
            vertebrates (<link linkend="bib66">Khodjakov et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10662665-->; <link linkend="bib90">Megraw et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10357928-->;
            <link linkend="bib119">Rebollo et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14758368-->; <link linkend="bib151">Vaizel-Ohayon and Schejter, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10469591-->),
            spindles fail to form in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos that lack functional centrosomes (<link linkend="bib51">Hamill et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12431374-->; <link linkend="bib64">Kemp et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15068791-->; <link linkend="bib110">Pelletier et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15186742-->) and the majority of characterized <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> proteins that are required for
            spindle assembly (<link linkend="bib136">S&#x000F5;nnichsen et al., 2005</link><!--; PMID 15791247-->) are known centrosome
            components. Interestingly, essentially perfect “half spindles” form in embryos that have
            a single centrosome instead of the normal two (<link linkend="bib68">Kirkham et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12600319-->;
            <link linkend="bib101">O'Connell et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID-->), indicating that the mechanisms that regulate spindle
            length in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo are largely independent of bipolarity. Experiments in
            which the size of mitotic centrosomes is modulated by varying the levels of centriole
            components have also revealed an interesting positive correlation between half-spindle
            length and centrosome size (<link linkend="bib27">Delattre et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15232593-->; <link linkend="bib68">Kirkham et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12600319-->).</para>
        <para>Concomitant with nuclear envelope break down, centrosomal microtubules penetrate the
            nuclear space and begin to interact with chromosomes. Spindle assembly is completed in
            the subsequent ~2.5 minute period between nuclear envelope breakdown and anaphase onset
            (see <xref linkend="figure2"/>). Tomographic reconstruction of a <emphasis>C.elegans</emphasis> mitotic
            spindle from electron micrographs indicates that <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> mitotic spindles consist
            primarily of microtubules that connect centrosomes to kinetochores. These kinetochore
            microtubules do not form bundles that resemble the kinetochore fibers present in
            vertebrate and <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> cells, probably because of the holocentric nature of <emphasis>C.
            elegans</emphasis> chromosomes (<link linkend="bib104">O'Toole et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14610052-->). Assembly of a stable mitotic
            spindle requires kinetochores that can form stable bipolar microtubule attachments. In
            the absence of functional kinetochores, the two spindle poles are abruptly pulled apart
            at a time that corresponds to the onset of cortical pulling forces on the two
            centrosomes that normally asymmetrically position the spindle within the embryo (<link linkend="bib105">Oegema et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11402065-->). The abrupt separation of the spindle poles in the absence
            of functional kinetochores is similar to that brought about by severing the spindle with
            a UV microbeam (<link linkend="bib45">Grill et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11214323-->), confirming the critical role of
            kinetochores in maintaining spindle integrity.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Chromosome segregation</title>
        <para>Chromosome segregation typically consists of two components: (1) anaphase A, in which
            the chromosomes move towards the spindle poles and, (2) anaphase B in which the spindle
            poles separate from each other with the chromosomes in tow. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> the majority
            of chromosome movement is due to anaphase B (<link linkend="bib105">Oegema et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11402065-->),
            powered by a combination of cortical forces that pull on the centrosomal microtubule
            asters to separate them, and pushing forces generated by the array of overlapping
            microtubules, called the central spindle, that forms between the separating chromosomes.
            If the mitotic spindle is severed during anaphase using a UV micro beam, the two spindle
            poles separate with increased velocity (<link linkend="bib45">Grill et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11214323-->). This
            experiment demonstrates the existence of pulling forces during the first mitotic
            division and suggests that the central spindle normally acts to limit the rate of pole
            separation. However, in embryos in which G protein signaling that mediates cortical
            pulling forces is disrupted, spindles still elongate (<link linkend="bib22">Colombo et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12750478-->) albeit at a slower rate, indicating that other spindle intrinsic forces
            contribute to anaphase spindle elongation.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Cytokinesis</title>
        <para>During cytokinesis, signals from the anaphase spindle trigger the assembly of an
            equatorial cortical contractile ring enriched in actin and myosin II. Constriction of
            the contractile ring changes the shape of the cell to facilitate cell division (reviewed
            in <link linkend="bib39">Glotzer, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15774750-->). The components of the microtubule and actin
            cytoskeletons that are known to contribute to cytokinesis in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo can
            be partitioned into three classes (<link linkend="table5">Table 5</link>). The first class consists of proteins
            required for cortical acto-myosin contractility (<xref linkend="figure7"/>). Embryos
            depleted of proteins in this class have defects in all cortical contractile events
            including: polar body extrusion, anterior cortical ruffling, pseudocleavage, and the
            initiation of a furrow during cytokinesis. This class includes the small GTPase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RHO-1;class=protein" role="_blank">RHO-1</ulink>
            (<link linkend="bib60">Jantsch-Plunger et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10871280-->) and its activating GEF (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-21;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-21</ulink>; <link linkend="bib26">Dechant and Glotzer, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12636915-->), which are thought to be at the top of the signaling
            cascade that regulates cortical contractility (<link linkend="bib39">Glotzer, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15774750-->). Downstream
            are proteins that regulate the assembly of the contractile ring and its constriction in
            response to activated Rho. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CYK-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CYK-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib131">Severson et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12498681-->; <link linkend="bib147">Swan et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9645949-->), a member of the formin family of proteins, is a Rho effector that
            promotes the assembly of actin filaments. The assembly and contractility of non-muscle
            myosin II (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMY-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink>; <link linkend="bib48">Guo and Kemphues, 1996</link><!--; PMID 8684486-->), the motor that powers
            acto-myosin contractility, is regulated by phosphorylation of its regulatory light
            chain, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MLC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink> (<link linkend="bib133">Shelton et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10427096-->). Phosphorylation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MLC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink> activates
            myosin II, allowing it to form bi-polar filaments that can interact with actin to
            generate cortical ingression (<link linkend="bib18">Citi and Kendrick-Jones, 1987</link><!--; PMID 3318821-->). One of the
            Rho effectors that regulates <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MLC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink> phosphorylation during cytokinesis is the Rho kinase
            homolog <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-502;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-502</ulink> (for details see <link linkend="table5">Table 5</link>; <link linkend="bib113">Piekny and Mains, 2002</link><!--; PMID 12006612-->).</para>
            <table id="table5" frame="all">
                <title>Table 5. Cytoskeletal proteins required for cytokinesis</title>
                <tgroup cols="6">
				<colspec colname="c1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c2" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c3" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c4" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colname="c5" align="left" colwidth="2.5*"/>
				<colspec colname="c6" align="left" colwidth="1.5*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> protein</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> gene</entry>
                        <entry>Required for embryonic viability?</entry>
                        <entry>Vertebrate orthologue</entry>
                        <entry>Summary of localization and functional analysis</entry>
                        <entry>Selected references</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMY-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink></entry>
                        <entry></entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>non-muscle myosin II</entry>
                        <entry>Localizes to the contractile ring during cytokinesis as well as to other cortical contractile structures; motor that powers contraction by moving towards the barbed end of actin filaments; all cortical contractile events fail in depleted embryos including polar body formation, ruffling, and cleavage furrow ingression. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=NMY-2;class=protein" role="_blank">NMY-2</ulink> is also required for the establishment of polarity.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib48">Guo, 1996</link>;
<link linkend="bib96">Munro, 2004</link>
</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MLC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mlc-4" role="_blank">mlc-4</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=C56G7.1;class=CDS" role="_blank">C56G7.1</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>non-muscle myosin II regulatory light chain</entry>
                        <entry>Regulates the ability of myosin II to form filaments and interact with actin; localizes to the cortical contractile ring during cytokinesis as well as to other cortical contractile structures; activated by phosphorylation; all cortical contractile events fail in depleted embryos including polar body formation, ruffling, and cleavage furrow ingression; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MLC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink> is also required for the establishment of polarity.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib133">Shelton, 1999</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-502;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-502</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-502" role="_blank">let-502</ulink></emphasis>
(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=C10H11.9;class=CDS" role="_blank">C10H11.9</ulink>)
</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Rho-binding kinase (ROK)</entry>
                        <entry>Rho-binding serine/threonine kinase that localizes to the contractile ring; promotes myosin II contractility by increasing the phosphorylation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MLC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink>; based on work in other systems, it is thought to do this by both directly phosphorylating <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MLC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink> and also by phosphorylating and inactivating myosin phosphatase; inhibition of Rho-kinase slows the rate of furrow ingression but does not prevent furrow assembly or ingression, suggesting the existence of redundant <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MLC-4;class=protein" role="_blank">MLC-4</ulink> kinases; failed cell divisions occur apparently at random in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-502" role="_blank">let-502</ulink></emphasis> embryos, with many divisions being normal.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib113">Piekny, 2002</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEL-11;class=protein" role="_blank">MEL-11</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mel-11" role="_blank">mel-11</ulink></emphasis>
(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=C06C3.1;class=CDS" role="_blank">C06C3.1</ulink>)
</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Myosin phosphatase
targeting subunit (MYPT)
</entry>
                        <entry>Regulatory subunit of myosin phosphatase; inhibits cortical contraction by de-phosphory- lating the regulatory light chain of myosin II; mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=mel-11" role="_blank">mel-11</ulink></emphasis> result in ectopic furrowing and faster furrow ingression; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-502;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-502</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=MEL-11;class=protein" role="_blank">MEL-11</ulink> co-localize in cleavage furrows and their mutations alleviate one another’s effects.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib113">Piekny, 2002</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RHO-1;class=protein" role="_blank">RHO-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=rho-1" role="_blank">rho-1</ulink></emphasis>
(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y51H4A.3;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y51H4A.3</ulink>)
</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>RhoA</entry>
                        <entry>Small GTPase thought to connect signaling by the anaphase spindle to assembly and ingression of a cortical contractile ring; all cortical contractile events fail in depleted embryos including polar body formation, ruffling, and cleavage furrow ingression; has not been localized in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> but active Rho has been localized to the contractile ring in other systems.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib60">Jantsch-Plunger, 2000</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=LET-21;class=protein" role="_blank">LET-21</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-21" role="_blank">let-21</ulink></emphasis>
(T19E10.1)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Ect2</entry>
                        <entry>Guanine nucleotide exchange factor that activates <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=RHO-1;class=protein" role="_blank">RHO-1</ulink>; all cortical contractile events fail in depleted embryos including polar body formation, ruffling, and cleavage furrow ingression; has not been localized in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, but in other systems has been localized to microtubule bundles in the central spindle and to the contractile ring.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib26">Dechant, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CYK-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CYK-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cyk-1" role="_blank">cyk-1</ulink></emphasis>
(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=F11H8.4;class=CDS" role="_blank">F11H8.4</ulink>)
</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>formins</entry>
                        <entry>A member of the formin family of proteins thought to promote actin assembly in response to activation of Rho family GTPases; localizes to the cleavage furrow and is required to initiate furrow ingression.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib147">Swan, 1998</link>;
<link linkend="bib131">Severson, 2002</link>
</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=PFN-1;class=protein" role="_blank">PFN-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=pfn-1" role="_blank">pfn-1</ulink></emphasis>
(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y18D10A.20;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y18D10A. 20</ulink>)
</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>profillin</entry>
                        <entry>One of three <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homologs of the actin binding protein profilin; the only <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> profilin that is required in the early embryo; depleted embryos exhibit defects in furrow ingression and the establishment of polarity; thought to function together with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CYK-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CYK-1</ulink> to promote actin assembly in response to activation by Rho family GTPases.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib131">Severson, 2002</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ANI-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ANI-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=ani-1" role="_blank">ani-1</ulink></emphasis>
(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y49E10.19;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y49E10.19</ulink>)
</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Anillin</entry>
                        <entry>One of three <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homologs of the actin-binding protein anillin; the only anillin homolog that appears to have a role in cortical events in the early embryo; localizes to the contractile ring, as well as to other cortical contractile structures, and is required for the septins to concentrate in the furrow; not essential for embryonic cytokinesis, but required for polar body extrusion, cortical ruffling, and pseudocleavage.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib82">Maddox, 2005</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-59;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-59</ulink>;
<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-61;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-61</ulink>
</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-59" role="_blank">unc-59</ulink></emphasis>
(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=W09C5.2;class=CDS" role="_blank">W09C5.2</ulink>);
<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-61" role="_blank">unc-61</ulink></emphasis>
(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y50E8A.4;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y50E8A.4</ulink>)
</entry>
                        <entry>NO</entry>
                        <entry>septins</entry>
                        <entry>The only <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homologs of the septins, small GTPases that form heteromeric complexes that polymerize to form filaments; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-59;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-59</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=UNC-61;class=protein" role="_blank">UNC-61</ulink> are interdependent for their localization to the cortex and for their localization to the contractile ring; require <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ANI-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ANI-1</ulink> to become enriched in the contractile ring, but are not required for the targeting of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ANI-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ANI-1</ulink>; neither is essential for embryonic cytokinesis.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib97">Nguyen, 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib82">Maddox, 2005</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>UNC-60A</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-60" role="_blank">unc-60</ulink></emphasis>
(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=C38C3.5;class=CDS" role="_blank">C38C3.5</ulink>)
</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>cofilin</entry>
                        <entry>Promotes actin turnover; concentrates in the cleavage furrow during cytokinesis; depleted embryos frequently exhibit cytokinesis defects; the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-60" role="_blank">unc-60</ulink> gene generates two ADF/cofilins, UNC-60A and UNC-60B, by alternative splicing that have different functions. UNC-60B is expressed not it embryos, but in somatic/adult tissues.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib106">Ono, 2003</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZEN-4;class=protein" role="_blank">ZEN-4</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=zen-4" role="_blank">zen-4</ulink></emphasis>
(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=M03D4.1;class=CDS" role="_blank">M03D4.1</ulink>)
</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>kinesin-6 family member MKLP1</entry>
                        <entry>Kinesin that physically associates with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CYK-4;class=protein" role="_blank">CYK-4</ulink>, a GAP for Rho family GTPases, to form a two protein complex called Centralspindlin; localizes to microtubule bundles in the spindle midzone and midbody; required for assembly of the spindle midzone and for the completion of cytokinesis, but not to form a furrow or initiate ingression.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib118">Raich, 1998</link>; <link linkend="bib114">Powers, 1998</link>; <link linkend="bib132">Severson, 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib91">Mishima, 2002</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CYK-4;class=protein" role="_blank">CYK-4</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=cyk-4" role="_blank">cyk-4</ulink></emphasis>
(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=K08E3.6;class=CDS" role="_blank">K08E3.6</ulink>)
</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>MgcRacGAP</entry>
                        <entry>A GTPase activating protein (GAP), an inhibitor for Rho family GTPases; associates with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZEN-4;class=protein" role="_blank">ZEN-4</ulink> to form a protein complex called Centralspindlin; localizes to microtubule bundles in the central spindle and midbody; required for assembly of the central spindle and for the completion of cytokinesis, but not to form a furrow or initiate ingression.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib60">Jantsch-Plunger, 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib91">Mishima, 2002</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AIR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=air-2" role="_blank">air-2</ulink></emphasis>
<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=let-603" role="_blank">let-603</ulink></emphasis>
<emphasis>stu-7</emphasis>
<emphasis>cyk-6</emphasis>
(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=B0207.4;class=CDS" role="_blank">B0207.4</ulink>)
</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Aurora B</entry>
                        <entry>Mitotic serine/threonine kinase; component of a four-protein chromosomal passenger protein complex that localizes to chromosomes during mitosis and to microtubule bundles in the central spindle and midbody during anaphase/ telophase; required for assembly of the central spindle/midbody and for the completion of cytokinesis, but not to form a furrow or initiate ingression; also required for chromosome segregation (see <link linkend="table3">Table 3</link>).</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib129">Schumacher, 1998</link>; <link linkend="bib61">Kaitna, 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib132">Severson, 2000</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ICP-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ICP-1</ulink>
CeINCENP
</entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=icp-1" role="_blank">icp-1</ulink></emphasis>
(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y39G10AR.13;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y39G10AR. 13</ulink>)
</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>INCENP</entry>
                        <entry>Component of a four-protein chromosomal passenger protein complex that localizes to chromosomes during mitosis and to microtubule bundles in the central spindle and midbody during anaphase/ telophase; phosphorylated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AIR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink> and stimulates <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AIR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink> kinase activity; required for assembly of the central spindle/midbody and for the completion of cytokinesis, but not to form a furrow or initiate ingression; also required for chromosome segregation (see <link linkend="table3">Table 3</link>).</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib61">Kaitna, 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib105">Oegema, 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib7">Bishop, 2002</link>; Romano, 2004</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=BIR-1;class=protein" role="_blank">BIR-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=bir-1" role="_blank">bir-1</ulink></emphasis> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=T27F2.3;class=CDS" role="_blank">T27F2.3</ulink>)</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Survivin</entry>
                        <entry>Component of a four-protein chromosomal passenger protein complex that localizes to chromosomes during mitosis and to microtubule bundles in the central spindle and midbody during anaphase/ telophase; required for assembly of the central spindle/midbody and for the completion of cytokinesis, but not to form a furrow or initiate ingression; also required for chromosome segregation (see <link linkend="table3">Table 3</link>).</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib34">Fraser, 1999</link>; <link linkend="bib61">Kaitna, 2000</link>; <link linkend="bib137">Speliotes, 2000</link>; Romano, 2004</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CSC-1;class=protein" role="_blank">CSC-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=csc-1" role="_blank">csc-1</ulink></emphasis>
(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y48E1B.12;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y48E1B.12</ulink>)
</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>Borealin, Dasra A/B</entry>
                        <entry>Component of a four-protein chromosomal passenger protein complex that localizes to chromosomes during mitosis and to microtubule bundles in the central spindle and midbody during anaphase/ telophase; required for assembly of the central spindle/midbody and for the completion of cytokinesis, but not to form a furrow or initiate ingression; also required for chromosome segregation (see <link linkend="table3">Table 3</link>).</entry>
                        <entry>Romano, 2004</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-1</ulink></entry>
                        <entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spd-1" role="_blank">spd-1</ulink></emphasis>
(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y34D9A.4;class=CDS" role="_blank">Y34D9A.4</ulink>)
</entry>
                        <entry>YES</entry>
                        <entry>PRC1</entry>
                        <entry>Localizes to microtubule bundles in the spindle midzone and midbody and to nuclei, as well as to short segments along the length of astral microtubules; required to form microtubule bundles in the central spindle; not required for the cytokinesis up to the four-cell stage, but cytokinesis often fails in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EMS;class=Cell" role="_blank">EMS</ulink> in depleted embryos.</entry>
                        <entry><link linkend="bib152">Verbrugghe, 2004</link></entry>
                    </row>
                    </tbody>
					</tgroup>
				</table>
        <para>A second group of proteins is required for the formation of the spindle midzone, an
            array of microtubule bundles that forms between the separating chromosomes during
            anaphase (<link linkend="bib39">Glotzer, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15774750-->). As cytokinesis progresses, the microtubule
            bundles in the central spindle compact to form a single structure called the midbody.
            The cleavage furrow constricts around the midbody, which is thought to promote membrane
            fusion to complete cytokinesis and generate the two topologically distinct daughter
            cells (reviewed in <link linkend="bib39">Glotzer, 2005</link><!--; PMID 15774750-->). During cytokinesis in embryos depleted
            of proteins required for central spindle assembly, a furrow initiates between the two
            asters, but cytokinesis fails to complete because the midbody is absent, and the furrow
            ultimately regresses. Depleted embryos also have defects in polar body extrusion (highly
            asymmetric cytokineses that bisect the midbodies of the small meiosis I and II
            spindles), but are able to form cortical ruffles that concentrate in the embryo anterior
            during polarity establishment and a pseudocleavage furrow. The microtubule bundles in
            the spindle midzone are also thought to function early in cytokinesis to signal to the
            cortex to promote assembly of the contractile ring. Disruption of the spindle midzone
            does not prevent furrow formation because this midzone-based signal is redundant with
            signals from the microtubule asters. In embryos in which the astral signaling mechanism
            is blocked, the spindle midzone becomes essential for furrow ingression (<link linkend="bib26">Dechant and Glotzer, 2003</link><!--; PMID 12636915-->). Proteins required to form the central spindle include:
            (1) a two protein complex called centralspindlin that includes the kinesin <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ZEN-4;class=protein" role="_blank">ZEN-4</ulink> and
            <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=CYK-4;class=protein" role="_blank">CYK-4</ulink>, a GAP for Rho family GTPases (<link linkend="bib60">Jantsch-Plunger et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10871280-->;
            <link linkend="bib91">Mishima et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11782313-->; <link linkend="bib114">Powers et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9778533-->; <link linkend="bib118">Raich et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9693365-->; <link linkend="bib132">Severson et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11050384-->), and (2) the 4 protein
            chromosomal passenger protein complex containing the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of the aurora B
            kinase, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=AIR-2;class=protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib7">Bishop and Schumacher, 2002</link><!--; PMID 12048181-->; <link linkend="bib34">Fraser et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10209096-->; <link linkend="bib61">Kaitna et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11050385-->; <link linkend="bib105">Oegema et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11402065-->; <link linkend="bib122">Romano et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12707312-->; <link linkend="bib129">Schumacher et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9852156-->; <link linkend="bib137">Speliotes et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10983970-->).</para>
        <mediaobject id="figure7" xreflabel="Figure 7">
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata entityref="fig7" align="center" width="4.5in"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
                <phrase> figure 7</phrase>
            </textobject> &fig7legend;</mediaobject>
        <para>A final protein, currently in a class of its own is <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib152">Verbrugghe and White, 2004</link><!--; PMID 15458647-->). Like the six proteins listed above, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-1</ulink> is also required for the
            formation of microtubule bundles in the spindle midzone. However, in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SPD-1;class=protein" role="_blank">SPD-1</ulink> depleted
            embryos the first cytokinesis does not fail (although later embryonic cytokineses often
            do). It is not yet clear if this result indicates that the midbody is less compromised
            in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=spd-1" role="_blank">spd-1</ulink></emphasis> embryos than it is in embryos depleted of or mutant for the other six proteins
            required for midbody formation—or if centralspindlin and the chromosomal passengers have
            a separate role in the completion of cytokinesis that is independent of their role in
            assembling the central spindle/midbody. Three additional proteins, dynamin (<link linkend="bib148">Thompson et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 12498685-->), RAB-11 (<link linkend="bib135">Skop et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11378383-->) and syntaxin 4
            (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=SYN-4;class=protein" role="_blank">SYN-4</ulink>; <link linkend="bib59">Jantsch-Plunger and Glotzer, 1999</link><!--; PMID 10421575-->), have been implicated in
            membrane fusion during abscission, which generates the two topologically distinct
            daughter cells, however their precise roles in this process remain to be
        elucidated.</para>
    </sect1>
<?newpage?>
<sect1>
	<title>Acknowledgements</title>
	<para>The authors would like to thank Arshad Desai for critical reading of the manuscript and Amy Shaub Maddox, Susan Kline-Smith, Vincent Galy, Carrie Cowan, Eva Hannak and Stephan Grill for their contributions to the figures.  Paul Maddox, Laurence Pelletier, Alexander Dammermann, Vincent Galy and Susan Kline-Smith provided invaluable assistance in constructing and referencing the tables. K.O. is a Pew Scholar in the Biomedical Sciences and is supported by funding from the Ludwig Institute for Cancer Research.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
        <title>References</title>
		<para/>
		&celldivision_Refs;</sect1>
</article>
