<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 1. The generation of oocytes depleted of target proteins by RNAi in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> does not require intrinsic protein turnover.</title>
        <para>(A) The gonad is a syncytial tube lined with nuclei in various stages of meiotic
            prophase. The meiotic nuclei contribute mRNA that is translated to generate the protein
            that is loaded into the developing oocytes. The meiotic nuclei and all of the developing
            oocytes except the final 4-5 (<link linkend="bib82">Maddox et al., 2005</link>) are diffusionally connected to the
            rachis (the central cytoplasmic core of the syncytial gonad). Introduction of a dsRNA
            triggers the degradation of the corresponding mRNA. However, the syncytial gonad and
            connected oocytes still contain the target protein that was present at the time of
            injection. Maternal stores are depleted by the continual packaging of gonad cytoplasm
            into developing oocytes. By 36 to 48 hours after introduction of the dsRNA oocytes are
            typically <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x003E;</symbol>95% depleted of the target
			protein. (B) Quantitative western blot of worms injected with a dsRNA against <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ANI-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ANI-1</ulink>, a
            protein required for cortical contractility in the early embryo (<link linkend="bib82">Maddox et al., 2005</link>).
            Serial dilutions of identically processed control worms were loaded to quantify the
            depletion level. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ANI-1;class=protein" role="_blank">ANI-1</ulink> is ~97% depleted in the injected worms, whereas levels of two
            control proteins, <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x03B1;</symbol>-tubulin and a related
            actin binding protein, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/seq/protein?name=ANI-2;class=protein" role="_blank">ANI-2</ulink>, are unaffected. Figure courtesy of Amy Maddox.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>