<caption>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Figure 6. Mitotic kinetochores in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo.</title>
        <para>(A) Images comparing the localized kinetochores in a vertebrate tissue culture cell
            with monocentric chromosomes to the diffuse kinetochores in a <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryo with
            holocentric chromosomes. (B) Schematic illustrating the hierarchy for mitotic
            kinetochore assembly based on pair-wise depletion and localization assays, phenotypic
            analysis, and biochemical purifications. Dotted lines indicate groups of proteins that
            have been shown to co-purify from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> extracts in immunoprecipitations and tagged
            protein isolations. The colored ovals group proteins together whose individual
            depletions result in a similar phenotype. (Red) “Kinetochore Null”/KNL proteins whose
            depletion is characterized by a failure to assemble kinetochores that are competent to
            form spindle microtubule attachments. Consequently, segregation is severely defective
            and spindle poles separate prematurely. (Blue) “MIS” proteins whose depletion results in
            relatively subtle chromosome segregation defects. In MIS embryos, kinetochore assembly
            occurs but at a slower rate and to a reduced extent relative to wild-type. (Yellow)
            “NDC” proteins whose depletion results in a chromosome alignment and segregation defects
            of intermediate severity, relative to the KNL and MIS classes. In NDC embryos,
            attachments that can sustain tension fail to form. Consequently, spindle poles separate
            prematurely. (Green) HCP/CLASP proteins, whose depletion causes sister chromatids to
            co-segregate to the same spindle pole. This defect likely arises from an inability to
            polymerize microtubules at kinetochores. (C) Schematic illustrating the temporal window
            during the first mitotic division when each of the indicated proteins localizes to
            kinetochores. Figure and images courtesy of Susan Kline-Smith and Arshad Desai, respectively.</para>
    </formalpara>
</caption>