<caption>
	<formalpara>
		<title>Figure 2. The integration of steps necessary for oxidative phosphorylation.</title>
		<para>Substrates that are electron donors for the respiratory chain are transported across the inner mitochondrial membrane by different carriers. In the matrix, electrons from pyruvate, glutamate, and malate are transferred to NAD+ by substrate-specific dehydrogenases and enter the respiratory chain via complex I. Succinate dehydrogenase is an integral activity of complex II. Electrons from complex I and II are transferred to complex III by the common shuttle CoQ. The electrons reach oxygen, the terminal acceptor, via cytochrome c and complex IV. Electron transport through the respiratory chain (flat gray arrows) is absolutely linked to proton extrusion by complexes I,-III, and IV (flat white arrows). The proton gradient across the inner mitochondrial membrane drives ATP production. ATP synthetase allows protons to re-enter the matrix and uses the energy released in this process to synthesize ATP. The substrates for phosphorylation, ADP and inorganic phosphate (Pi), enter the matrix via the ADP/ATP translocase (ANT) and the phosphate carrier. Measuring respiration of isolated mitochondria in response to natural and artificial electron donor substrates allows the integrated function of mitochondria to be assessed and the localization of defective steps. The positions of the defective steps for <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gas-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gas-1</ulink></emphasis> (complex I), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mev-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">mev-1</ulink></emphasis>(complex II), <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=isp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">isp-1</ulink></emphasis>(complex III), and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=clk-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">clk-1</ulink></emphasis>(CoQ) mitochondria are indicated by the red bars.</para>
	</formalpara>
</caption>