<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY % local.notation.class '| MOV'>
<!NOTATION MOV SYSTEM 'MOV'>
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'anesthfig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'anesthfig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'anesthfig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'anesthfig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'anesthfig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'anesthfig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY mov1 SYSTEM 'anesthmov1.mov' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov1legend SYSTEM 'anesthmov1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY mov2 SYSTEM 'anesthmov2.mov' NDATA MOV>
<!ENTITY mov2legend SYSTEM 'anesthmov2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY anesth_Refs SYSTEM 'anesthrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="anesth_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
		<!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title><emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and volatile anesthetics<footnote>
			<para>Edited by Adres Villu Maricq and Steven McIntire. Last revised December 28, 2006. Published May 3, 2007. This chapter should be cited as: Morgan, P.G., et al. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and volatile anesthetics (May 3, 2007), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.140.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2007 P.G. Morgan, et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
		<author>
			<othername>P.G. Morgan, E.-B. Kayser, M.M. Sedensky<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:margaret.sedensky@uhhs.com">margaret.sedensky@uhhs.com</ulink></para></footnote></remark></othername>
			<affiliation><address>Departments of Anesthesiology and Genetics, Case School of Medicine, Cleveland, OH 44106 USA</address></affiliation>
	</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">The mechanism of action of volatile anesthetics remains an enigma, despite their worldwide use. The nematode</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">has served as an excellent model to unravel this mystery. Genes and gene sets that control the behavior of the animal in volatile anesthetics have been identified, using multiple endpoints to mimic the phenomenon of anesthesia in man. Some of these studies have clear translational implications in more complicated organisms.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>The first successful public demonstration of reversible loss of consciousness by a volatile anesthetic occurred on October 16, 1846. Administration of diethyl ether allowed the removal of a neck tumor from a quiescent and pain free patient. Not only did this stunning demonstration revolutionize medical practice by changing the scope and frequency of surgery, but it was viewed as a triumph over pain and hailed as a gift to humanity. Oliver Wendell Holmes, who went on to become the dean of the Harvard School of Medicine, coined the phrase &#x0201C;anesthesia&#x0201D; in order to give a name to something that had never been conceived as possible by physicians prior to that time (<link linkend="bib8">Fenster, 2001</link>). The hallmarks of volatile agents as complete general anesthetics include amnesia, analgesia, muscle relaxation, and loss of consciousness, which are not provided <emphasis>in toto</emphasis> by any other single class of medicinal agents (<link linkend="bib59">Zhang et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11049925-->). In the past 150 years a number of seemingly unrelated volatile compounds have been used as volatile anesthetics. From heavily substituted halogenated alkanes and ethers to elemental noble gases, volatile anesthetics are still a mainstay of modern medicine (<link linkend="bib59">Zhang et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 11049925-->). However, their volatility, lack of physical similarity to each other, and apparent weak affinity for their target(s), has hampered understanding of their mechanism(s) of action at the molecular level. Although empirically well understood in their clinical administration, volatile anesthetics do not yet lend themselves well to rational drug design. Each volatile anesthetic currently in use is associated with its own characteristic side effects and limitations.</para>
<para>Early work on the mechanism of action of volatile anesthetics took note of the high lipid solubility of this class of compounds, as well as the high amount of lipid staining in the brain. By the turn of the 20th century, Meyer and Overton independently noted that volatile anesthetics increase in potency as a function of their solubility in olive oil, a heterogeneous collection of non-polar lipids. This held true for all species in which anesthetics were tested, over four to five orders of magnitude of lipid solubility (<link linkend="bib24">Meyer, 1899</link>; <link linkend="bib35">Overton, 1901</link>; <link linkend="bib50">Tanifuji et al., 1977</link><!--; PMID 559438-->). Termed the Meyer-Overton rule, the correlation led to early hypotheses about how volatile anesthetics work. A plot of this relationship could be used to derive an interesting corollary. Assuming that the anesthetic target and/or its milieu shares physical properties with the solvent olive oil, all inhaled anesthetics, are present in equimolar concentrations at the anesthetic site when they have reached their effective volatile concentrations (<link linkend="bib50">Tanifuji et al., 1977</link><!--; PMID 559438-->). It was therefore viewed that lipid solubility was the parameter that controlled access to the anesthetic target, but that once actually reaching their site of action, all inhaled anesthetics were equally potent. Also, volatile anesthetics are generally additive in their effects, <emphasis>i.e.</emphasis> a mixture of a half dose of two different volatile anesthetics was in fact equal to a full dose of either drug in isolation. In this manner a unitary theory of narcosis was born, in which all volatile anesthetics work at the same single target in all species (<link linkend="bib5">Deady et al., 1981</link><!--; PMID 7195159-->). Most theories originally favored a fairly non-specific insinuation of the volatile anesthetic into the lipid bilayer of excitable cell membranes, causing inhibition of neuronal conduction. Changes in membrane density (critical volume hypothesis) and membrane fluidity were invoked as the mechanism of action of volatile anesthetics (<link linkend="bib48">Suezaki et al., 1990</link><!--; PMID 2223805-->). Although these physical changes definitely occur in membranes in the presence of volatile anesthetics, relatively small increases in temperature can mimic these effects on membrane fluidity and density without causing anesthesia. For this and other reasons (see below), these early models that hypothesized a general, non-specific interaction of volatile anesthetics with cell membranes fell into disfavor.</para>
<para>Through the work of Franks and Lieb and others, it was shown that in fact a Meyer-Overton plot could be obtained by substituting octanol for olive oil as the solvent in which volatile anesthetic solubility was measured (<link linkend="bib1">Abraham et al., 1991</link><!--; PMID 1791528-->). An equally good fit exists between potency and solubility of volatile anesthetics in this polar molecule. In addition, volatile anesthetics can inhibit luciferase in a cell free extract; their potency of inhibition correlates well with their potency as anesthetics (<link linkend="bib61">Moss et al., 1991</link><!--; PMID 1986359-->). Proteins are currently favored as potential targets of volatile anesthetics, and many molecules have been proposed as anesthetic targets. In particular, various membrane ion channels and receptors are hypothesized to be the site of action of volatile anesthetics. Volatile anesthetics affect the functions of multiple membrane proteins, most notably ligand gated ion channels (GABA<subscript>A</subscript> receptors, glutamate receptors), voltage gated ion channels, G-protein coupled receptors and various other ion channels (reviewed in <link linkend="bib6">Evers and Crowder, 2006</link>). Currently no single protein or channel has emerged as the likely anesthetic target to the exclusion of all others. Current debate entertains the possibility that multiple targets may exist for volatile anesthetics. The extremely steep dose-response curves seen for this class of molecules are certainly most consistent with multiple sites of action. If this is the case, then the relative importance of each potential target cannot be easily determined using an <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> approach.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Nematode response to volatile anesthetics</title>
<para>&#x0201C;Anesthesia&#x0201D; is clearly a whole animal phenomenon. Anesthetics as volatile, lipid soluble chemicals can perturb virtually any experimental system into which they are introduced. Therefore a model organism such as the nematode is invaluable in understanding how the volatile anesthetics work. <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> has multiple behaviors which can be used as anesthetic endpoints (<link linkend="bib30">Morgan and Cascorbi, 1985</link><!--; PMID 4003794-->; <link linkend="bib3">Crowder et al., 1996</link><!--; PMID 8873562-->). When exposed to volatile anesthetics, wild-type nematodes first increase movement, become &#x02018;excited&#x02019;, and lose their response to volatile attractants. This behavior proceeds to a progressive lack of coordination, followed by immobility and unresponsiveness to a tap to the snout (see <link linkend="movie1">Movie 1</link>; <link linkend="bib30">Morgan and Cascorbi, 1985</link><!--; PMID 4003794-->). This progression of neurologic changes is reminiscent of the neurological responses seen in patients, who experience an excitatory phase upon induction of general anesthesia. Excitation gradually becomes progressively uncoordinated movement that eventually slows to complete immobility in response to a surgical stimulus. Several different endpoints have been used to measure anesthetic effects in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. The two most commonly used have been (1) some form of uncoordination or change in motion in response to anesthetic exposure and (2) immobility. Both endpoints can demonstrate a Meyer-Overton relationship, <emphasis>i.e.</emphasis> potency strictly follows lipid solubility; in each assay then the order of potency of gases is very similar to that seen in humans. The mechanisms of the two anesthetic actions are distinct and likely correspond to different components of the set of complex behavioral effects seen in the vertebrate nervous system (see <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). Insight concerning the mechanisms of action of volatile anesthetics will probably come from studies of several endpoints.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="movie1" xreflabel="Movie 1">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="mov1" width="3in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>movie 1</phrase>
	</textobject> &mov1legend;</mediaobject>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.4in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 1</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Radial dispersion, uncoordination/Presynaptic effects</title>
<para>Concentrations of volatile anesthetics that produce immobility in response to a surgical stimulus in humans do not immobilize worms. However, at these concentrations worms do exhibit an easily scored sluggishness and uncoordination (<link linkend="bib3">Crowder, 1996</link><!--; PMID 8873562-->). Using radial dispersion as an endpoint, Crowder and colleagues (<link linkend="bib3">Crowder et al. 1996</link><!--; PMID 8873562-->; <link linkend="bib53">van Swinderen et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10051668-->; <link linkend="bib51">van Swinderen et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12019227-->) screened nematodes carrying previously identified mutations in neuronal proteins of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> for altered sensitivity to anesthetics. They found that mutations in syntaxin (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-64;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-64</ulink></emphasis>) caused either resistance or hypersensitivity to volatile anesthetics. Syntaxin is a member of the protein complex that controls presynaptic vesicular fusion with the cell membrane, resulting in neurotransmitter release into the synaptic cleft (<link linkend="bib20">Koushika and Nonet, 2000</link><!--; PMID 10873821-->). This complex, the SNARE complex, includes the syntaxin-binding proteins synaptobrevin and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SNAP-25;class=Protein" role="_blank">SNAP-25</ulink> (<link linkend="bib34">Nonet et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9412487-->; <link linkend="bib40">Rand and Nonet, 1997</link>). The syntaxin allelic variation was striking, particularly for isoflurane, where a 33-fold range of sensitivities was seen. Mutations causing hypersensitivity reduced neurotransmitter release, while the resistant class generally increased release. However, one mutation dominantly conferred resistance to the volatile anesthetics, isoflurane and halothane, but decreased neurotransmitter release. The authors concluded that syntaxin is a possible target of volatile anesthetics, and that anesthetics ordinarily work by decreasing neurotransmitter release via syntaxin binding. Later data indicated that mammalian syntaxin is capable of binding halothane (<link linkend="bib31">Nagele et al., 2005a</link><!--; PMID 16192769-->).</para>
<para>Using a different set of endpoints (velocity of locomotion and the body bend assay), Crowder and Nonet tested anesthetic sensitivity of mutants isolated in a screen for enhancers of transmitter release (<link linkend="bib55">Wang et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11738032-->; <link linkend="bib11">Hawasli et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15514057-->). They screened for suppression of a hypomorphic <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-64;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-64</ulink></emphasis> to facilitate identification of mutations that enhanced syntaxin function. The largest group of genes included loss of function alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes the calcium activated potassium channel (BK channel); not surprisingly, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> animals were resistant to halothane (see <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). Wang showed that this channel negatively regulates neurotransmitter release in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib55">Wang et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11738032-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink></emphasis> alleles have also been identified in screens for resistance to ethanol (<link linkend="bib4">Davies et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 14675531-->) which has been thought to share some mechanistic similarities to the volatile anesthetics. <link linkend="bib11">Hawasli et al. (2004<!--; PMID 15514057-->)</link> also found that mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-43;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-43</ulink></emphasis> suppressed the syntaxin mutants (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-43;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-43</ulink></emphasis> is a calcium/calmodulin dependent protein kinase). Mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-43;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-43</ulink></emphasis> did not change volatile anesthetic sensitivity in isolation (see <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>).</para>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="100%">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1. Mutations with multiple interactions that affect anesthetic sensitivity in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans.</emphasis></emphasis></title>
<tgroup cols="7">
<colspec colname="c1" align="center" colwidth="0.9*"/>
<colspec colname="c2" align="left" colwidth="1.2*"/>
<colspec colname="c3" align="left" colwidth="1.1*"/>
<colspec colname="c4" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c5" align="left" colwidth="1.1*"/>
<colspec colname="c6" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
<colspec colname="c7" align="left" colwidth="1.1*"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Mutants</entry>
<entry>Product</entry>
<entry>Nonanesthetic phenotype</entry>
<entry>Endpoint</entry>
<entry>Anesthetic phenotype</entry>
<entry>Interactions</entry>
<entry>Comments</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-64;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-64</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>Syntaxin</entry>
<entry>sluggish</entry>
<entry>Radial dispersion</entry>
<entry>Allele specific changes</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=goa-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">goa-1</ulink>,<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-43;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-43</ulink>,<ulink url="http://wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=egl-30;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-30</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>Postulated direct target</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=slo-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">slo-1</ulink>(lf)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>BK channel</entry>
<entry/>
<entry>Velocity of locomotion</entry>
<entry>Resistant</entry>
<entry>Suppress
<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-64;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-64</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=goa-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">goa-1</ulink>(lf)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Alpha subunit of Go</entry>
<entry>hyperactive</entry>
<entry>Radial dispersion</entry>
<entry>Resistant</entry>
<entry/>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-30;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-30</ulink>(gf)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Alpha subunit of Gq</entry>
<entry/>
<entry>Velocity of locomotion</entry>
<entry><emphasis>egl-30(lf)</emphasis> hyper-sensitive</entry>
<entry>Suppress <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-64;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-64</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-43;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-43</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>Calcium dependent protein kinase</entry>
<entry/>
<entry>Velocity of locomotion</entry>
<entry>None</entry>
<entry>Suppress <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-64;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-64</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>Novel</entry>
<entry>fainter</entry>
<entry>immobility</entry>
<entry>Hyper-sensitive to specific anesthetics</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-8</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-7</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-9</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-24;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-24</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-80;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-80</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>Unknown</entry>
<entry>fainter</entry>
<entry>immobility</entry>
<entry>Hyper-sensitive to specific anesthetics</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-8</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-7</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-9</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-24;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-24</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-1</ulink>(lf), <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-24;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-24</ulink>(lf)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Stomatins</entry>
<entry>kinker</entry>
<entry>immobility</entry>
<entry>Hyper-sensitive to ether</entry>
<entry>Suppress fainters</entry>
<entry><emphasis>gf</emphasis> alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-1</ulink></emphasis> hyper-sensitive to all VAs</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-7</ulink>(lf) <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-9</ulink>(lf)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Gap junction proteins</entry>
<entry>kinker</entry>
<entry>immobility</entry>
<entry>Hyper-sensitive to ether</entry>
<entry>Suppress fainters</entry>
<entry/>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-8</ulink>(gf)</emphasis></entry>
<entry>Degenerin/ENaC</entry>
<entry>kinker</entry>
<entry>immobility</entry>
<entry>Hyper-sensitive to ether</entry>
<entry>Suppress fainters</entry>
<entry><emphasis>lf</emphasis> alleles suppress <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nca-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">nca-2</ulink>,<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nca-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">nca-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>Cation channels</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nca-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">nca-2</ulink>;<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nca-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">nca-1</ulink></emphasis> is a fainter</entry>
<entry>immobility</entry>
<entry>Hyper-sensitive to specific anesthetics</entry>
<entry><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-8</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-7</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-9</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-24;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-24</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry>Protein product lost in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-80;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-80</ulink></emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry namest="c1" nameend="c7" align="left">Note: Mitochondrial mutations are not listed. See text.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>Finally, and perhaps most remarkably, a gain-of-function mutation in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-30;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-30</ulink></emphasis> suppressed the hypersensitive syntaxin mutants, while loss-of-function mutants in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-30;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-30</ulink></emphasis> increased anesthetic sensitivity (<link linkend="bib11">Hawasli et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15514057-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-30;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-30</ulink></emphasis> encodes the a subunit of the G protein Gq, previously shown to positively regulate locomotion and other elements of behavior (<link linkend="bib25">Miller et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10571227-->; <link linkend="bib21">Lackner et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10571228-->). These results are particularly interesting in that the same laboratory earlier showed that loss of function mutations in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=goa-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">goa-1</ulink></emphasis> led to volatile anesthetic resistance (<link linkend="bib52">van Swinderen et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11404329-->). The results are consistent with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=goa-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">goa-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=egl-30;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-30</ulink></emphasis> having antagonistic functions in regulating neurotransmitter release and volatile anesthetic sensitivity of this endpoint. In summary, each of these mutations indicates that the general activity of the presynaptic region is of importance in determining anesthetic sensitivity. Neurotransmitter release may be elevated or depressed, with resulting changes in anesthetic sensitivity. The authors also concluded that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=SLO-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLO-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=EGL-30;class=Protein" role="_blank">EGL-30</ulink> were unlikely to encode a volatile anesthetic target.</para>
<para>Corroborating their work in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, Crowder and colleagues later showed that isoflurane inhibited the presynaptic action potential in the rat brainstem at the Calyx of Held (<link linkend="bib57">Wu et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15108983-->). This inhibition decreased glutamate release and, in turn, the excitatory postsynaptic potential as a secondary effect. The authors concluded that the presynaptic effects contributed to the inhibition of postsynaptic currents. The same laboratory expressed rat orthologues of many of the SNARE proteins in a heterologous system, and found that both the SNARE complex and the syntaxin protein were capable of binding both halothane and isoflurane (<link linkend="bib31">Nagele et al., 2005a</link><!--; PMID 16192769-->).</para>
<para>In closely related work, Crowder and colleagues studied the action of nitrous oxide (laughing gas) in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib33">Nagele et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15159532-->). They found that nitrous oxide produced a behavior similar to that produced by loss-of-function mutations affecting either the AMPA or NMDA glutamate receptors in the worm. Only the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nmr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">nmr-1</ulink></emphasis> mutant animal (the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nmr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">nmr-1</ulink></emphasis> gene codes for the NMDA receptor) was resistant to the effects of nitrous oxide. They concluded that the NMDA receptor was required for the effects of nitrous oxide. The same laboratory also studied the effects of the volatile anesthetic xenon and found that the non-NMDA glutamate receptor <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=glr-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">glr-1</ulink></emphasis> was necessary for the anesthetic effects of the drug (<link linkend="bib32">Nagele et al., 2005b</link><!--; PMID 16129975-->).</para>
<para>Interestingly, and in contrast to studies in syntaxin by this group, these last two studies implicate postsynaptic activity as key to controlling sensitivity to xenon and nitrous oxide. Thus, it appears that different volatile anesthetics may function differently in causing uncoordination and decreased speed of locomotion.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Immobility/Neuronal effects</title>
<para>In human patients, the effective concentration of a volatile anesthetic necessary for surgical anesthesia is termed &#x0201C;MAC&#x0201D; for &#x0201C;minimal alveolar concentration.&#x0201D; It is the concentration of a gas that, in 50% of patients, will cause a patient to remain immobile during a surgical stimulus (<link linkend="bib41">Regan and Eger, 1967</link><!--; PMID 4381898-->). In an effort to mimic MAC in worms, Morgan and Sedensky used reversible immobility as an endpoint to study control of anesthetic behavior in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib30">Morgan and Cascorbi, 1985</link><!--; PMID 4003794-->). This screen uses higher concentrations of anesthetics than those safely used in patients, although the relative order of their potency is nearly identical to that seen in humans. In this assay, the Meyer-Overton relationship holds true for a range of lipid solubilities that varies by nearly 4 orders of magnitude. Mutations affecting immobility in anesthetics identified an interacting set of genes that have been ordered relative to each other, and has yielded some surprising correlates in studies in other species. However, it is important to note that the gene products may not directly interact with each other or be in a common metabolic pathway. Apparently epistatic mutations may actually affect cells or functions which are themselves &#x0201C;downstream&#x0201D; in causing immobility. In addition, those genes identified in screens for uncoordination caused by anesthetics generally have little effect in immobility assays; vice versa - genes identified in screens for immobility have not been found in screens using radial dispersion as an endpoint.</para>
<para>Screening for hypersensitivity to the anesthetic halothane, Sedensky and Morgan identified a new allele of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink>(III)</emphasis> which caused the animal to be very hypersensitive to a number of gases (<link linkend="bib30">Morgan and Cascorbi, 1985</link><!--; PMID 4003794-->; <link linkend="bib42">Sedensky and Meneely, 1987</link><!--; PMID 3576211-->). In general, using immobility as an endpoint gives steep dose-response curves, such that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis> animals are absolutely immobile in 2% halothane, while N2 animals move vigorously. However, an unexpected feature of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis> animals was that they did not respond equally to all volatile anesthetics. They are hypersensitive to halothane (and the most lipid soluble volatile anesthetics), but react like wildtype to a second set of volatile anesthetics, and are resistant to yet other gases. This ability to separate out anesthetic-specific behavior flew in the face of the so-called unitary theory of general anesthesia, which maintains that all anesthetics work at the same site of action in all organisms (<link linkend="bib5">Deady et al., 1981</link><!--; PMID 7195159-->; <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis> animals were first characterized as &#x0201C;fainters&#x0201D;, but otherwise moved well in air. Fainting refers to alternating periods of stopping and moving; motion is normal when moving but interrupted by periods of inactivity lasting several seconds (see <link linkend="movie2">Movie 2</link>). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis> is not the only known mutation that confers a fainter phenotype. Animals carrying alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-80;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-80</ulink></emphasis> (an uncharacterized gene; <link linkend="bib27">Morgan et al., 1988</link><!--; PMID 2900611-->), and animals containing a loss of function mutation in both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nca-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">nca-1</ulink></emphasis> (also known as <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-77;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-77</ulink></emphasis> for gain-of-function alleles; E. Yeh, S. Ng and M. Zhen, personal communication) and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nca-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">nca-2</ulink></emphasis>, faint in air and are hypersensitive to anesthetics in a manner similar to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis> (K. Hamming, personal communication; Morgan and Sedensky, unpublished). By homology, both <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nca-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">nca-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nca-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">nca-2</ulink></emphasis> encode probable cation channel proteins (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org" role="_blank">Wormbase</ulink>).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="movie2" xreflabel="Movie 2">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="mov2" width="3in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>movie 2</phrase>
	</textobject> &mov2legend;</mediaobject>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-79;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-79</ulink> is a sentinel member of a novel family of highly conserved proteins expressed in the nervous systems of animals from nematodes to human. Expression of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis>, which has 27 introns, appears to be tightly developmentally regulated when assayed by a GFP reporter. It is restricted to cells of the ventral nerve cord in young larvae, and becomes confined to a few head neurons in the adult. The gene has 3 introns which are highly conserved between <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>, and its predominant message contains retained introns. It is likely that the expression pattern of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis> is dependent on which introns are retained. In <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis> mutants, neither <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NCA-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">NCA-1</ulink> nor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=NCA-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">NCA-2</ulink> is found on Western blots, while transcription of these genes is normal (Sedensky and Morgan, unpublished). Thus, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis> may exert its effect through stabilization of these two proteins.</para>
<para>This behavior of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-80;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-80</ulink></emphasis> animals was completely suppressed by null mutations in the X-linked gene <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-1</ulink></emphasis>, which encodes the protein stomatin (<link linkend="bib28">Morgan et al., 1990</link><!--; PMID 2326259-->; <link linkend="bib38">Rajaram et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9671752-->). Animals containing different alleles of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-1</ulink></emphasis> display different behaviors in the gaseous anesthetics; <emphasis>unc-1(0)</emphasis> animals have a kinking motion and are only sensitive to diethyl ether, while <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-1</ulink>(d)</emphasis> animals are hypersensitive to halothane, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink>;unc-1(d)</emphasis> animals are extremely anesthetic sensitive. The other kinked mutations <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-7</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-9</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-24;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-24</ulink></emphasis> also suppress <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-80;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-80</ulink></emphasis>, and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nca-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">nca-2</ulink>;<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nca-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">nca-1</ulink></emphasis> (Morgan and Sedensky, unpublished; <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>).</para>
<para><emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-1</ulink></emphasis> encodes a stomatin homologue that is broadly, but exclusively, expressed within the nematode nervous system (and in the 4 vulval muscles) in a pattern consistent with localization in the nerve cell membrane (<link linkend="bib38">Rajaram et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9671752-->; <link linkend="bib39">Rajaram et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10581275-->; <link linkend="bib43">Sedensky et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11287347-->). Stomatins are membrane proteins that are associated with membrane channels, within microdomains known as lipid rafts (<link linkend="bib46">Snyers et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10604657-->). Two other stomatins have been studied in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-24;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-24</ulink>, which controls the distribution of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib44">Sedensky et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15102610-->) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=MEC-2;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEC-2</ulink> which is involved with mechanosensation (<link linkend="bib13">Huang et al., 1995</link><!--; PMID 7477350-->) and does not affect anesthetic sensitivity (Morgan and Sedensky, unpublished).</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-1</ulink> had been postulated to form homo-oligomers based on its complicated intra-allelic complementation patterns, a prediction now known to be true (<link linkend="bib36">Park and Horvitz, 1986</link><!--; PMID 3744028-->; <link linkend="bib47">Snyers et al., 1998</link><!--; PMID 9642292-->). In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> it was established that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-1</ulink> was normally localized almost entirely within lipid rafts, and that it physically interacted with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-8</ulink>, which is also primarily localized to rafts (<link linkend="bib44">Sedensky et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15102610-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-8</ulink></emphasis> encodes a degenerin that is part of a large family of channel proteins that includes DEG/ENaCs (degenerins/epithelial sodium channels) and ASICs (acid-sensing ion channels; <link linkend="bib49">Tavernarakis et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9010209-->; <link linkend="bib54">Waldmann et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9062189-->). Like <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-8</ulink></emphasis> displays multiple classes of alleles (<link linkend="bib36">Park and Horvitz., 1986</link><!--; PMID 3744028-->; <link linkend="bib49">Tavernarakis et al., 1997</link><!--; PMID 9010209-->), which includes one with a phenotype similar to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-1</ulink>(0)</emphasis>, <emphasis>i.e.</emphasis> a kinked phenotype that can suppress <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-8</ulink>(d);<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-1</ulink>(d)</emphasis> displays a novel phenotype; this double mutant is a kinker unlike either coiler parent. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-1;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-8</ulink> co-immunoprecipitate and thus probably physically interact in lipid rafts. Thus, there is a complicated interaction between these two gene products (<link linkend="bib39">Rajaram et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10581275-->; <link linkend="bib44">Sedensky et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15102610-->). Interestingly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-79;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-79</ulink> is also apparently necessary for normal processing of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-8;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-8</ulink> within a raft, although <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=UNC-79;class=Protein" role="_blank">UNC-79</ulink> itself appears to be confined to the cytosol (Morgan and Sedensky, unpublished).</para>
<para>It is interesting that the members of the SNARE complex have been found to be associated with lipid rafts and with ENaC channels (<link linkend="bib23">Lafont et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10097106-->). Syntaxin mutations do not alter anesthetic sensitivity when immobility is used as an endpoint. However, the association of the SNARE complex, stomatin and ENaC channels with lipid rafts and with each other suggests a common pathway or target may be affected by these mutations. These data are further emphasized by the fact that the anesthetic response of yeast is modulated by the ubiquitin system, which also resides in lipid rafts (<link linkend="bib56">Wolfe et al. 1999</link><!--; PMID 10567550-->; <link linkend="bib22">Lafont and Simons, 2001</link><!--; PMID 11248052-->). Thus, proteins identified by diverse screens for changes in volatile anesthetic sensitivity may implicate related targets associated with lipid rafts in both yeast and in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>.</para>
<para>Stomatins and ENaCs are known to co-localize within tissues like the dorsal root ganglion, part of the sensory pathway in mammals (<link linkend="bib9">Fricke et al., 2000</link><!--; PMID 10772247-->). In addition, stomatins are known to affect channel properties of ASICs/ENaCs (<link linkend="bib37">Price et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 15471860-->). A mouse knock out for stomatin gives a profile of anesthetic sensitivity similar to that seen in the worm (<link linkend="bib45">Sedensky et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16931982-->). This knockout is of a stomatin that is expressed in the spinal cord and periphery of the animal; there are no other mutant forms of stomatin for mammals (<link linkend="bib60">Zhu et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 10090952-->). In particular there is none specific to brain stomatin, and no dominant mutations similar to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-1</ulink>(d).</emphasis></para>
<para>The above studies thus identify several genes that interact to affect sensitivity to volatile anesthetics. The identified genes include three that code for ion channels (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-8;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-8</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nca-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">nca-1</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=nca-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">nca-2</ulink></emphasis>), two that encode stomatin-like proteins (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-24;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-24</ulink></emphasis>), two that encode gap junction proteins (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-7;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-7</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-9;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-9</ulink></emphasis>) and one novel protein (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis>). The protein product of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-80;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-80</ulink></emphasis> remains to be identified. The interactions of these genes, as well as those that effect endpoints other than immobility, are summarized in <link linkend="table1">Table 1</link>.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Immobility/Mitochondrial effects</title>
<para>Another mutation was identified in a screen for hypersensitivity to the volatile anesthetic isoflurane. Unlike <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis> animals, this new mutation conferred extreme hypersensitivity to all volatile anesthetics, as well as to ethanol (<link linkend="bib29">Morgan and Sedensky, 1994</link><!--; PMID 7943840-->; <link linkend="bib14">Kayser et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12711920-->). Named <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gas-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gas-1</ulink></emphasis> (<emphasis role="bold">g</emphasis>eneral <emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis>nesthetic <emphasis role="bold">s</emphasis>ensitive), it is a temperature-sensitive lethal with reduced fecundity, increased oxygen sensitivity, and a shortened lifespan at 20&#x000B0;C. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gas-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gas-1</ulink></emphasis> encodes a subunit - an ortholog of the bovine &#x0201C;49kD&#x0201D; protein of complex I-, of the respiratory chain in mitochondria (<link linkend="bib18">Kayser et al., 1999</link><!--; PMID 9952163-->). In the mitochondrion, electrons are passed from specific electron donors through a series of protein complexes to the final electron acceptor, oxygen (see <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). A proton gradient is established in the process, which drives the synthesis of ATP. The concerted action of electron transport and ATP production is termed oxidative phosphorylation. Complex I is one of the points of entry for electrons into the respiratory chain and one of the proton pumps. It is the largest and least well-characterized complex, with an estimated size in mammals of almost 1000kD. (<link linkend="bib12">Hirst et al., 2003</link><!--; PMID 12837546-->) <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=gas-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">gas-1</ulink></emphasis> mitochondria are quite defective in oxidative phosphorylation using complex I specific substrates; individual steps of electron passage within the complex are also reduced, but rates of passage of electrons to CoQ is reduced by over 90% (<link linkend="bib15">Kayser et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11278828-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=clk-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">clk-1</ulink></emphasis>, a defect in CoQ synthesis, is also specifically defective in passage of electrons from complex I, and is mildly hypersensitive to volatile anesthetics (<link linkend="bib10">Hartman et al., 2001</link><!--; PMID 11389932-->; <link linkend="bib16">Kayser et al., 2004a</link><!--; PMID 15269213-->). RNAi induced hypomorphs in complex I subunits are also anesthetic sensitive, in a manner that matches their rates of oxidative phosphorylation with complex I substrates (<link linkend="bib17">Kayser et al., 2004b</link><!--; PMID 15277919-->; <link linkend="bib7">Falk et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16920626-->).</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="5in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 2</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>In addition, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> animals were tested for anesthetic sensitivity based on the longevity phenotype they share with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=clk-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">clk-1</ulink></emphasis>. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-2;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-2</ulink></emphasis> animals are resistant to volatile anesthetics and have an increased rate of complex I dependent oxidative phosphorylation (Morgan and Sedensky, unpublished). The effects of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=daf-16;class=Gene" role="_blank">daf-16</ulink></emphasis> on this response have not been determined. In contrast, animals containing mutations in complex II (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=mev-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">mev-1</ulink></emphasis>) and complex III (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=isp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">isp-1</ulink></emphasis>), which possess defects in other components of the electron transport chain, behave like wildtype in anesthetics (<link linkend="bib17">Kayser et al., 2004b</link><!--; PMID 15277919-->; <link linkend="bib7">Falk et al., 2006</link><!--; PMID 16920626-->). <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=isp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">isp-1</ulink></emphasis> animals have decreased rates of complex I function, as well as decreased rates of complex II, due to its position downstream in the electron transport chain (see <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). Despite the decreased complex I dependent oxidative phosphorylation rates seen in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=isp-1;class=Gene" role="_blank">isp-1</ulink></emphasis>, the anesthetic sensitivity of this mutant is normal. Previously, work had shown that radiolabeled halothane accumulates in mitochondria, with more label within the organelle in <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=unc-79;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-79</ulink></emphasis> animals than in N2. (R.E. Eckenhoff, personal communication) In mammals a similar labeling experiment showed that in the 25 proteins that could be identified as labeled with halothane, 17 were mitochondrial proteins. (<link linkend="bib58">Xi et al., 2004</link><!--; PMID 14988400-->) It has also been demonstrated in mammals and in worms that of all the complexes of the electron transport chain, complex I is the most sensitive to inhibition by the volatile anesthetics (<link linkend="bib17">Kayser et al., 2004b</link><!--; PMID 15277919-->; <link linkend="bib2">Cohen, 1973</link><!--; PMID 4146381-->).</para>
<para>In the nematode, it does not appear to be amounts of ATP that account for the difference in anesthetic sensitivity between wildtype and mutant worms. Nor does oxidative damage of a putative anesthetic target explain the sensitivity of complex I mutants to volatile agents. The sum of data indicates that complex I rates of oxidative phosphorylation, assayed <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> for near maximal capacity, reflect vulnerability of the animal to volatile anesthetics when the defect is due to a change within complex I itself. Defects in other complexes, or defects downstream of complex I, cause minor or no changes in anesthetic response. Mitochondrial function represents a novel potential mechanism of action of volatile anesthetics.</para>
<para>Regardless of the exact mechanism by which this novel putative target affects anesthetic behavior, a striking correlate of this finding has been found in patients (<link linkend="bib26">Morgan et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11981173-->). Children undergoing surgery, primarily for muscle biopsies taken for diagnosis of suspected mitochondrial defects, were anesthetized with the volatile anesthetic sevoflurane (<link linkend="bib26">Morgan et al., 2002</link><!--; PMID 11981173-->). Each patient&apos;s anesthetic sensitivity was determined via an integrated encephalogram obtained with a cutaneously applied sensor called a bispectral index (BIS). Those children with a confirmed complex I defect lost consciousness (indicated by a BIS reading of 60) at lower concentrations of anesthetic than normal children or those with other mitochondrial disorders - often by an order of magnitude.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Summary</title>
<para>At first glance data from <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> implicate quite disparate molecules as possible targets for volatile anesthetics. However, closer inspection indicates that these studies are beginning to form a picture of the molecular sites that control anesthetic sensitivity (see <link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). The genetic studies strongly suggest that anesthetic response is dependent on a broad group of molecular targets or pathways. The finding of altered sensitivity in patients with mitochondrial disease, the similarities between the responses of related mutants in mouse and nematodes, and the potential involvement of presynaptic proteins from mammals in anesthetic action underscores the applicability of these studies to the human population. A recent resurgence in interest in the role of mitochondria in regulating synaptic function may eventually tie a novel potential target to pathways that intuitively appear more directly related to the anesthetic state.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="5in" align="center"/>
	</imageobject>
	<textobject>
		<phrase>figure 3</phrase>
	</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
<para>It is also interesting to note what genetic data fail to do. They do not identify a single protein or channel that is uniquely responsible for the effects of anesthetics. The many endpoints associated with the anesthetic state are probably the result of effects at different sites of anesthetic action. In addition, even when considering a defined simple endpoint, the volatile anesthetics behave differently from each other. This indicates that, even with single endpoints, multiple targets or mechanisms are involved. However, the recurring theme of presynaptic function affecting volatile anesthetic sensitivity makes this cellular region an enticing possibility.</para>
<para>It is clear that volatile anesthetics are invaluable, time-tested, tools of modern clinical medicine. Understanding the mechanism of volatile anesthetic action will certainly be the key to produce the perfect anesthetic. But many questions remain as to the basis of their clinical effect, some of which remain with us from the inception of their use. Are there truly multiple targets for volatile anesthetics, or are we measuring multiple effects upstream or downstream from a single anesthetic target? If there are multiple targets, then how many? Do they encompass a family of receptors, or very different sorts of molecules? How can the target(s) react with so many different types of molecules?</para>
<para>In addition, as a class of drugs that quickly and reversibly produce loss of consciousness and pain, volatile anesthetics represent potential experimental probes into large questions of modern biology. What is the mechanism of consciousness? The nature of normal sleep? Can novel means be found to treat acute and chronic pain? What is the relation between hibernation and the anesthetized state? If one assumes that fundamental physiologic processes are highly conserved within the animal kingdom, then using <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> as a model to understand the mechanism of action of volatile anesthetics is a logical starting point to answer these questions. Concurrently, significant efforts can be made to extrapolate findings in worms to more complex animals. Ultimate success in understanding how the volatile anesthetics work will have far reaching ramifications for modern biology.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>References</title>
	&anesth_Refs;
	<para/>
</sect1>
</article>