<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'gm2pmfigch2-1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'gm2pmfigch2-1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'gm2pmfigch2-2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'gm2pmfigch2-2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'gm2pmfigch2-3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'gm2pmfigch2-3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY gm2pmch2_Refs SYSTEM 'gm2pmch2refs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="WMgm2pmch2_ArticleID">
	<articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
		<title>Genetic mapping and manipulation: Chapter 2-Two-point mapping with genetic markers<footnote>
				<para>Edited by Victor Ambros. Last revised April 30, 2005. Published February 17, 2006. This chapter should be cited as: Fay, D. Genetic mapping and manipulation: Chapter 2-Two-point mapping with genetic markers (February 17, 2006), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.91.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
		<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2006 David Fay. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
			</footnote>
		</title>
<!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 4/30/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory>
-->
		<author>
			<firstname>David</firstname>
			<surname>Fay<remark>
					<footnote>
						<para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:davidfay@uwyo.edu">davidfay@uwyo.edu</ulink>
						</para>
					</footnote>
				</remark>
			</surname>
			<affiliation>
				<address>Department of Molecular Biology, University of Wyoming, Laramie, Wyoming 82071-3944 USA</address>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
	</articleinfo>
	<sect1>
		<title>The basics</title>
		<para>The basics. Two-point mapping, wherein a mutation in the gene of interest is mapped against a marker mutation, is primarily used to assign mutations to individual chromosomes. It can also give at least a rough indication of distance between the mutation and the markers used. On the surface, the concept of two-point mapping to determine chromosomal linkage is relatively straightforward. It can, however, be the source of some confusion when it comes to processing the actual data based on phenotypic frequencies to accurately determine genetic distances. It is also worth noting that most researchers don't bother much with exhaustive two-point mapping anymore. Once we've assigned our mutation to a linkage group, it's generally off to the races with three-point and SNP mapping methods, as these will almost always be necessary to clone our genes anyway. It is worth noting, however, that high-throughput methods for two-point mapping using SNPs (also see below) have been used successfully by some groups and can provide a very precise map position for mutations. These methods may even (in some cases) allow for the molecular cloning of mutations in the absence of further three-point or SNP mapping (<link linkend="bib2">Wicks et al., 2001</link>; <link linkend="bib1">Swan et al., 2002</link>). Nevertheless, the vast majority of researchers still use the standard tiered cloning progression for which two-point mapping is simply step one.</para>
		<para>In carrying out two-point mapping, one can use either genetic or <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_SNPsintrotwopointmap/SNPsintrotwopointmap.html" role="_blank">SNP markers</ulink>. For the purpose of this section, we will cover the use of genetic markers, as the principals are the same and may be somewhat easier to grasp. Often we will carry out traditional two-point mapping using strains that contain two adjacent chromosomal markers, as the strains generated by these crosses can potentially be used later for three-point genetic mapping.</para>
		<para>The two most basic outcomes for two-point mapping are shown in (<xref linkend="figure1" />). In outcome #1, the chromosomal position of the affected gene (mutation) happens to be on the same/homologous chromosome as the markers being tested. In this case, the mutation is actually flanked by the markers to produce a reasonably well-balanced strain. The genotypes of the progeny are indicated along with the ratios (or fractions) of their occurrences. Three genotypes are generated (<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m/a b</emphasis></emphasis>, <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m/m</emphasis></emphasis>, <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a b/a b</emphasis></emphasis>) with three corresponding phenotypes (wild type, M, A B). In this situation we essentially never see the appearance of the triple mutant phenotype <emphasis role="bold">MAB</emphasis>, as this would require an exceedingly rare double-recombination event to take place. Furthermore, if we were to pick animals of phenotype <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> and examine their self-progeny, we would never see <emphasis role="bold">M A B</emphasis> animals. Likewise, <emphasis role="bold">A B</emphasis> animals will also fail to segregate <emphasis role="bold">M A B</emphasis> progeny. Finally, wild-type animals will always throw both <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">A B</emphasis> along with wild-type animals. Seeing segregation patterns of this type tells us that <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a b</emphasis></emphasis> reside on the same chromosome and also that <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> resides close to or in between the markers <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">b</emphasis></emphasis>. In the circumstance that the <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> phenotype is lethal, this may be a useful strain for maintaining <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> as a balanced heterozygote. Namely, by isolating wild-type segregants at each generation, we can propagate the mutation with relative ease. In addition, this strain can be used for <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_threepointmapmarkers/threepointmapmarkers.html" role="_blank">three-point mapping</ulink>.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
			<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject><phrase>two-point mapping with genetic markers Figure 2-1</phrase></textobject> &fig1legend;
			</mediaobject>
		<para>In contrast, the situation depicted in scheme #2 shows <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a b</emphasis></emphasis> on distinct chromosomes. In the first generation, we therefore already expect to see 1/16 of the progeny displaying the triple-mutant phenotype <emphasis role="bold">M A B</emphasis>. In addition, if we specifically pick <emphasis role="bold">A B</emphasis> animals from this generation, 2/3 will throw <emphasis role="bold">M A B</emphasis> progeny. If necessary, draw out all the possible genotypes and corresponding phenotypes to convince yourself that these numbers are correct. Observing these kinds of segregation patterns indicates that the mutation and the markers are on different chromosomes. Another possibility is that the mutation resides on one of the ends of the chromosome (see below). If necessary, these two possibilities can usually be resolved by scoring more animals. <emphasis>In general, basing linkage designation on a small number of data points (fewer than 20) should be avoided.</emphasis></para>
		<para>The genetic patterns described above are for the ideal situation where there is no ambiguity in the determination of chromosomal location. But what happens when the mutation lies to one side of the markers, perhaps at some distance? As shown in <xref linkend="figure2" />, if the mutation lies to one side, a cross over may occur that will lead to the creation of the two recombinant chromosomes shown. One recombinant chromosome will now contain all three mutations in cis, whereas the other is completely wild type. Also shown are the genotypes occurring when such a recombinant chromosome is paired with one of the parental chromosomes. Now we have a situation where an animal of phenotype <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">AB</emphasis> can throw <emphasis role="bold">MAB</emphasis> animals. In addition, a wild-type animal can now fail to throw both <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=AB;class=Cell" role="_blank">AB</ulink> animals. In thinking about this, keep in mind that these "rare" recombinant chromosomes will usually - by chance - wind up paired with one of the non-recombinant parental chromosomes in a fertilized zygote. Of course, the farther the mutation is from the markers, the higher the proportion of recombinant chromosomes in the pool, and the greater the possibility that any two recombinant chromosomes may end up together in a zygote.</para>
<literallayout></literallayout>
			<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="3in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject><phrase>two-point mapping with genetic markers Figure 2-2</phrase></textobject> &fig2legend;
			</mediaobject>
		<para>In these situations we must be careful not to hastily conclude that the presence of such genotypes automatically means that <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a b</emphasis></emphasis> are on separate chromosomes. The question is more one of frequency. For example, if <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a b</emphasis></emphasis> are 10.0 map units apart, this means that 10% of the gametes produced by the heterozygote will contain a chromosome that experienced a recombination event in this region. Worms are of course diploid, and progeny therefore have a chance to receive such a recombinant chromosome from either the sperm or the oocyte. Given this distance, the frequency with which progeny will inherit two non-recombinant (also called parental) chromosomes is 0.9 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00D7;</symbol> 0.9 = 0.81 or 81%. The chance of progeny receiving two recombinant chromosomes will be quite small, in this case 0.1 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00D7;</symbol> 0.1 = 1%. However, the frequency of progeny receiving one recombinant and one non-recombinant chromosome is 100 - 81 - 1 = 18%. A significant fraction!</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Calculating map distances</title>
		<para>How then do we determine if a mutation is really on the same chromosome as the markers, and if so, what is the distance? This depends in part on how we are doing the mapping. Let us consider one specific example of mapping a sterile (<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste</emphasis></emphasis>) mutation relative to an <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis> mutation. In the example given in <xref linkend="figure3"/>, the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis> mutations are 10.0 map units apart. Again, this means that 90% of the gamete chromosomes will be of the parental type and 10% will be recombinant. As just stated, the chance of a progeny receiving two non-recombinant chromosomes will be 81% (<xref linkend="figure3" />A), two recombinant chromosomes will be 1% (<xref linkend="figure3" />B), and one recombinant plus one non-recombinant chromosome will be 18% (<xref linkend="figure3" />C).</para>
			<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="5.5in" align="center"/>
				</imageobject>
				<textobject><phrase>two-point mapping with genetic markers Figure 2-3</phrase></textobject> &fig3legend;
			</mediaobject>
		<para>Of the recombinant chromosomes, one-half (5% of total chromosomes) will be <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste unc</emphasis></emphasis> and one-half (5%) will be wild type (+ +). Each recombinant chromosome has an equal chance of pairing with either of the two parental chromosomes. Therefore, for the animals that contain one recombinant and one non-recombinant chromosome, one-fourth will be <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste unc/unc</emphasis></emphasis>, one-fourth <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste unc/ste</emphasis></emphasis>, one-fourth +/<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis>, and one-fourth +/<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste</emphasis></emphasis>. These genotypes will therefore be present at a frequency of 0.25 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00D7;</symbol> 0.18 = 0.045 or 4.5% each (<xref linkend="figure3" />C).</para>
		<para>Now consider mapping in the following way. From plates where the parent is <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste/unc</emphasis></emphasis>, we clone <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> progeny. We want to determine the frequency at which such <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> animals throw <emphasis role="bold">Ste Unc</emphasis> versus <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> only progeny. We therefore look for the presence of <emphasis role="bold">Ste Unc</emphasis> animals in the next generation. We know that there will be two genotypic possibilities for animals with an <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> phenotype, <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc/unc</emphasis></emphasis>, where both chromosomes are parental, and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste unc/unc</emphasis></emphasis>, where we have one of each. The percentage of animals with the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc/unc</emphasis></emphasis> genotype is 0.81 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00D7;</symbol> 0.25 = 0.2025 (20.25%), as 81% will have only parental chromosomes and of these, one-fourth will receive two <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis> chromosomes. The percentage with a <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste unc/unc</emphasis></emphasis> genotype will be 0.18 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00D7;</symbol> 0.25 = 0.045 (4.5%), as 18% of progeny will have one recombinant and one parental chromosome and there is a 25% chance of receiving both the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste unc</emphasis></emphasis> and the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis> chromosome (0.5 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00D7;</symbol> 0.5 = 0.25). The overall percentage of animals with an <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> phenotype will therefore be 4.5 + 20.25 = 24.75%. Finally, the percentage of <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> animals with a <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste unc/unc</emphasis></emphasis> genotype will be 4.5/24.75 = 18.2%.</para>
		<para>The above determination tells us that if our mutation and marker(s) are 10.0 map units apart, we should expect to see about 18% of the cloned <emphasis role="bold">Uncs</emphasis> throwing <emphasis role="bold">Ste Unc</emphasis> progeny. Similar calculations can be carried out for various genetic distances. To facilitate these determinations, the formula (1-p)(1-p)/4 (where p is the map distance expressed as a fraction; e.g., 10 map units = 0.1) can be used to calculate the predicted fraction of <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc/unc</emphasis></emphasis> animals, whereas the fraction of <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste unc/unc</emphasis></emphasis> animals can be calculated using the formula 2p(1-p)/4. The total sum of these two products will give the fraction of all <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> animals, and the relative percentage of recombinant genotypes (<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste unc/unc</emphasis></emphasis>) can be obtained by dividing the fraction of <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste unc/unc</emphasis></emphasis> animals from the total sum. For example, if the marker and mutation are 1.0 map unit apart, we will see <emphasis role="bold">Ste Unc</emphasis> animals appearing from ~ 2% of the cloned <emphasis role="bold">Uncs</emphasis>. At 5.0 map units apart, it will be ~ 9.5%; at 25.0 map units, ~40%. The general rule is that when mapping by this strategy, the frequency of animals containing the recombinant chromosome will be about double that of the map distance between the marker and the mutation. As the distance between the mutation and marker increases, this frequency decreases.</para>
		<para>Interestingly, by the time we get to 50.0 map units, 67% or 2/3 of <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> animals will throw <emphasis role="bold">Ste Unc</emphasis> progeny. This latter number should sound familiar; it's the same percentage you would get if the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis> mutations were on separate chromosomes. <emphasis role="bold">In fact, at 50.0 map units or greater, two mutations will appear to be unlinked</emphasis>. This usually is not an issue because we tend to carry out two-point mapping with markers at the chromosome center, guaranteeing distances no greater than about 25.0 map units.</para>
		<para>There are often multiple ways to carry out two-point mapping using the same set of markers. For example, in the previously described cross we could have picked wild-type rather than <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> animals and looked for the absence of either <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">Ste</emphasis> animals in their progeny, signifying a + + or wild-type recombinant chromosome. If the marker and mutation are 10.0 map units apart, we will predict to have 0.81 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00D7;</symbol> 0.5 = 40.5% of animals with an <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc/ste genotype</emphasis></emphasis>. We will also have 0.18 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00D7;</symbol> 0.5 = 9% of animals with either an <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis>/+ or <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">ste</emphasis></emphasis>/+ genotype (4.5% each). Thus we predict that 9.0/49.5 = 18.2% of the wild-type animals we pick will fail to segregate either <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">Ste</emphasis> progeny. These numbers are identical to those previously calculated for picking <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> progeny and looking for <emphasis role="bold">Ste Unc</emphasis> in the next generation.</para>
		<para>Consider this final case however. Imagine you are trying to map an embryonic lethal mutation (<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">emb</emphasis></emphasis>) relative to a known <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis>. The easiest way to do this would be to pick wild-type animals from an <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">emb/unc</emphasis></emphasis> parent and then look for the absence of <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> animals in the progeny (embryonic lethals are usually difficult to score directly by their plate phenotype). If the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">emb</emphasis></emphasis> are on the same chromosome and close, very few phenotypically wild-type animals will fail to throw <emphasis role="bold">Unc</emphasis> (as well as <emphasis role="bold">Emb</emphasis>) progeny. To calculate the map distance, however, we must realize that using our methods, <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis>/+ animals will not be among those counted as "recombinants" (those wild-type animals that fail to throw Uncs). Thus, if the distance between the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">emb</emphasis></emphasis> is 10.0 map units, we predict to have 0.81 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00D7;</symbol> 0.5 = 40.5% animals of genotype <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">emb/unc</emphasis></emphasis>. We will also have 0.18 <symbol role="symbolfont">&#x00D7;</symbol> 0.25 = 4.5% of animals with an <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">emb</emphasis></emphasis>/+ genotype and 4.5% with an <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">unc</emphasis></emphasis>/+ genotype. Therefore, when picking among the phenotypically wild-type animals, the frequency of <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">emb</emphasis></emphasis>/+ animals will be 4.5/(40.5+4.5+4.5) = 9.1% (and not 18.2%) of the total. <emphasis role="bold">Being aware of these factors and, as always, drawing out the cross carefully will prevent interpretive errors.</emphasis> For a discussion of additional two-point mapping strategies as well as potentially useful formulas for correlating map distances with phenotypes, see <link linkend="bib3">Hodgkin (1999)</link>.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Other considerations</title>
		<para>A question of strategy: To map all chromosomes at once or to do so sequentially? This may depend on several factors such as time constraints and competitive pressures. Everything being equal, mapping sequentially is the most efficient allocation of time because once one has positively identified a chromosomal location, one need not check all the other chromosomes. In practice though, we often want to map our mutants as quickly as possible and will test multiple chromosomes at once. In addition, the presence of clear negative data can strengthen conclusions when the mutation lies at some distance from the markers. Along these lines, it is worth noting that a number of strains containing markers for multiple chromosomes have been generated for the express purpose of enhancing mapping efficiency. For example, strain MT464 contains the markers <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=unc-5" role="_blank">unc-5</ulink></emphasis></emphasis>, <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=dpy-11" role="_blank">dpy-11</ulink></emphasis></emphasis>, and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lon-2" role="_blank">lon-2</ulink></emphasis></emphasis>, thereby permitting the simultaneous mapping of chromosomes IV, V, and X, respectively.</para>
<?newpage?>
		<para>It is also worth pointing out that <emphasis>an observant experimentalist can often get a good sneak peak at what the three-point data will ultimately confirm during the two-point mapping process!</emphasis> In fact, this is another good reason to carry out two-point mapping using adjacent markers. To reiterate, we already know that if the mutation (<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis>) happens to be on the same chromosome as the markers <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">a</emphasis></emphasis> and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">b</emphasis></emphasis>, then the large majority of <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> animals coming from the heterozygous parent (<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m/a b</emphasis></emphasis>) will fail to throw <emphasis role="bold">A B</emphasis> progeny. Because of recombination, however, you may observe a small percentage of <emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis> animals throwing either <emphasis role="bold">A B</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">M B</emphasis>, or <emphasis role="bold">M A B</emphasis> animals. For example, if you happened to observe three plates (out of 25) with <emphasis role="bold">M A B</emphasis> animals and one plate with <emphasis role="bold">A B</emphasis> animals, that would suggest that <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> lies to right of <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">b</emphasis></emphasis> and is at some distance from the markers. In contrast, if you were to only observe several plates with <emphasis role="bold">A B</emphasis> animals, <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> would be likely to lie to the right of <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">b</emphasis></emphasis> but close to the markers (or perhaps between them and just to the left of <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">b</emphasis></emphasis>). If <emphasis role="bold">M A B</emphasis> animals are never observed but there are a small percentage of <emphasis role="bold">A B</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">M B</emphasis> animals, then <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">m</emphasis></emphasis> must lie between the markers. If this reasoning is not yet clear, read over the three-point mapping chapter and then come back and draw this out to confirm the predictions. This bonus gift of two-point mapping can be a real time saver.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>References</title>
		&gm2pmch2_Refs;
		<para/>
		</sect1>
</article>