<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4CR2/docbookx.dtd"
[<!ENTITY GenSupp_Refs SYSTEM 'geneduplicationsrefs.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="GeneDupl_ArticleID">
    <articleinfo>
        <!--see DocBook's authorgroup element -->
        <!--    Note PDF style sheet  changes
                <xsl:attribute-set name="normal.para.spacing">
              <xsl:attribute name="space-before.optimum">1.2em</xsl:attribute>
              <xsl:attribute name="space-before.minimum">1em</xsl:attribute>
              <xsl:attribute name="space-before.maximum">1.4em</xsl:attribute>
              <xsl:attribute name="text-indent">24pt</xsl:attribute> 
                </xsl:attribute-set> -->
        <title>Gene duplications and genetic redundancy in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis><footnote><para>Edited by Philip Anderson and Jonathan Hodgkin. Last revised June 8, 2005. Published June 25, 2005. This chapter should be cited as: Woollard, A. Gene duplications and genetic redundancy in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (June 25, 2005), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.2.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2005 Alison Woollard. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para>
</footnote></title>
        <!--		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
				<date>Last revised 4/3/05</date>
			</revision>
		</revhistory> 
-->
        <author>
            <firstname>Alison</firstname>
            <surname>Woollard<remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <ulink url="mailto:woollard@bioch.ox.ac.uk">woollard@bioch.ox.ac.uk</ulink></para></footnote></remark></surname>
            <affiliation>
                <address>Genetics Unit, Department of Biochemistry, University of Oxford, Oxford OX1 3QU, UK</address>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </articleinfo>
    <abstract>
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Evolutionary innovation requires genetic raw materials upon which selection can act.
            The duplication of genes is of fundamental importance in providing such raw materials.
            Gene duplications are very widespread in</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">and appear to arise more frequently
            than in either</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Drosophila</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">or yeast. It has been proposed that the rate of duplication of
            a gene is of the same order of magnitude as the rate of mutation per nucleotide site,
            emphasising the enormous potential that gene duplication has for generating substrates
            for evolutionary change.</emphasis></para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">The fate of duplicated genes is discussed. Complete functional redundancy seems
            unstable in the long term. Most models require that equality amongst duplicated genes
            must be disrupted if they are to be preserved. There are various ways of achieving
            inequality, involving either the nonfunctionalization of one copy, or one copy acquiring
            some novel, beneficial function, or both copies becoming partially compromised so that
            both copies are required to provide the overall function that was previously provided by
            the single ancestral gene. Examples of</emphasis> <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">C. elegans</emphasis></emphasis> <emphasis role="bold">gene duplications that appear to have
            followed each of these pathways are considered.</emphasis></para>
    </abstract>
    <sect1><title>Gene duplications and genetic redundancy</title>
    <para>The duplication of genes is of paramount importance in providing raw materials for the
    evolution of genetic diversity. It is therefore of interest to consider <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> gene
    duplications in the context of other sequenced genomes. Two recent estimates of the overall
    extent of gene duplications in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> have come up with very similar figures. There are
    thought to be around 1,200 gene families containing two or more paralogues in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>
    (<link linkend="bib3">Cavalcanti et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12569420 -->; <link linkend="bib8">Gu et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 11861885 -->). The total number of
    genes in the paranome is around 6,000, or <symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x223C;</symbol> 32<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>  of the genome, where the paranome is defined as
    the set of proteins that have one or more paralogues, that is, those that are not singletons. In
    addition, 7.1<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>  of the duplicated genes in the worm are thought to have resulted from block
    duplications (duplication events involving more than one gene; <link linkend="bib3">Cavalcanti et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 12569420 -->). Simple sequence duplications range in size from hundreds of bases to tens of
    kilobases and copies may be dispersed or clustered (<link linkend="bib23">The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Sequencing Consortium, 1998</link><!--  PMID 9851916  -->). Local clusters of duplicated genes are easily identified and there are 402 such
    clusters (where a cluster is defined as a group of N genes that are similar within a window of
    2N genes along the chromosome and where N <symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x003D;</symbol>
 3 or more) distributed throughout the genome (<link linkend="bib23">The <emphasis>C.
    elegans</emphasis> Sequencing Consortium, 1998</link><!--  PMID 9851916  -->). The worm genome contains twice the number of
    local gene duplications as <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib21">Rubin et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10731134 -->), and also differs from
    the fly genome in terms of the distribution of gene duplicates. Gene duplications are found
    randomly throughout the fly genome, whereas in the worm duplicated genes are mostly
    clustered in the recombinogenic segments of the autosomal arms (<link linkend="bib21">Rubin et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10731134 -->).</para> <para>The rate of origin of gene duplicates in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> over the past few hundred
    thousand years appears to be substantially higher than that for <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> or yeast (<link linkend="bib16">Lynch and
    Conery, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11073452 -->). <link linkend="bib16">Lynch and Conery (2000</link>) propose a per-gene rate of duplication of 0.02
    per million years for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, compared with a rate of 0.002 duplications per gene per
    million years in <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> and 0.008 in yeast. <link linkend="bib8">Gu et al. (2002)</link> have reported exactly the same figure for <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, compared with a rate of only 0.0014 for
    <emphasis>Drosophila</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib9">Gu, 2003</link><!-- PMID 12850437 -->).</para> <para>Given the range of values predicted for different species,
    it has been proposed that 50<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>  of genes in a genome would be expected to duplicate, on average,
    at least once on time scales of 35 to 350 million years (<link linkend="bib16">Lynch and Conery, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11073452 -->).
    Thus, even in the absence of direct amplification of the entire genome (polyploidization), gene
    duplication has substantial potential for generating substrates for evolutionary innovation.
    Indeed, it has been proposed that the rate of duplication of a gene is of the same order of
    magnitude as the rate of mutation per nucleotide site (<link linkend="bib16">Lynch and Conery, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11073452 -->).</para>
   <para> What is the mechanism of gene duplication? Replication slippage and unequal exchange are often
    invoked as an explanation for closely spaced gene duplicates, but these mechanisms would be
    expected to give rise to tandem duplicates pointing in the same direction. A recent study found,
    however, that up to 69<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>  of <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> duplicate genes reside in the inverse orientation,
    especially young duplicates (<link linkend="bib11">Katju and Lynch, 2003</link><!-- PMID 14704166 -->). Inversions are considered by
    these authors to be part and parcel of the original duplication event, rather than secondary
    rearrangements (<link linkend="bib11">Katju and Lynch, 2003</link><!-- PMID 14704166 -->). It has been hypothesized that inverted
    duplications could be generated by an illegitimate recombination event during DNA replication,
    involving strand switching by the DNA polymerase or strand misalignment-realignment.
    RNA-mediated transposition is thought unlikely to have played a significant role in gene
    duplication within the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome because of the very small proportion of duplicate genes
    that lack introns relative to the original copy (<link linkend="bib11">Katju and Lynch, 2003</link><!-- PMID 14704166 -->). The
    mechanisms responsible for gene duplication are therefore, in general, unlikely to respect gene
    boundaries. This is borne out by the Katju and Lynch study, which analysed 290 gene pairs with <symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x2264;</symbol>

    10<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>  divergence at synonymous sites (Ks) within the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome. They found that the
    average duplication span of 1.4 kb is less than the average gene length in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (2.5 kb),
    suggesting that partial gene duplications are frequent (<link linkend="bib11">Katju and Lynch, 2003</link><!-- PMID 14704166 -->).</para>
    <para>Around half of the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> gene duplicates with very low levels of synonymous site
    substitution were found to also contain unique coding sequence not present in the other copy, in
    addition to the region of close homology (<link linkend="bib11">Katju and Lynch, 2003</link><!-- PMID 14704166 -->). Thus,
    structural heterogeneity between duplicate genes is common. Chimeric duplicates may well have
    creative potential, especially when they act in conjunction with shuffling events.</para> <para>What fate
    awaits duplicate genes? Three alternative theories have been proposed (<link linkend="bib15">Lynch, 2002</link><!-- PMID 12169715 -->; <link linkend="bib16">Lynch and Conery, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11073452 -->). The first is the nonfunctionalization of one
    copy by the accumulation of degenerative mutations. The second is neofunctionalization. In this
    scenario, one copy acquires a novel, beneficial function and becomes preserved by natural
    selection, with the other copy retaining the original function. A variation of this scenario is
    that the two genes could acquire divergent functions but maintain a functional overlap.
    Selection would then act on these divergent properties and indirectly maintain the functional
    overlap. Selection could also act on a newly emergent property unique to the combined action of
    two closely related genes, or on some enhanced efficiency or fidelity achieved by the combined
    action of two such genes (<link linkend="bib24">Thomas, 1993</link><!-- PMID 8310537 -->). In the third scenario,
    subfunctionalization, both copies become partially compromised by the accumulation of mutations,
    to a point where their total capacity is reduced to the level of the single-copy ancestral gene.</para>
    <para>Whatever the mechanism, most models for conserving redundancy over the course of evolution
    require some degree of symmetry-breaking: equality amongst duplicated genes must be disrupted if
    they are to be preserved. The fate awaiting most gene duplicates in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, as well as in
    most other species studied, is likely to be silencing and ultimate loss, rather than
    preservation (<link linkend="bib16">Lynch and Conery, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11073452 -->). It has been estimated that the average
    half-life of a gene duplicate is around 4 million years (<link linkend="bib16">Lynch and Conery, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11073452 -->).
    The propensity of recently duplicated genes to become nonfunctional pseudogenes is borne out in
    a recent study by <link linkend="bib17">Mounsey et al. (2002)</link><!-- PMID 11997343 -->, who found a lower than expected success rate in generating
    expression patterns for recently duplicated genes, suggesting that recently duplicated genes are
    less likely to be expressed. Given our current state of
    knowledge of gene function in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, it is impossible to estimate the actual proportion of
    duplicated genes in the genome that are redundant. This will become clearer as sensitized
    screens and combinatorial RNAi approaches seek to address the general problem of assigning gene
    function.</para><para>One recent study examined the relationship between the prevalence of gene duplications
    and ontogeny in <emphasis>Caenorhabditis</emphasis> species (<link linkend="bib2">Castillo-Davis and Hartl, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11961106 -->). It was
    found that genes expressed after embryogenesis had a significantly greater number of duplicates
    than those expressed early in development. This was found to be true in both the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> genomes. For example, 18.36<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>  of early-expressed genes (n<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x003D;</symbol>1,280) were found to have
    detectable paralogs in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome versus 35.31<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>  of late-expressed genes (n<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x003D;</symbol>1,014).
    For <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>, the figures are even more striking, 6.7<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>  (n<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x003D;</symbol>165) and 38.8<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>  (n<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x003D;</symbol>237),
    respectively (<link linkend="bib2">Castillo-Davis and Hartl, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11961106 -->). Therefore, duplicated copies of
    early-expressed genes appear to be selectively lost. Based on earlier calculations of the rate
    of origin of gene duplicates in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib16">Lynch and Conery, 2000</link><!-- PMID 11073452 -->) and the
    divergence between <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis>, Castillo-Davis and Hartl estimated that more than
    40<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>  of all genes are expected to have duplicated at least once in both the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>C.
    briggsae</emphasis> lineages since their divergence (<link linkend="bib2">Castillo-Davis and Hartl, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11961106 -->). The
    proportion of duplicated genes in the late-expressed class thus falls close to this estimate,
    whereas the proportion of duplicated genes in the early-expressed class is much lower than
    expected. It is suggested that the selective loss of duplicates of early-expressed genes
    reflects developmental constraint (<link linkend="bib2">Castillo-Davis and Hartl, 2002</link><!-- PMID 11961106 -->). A related
    study found that gene duplications were more prevalent amongst the set of conserved,
    slowly-evolving genes versus the set of non-conserved genes in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>S. cerevisiae</emphasis>
    genomes, suggesting that slowly evolving genes may be the main source of new genes in eukaryotic
    genomes (<link linkend="bib4">Davis and Petrov, 2004</link><!-- PMID 15024414 -->).</para><para>11 of 33 of the largest clusters of duplicated
    genes in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> consist of olfactory receptors (<link linkend="bib21">Rubin et al., 2000</link><!-- PMID 10731134 -->).
    Olfactory receptors are seven-transmembrane G-protein coupled receptors (GPCRs), each of which
    specifically recognises a set of odorant and tastant chemicals, allowing the worm to sense and
    respond to its chemical environment. GPCRs comprise by far the largest multigene family in <emphasis>C.
    elegans</emphasis>, with over 1000 members, making up <symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x223C;</symbol> 5<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>  of the genome (<link linkend="bib1">Bargmann, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9851919 -->),
    although around a third of this group of genes are thought to be pseudogenes (<link linkend="bib1">Bargmann, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9851919 -->). Thus many duplications in this large multigene family are fated to become
    nonfunctional. Several recent studies have charted the molecular evolution of some of these
    genes and found that processes of duplication, diversification and movement that have led to
    these large gene families are very much ongoing. For example, the 3126 bp inverse orientation
    duplication that duplicates the 5’ half of gene <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=T08H10.2" role="_blank">T08H10.2</ulink> to give rise to pseudogene T08H10.a is
    thought to have occurred very recently as the duplicated sequences are identical (<link linkend="bib19">Robertson, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9582190 -->). It has been suggested that strong selective pressures are at work for the
    continued functionality of these genes because the occurrence of synonymous changes in
    duplicated GPCR genes is 11-fold higher than the occurrence of amino acid substitutions or
    nonsynonymous changes (<link linkend="bib19">Robertson, 1998</link><!-- PMID 9582190 -->; <link linkend="bib20">Robertson, 2000</link><!-- PMID 10673277 -->). Indeed,
    it has been proposed that natural selection might somehow favour duplications of genes that are
    generally involved in responses to environmental stress and pathogens, in organisms facing a
    challenging and dynamic molecular environment (<link linkend="bib14">Lespinet et al., 2002</link><!-- PMID 12097341 -->). The massive
    lineage specific expansion of worm odorant/chemosensory receptors could be just one example of
    this.</para><para>Other large gene families in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> include C-type lectins, hormone receptors,
    collagens and serine/threonine/tyrosine protein kinases. A full description of major
    protein-coding gene families, including a discussion of family size distribution, can be found
    in <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_genomclassprot/genomclassprot.html" role="_blank">Genomic classification of protein-coding gene families</ulink>. An example of a <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> transcription factor gene family in which
    duplications abound is the T-box family. There are 21 T-box genes in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome
    (WormBase release WS132, 2004), most of which lack clear orthologs in other species. There are 4
    pairs of genes that are likely to have arisen from relatively recent duplication events and a
    functional analysis of 2 of these pairs has been reported. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tbx-37" role="_blank">tbx-37</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tbx-38" role="_blank">tbx-38</ulink></emphasis> (83<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>  amino acid
    identity) have redundant functions in mesoderm induction in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> embryos (<link linkend="bib7">Good et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15056620 -->), whereas <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tbx-8" role="_blank">tbx-8</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tbx-9" role="_blank">tbx-9</ulink></emphasis> (59<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>  amino acid identity), have overlapping, but
    probably not completely redundant, functions in embryonic morphogenesis (<link linkend="bib18">Pocock et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15102704 -->). The most recent duplication in the T-box gene family would appear to be the one
    that gave rise to the genes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y59E9AR.3" role="_blank">Y59E9AR.3</ulink> (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tbx-30" role="_blank">tbx-30</ulink></emphasis>) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=Y59E9AR.5" role="_blank">Y59E9AR.5</ulink> (<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tbx-30" role="_blank">tbx-30.1</ulink></emphasis>). These two sequences are
    100<symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x0025;</symbol>  identical and situated in inverse orientations, <symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x223C;</symbol> 2 kb apart. Biological function has been
    ascribed to <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tbx-30" role="_blank">tbx-30</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib18">Pocock et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15102704 -->), but it is unclear at present whether or
    not <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=tbx-30" role="_blank">tbx-30.1</ulink></emphasis> is expressed.</para>
<para>There are several other good examples of duplicated gene pairs that
    have undergone neofunctionalization. A recent one is the <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fbf-1" role="_blank">fbf-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fbf-2" role="_blank">fbf-2</ulink></emphasis> gene pair involved in germ
    line development in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fbf-1" role="_blank">fbf-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=fbf-2" role="_blank">fbf-2</ulink></emphasis> encode closely related RNA binding proteins that
    reciprocally regulate the expression of one another in order to modulate the size of the germ
    line mitotic region (<link linkend="bib13">Lamont et al., 2004</link><!-- PMID 15525531 -->). Thus, there appears to be a benefit
    unique to the combined action of these two closely related genes; the duplication event in this
    case has provided an opportunity for fine-tuning of a developmental process.</para> <para>A good potential
    example of the subfunctionalization of a duplicated gene pair in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> is the case of the
    Notch-like receptors <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis>. In <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis>, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> posess both overlapping
    and separate biological functions. When both gene functions are removed, larval lethality
    results (the Lag – Lin And Glp phenotype; <link linkend="bib12">Lambie and Kimble, 1991</link><!-- PMID 1769331 -->). However, in
    <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. remanei</emphasis>, the Lag phenotype is seen when only <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> expression is silenced
    (<link linkend="bib22">Rudel and Kimble, 2002</link><!-- PMID 12356262 -->). It is suggested that ancestral functions may have been
    divided between <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=glp-1" role="_blank">glp-1</ulink></emphasis> in <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> after duplication in such a way that their total
    capacity became reduced to the level of the single-copy ancestral gene. In <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. remanei</emphasis>, on the other hand, <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=lin-12" role="_blank">lin-12</ulink></emphasis> appears to have retained this ancestral function following
    duplication (<link linkend="bib22">Rudel and Kimble, 2002</link><!-- PMID 12356262 -->).</para> <para>An interesting example of the apparent
    gradual evolutionary demise of a duplicated gene is presented in the case of <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elt-4" role="_blank">elt-4</ulink></emphasis>. <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elt-4" role="_blank">elt-4</ulink></emphasis>
    encodes a truncated GATA type zinc finger transcription factor of just 8.1kDa (72 amino acids),
    and is situated <symbol role= "symbolfont">&#x223C;</symbol> 5 kb upstream of the highly conserved <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elt-2" role="_blank">elt-2</ulink></emphasis>, proposed to be the original copy
    of the duplicate pair (<link linkend="bib5">Fukushige et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14573471 -->). The bigger <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elt-2" role="_blank">elt-2</ulink></emphasis> gene is
    expressed in intestinal cells and is required for intestinal development (<link linkend="bib6">Fukushige et al., 1998</link><!-- PMID 9659934 -->). While it is clear that <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elt-4" role="_blank">elt-4</ulink></emphasis> is expressed in the intestine, no effect was
    found of deleting <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elt-4" role="_blank">elt-4</ulink></emphasis>, in the gut or elsewhere, either alone or in combination with <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elt-2" role="_blank">elt-2</ulink></emphasis>.
    Furthermore, experiments in yeast and <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> could not demonstrate any role for ELT-4 in
    activating or repressing transcription, or indeed any specific DNA binding activity (<link linkend="bib5">Fukushige et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14573471 -->). The <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elt-2" role="_blank">elt-2</ulink></emphasis>/<emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elt-4" role="_blank">elt-4</ulink></emphasis> duplication event is thought to have occurred only
    in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> lineage, after the point at which <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> and <emphasis>C. briggsae</emphasis> diverged. Thus,
    the proposal is that although <emphasis><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/gene/gene?name=elt-4" role="_blank">elt-4</ulink></emphasis> may have conferred some selective advantage to <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> in
    the past (hence the high level of conservation of the zinc finger domain), its ultimate
    evolutionary fate will be disappearance from the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome (<link linkend="bib5">Fukushige et al., 2003</link><!-- PMID 14573471 -->).</para>
    
    <para>Genome sequence analysis is thus providing the community with far more than simply the informational content of genomes. Gene duplications are widespread in the <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> genome and provide raw material for evolutionary novelty. The data are a snapshot of evolutionary time, from which we can glimpse into the past as well as, perhaps, seek to prophesy the future.
    </para></sect1>
    
    <sect1><title>Acknowledgements</title><para>I would like to thank members of my laboratory and Andreas Russ for useful
    discussions and the reviewers for helpful comments.</para></sect1> 
    <sect1>
        <title>References</title><para/>
	&GenSupp_Refs;
	</sect1>
</article>