<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4CR2//EN" "docbookx.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY fig1 SYSTEM 'meiosis_fig1.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig2 SYSTEM 'meiosis_fig2.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig3 SYSTEM 'meiosis_fig3.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig4 SYSTEM 'meiosis_fig4.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig5 SYSTEM 'meiosis_fig5.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig6 SYSTEM 'meiosis_fig6.jpg' NDATA JPG>
<!ENTITY fig1legend SYSTEM 'meiosis_fig1leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig2legend SYSTEM 'meiosis_fig2leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig3legend SYSTEM 'meiosis_fig3leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig4legend SYSTEM 'meiosis_fig4leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig5legend SYSTEM 'meiosis_fig5leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY fig6legend SYSTEM 'meiosis_fig6leg.xml'>
<!ENTITY meiosis_ref SYSTEM 'meiosis_ref.xml'>
<!ENTITY pubmed_url 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;list_uids='>
<!ENTITY crossref_url 'http://dx.doi.org/'>
]>
<article id="meiosis">
<articleinfo>
<title>Meiosis<footnote><para>Edited by Anne Villeneuve and David Greenstein Last revised May 26, 2015. Published May 4, 2017. This chapter should be cited as: Hillers K.J., Jantsch V., Martinez-Perez E., Yanowitz J.L. Meiosis. (May 4, 2017), <emphasis>WormBook</emphasis>, ed. The <emphasis>C. elegans</emphasis> Research Community, WormBook, doi/10.1895/wormbook.1.178.1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org">http://www.wormbook.org</ulink>.</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Copyright:</emphasis> &#x000A9; 2016 Kenneth J Hillers, Verena Jantsch, Enrique Martinez-Perez, Judith L Yanowitz. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</para></footnote></title>
<author><othername>Kenneth J Hillers<superscript>1<emphasis role="italic">&sect;</emphasis></superscript>, Verena Jantsch<superscript>2<emphasis role="italic">&sect;</emphasis></superscript>, Enrique Martinez-Perez<superscript>3<emphasis role="italic">&sect;</emphasis></superscript>, Judith L Yanowitz<superscript>4<emphasis role="italic">&sect;</emphasis></superscript><remark><footnote><para>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Email: <ulink url="mailto:khillers@calpoly.edu">khillers@calpoly.edu</ulink>; <ulink url="mailto:verena.jantsch@univie.ac.at">verena.jantsch@univie.ac.at</ulink>; <ulink url="mailto:enrique.martinez-perez@imperial.ac.uk">enrique.martinez-perez@imperial.ac.uk</ulink>; <ulink url="mailto:yanowitzjl@mwri.magee.edu">yanowitzjl@mwri.magee.edu</ulink></para></footnote></remark></othername>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>1</superscript>Biological Sciences Department, California Polytechnic State University, San Luis Obispo, CA 93407, United States</orgname></affiliation>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>2</superscript>Department of Chromosome Biology, Max F. Perutz Laboratories, University of Vienna, Vienna Biocenter,1030 Vienna, Austria.</orgname></affiliation>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>3</superscript>MRC Clinical Sciences Centre, Imperial College, London W12 0NN, United Kingdom</orgname></affiliation>
<affiliation><orgname><superscript>4</superscript>Magee-Womens Research Institute, Department of Obstetrics, Gynecology, and Reproductive Sciences, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh, PA 15213, United States</orgname></affiliation>
</author></articleinfo>
<abstract>
<title><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Sexual reproduction requires the production of haploid gametes (sperm and egg) with only one copy of each chromosome; fertilization then restores the diploid chromosome content in the next generation. This reduction in genetic content is accomplished during a specialized cell division called meiosis, in which two rounds of chromosome segregation follow a single round of DNA replication. In preparation for the first meiotic division, homologous chromosomes pair and synapse, creating a context that promotes formation of crossover recombination events. These crossovers, in conjunction with sister chromatid cohesion, serve to connect the two homologs and facilitate their segregation to opposite poles during the first meiotic division. During the second meiotic division, which is similar to mitosis, sister chromatids separate; the resultant products are haploid cells that become gametes.</emphasis></para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">In <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> (and most other eukaryotes) homologous pairing and recombination are required for proper chromosome inheritance during meiosis; accordingly, the events of meiosis are tightly coordinated to ensure the proper execution of these events. In this chapter, we review the seminal events of meiosis: pairing of homologous chromosomes, the changes in chromosome structure that chromosomes undergo during meiosis, the events of meiotic recombination, the differentiation of homologous chromosome pairs into structures optimized for proper chromosome segregation at Meiosis I, and the ultimate segregation of chromosomes during the meiotic divisions. We also review the regulatory processes that ensure the coordinated execution of these meiotic events during prophase I.</emphasis></para>
</abstract>
<sect1 id="sec1">
<title>Abbreviations</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">CO</emphasis>&ndash;crossover, <emphasis role="bold">DSB</emphasis>&ndash;double strand break, <emphasis role="bold">HR</emphasis>&ndash;homologous recombination, <emphasis role="bold">HRR</emphasis>&ndash;homology recognition region, <emphasis role="bold">IR</emphasis>&ndash;ionizing radiation, <emphasis role="bold">NCO</emphasis>&ndash;non-crossover, <emphasis role="bold">NHEJ</emphasis>&ndash;non-homologous end joining, <emphasis role="bold">PC</emphasis>&ndash;pairing center, <emphasis role="bold">SC</emphasis>&ndash;synaptonemal complex</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec2">
<title>Overview</title>
<para>Sexual reproduction requires the generation of haploid gametes from diploid precursors through the specialized cell division program of meiosis. This reduction in ploidy is essential to ensure the restoration of diploidy upon fertilization and requires completion of several key events (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>). During early prophase (leptotene and zygotene stages), each chromosome must locate and recognize its appropriate homologous pairing partner and align with it. During the zygotene stage, a specialized protein structure called the synaptonemal complex (SC) assembles between the aligned chromosomes to hold homologs together; full synapsis of homologs defines the pachytene stage. Crossover (CO) recombination events must be completed between the DNA molecules of the aligned and synapsed homologs, a process started by the deliberate formation of DNA double strand breaks (DSBs). Crossing over is essential for the formation of chiasmata, connections between homologs that become evident upon structural remodeling of chromosomes during later stages of meiotic prophase (diplotene and diakinesis). Therefore, there are multiple surveillance mechanisms that act to ensure that each homolog pair undergoes an exchange. Late prophase remodeling of chromosome pairs connected by chiasmata results in bivalents wherein the connected homologs are oriented away from each other; this promotes bipolar attachment of homologs to the meiosis I spindle, leading to segregation of homologous chromosomes at anaphase I. The separation of sister chromatids on the meiosis II spindle completes the meiotic program.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure1" xreflabel="Figure 1">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig1" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Figure 1</phrase>
</textobject> &fig1legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Despite the fundamental importance of meiosis in sexual reproduction, many basic questions about the process and the underlying mechanisms remain unanswered. Over the past twenty years, <emphasis role="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</emphasis> has emerged as a major model organism for investigating meiotic mechanisms. Several features of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> biology have contributed to this emergence. The worm germ line is especially amenable to high-resolution cytological analysis of chromosome and nuclear organization in the context of whole mount preparations that preserve 3D nuclear architecture. Importantly, each germ line contains a complete time course of meiosis, with nuclei organized in a temporal/spatial gradient corresponding to the stages of meiotic prophase (<link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link> and <link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). Further, the chromosomal basis of sex determination can be exploited to identify meiotic mutants on the basis of sex chromosome missegregation. The availability of worms expressing GFP::histone has also made it possible to screen for mutants based on lack of chiasmata connecting homologs at the end of meiotic prophase. Mutant hermaphrodites can still produce a few percent euploid survivors even if all six chromosome pairs lack chiasmata, a feature that has greatly facilitated analysis of meiotic mutants. Germline mRNA expression profiles have accelerated identification of molecular defects associated with meiotic mutants and have provided a basis for identification of candidate genes tested for meiotic roles in targeted RNAi screens. Finally, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has a robust tradition of investigating the genetic behavior of chromosome rearrangements, which has led to the discovery of <emphasis role="italic">cis</emphasis>-acting chromosome features that govern meiotic chromosome behavior.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure2" xreflabel="Figure 2">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig2" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Figure 2</phrase>
</textobject> &fig2legend;</mediaobject>
<para>This chapter begins with a &ldquo;parts list&rdquo; of meiotic machinery components identified in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, followed by a description of the events of meiosis that integrates information about the roles of these components. We will focus on oocyte meiosis, as later stages of prophase in oocytes are cytologically more accessible than during spermatocyte meiosis. We will discuss the interrelated processes of chromosome movement and pairing (<link linkend="sec3">Section 3</link>), and the protein complexes that drive the dramatic changes seen in chromosome structure during meiosis (<link linkend="sec4">Section 4</link>; also see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlinechromatin/germlinechromatin.html">Germline chromatin</ulink>). We will then discuss the process of meiotic recombination (<link linkend="sec5">Section 5</link>). Following chiasma formation, late pachytene bivalents differentiate around the site of the chiasma in preparation for subsequent segregation (<link linkend="sec6">Section 6</link>). We round off the chapter with an overview of surveillance mechanisms that monitor meiotic events for proper completion (<link linkend="sec7">Section 7</link>) and a description of the events that occur during meiotic chromosome segregation (<link linkend="sec8">Section 8</link>).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec3">
<title>Chromosome pairing in prophase of meiosis I</title>
<para>Pairing of homologous chromosomes, which occurs during the leptotene and zygotene stages of prophase I (transition zone of the germ line, <link linkend="figure1">Figure 1</link>), is a crucial event in meiosis. During this highly dynamic process, the two homologous copies of each chromosome find each other within the nucleus through an active search process that enables chromosomes to distinguish &ldquo;self versus non-self&rdquo; and assume a side-by-side alignment. This pairing is a necessary prerequisite for CO formation, and thus successful completion of meiosis. In many organisms pairing is mediated by tethering chromosome ends to the nuclear periphery where they become attached to cytoplasmic motor proteins via SUN/KASH domain protein complexes that span the nuclear envelope. The motor proteins then drive chromosome movement that is essential for the timely completion of pairing. In <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> <emphasis role="italic">cis</emphasis>-acting sequences near one end of each chromosome, rather than the telomere itself, assemble a nucleoprotein complex that tethers the chromosome ends to the nuclear envelope. These events occur in the transition zone and coincide with chromatin adopting a special configuration, with chromosomes pushed to one side of the nucleus opposite the nucleolus, giving the chromatin a half-moon shape (<link linkend="figure2">Figure 2</link>). Pairing is complete by exit from the transition zone (<link linkend="bib89">MacQueen and Villeneuve, 2001</link>)<!--:PMID 11445542-->. Mutations that disrupt chromosome movements also result in loss of this nuclear reorganization during leptotene/zygotene (<link linkend="bib89">MacQueen and Villeneuve, 2001</link><!--:PMID 11445542-->; <link linkend="bib32">Couteau et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15062099-->; <link linkend="bib33">Couteau and Zetka, 2005</link><!--:PMID 16291647-->; <link linkend="bib94">Martinez-Perez and Villeneuve, 2005</link><!--:PMID 16291646-->; <link linkend="bib116">Penkner et al., 2007b</link>)<!--:PMID 17543861-->. The process of pairing is normally coupled with SC assembly between homologs (<link linkend="sec4">Section 4</link>). However, the chromosome alignment process is genetically separable from synapsis, although both take place along the entire length of the chromosome (<link linkend="bib114">Pasierbek et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11390355-->; <link linkend="bib87">MacQueen et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12231631-->; <link linkend="bib106">Nabeshima et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 21876678-->.</para>
<sect2 id="sec3.1">
<title><emphasis role="italic">Cis-</emphasis>acting sequences promote pairing</title>
<para>Each <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> chromosome has a localized <emphasis role="italic">cis</emphasis>-acting region near one end that plays crucial roles in meiotic chromosome behavior. These regions have been termed HRRs (homology recognition regions) or PCs (pairing centers) (<link linkend="bib134">Rosenbluth and Baillie, 1981</link><!--:PMID 6953041-->; <link linkend="bib133">Rose et al., 1984</link><!--:PMID 6593563-->; <link linkend="bib95">McKim et al., 1988</link><!--:PMID 3224815-->; <link linkend="bib59">Herman and Kari, 1989</link><!--:PMID 2721932-->; <link linkend="bib169">Villeneuve, 1994</link>)<!--:PMID 8005443-->. These HRRs/PCs (hereafter, PCs) are each comprised of repetitive DNA sequences (<link linkend="bib178">Sanford and Perry, 2001</link><!--:PMID 11452017-->; <link linkend="bib121">Phillips et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19620970-->. The PC ends of chromosomes are in close proximity to the nuclear envelope in the transition zone, when the chromosome pairing process is initiated (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>) (<link linkend="bib49">Goldstein, 1982</link><!--:PMID 7172867-->; <link linkend="bib88">MacQueen et al., 2005</link>)<!--:PMID 16360034-->. Chromosomes lacking PCs display severe defects in pairing and synapsis (<link linkend="bib88">MacQueen et al., 2005</link>)<!--:PMID 16360034-->.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure3" xreflabel="Figure 3">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig3" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Figure 3</phrase>
</textobject> &fig3legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3.2">
<title>PCs assemble as nucleoprotein complexes at the nuclear periphery</title>
<para>In <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> meiosis, each PC is bound by one of four C2H2 zinc finger proteins (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36715;class=Protein" role="_blank"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HIM-8;class=Strain" role="_blank">HIM-8</ulink></ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42593;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZIM-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29521;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZIM-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45931;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZIM-3</ulink>) (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). The genes encoding the HIM/ZIM proteins are found within a single operon, ensuring their coordinated germline expression (<link linkend="bib122">Phillips et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16360035-->; <link linkend="bib120">Phillips and Dernburg, 2006</link>)<!--:PMID 17141157-->. PC repeats are sufficient to recruit ZIM proteins as shown by the injection of plasmids carrying synthetic repeats of the PC motifs (<link linkend="bib178">Sanford and Perry, 2001</link><!--:PMID 11452017-->; <link linkend="bib121">Phillips et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19620970-->. Furthermore, PC proteins are required both for aligning homologs and for homologous synapsis of the specific chromosomes to which they are bound (<link linkend="bib122">Phillips et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16360035-->; <link linkend="bib120">Phillips and Dernburg, 2006</link><!--:PMID 17141157-->; <link linkend="bib121">Phillips et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19620970-->; <link linkend="bib55">Harper et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22018922-->; <link linkend="bib77">Labella et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 22018921-->. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36715;class=Protein" role="_blank"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HIM-8;class=Strain" role="_blank">HIM-8</ulink></ulink> appears to have an additional role(s) as it is required for elongation of the X chromosomes in transition zone nuclei, where all chromosomes start to occupy extended territories, a process that may facilitate their lengthwise alignment (<link linkend="bib106">Nabeshima et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 21876678-->.</para>
<para>Although functionally similar, the X and autosome PCs differ with respect to the persistence and regulation of nuclear envelope attachment and association of their PC-binding proteins. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36715;class=Protein" role="_blank"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HIM-8;class=Strain" role="_blank">HIM-8</ulink></ulink> localizes to X chromosome PCs from premeiotic stages through late pachytene (<link linkend="bib122">Phillips et al., 2005</link>)<!--:PMID 16360035-->. Autosomal PC proteins, by contrast, are detected at PCs primarily from leptotene to early pachytene (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42593;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZIM-1</ulink> on chromosomes II and III, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29521;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZIM-2</ulink> on chromosome V and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45931;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZIM-3</ulink> on chromosomes I and IV). In contrast to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36715;class=Protein" role="_blank"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HIM-8;class=Strain" role="_blank">HIM-8</ulink></ulink>, concentration of the autosomal PC proteins at PCs depends on the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27297;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHK-2</ulink> protein kinase (<link linkend="bib122">Phillips et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16360035-->; <link linkend="bib120">Phillips and Dernburg, 2006</link>)<!--:PMID 17141157-->, a master regulator of early events of prophase (<link linkend="bib89">MacQueen and Villeneuve, 2001</link>)<!--:PMID 11445542-->.</para>
<para>The PC nucleoprotein complexes act as recruitment sites for polo kinase, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink> (or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink>, if <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink> is absent). <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink> induces structural reorganization of the nuclear envelope (<link linkend="bib55">Harper et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22018922-->; <link linkend="bib77">Labella et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 22018921-->: the inner and outer nuclear envelope proteins <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32088;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink> relocate into pronounced aggregates corresponding to the sites where PCs localize to the nuclear envelope (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>) (<link linkend="bib117">Penkner et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913286-->; <link linkend="bib141">Sato et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19913287-->. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32088;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink> form a functional SUN/KASH protein&ndash;protein interaction module, broadly conserved among eukaryotes (<link linkend="bib91">Malone et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14697201-->; <link linkend="bib44">Fridkin et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15100407-->; <link linkend="bib116">Penkner et al., 2007b</link><!--:PMID 17543861-->; <link linkend="bib102">Minn et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19759181-->, that spans the nuclear membranes and connects chromosomes to the cytoskeleton.</para>
<para>If the SUN/KASH interaction is abrogated, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32088;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink> retention at the outer nuclear envelope is lost (<link linkend="bib91">Malone et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14697201-->; <link linkend="bib116">Penkner et al., 2007b</link>)<!--:PMID 17543861--> despite the assembly of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> aggregates with PCs at the inner nuclear envelope (<link linkend="bib117">Penkner et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19913286-->. Therefore, the trigger for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> aggregation is transmitted from the nucleus to the cytoplasm where <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32088;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink> mirrors <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> aggregates. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> aggregate formation is independent of DSBs, recombination, pairing, and synapsis, but requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27297;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHK-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib117">Penkner et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913286-->; <link linkend="bib141">Sato et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19913287-->. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32088;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink> aggregates at autosomal PC attachment sites are found in leptotene/zygotene (TZ). In contrast the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32088;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink> aggregates around the X chromosome PC persist throughout early pachytene. In mid- and late pachytene, most nuclei lack <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32088;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink> aggregates, despite the presence of a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36715;class=Protein" role="_blank"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HIM-8;class=Strain" role="_blank">HIM-8</ulink></ulink> focus at the nuclear envelope (<link linkend="bib122">Phillips et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16360035-->; <link linkend="bib117">Penkner et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913286-->; <link linkend="bib141">Sato et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19913287-->. Disappearance of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32088;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink> aggregates correlates with the establishment of full synapsis and relocalization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink> from PCs to the SC (<link linkend="bib55">Harper et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22018922-->; <link linkend="bib77">Labella et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 22018921-->. The recruitment of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink> to PCs and the subsequent formation of dynamic <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32088;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink> aggregates is essential to ensure faithful SC assembly, as mutants defective in <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006311;class=Gene" role="_blank">sun-1</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006997;class=Gene" role="_blank">zyg-12</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004043;class=Gene" role="_blank">plk-2</ulink>,</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001867;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-8</ulink>/zim&Delta;</emphasis> (lacking all PC-binding proteins) display aberrant synapsis (<link linkend="bib116">Penkner et al., 2007b</link><!--:PMID 17543861-->; <link linkend="bib141">Sato et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913287-->; <link linkend="bib55">Harper et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22018922-->; <link linkend="bib77">Labella et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22018921-->; <link linkend="bib176">Woglar et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23505384-->.</para>
<para>PCs play a prominent role in promoting homolog recognition, but several lines of evidence suggest that they cannot be the sole determinants of chromosome identity. Some PC proteins (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42593;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZIM-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45931;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZIM-3</ulink>) localize to more than one chromosome; despite this, nonhomologous pairing between different <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE42593;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZIM-1</ulink> or ZIM-3-binding PCs is not detected in wild-type animals (<link linkend="bib121">Phillips et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19620970-->. Moreover, pre-synaptic alignment has been demonstrated along the entire length of chromosomes (<link linkend="bib106">Nabeshima et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 21876678-->. The chromodomain protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE20213;class=Protein" role="_blank">MRG-1</ulink>, present on the autosomes, plays a role in the non-PC mediated homolog alignment and its absence leads to defects in homolog alignment and synapsis of non-PC regions (<link linkend="bib39">Dombecki et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 22172672-->. Mutations in the gene encoding the serine/threonine phosphatase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE23041;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPH-4.1</ulink> cause defective autosomal chromosome pairing and synapsis between non-homologous chromosomes. The relevant targets for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE23041;class=Protein" role="_blank">PPH-4.1</ulink> are still unknown (<link linkend="bib142">Sato-Carlton et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25340746-->. In <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, homologous recombination is not required for establishment of homolog alignment since <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004985;class=Gene" role="_blank">spo-11</ulink></emphasis> mutants, in which meiotic DSBs are not formed, are proficient to pair and synapse with their homologs (<link linkend="bib37">Dernburg et al., 1998</link>)<!--:PMID 9708740-->.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec3.3">
<title>PC movements promote efficient homolog pairing</title>
<para>PCs display a highly dynamic behavior during leptotene/zygotene (<link linkend="bib117">Penkner et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913286-->; <link linkend="bib141">Sato et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913287-->; <link linkend="bib11">Baudrimont et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 21124819-->; in contrast, other chromosomal regions are relatively static (<link linkend="bib178">Wynne et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22232701-->. During leptotene/zygotene, PCs have a strong tendency to come together into transient local clusters. From there they may continue to move in groups/pairs or dissociate and resume independent movement (<link linkend="figure3">Figure 3</link>). Tracking PC movements showed that they comprise both small short-range tracks and long saltatory trajectories (up to 2 &micro;m) with an average track length of 0.5 &micro;m and an average speed of 0.19 &micro;m/sec (<link linkend="bib117">Penkner et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913286-->; <link linkend="bib141">Sato et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913287-->; <link linkend="bib11">Baudrimont et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 21124819-->; <link linkend="bib178">Wynne et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22232701-->. Chromosomes progressively pair and synapse while progressing through leptotene/zygotene. In spite of this, the characteristics of chromosome movement remain essentially the same (<link linkend="bib11">Baudrimont et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 21124819-->; <link linkend="bib178">Wynne et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22232701-->, suggesting that PC-mediated chromosome end movement does not cease once synapsis of a given chromosome pair is achieved.</para>
<para>Chromosome movement in the gonad relies on microtubules (<link linkend="bib141">Sato et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913287-->; <link linkend="bib178">Wynne et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22232701-->. Further, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32088;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink> recruits components of the dynein motor complex to the cytoplasmic side of the PC attachments (<link linkend="bib141">Sato et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913287-->; <link linkend="bib78">Labrador et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23671424--> to mobilize chromosome ends in leptotene/zygotene and to facilitate pairing and synapsis. Dynein knock-down, ATP depletion, or a specific allele affecting the mitochondria-localized <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE19499;class=Protein" role="_blank">SPD-3</ulink> protein (with a likely role in energy production for dynein function) consistently result in reduced pairing and in synapsis with non-homologs (<link linkend="bib78">Labrador et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23671424-->. However, a direct role of dynein-driven chromosome movements in licensing SC assembly has also been proposed, since severe dynein knockdown inhibited SC assembly (<link linkend="bib141">Sato et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19913287-->. <link linkend="bib141">Sato et al. (2009)</link><!--: PMID 19913287--> further propose that dynein functions to oppose inappropriate chromosome interactions, enabling dissociation of non-homologous chromosomes.</para>
<para>Upon completion of pairing and synapsis, meiocytes enter early pachytene and chromosome clustering is loosened but not completely abrogated. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32088;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink> aggregates dissolve around the autosome PCs, whereas they persist longer at the X chromosome PCs, which remain mobile in early pachytene (<link linkend="bib117">Penkner et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913286-->; <link linkend="bib141">Sato et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913287-->; <link linkend="bib178">Wynne et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22232701-->. The study of the <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00022390;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-19</ulink></emphasis> mutant revealed that regulation of chromosome end mobilization deteriorates with progressive age in this mutant (<link linkend="bib117">Penkner et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913286-->; <link linkend="bib165">Tang et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20071466-->. The decreased movement and associated increase in nondisjunction with age might suggest an underlying cause for age-related chromosomal abnormalities in systems where meiosis continues throughout one&apos;s lifetime, such as during human spermatogenesis.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec4">
<title>Meiotic chromosome structure</title>
<para>The meiotic program involves dramatic changes in chromosome structure, which are driven by the regulated association and dissociation of different protein complexes from chromosomes. Some of these protein complexes represent meiosis-specific elaborations upon structures that occur in mitotically cycling cells. Critically important is the loading of multiple, partially redundant cohesin complexes (<link linkend="sec4.1">Section 4.1</link>), which tether sister chromatids together and serve as the basis for assembly of axial elements containing four HORMA-domain proteins (<link linkend="sec4.2">Section 4.2</link>). During pachytene, the axial elements of paired homologous chromosomes are connected by yet another meiosis-specific structure, the SC (<link linkend="sec4.3">Section 4.3</link>). Proper assembly of the SC depends on axis assembly, and in turn is required for regulated formation of meiotic COs between homologs (and thus, proper chromosome segregation) (<link linkend="sec5">Section 5</link> and <link linkend="sec6">Section 6</link>). The correct execution of these structural changes is essential to promote pairing, CO formation, and chromosome segregation.</para>
<sect2 id="sec4.1">
<title>Meiosis-specific cohesin complexes</title>
<para>The acquisition of meiosis-specific chromosome features starts with DNA replication, during which sister chromatid cohesion must be established. Meiotic S-phase is twice as long as that of cells in the mitotic compartment of the germ line (<link linkend="bib66">Jaramillo-Lambert et al., 2007</link>)<!--:PMID 17599823-->, perhaps reflecting the time required to adopt the unique chromosome configurations required for meiotic success. <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> expresses three different meiosis-specific cohesin complexes differing in their kleisin subunit: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink>, and the nearly identical and functionally redundant <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35852;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27409;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-4</ulink> (<link linkend="bib114">Pasierbek et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11390355-->; <link linkend="bib149">Severson et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19574299-->; <link linkend="bib150">Severson and Meyer, 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25171895-->. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> is present during meiotic DNA replication&mdash;it provides cohesion independently of DSBs, and its loading onto chromosomes depends on the HORMA-domain protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11330;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-3</ulink>, and on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE23033;class=Protein" role="_blank">TIM-1</ulink> (ortholog of the TIMELESS clock protein) (<link linkend="bib114">Pasierbek et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11390355-->; <link linkend="bib20">Chan et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12827206-->; <link linkend="bib149">Severson et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19574299-->; <link linkend="bib150">Severson and Meyer, 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25171895-->. In contrast, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35852;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-3</ulink>/4 complexes are only detected in meiotic nuclei following the completion of S-phase, their ability to provide cohesion requires DSBs, and their loading is independent of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11330;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE23033;class=Protein" role="_blank">TIM-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib150">Severson and Meyer, 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25171895-->. Loss of cohesion, evidenced by extensive separation of sister chromatids in diakinesis oocytes, is observed in mutants lacking <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35852;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-3</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27409;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-4</ulink>, but not in <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004333;class=Gene" role="_blank">rec-8</ulink></emphasis> single or <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000592;class=Gene" role="_blank">coh-3</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021560;class=Gene" role="_blank">coh-4</ulink></emphasis> double mutants (<link linkend="bib149">Severson et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19574299-->; <link linkend="bib168">Tzur et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22927794-->; <link linkend="bib150">Severson and Meyer, 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25171895-->, demonstrating that both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35852;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-3</ulink>/4 complexes contribute to sister chromatid cohesion.</para>
<para>Cohesin loading to meiotic chromosomes is not only essential for sister chromatid cohesion, but also for successful completion of key meiotic prophase events. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35852;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-3</ulink>/4 cohesin complexes associate with axial elements in the transition zone of the germ line, where chromosomes become dramatically elongated compared to mitotic cells (<link linkend="bib114">Pasierbek et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11390355-->; <link linkend="bib56">Hayashi et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17983271-->; <link linkend="bib106">Nabeshima et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21876678-->; <link linkend="bib150">Severson and Meyer, 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25171895-->. Assembly of axial elements is fully dependent on cohesin loading, as depletion of SMC-1 or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05664;class=Protein" role="_blank">SCC-3</ulink> (which are common to all meiotic cohesin complexes), lack of all three meiotic kleisins, or lack of the cohesin loading factor SCC-2, prevent association of HORMA-domain proteins with axial elements and cause severe meiotic defects that prevent CO formation (<link linkend="bib113">Pasierbek et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14499625-->; <link linkend="bib172">Wang et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 14560015-->; <link linkend="bib50">Goodyer et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18267094-->; <link linkend="bib149">Severson et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19574299-->; <link linkend="bib85">Lightfoot et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 21856158-->. Loading of different meiosis-specific cohesin complexes is also required for the assembly of axial elements in mice (reviewed in <link linkend="bib96">McNicoll et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23287028-->. Furthermore, meiotic defects, including impaired chiasma formation, are present in mutants that display a partial reduction in the overall amount of cohesin associated with axial elements, such as in worms carrying a hypomorphic <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004873;class=Gene" role="_blank">smc-3</ulink></emphasis> allele or mutants lacking the axis-associated <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15580;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAB-1</ulink> protein (<link linkend="bib12">Baudrimont et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21957461-->; <link linkend="bib168">Tzur et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22927794-->. CO formation is impaired in mutants lacking either <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35852;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-3</ulink>/4, demonstrating that both types of cohesin play important roles during meiotic recombination (<link linkend="bib114">Pasierbek et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11390355-->; <link linkend="bib56">Hayashi et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17983271-->; <link linkend="bib149">Severson et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19574299-->. Moreover, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35852;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-3</ulink>/4 cohesin also play different roles in ensuring SC assembly between homologous chromosomes, since SC assembly is greatly reduced in <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000592;class=Gene" role="_blank">coh-3</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021560;class=Gene" role="_blank">coh-4</ulink></emphasis> double mutants and SC installation is thought to occur between sister chromatids in <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004333;class=Gene" role="_blank">rec-8</ulink></emphasis> mutants (<link linkend="bib149">Severson et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19574299-->; <link linkend="bib150">Severson and Meyer, 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25171895-->.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4.2">
<title>HORMA-domain proteins</title>
<para>Proteins containing a HORMA domain, a protein motif also found in spindle-assembly checkpoint protein MAD2 (<link linkend="bib7">Aravind and Koonin, 1998</link>)<!--:PMID 9757827-->, play fundamental roles in establishing meiotic chromosome structure. The <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> genome encodes four of these proteins&mdash;HIM-3, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37734;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-2</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11330;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-3</ulink>, with unique and redundant functions. Collectively, these HORMA-domain proteins regulate almost all key events of meiosis, ranging from homolog recognition to the correct release of sister chromatid cohesion during the meiotic divisions.</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07625;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink>/2 consist mostly of a HORMA domain flanked by short N- and C-terminal regions, while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11330;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-3</ulink> contains a long C-terminal tail that contains four docking sites for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07625;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-3</ulink> and two for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink>/2 (<link linkend="bib74">Kim et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25446517-->. Therefore, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11330;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-3</ulink> is essential for the assembly of axial elements. In addition, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink>/2 can also be recruited to axial elements by binding directly to the C-terminal tail of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07625;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-3</ulink> (<link linkend="bib74">Kim et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25446517-->. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11330;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-3</ulink> is also required to promote loading of REC-8-containing cohesin complexes (<link linkend="bib149">Severson et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19574299--> and to mediate the formation of DSBs (<link linkend="bib50">Goodyer et al., 2008</link>)<!--:PMID 18267094-->, both of which are independent of its requirement to recruit <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07625;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink>/2 (<link linkend="bib74">Kim et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25446517-->. Interestingly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11330;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-3</ulink> is the only meiotic HORMA-domain protein that localizes to chromatin in the mitotic compartment of the germ line (<link linkend="bib56">Hayashi et al., 2007</link><!--:PMID 17983271-->; <link linkend="bib50">Goodyer et al., 2008</link>)<!--:PMID 18267094-->. Finally, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11330;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-3</ulink> is required for the acquisition of posttranslational modifications on axis-associated chromatin (<link linkend="bib34">Couteau and Zetka, 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 21397846-->. Thus, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11330;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-3</ulink> is not only essential to promote axial element assembly, but may also orchestrate changes in chromatin structure for multiple meiotic prophase events.</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07625;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink> are both required to ensure homolog recognition and to promote faithful SC assembly; as a consequence, <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001862;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-3</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002032;class=Gene" role="_blank">htp-1</ulink></emphasis> null mutants display severe impairment in CO formation (<link linkend="bib185">Zetka et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10485848-->; <link linkend="bib33">Couteau and Zetka, 2005</link><!--:PMID 16291647-->; <link linkend="bib94">Martinez-Perez and Villeneuve, 2005</link>)<!--:PMID 16291646-->. Although the mechanisms by which these two proteins promote homolog pairing are not well understood, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink> has been proposed to participate in two checkpoint-like mechanisms: the first makes initiation of SC assembly contingent on successful homology recognition, while the second prolongs the homology search process until homolog interactions are stabilized by SC loading (<link linkend="bib33">Couteau and Zetka, 2005</link><!--:PMID 16291647-->; <link linkend="bib94">Martinez-Perez and Villeneuve, 2005</link><!--:PMID 16291646-->; <link linkend="bib153">Silva et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25455309-->. A mutant form of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink> that fails to associate with axial elements still supports the delayed exit from early prophase triggered by synapsis defects, suggesting that nuclear soluble <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink> may participate in the quality control of SC assembly (<link linkend="bib153">Silva et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25455309-->. An important difference between <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002032;class=Gene" role="_blank">htp-1</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001862;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-3</ulink></emphasis> null mutants is that SC assembly is dramatically reduced in <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001862;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-3</ulink></emphasis> mutants, whereas lack of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink> results in high levels of SC assembly between non-homologous chromosomes. Non-homologous synapsis is also observed in mutants expressing hypomorphic alleles of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001862;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-3</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib32">Couteau et al., 2004</link>)<!--:PMID 15062099-->, demonstrating that both <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07625;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-3</ulink> have regulatory roles in SC assembly. Removal of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37734;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-2</ulink> (which shares 82% identity at the amino acid level with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink>) from <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002032;class=Gene" role="_blank">htp-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants results in a dramatic reduction in SC assembly, demonstrating that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37734;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-2</ulink> can promote homology-independent SC assembly (<link linkend="bib33">Couteau and Zetka, 2005</link><!--:PMID 16291647-->; <link linkend="bib93">Martinez-Perez et al., 2008</link>)<!--:PMID 18923085-->. However, the analysis of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002033;class=Gene" role="_blank">htp-2</ulink></emphasis> single mutants failed to identify obvious meiotic defects; thus, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37734;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-2</ulink> function appears largely redundant with that of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib93">Martinez-Perez et al., 2008</link>)<!--:PMID 18923085-->.</para>
<para>In addition to promotion of pairing and synapsis between homologs, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07625;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-3</ulink> also directly affect meiotic recombination, presumably by making the sister chromatid inaccessible for repair, thereby encouraging repair off the homolog (<link linkend="bib32">Couteau et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15062099-->; <link linkend="bib94">Martinez-Perez and Villeneuve, 2005</link>)<!--:PMID 16291646--> (see also <link linkend="sec5.2.4">Section 5.2.4</link> and <link linkend="sec5.5">Section 5.5</link>). <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002032;class=Gene" role="_blank">htp-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants show a reduction in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> foci (see <link linkend="sec5">Section 5</link>) which can be explained by a reduction in the overall number of DSBs formed and/or faster DSB turnover (<link linkend="bib33">Couteau and Zetka, 2005</link><!--:PMID 16291647-->; <link linkend="bib94">Martinez-Perez and Villeneuve, 2005</link>)<!--:PMID 16291646-->. Finally, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37734;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-2</ulink> participate in the two-step release of sister chromatid cohesion during the meiotic divisions, where they act to ensure that a subset of REC-8-containing cohesin remains associated with chromosomes during the first meiotic division (<link linkend="bib93">Martinez-Perez et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18923085-->; <link linkend="bib149">Severson et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19574299-->. Of note, the connection between HORMA-domain proteins and the regulation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> complexes goes beyond the release of sister chromatid cohesion in the meiotic divisions, since <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002032;class=Gene" role="_blank">htp-1</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002033;class=Gene" role="_blank">htp-2</ulink></emphasis> double mutants, <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001862;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-3</ulink></emphasis> mutants, and <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004333;class=Gene" role="_blank">rec-8</ulink></emphasis> mutants display premature centriole disengagement during meiosis II in spermatogenesis (<link linkend="bib145">Schvarzstein et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23401519-->.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec4.3">
<title>The SC</title>
<para>The most prominent, and highly conserved, structural feature of meiotic prophase is the SC. When observed by electron microscopy, the SC appears as a tripartite, ladder-like structure consisting of a central region that contains transverse filaments that bridge the axial elements of paired homologs (<link linkend="bib87">MacQueen et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12231631-->; <link linkend="bib27">Colai&aacute;covo, 2006</link>)<!--:PMID 16555015--> (<link linkend="figure4">Figure 4</link>). Although structurally similar, with long coiled-coil domains, the major components of the SC in different organisms are poorly conserved at the primary amino acid level. In <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, four components of the central region of the SC have been identified: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33925;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYP-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17456;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYP-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYP-3</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE23830;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYP-4</ulink>. Analysis of the corresponding single mutants reveals that these four proteins are interdependent for their loading onto chromosomes; consequently, SC assembly is fully abrogated in each one of the single mutants (<link linkend="bib87">MacQueen et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12231631-->; <link linkend="bib28">Colai&aacute;covo et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12967565-->; <link linkend="bib156">Smolikov et al., 2007b</link><!--:PMID 17565948-->; <link linkend="bib158">Smolikov et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19798442-->. SC assembly is also abrogated in <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002034;class=Gene" role="_blank">htp-3</ulink></emphasis> mutants and in mutants lacking all three meiotic kleisins (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35852;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-3</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27409;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-4</ulink>) (<link linkend="bib50">Goodyer et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18267094-->; <link linkend="bib149">Severson et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19574299-->. Investigation of the interactions among the four SYP proteins by immunoprecipitation, yeast two-hybrid experiments, and immuno-electron microscopy, suggests that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33925;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYP-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE17456;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYP-2</ulink> occupy a central position within the SC, while <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYP-3</ulink> interacts directly with axis components, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE23830;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYP-4</ulink>, the largest of these proteins, interacts with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYP-3</ulink> and reaches into the center of the SC (<link linkend="bib143">Schild-Pr&uuml;fert et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 21840865-->.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure4" xreflabel="Figure 4">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig4" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Figure 4</phrase>
</textobject> &fig4legend;</mediaobject>
<para>Once assembled, the SC stabilizes the pairwise association of homologous chromosomes and promotes the formation of interhomolog COs (see also <link linkend="sec5.2.4">Section 5.2.4</link> and <link linkend="sec5.5">Section 5.5</link>) (<link linkend="bib87">MacQueen et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12231631-->; <link linkend="bib28">Colai&aacute;covo et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12967565-->; <link linkend="bib155">Smolikov et al., 2007a</link><!--:PMID 17565963-->; <link linkend="bib158">Smolikov et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19798442-->. In addition, the SC is required for normal levels of CO interference (see <link linkend="sec5.4">Section 5.4</link> and <link linkend="sec5.5">Section 5.5</link>) (<link linkend="bib57">Hayashi et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 20592266-->; <link linkend="bib84">Libuda et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 24107990--> and to promote normal meiotic progression, as evidenced by the persistence of chromosome clustering in <emphasis role="italic">syp</emphasis> mutants (see <link linkend="sec7.1">Section 7.1</link>) (<link linkend="bib87">MacQueen et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12231631-->; <link linkend="bib28">Colai&aacute;covo et al., 2003</link>)<!--:PMID 12967565-->.</para>
<sect3 id="sec4.3.1">
<title>Regulation of SC assembly</title>
<para>SC assembly appears to be a cooperative process and occurs preferentially in a pairwise fashion, linking the axis of two chromosomes (<link linkend="bib88">MacQueen et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16360034-->; <link linkend="bib57">Hayashi et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 20592266-->; <link linkend="bib103">Mlynarczyk-Evans et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 24339786-->. In vivo imaging of GFP-tagged <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYP-3</ulink> suggests that synapsis of each homolog pair is initiated only once and that PCs are the primary sites for initiation; once initiated, SC extension continues at a constant rate until full synapsis is achieved (<link linkend="bib129">Rog and Dernburg, 2015</link>)<!--:PMID 25772351-->. Whereas the SC normally assembles only between correctly paired homologs, the SC structure itself is indifferent to homology, as seen by the presence of normal-appearing SC structures between non-homologous chromosomes in some meiotic mutants and in worms heterozygous for chromosome rearrangements (<link linkend="bib32">Couteau et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15062099-->; <link linkend="bib33">Couteau and Zetka, 2005</link><!--:PMID 16291647-->; <link linkend="bib94">Martinez-Perez and Villeneuve, 2005</link><!--:PMID 16291646-->; <link linkend="bib116">Penkner et al., 2007b</link><!--:PMID 17543861-->; <link linkend="bib58">Henzel et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 21212235-->. Thus, SC assembly must be tightly regulated to ensure a productive outcome. Regulation of SYP protein loading involves axial element components <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07625;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink> (see <link linkend="sec4.2">Section 4.2</link>), but proteins that do not become incorporated into the SC structure have also been reported to control the loading of SYP proteins, both in a chromosome-specific and a nucleus-wide manner. For example, the PC-binding <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE36715;class=Protein" role="_blank"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=HIM-8;class=Strain" role="_blank">HIM-8</ulink></ulink>/ZIM proteins are required for proper assembly of SC in a chromosome-specific manner (<link linkend="bib122">Phillips et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16360035-->; <link linkend="bib120">Phillips and Dernburg, 2006</link><!--:PMID 17141157-->; <link linkend="bib128">Rog and Dernburg, 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23578368--> (see also <link linkend="sec3.2">Section 3.2</link>), and in the absence of all PC-binding proteins, SC assembly becomes misregulated and non-homologous SC assembly takes place (<link linkend="bib55">Harper et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22018922-->; <link linkend="bib77">Labella et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 22018921-->. In addition, the chromosome motions characteristic of early prophase have been shown to be important for proper SC assembly: in their absence, SC assembly often occurs between nonhomologous chromosomes (see <link linkend="sec3.3">Section 3.3</link>). Factors that affect the loading of SYP proteins in a nucleus-wide fashion include: the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27297;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHK-2</ulink> kinase, required to induce normal levels of SC assembly in early prophase (<link linkend="bib89">MacQueen and Villeneuve, 2001</link><!--:PMID 11445542-->; <link linkend="bib94">Martinez-Perez and Villeneuve, 2005</link>)<!--:PMID 16291646-->; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE48020;class=Protein" role="_blank">HAL-2</ulink>, a nucleoplasmic protein that prevents the inappropriate loading of SYP proteins, which can interfere with the pairing process (<link linkend="bib188">Zhang et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22912597-->; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15580;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAB-1</ulink>, a component of axial elements that targets protein phosphatase 1 and is required for full SC assembly (<link linkend="bib168">Tzur et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22927794-->; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31579;class=Protein" role="_blank">CRA-1</ulink>, the <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> homolog of the non-catalytic subunit of the N-terminal acetyltransferases B, which is required to promote normal loading of SYP proteins (<link linkend="bib157">Smolikov et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18535664-->; <link linkend="bib46">Gao et al., 2015</link>)<!--:PMID 25768301-->; the CSN/COP9 signalosome, which is required to prevent the formation of extrachromosomal aggregates of SC proteins during early prophase (<link linkend="bib17">Brockway et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25375142-->; and the AAA+- ATPase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01547;class=Protein" role="_blank">PCH-2</ulink>, which localizes to the SC but is dispensable for SC formation and is proposed to prevent synapsis defects by acting as a &ldquo;brake&rdquo; that limits the rate of SC assembly to allow time for error correction (<link linkend="bib38">Deshong et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 24762417-->.</para>
<para>SC disassembly starts in late pachytene in a process that is linked to the progression of meiotic recombination (see <link linkend="sec6">Section 6</link>). Interestingly, the SC can be locally disassembled in response to exogenous DNA damage (<link linkend="bib34">Couteau and Zetka, 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 21397846--> or can be completely disassembled from an X chromosome without a CO (<link linkend="bib98">Meneely et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22267496-->, demonstrating that the SC is a dynamic structure.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec5">
<title>Meiotic recombination</title>
<para>In most organisms, including <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, successful chromosome segregation during meiosis requires formation of CO recombination events between homologous chromosomes; these COs, in conjunction with sister chromatid cohesion, serve to tether homologs together. These connections between homologs, in turn, allow correct (bipolar) attachment of homologs to the meiosis I spindle. Release of a subset of cohesin complexes at anaphase I then allows separation of homologs, thereby accomplishing the reduction in ploidy necessary for sexual reproduction.</para>
<para>Meiotic recombination is initiated through introduction of DSBs by the enzyme <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49824;class=Protein" role="_blank">SPO-11</ulink> (<link linkend="sec5.1">Section 5.1</link>). Repair of these DSBs can result in formation of COs (<link linkend="sec5.2">Section 5.2</link>) and the role of the meiotic machinery is to ensure that each chromosome receives at least one CO (the obligate CO). COs do not occur randomly along the chromosomes: each chromosome has a characteristic distribution of COs (<link linkend="sec5.3">Section 5.3</link>). Further, the number of COs per chromosome pair, and their positions relative to each other, are not random, reflecting several types of regulation (<link linkend="sec5.4">Section 5.4</link>). In addition, chromosome structure affects meiotic recombination (<link linkend="sec5.5">Section 5.5</link>), as does the meiotic cell cycle (<link linkend="sec5.6">Section 5.6</link>). See <link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link> for an overview of the key steps of meiotic recombination.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure5" xreflabel="Figure 5">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig5" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Figure 5</phrase>
</textobject> &fig5legend;</mediaobject>
<sect2 id="sec5.1">
<title>DSB formation</title>
<para>Recombination initiates with a DSB, introduced by the conserved topoisomerase-like enzyme <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49824;class=Protein" role="_blank">SPO-11</ulink> (<link linkend="bib37">Dernburg et al., 1998</link>)<!--:PMID 9708740-->. Mutants defective in genes required for DSB formation, such as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004985;class=Gene" role="_blank">spo-11</ulink></emphasis>, manifest 12 univalents at diakinesis because the achiasmate homologs condense and separate from one another during diplotene. A hallmark of this class of mutants is that bivalent formation can be restored by exposing the mutant to sources of exogenous breaks such as ionizing radiation (IR). In addition to <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004985;class=Gene" role="_blank">spo-11</ulink></emphasis> itself, genes that fall into this category include <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001874;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-17</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib124">Reddy and Villeneuve, 2004</link>)<!--:PMID 15315757-->, <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008580;class=Gene" role="_blank">dsb-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib162">Stamper et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23990794-->, and <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00194892;class=Gene" role="_blank">dsb-2</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib136">Rosu et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23950729-->. Two other genes, <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001514;class=Gene" role="_blank">xnd-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib171">Wagner et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20944745--> and <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001864;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-5</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib98">Meneely et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22267496-->, influence DSB formation mainly on the X chromosome. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37459;class=Protein" role="_blank">MRE-11</ulink> (<link linkend="bib24">Chin and Villeneuve, 2001</link>)<!--:PMID 11238374-->, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41010;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-50</ulink> (<link linkend="bib56">Hayashi et al., 2007</link>)<!--:PMID 17983271-->, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11330;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-3</ulink> (<link linkend="bib50">Goodyer et al., 2008</link>)<!--:PMID 18267094--> are also required for efficient DSB induction, but play additional roles in DSB repair (see below). Finally, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31579;class=Protein" role="_blank">CRA-1</ulink> regulates histone acetylation and promotes efficient DSB formation (<link linkend="bib46">Gao et al., 2015</link>)<!--:PMID 25768301-->, suggesting that regulation of chromatin structure by histone modifications is an important modulator of DSB, as observed in other organisms.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5.2">
<title>DSB repair by meiosis-specific adaptation of homologous recombination</title>
<para>Repair of DSBs during meiosis shares many features in common with homologous recombination (HR) in mitotic cell cycles, with several meiosis-specific modifications. Following DSB formation, 5&rsquo; ending DNA strands are resected, leaving 3&rsquo; single-stranded DNA flanking the DSB site. A 3&rsquo; end then invades an intact double-stranded template DNA molecule (in meiosis, typically the homologous chromosome rather than the sister chromatid, the preferred repair partner in other contexts) and primes DNA synthesis. Following repair synthesis, this intermediate can be disassembled (e.g., through the action of DNA helicases (<link linkend="bib112">P&acirc;ques and Haber, 1999</link>)<!--:PMID 10357855-->); the released ssDNA end can then re-anneal to the other DSB end, leading to repair of the DSB without CO formation. Alternatively, the intermediate can be stabilized through the action of meiosis-specific CO-promoting factors, leading to formation of more complex, branched CO recombination intermediates (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>). These intermediates must be enzymatically resolved by DNA strand cleavage; this can result in crossing over (reciprocal exchange of information between chromosomes). We depict these meiotic CO-intermediates as double Holliday junctions by analogy to <emphasis role="italic">S. cerevisiae,</emphasis> where recombination intermediate structures have been analyzed using physical assays; in most cases, the existence of specific DSB repair intermediates in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> is inferred rather than directly demonstrated.</para>
<para>Mutants defective in genes required for DSB repair cannot be rescued by IR. Instead, exposure of repair-deficient mutants to IR leads to significant chromosomal abnormalities including DNA fragmentation, chromosome aggregation and defects in chromosome condensation, which are readily visible in diakinesis-stage oocytes (e.g., <link linkend="bib24">Chin and Villeneuve, 2001</link>)<!--:PMID 11238374-->.</para>
<sect3 id="sec5.2.1">
<title>Resection</title>
<para>The first step in the repair of meiotic DSBs is resection, the processing of ends into 3&rsquo; single-stranded DNA (ssDNA) overhangs. Based on the high degree of conservation between <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49824;class=Protein" role="_blank">SPO-11</ulink> homologs, it is believed that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49824;class=Protein" role="_blank">SPO-11</ulink> becomes covalently attached to the DNA upon DSB formation, and that further processing requires removal of the SPO-11-DNA nucleoprotein complexes to create short 3&rsquo; overhangs. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37459;class=Protein" role="_blank">MRE-11</ulink> 5&rsquo;-3&rsquo; exonuclease is then normally required to generate long 3&rsquo; ssDNA tails (<link linkend="bib181">Yin and Smolikove, 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23671188--> that ultimately get coated with the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> recombinase (<link linkend="bib6">Alpi et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12684824-->; <link linkend="bib28">Colai&aacute;covo et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12967565-->; <link linkend="bib119">Petalcorin et al., 2006</link>)<!--:PMID 16843491-->. In the absence of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003405;class=Gene" role="_blank">mre-11</ulink></emphasis>, the exonuclease <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE28728;class=Protein" role="_blank">EXO-1</ulink> has also been shown to contribute to resection of meiotic DSBs, although resection is then delayed until mid-late pachytene (<link linkend="bib181">Yin and Smolikove, 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23671188-->.</para>
<para>Mutants defective in resection, such as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003405;class=Gene" role="_blank">mre-11</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib24">Chin and Villeneuve, 2001</link><!--:PMID 11238374-->; <link linkend="bib181">Yin and Smolikove, 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23671188--> and <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004296;class=Gene" role="_blank">rad-50</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib56">Hayashi et al., 2007</link>)<!--:PMID 17983271-->, are characterized by impaired loading of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> to SPO-11-dependent DSBs and display diakinesis-stage oocytes with abnormal chromosome aggregations. These aggregates arise from repair by non-homologous end joining (NHEJ). The predominance of HR over NHEJ suggests that active mechanisms suppress NHEJ in the meiotic germ line (<link linkend="bib155">Smolikov et al., 2007a</link><!--:PMID 17565963-->; <link linkend="bib1">Adamo et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 20598602-->; <link linkend="bib83">Lemmens et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23408909-->. A key player in this inhibition is <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43543;class=Protein" role="_blank">COM-1</ulink> (the Sae2/CtIP homolog (<link linkend="bib115">Penkner et al., 2007a</link>)<!--:PMID 18007596-->) that actively inhibits the binding of Ku proteins to the DNA ends (<link linkend="bib83">Lemmens et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23408909-->. The involvement of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37459;class=Protein" role="_blank">MRE-11</ulink> in both DSB formation and subsequent resection is another potential mechanism to ensure that DSBs are shunted towards HR.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec5.2.2">
<title>Strand exchange and formation of downstream repair intermediates</title>
<para>The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> nucleoprotein filament serves the important role of promoting the homology search and strand invasion into the homologous duplex DNA (<link linkend="figure5">Figure 5</link>). Displacement of the homologous template strand forms a D loop structure wherein the invading 3&rsquo; end is used to prime DNA synthesis. COs can result from subsequent formation and cleavage of more complex intermediates (possibly double Holliday junctions) made by second end capture. Non-crossovers (NCOs) are presumed to arise from ejection of the invading strand and repair via synthesis-dependent strand annealing. Failure to execute these steps can allow for aberrant repair via NHEJ and ultimately can cause chromosome fusions.</para>
<para>Due to the central role of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> to HR, it is no surprise that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> filament formation is highly regulated (<link linkend="bib125">Rinaldo et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 11861554-->; <link linkend="bib6">Alpi et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12684824-->; <link linkend="bib28">Colai&aacute;covo et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12967565-->; <link linkend="bib164">Takanami et al., 2003</link>)<!--:PMID 12733639-->. The worm homolog of the BRCA2 breast cancer associated protein, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32718;class=Protein" role="_blank">BRC-2</ulink><emphasis role="italic">,</emphasis> facilitates nuclear localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink>, its loading onto ssDNA (<link linkend="bib92">Martin et al., 2005</link>)<!--:PMID 15798199-->, and D loop formation (<link linkend="bib118">Petalcorin et al., 2007</link>)<!--:PMID 17483448-->. In <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020316;class=Gene" role="_blank">brc-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants, RPA-coated ssDNA can be detected; this either reflects the fact that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE04405;class=Protein" role="_blank">RPA-1</ulink> loads onto resected ssDNA before <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink>, as in other organisms, or is an aberrant outcome resulting from the failure to load <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink>. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15894;class=Protein" role="_blank">RTEL-1</ulink> may also influence <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> dynamics through its role as an anti-recombinase, disrupting D loops and promoting alternative pathways of repair (<link linkend="bib8">Barber et al., 2008</link>)<!--:PMID 18957201-->.</para>
<para>In order for HR to proceed, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> must also be removed from the D loop. Three proteins have been thought to promote <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> turnover: <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE25143;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-54</ulink> (<link linkend="bib99">Mets and Meyer, 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19781752-->, the helicase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37439;class=Protein" role="_blank">HELQ-1</ulink>/HEL308, and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> paralog, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00094;class=Protein" role="_blank">RFS-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib173">Ward et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20122407-->, with the latter two having a redundant function in wild-type cells. Cytological examination of both <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004298;class=Gene" role="_blank">rad-54</ulink></emphasis> single mutants and <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021905;class=Gene" role="_blank">helq-1</ulink> <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004342;class=Gene" role="_blank">rfs-1</ulink></emphasis> double mutants shows prolonged persistence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> filaments, indicating the persistence of unrepaired DSBs.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec5.2.3">
<title>CO designation</title>
<para>Once strand exchange has occurred, additional regulation is required to ensure that a subset of these intermediates become committed to a CO fate. Classically, two CO pathways were described in model systems: the class I pathway, requiring the meiosis-specific homologs of the mismatch repair protein MutS, MSH4 and MSH5, and certain SC associated proteins, is considered responsible for COs subject to interference (see <link linkend="sec5.4">Section 5.4</link>); the class II pathway, dependent on the structure-specific nuclease components MUS81 and MMS4, accounts for the interference-independent COs (reviewed in <link linkend="bib76">Kohl and Sekelsky, 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23733849-->. In <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, the class I pathway predominates, as mutations in the respective orthologs, <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003420;class=Gene" role="_blank">msh-4</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003421;class=Gene" role="_blank">msh-5</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib175">Winand et al., 1998</link><!--:PMID 9787078-->; <link linkend="bib184">Zalevsky et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10545458-->; <link linkend="bib71">Kelly et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 11014811-->; <link linkend="bib28">Colai&aacute;covo et al., 2003</link>)<!--:PMID 12967565-->, and <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006976;class=Gene" role="_blank">zhp-3</ulink></emphasis> (Zip3 homologous protein; <link linkend="bib64">Jantsch et al., 2004</link>)<!--:PMID 15340062--> leads to univalents at diakinesis. It should be noted that MSH-4 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26678;class=Protein" role="_blank">MSH-5</ulink> are first detected broadly in presumptive DSB repair foci that exceed the number of eventual COs; they then become restricted to CO sites by late pachytene (<link linkend="bib182">Yokoo et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22464324-->. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43850;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZHP-3</ulink> is initially present along the entire SC in mid-pachytene and then gradually becomes restricted to CO sites (<link linkend="bib14">Bhalla et al., 2008</link>)<!--:PMID 18949042-->. Thus, additional proteins must function in designating a subset of recombination intermediates for CO fates. Anti-recombinases such as RTEL function at this step to shunt repair intermediates into a NCO outcome (possibly by promoting synthesis-dependent strand annealing); thus, in the absence of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009124;class=Gene" role="_blank">rtel-1</ulink></emphasis> function, additional COs are made (<link linkend="bib183">Youds et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20203049-->. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41080;class=Protein" role="_blank">COSA-1</ulink>, a cyclin-like protein that is required for CO formation, has been proposed to function in reinforcement of CO designation, as it is predominantly detected as a single focus on each chromosome pair during late pachytene (<link linkend="bib182">Yokoo et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22464324-->. Additional <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41080;class=Protein" role="_blank">COSA-1</ulink> foci are observed on very large fusion chromosomes, such at the X;IV fusion chromosome mnT12 (<link linkend="bib84">Libuda et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 24107990-->, where multiple COs can be detected genetically (<link linkend="bib60">Hillers and Villeneuve, 2003</link>)<!--:PMID 13678597-->.</para>
<para>Loss of function mutations in MSH-4, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26678;class=Protein" role="_blank">MSH-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43850;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZHP-3</ulink>, or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41080;class=Protein" role="_blank">COSA-1</ulink> result in 12 univalents at diakinesis. Irradiation cannot restore bivalent formation in these mutants. The mutants also do not show chromosome fusions indicative of mutations in strand exchange proteins. The kinetics of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> foci turnover is slower in these mutants, but they do disappear prior to diplotene indicating that DSB repair has occurred (<link linkend="bib184">Zalevsky et al., 1999</link><!--:PMID 10545458-->; <link linkend="bib28">Colai&aacute;covo et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12967565-->; <link linkend="bib64">Jantsch et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15340062-->; <link linkend="bib159">Song et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 20530576-->; <link linkend="bib182">Yokoo et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22464324-->.</para>
<para>The emerging picture of CO formation from studies in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> and other systems is that an excess of DSBs are made; these get initially bound by repair proteins and putative CO designation proteins and winnowed down to a small number of CO sites. Understanding this selection process is an area of active research in many organisms including <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans.</emphasis></para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec5.2.4">
<title>Partner choice</title>
<para>Although many events of DSB repair are conserved between mitosis and meiosis, a major difference is that the homolog is used as a repair template during meiosis, whereas the sister chromatid is the preferred repair template for cells in S and G2 of mitotic cell cycles. The preference for the homolog rather than the sister is thought to be mediated in large part by axial element components (<link linkend="sec4.2">Section 4.2</link>). Use of the homolog as a recombination partner also appears to be a temporally regulated feature of the meiotic program: access to the homolog as repair template for both CO and non-CO repair is shut down upon transition into the late pachytene stage. Thus, DSBs that are made or persist into late pachytene or beyond are presumed to be repaired using the sister chromatid as a repair template (<link linkend="bib28">Colai&aacute;covo et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12967565-->; <link linkend="bib135">Rosu et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 22144627-->.</para>
<para>During meiosis, an excess of DSBs is formed (relative to the number of COs). Many of these breaks are repaired as NCOs using the homolog as a repair template (<link linkend="bib126">Robert et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18757928-->; <link linkend="bib135">Rosu et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 22144627-->, but repair using the sister chromatid as a template likely also occurs. The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27096;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMC-5</ulink>/6 complex and the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43190;class=Protein" role="_blank">BRC-1</ulink> protein have been shown to be important for repair of meiotic DSBs under conditions where inter-homolog CO formation is abrogated and/or in mutant situations when inter-sister repair is the only option (<link linkend="bib16">Boulton et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 14711411-->; <link linkend="bib2">Adamo et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18219312-->; <link linkend="bib15">Bickel et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20661436-->. These papers provided evidence that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27096;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMC-5</ulink>/6 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43190;class=Protein" role="_blank">BRC-1</ulink> are important for inter-sister repair, but the data are consistent with these proteins also participating in inter-homolog non-CO repair as well.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sec5.2.5">
<title>CO resolution</title>
<para>The final step of CO recombination is cleavage of CO intermediates to yield mature CO products. <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> contains several resolvase functions that are scaffolded by the SLX-4/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE48043;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-18</ulink> protein (<link linkend="bib139">Saito et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19936019-->. These can either act redundantly or can substitute for each other to resolve CO intermediates. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24855;class=Protein" role="_blank">XPF-1</ulink> (in combination with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31724;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-6</ulink>/BLM) and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11216;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLX-1</ulink> (in combination with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32609;class=Protein" role="_blank">MUS-81</ulink>) are proposed to define two mechanistically distinct pathways for resolving CO intermediates (<link linkend="bib3">Agostinho et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23901331-->; <link linkend="bib111">O&apos;Neil et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23874209-->; <link linkend="bib137">Saito et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23874210-->. Double mutants lacking both pathways exhibit defects in post-pachytene chromosome reorganization and disassembly of the SC. Unique to these mutants, diakinesis univalents appear closely apposed and connected by chromatin bridges (<link linkend="bib3">Agostinho et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23901331-->; <link linkend="bib111">O&apos;Neil et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23874209-->; <link linkend="bib137">Saito et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23874210-->. These bridges are ultimately resolved in meiosis II, however, suggesting that additional resolvase functions are present in the worm germ line.</para>
<para>The <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31724;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-6</ulink>/BLM helicase may play a central role in ensuring that CO-designated recombination intermediates are eventually resolved into COs. In the absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31724;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-6</ulink> protein, nuclei appear to carry out the early steps of meiotic recombination normally; CO designation also seems normal, as 6 <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41080;class=Protein" role="_blank">COSA-1</ulink> foci can be seen in late pachytene oocytes. However, a subset of these CO-designated intermediates fail to form COs, evidenced by the presence of univalents at diakinesis (<link linkend="bib146">Schvarzstein et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25053665-->. It may be that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31724;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-6</ulink> acts to ensure the CO outcome by biasing resolution of intermediates (by either <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24855;class=Protein" role="_blank">XPF-1</ulink> or <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11216;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLX-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32609;class=Protein" role="_blank">MUS-81</ulink>) towards CO formation or by protecting CO-designated intermediates from NCO resolution.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5.3">
<title>The recombination landscape</title>
<para>CO frequency and distribution can be assayed genetically, using either phenotypic markers or DNA sequence polymorphisms; the latter approach allows a more detailed analysis of crossing over, as a higher density of markers can be used in a single experiment (<link linkend="bib36">Davis et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16156901-->; <link linkend="bib61">Hillers and Villeneuve, 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19799178-->. Next-generation DNA sequencing has the potential to allow genome-wide determination of the recombination landscape but to date has only been used to probe targeted genomic regions (<link linkend="bib70">Kaur and Rockman, 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 24172135-->. Crossing over can also be analyzed cytologically, by visualizing the number and distribution of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41080;class=Protein" role="_blank">COSA-1</ulink> foci in late pachytene cells (<link linkend="bib182">Yokoo et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22464324-->; <link linkend="bib84">Libuda et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 24107990-->.</para>
<para>In many eukaryotes, COs are non-randomly distributed along chromosomes, with a tendency to occur within small regions called hotspots (<link linkend="bib109">Nicolas et al., 1989</link><!--:PMID 2537472-->; <link linkend="bib10">Baudat et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20044539-->. No evidence for CO hotspots has been found in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, however, despite considerable efforts (<link linkend="bib70">Kaur and Rockman, 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 24172135-->. Nevertheless, meiotic COs in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> are not randomly distributed along chromosomes. As described in the WormBook chapter Karyotype, ploidy and gene dosage, the distribution of COs along the autosomes is uneven, with roughly the central third of each autosome having a paucity of events; interestingly, the same region of each autosome has a higher density of genes (the &ldquo;central gene cluster&rdquo;). Conversely, the arms of each chromosome have a higher frequency of crossing over and a lower gene density, thus the physical and genetic maps of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> are said to be &ldquo;out of alignment&rdquo;. This type of CO density domain structure is also observed on the X chromosome, but is much less pronounced (<link linkend="bib9">Barnes et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 8536965-->; <link linkend="bib127">Rockman and Kruglyak, 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19283065-->. Together, these features indicate that some aspect of CO formation is subject to regional regulation; the DNA sequence determinants of this regulation (if any) are unclear.</para>
<para>Evidence that CO distribution is influenced by genetic factors came initially from the isolation of a mutation in the <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004332;class=Gene" role="_blank">rec-1</ulink></emphasis> gene. This allele alters the distribution of COs along autosomes without changing overall frequency. This redistribution of COs towards the middle of each chromosome aligns the physical and genetic maps of <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> (<link linkend="bib131">Rose and Baillie, 1979a</link><!--:PMID 492325-->; <link linkend="bib187">Zetka and Rose, 1995</link>)<!--:PMID 8601478-->. Mutations in the <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001864;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-5</ulink></emphasis> gene also cause redistribution of meiotic COs along autosomes, resulting in an increased incidence of COs in the central gene cluster; similar to <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004332;class=Gene" role="_blank">rec-1</ulink></emphasis>, there is not an overall increase of COs along autosomes (<link linkend="bib98">Meneely et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22267496-->. In contrast to <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004332;class=Gene" role="_blank">rec-1</ulink></emphasis>, however, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE09062;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-5</ulink> also plays a role in facilitating meiotic DSB formation on the X chromosomes: in a <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001864;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-5</ulink></emphasis> mutant the frequency of COs on the <emphasis role="italic">X</emphasis> is reduced, with a concomitant increase in X chromosome nondisjunction (the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0001175;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">Him</ulink> phenotype).</para>
<para>The phenotypes of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001874;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-17</ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001514;class=Gene" role="_blank">xnd-1</ulink></emphasis>, and condensin mutants suggest that chromatin structure and condensation state are also critical determinants of DSB sites. <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001874;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-17</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001514;class=Gene" role="_blank">xnd-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants both show aberrant histone post-translational modifications and are impaired in DSB formation (<link linkend="bib124">Reddy and Villeneuve, 2004</link><!--:PMID 15315757-->; <link linkend="bib171">Wagner et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20944745-->. Both genes are also required for normal localization of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE09062;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-5</ulink>, revealing interplay between chromatin and the recombination landscape (<link linkend="bib98">Meneely et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22267496-->. Likewise, condensin proteins, which play crucial roles in chromosome condensation during cell divisions, play roles in establishing the wild-type distribution of DSBs and COs. Heterozygosity for a null mutation in any of the subunits of Condensin I (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31734;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-28</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE08398;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-26</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18083;class=Protein" role="_blank">MIX-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03287;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMC-4</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE09790;class=Protein" role="_blank">CAPG-1</ulink>) or of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30620;class=Protein" role="_blank">KLE-2</ulink> (a subunit of Condensin II) leads to HIM-3-dependent alterations in recombination and chromosome structure: COs are redistributed along the <emphasis role="italic">X</emphasis> chromosome, the overall frequency of COs is increased, and pachytene chromosome axis length is increased (<link linkend="bib167">Tsai et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18198337-->; <link linkend="bib99">Mets and Meyer, 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19781752-->. Mutants homozygous for a partial loss of function allele of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001087;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-28</ulink></emphasis>, which does not increase CO frequencies, showed that CO distribution correlated with a shift in the distribution of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> foci (<link linkend="bib99">Mets and Meyer, 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19781752-->. Moreover, the <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001087;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-28</ulink></emphasis> partial loss of function allele suppresses the defect in chiasma formation of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001874;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-17</ulink></emphasis> mutants, suggesting that higher-order chromosome structures promoted by condensin limit DSB formation (<link linkend="bib167">Tsai et al., 2008</link>)<!--:PMID 18198337-->. Together, this set of genes points to a complex interplay between chromosome/ chromatin structure and the meiotic recombination machinery.</para>
<para>Despite these general features, CO frequency and position are not fixed within the population, and the number and frequency of COs differs between the sexes, with maternal age, and with temperature (<link linkend="bib62">Hodgkin et al., 1979</link><!--:PMID 17248881-->; <link linkend="bib132">Rose and Baillie, 1979b</link><!--:PMID 17248928-->; <link linkend="bib186">Zetka and Rose, 1990</link><!--:PMID 2245915-->; <link linkend="bib86">Lim et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18780748-->; <link linkend="bib159">Song et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20530576-->. However, in all these situations, the arm/cluster differences in CO distribution remain (<link linkend="bib9">Barnes et al., 1995</link>)<!--:PMID 8536965-->. Thus, at the global level, there are defined regions of the genome that are more or less prone to receive a CO.</para>
<para>CO distribution can also be influenced by events subsequent to DSB formation. DSB sites can be mapped cytologically using anti-RAD-51 antibodies in a mutant such as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004298;class=Gene" role="_blank">rad-54</ulink></emphasis> that prevents further processing of the filament and effectively traps the recombination intermediate (<link linkend="bib99">Mets and Meyer, 2009</link><!--:PMID 19781752-->; <link linkend="bib110">Nottke et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 21768382-->; <link linkend="bib135">Rosu et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22144627-->; <link linkend="bib138">Saito et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22927825-->. Cytological examination of RAD-51-marked DSB sites in wild type failed to detect an arm/cluster bias in DSB distribution (<link linkend="bib138">Saito et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22927825-->, which would be expected if CO distribution were predominantly enforced at the step of DSB formation. Rather, it appears that CO formation in the central gene cluster is actively inhibited at a step post-recruitment of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink>. The resolvase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11216;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLX-1</ulink> (<link linkend="sec5.2.5">Section 5.2.5</link>) appears to function in this inhibition, as mutation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11216;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLX-1</ulink> leads to a redistribution of exchanges along chromosome V: there is an increase in COs in the central gene cluster of chromosome V, with a compensatory decrease in COs in the arm regions (<link linkend="bib138">Saito et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22927825-->.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5.4">
<title>CO interference, assurance, and homeostasis</title>
<para>Each of the 6 chromosome pairs in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has a genetic map size near 50 cM. A map size of 50 cM indicates that each chromosome pair experiences (on average) only one CO per meiosis. Each homolog pair must receive the &ldquo;obligate CO&rdquo;, to promote accurate chromosome segregation, and different mechanisms operate during meiosis to ensure this outcome. The ability to ensure the formation of at least one CO per homolog pair is known as CO assurance, while the ability to maintain CO number in the face of variability in numbers of DSBs is known as CO homeostasis. As homeostasis is a mechanism that promotes COs at the expense of NCOs in situations where DSB numbers are limiting, CO homeostasis helps to achieve CO assurance, suggesting that these two manifestations of CO regulation are mechanistically linked. Evidence for the operation of these mechanisms during worm meiosis comes from studies in which a limited number of DSBs are exogenously introduced in <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004985;class=Gene" role="_blank">spo-11</ulink></emphasis> mutants. For example, when a single DSB is generated by transposon excision, this event is converted into a CO with high efficiency (<link linkend="bib135">Rosu et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 22144627-->. This suggests that CO assurance can be achieved by ensuring that each chromosome receives at least one DSB. Similarly, when a limited number of DSBs are generated by irradiation, these are also efficiently converted into a single CO per chromosome pair. Further increases in the number of DSBs by increased irradiation does not result in the formation of more <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41080;class=Protein" role="_blank">COSA-1</ulink> marked events, providing evidence for CO homeostasis (<link linkend="bib182">Yokoo et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22464324-->. In addition, CO homeostasis may explain why only the X chromosome is devoid of a CO in <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001864;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-5</ulink></emphasis> mutants whereas <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> foci are reduced over four-fold genome-wide (<link linkend="bib98">Meneely et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22267496-->.</para>
<para>In <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, most chromosome pairs undergo only a single CO per meiosis (<link linkend="bib60">Hillers and Villeneuve, 2003</link><!--:PMID 13678597-->; <link linkend="bib54">Hammarlund et al., 2005</link>)<!--:PMID 16118192-->, but when multiple COs have been mapped, they tend to be widely spaced along the chromosome (<link linkend="bib60">Hillers and Villeneuve, 2003</link><!--:PMID 13678597-->; <link linkend="bib86">Lim et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18780748-->; <link linkend="bib84">Libuda et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 24107990-->. This non-random distribution of COs is known as CO interference (<link linkend="bib105">Muller, 1916</link>). The fact that most chromosome pairs receive only a single CO suggests that CO interference operates over distances greater than the length of a typical chromosome to discourage additional exchanges once one has occurred. Indeed, studies with fusion chromosomes have demonstrated that end-to-end fusions of two and even three chromosomes still frequently only received a single CO in meiosis (<link linkend="bib60">Hillers and Villeneuve, 2003</link>)<!--:PMID 13678597-->. Further, cytological mapping of COs along the length of <emphasis role="italic">mnT12</emphasis> (an end-to-end fusion of chromosomes <emphasis role="italic">IV</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">X</emphasis>) enabled measurement of the distance along chromosomes over which CO interference operates in <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, and strengthened the idea that interference operates over distances longer than the length of a typical chromosome (<link linkend="bib84">Libuda et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 24107990-->.</para>
<para>While cytological evaluation of CO interference using <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41080;class=Protein" role="_blank">COSA-1</ulink> foci suggests that chromosome pairs rarely have more that one cytologically differentiated CO site, double COs have been characterized using genetic recombination assays. Double CO data for individual autosomes range between 2-10% per chromosome pair (<link linkend="bib97">Meneely et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12454064-->; <link linkend="bib108">Nabeshima et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15579685-->; <link linkend="bib86">Lim et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18780748-->; <link linkend="bib38">Deshong et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 24762417-->; <link linkend="bib45">Gabdank and Fire, 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 24240780-->. Extrapolating these data for all 5 autosomes, this genetic evidence suggests up to 35% of nuclei have at least one autosome that obtains a second CO. These extra COs are cytologically distinct, however, as they are apparently not associated with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41080;class=Protein" role="_blank">COSA-1</ulink> foci (<link linkend="bib182">Yokoo et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22464324-->; <link linkend="bib38">Deshong et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 24762417-->. The X chromosome, in contrast, appears particularly immune to double COs in some studies (<link linkend="bib86">Lim et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18780748-->; <link linkend="bib167">Tsai et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18198337-->; but see <link linkend="bib38">Deshong et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 24762417-->, perhaps due to its heterochromatic-like state (<link linkend="bib72">Kelly et al., 2002</link>)<!--:PMID 11807039-->. Further, the frequency of double COs differs between oocyte and sperm meiosis (<link linkend="bib186">Zetka and Rose, 1990</link><!--:PMID 2245915-->; <link linkend="bib86">Lim et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18780748-->; <link linkend="bib45">Gabdank and Fire, 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 24240780-->. Data are only available for male sperm: they appear to have less stringent genetic interference compared to oocytes, having both increased numbers of double COs and more closely spaced COs (<link linkend="bib86">Lim et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18780748-->; <link linkend="bib45">Gabdank and Fire, 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 24240780-->.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5.5">
<title>Interplay between recombination and chromosome structure</title>
<para>While the analysis of null mutants lacking any of the SYP proteins reveals that these proteins are required for CO/chiasma formation, partial depletion of SYP proteins by RNAi results in an increased incidence of double COs (<link linkend="bib57">Hayashi et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 20592266-->; <link linkend="bib84">Libuda et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 24107990-->. Similarly, a non-null allele of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001862;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-3</ulink></emphasis> that allows partial synapsis of homologs also results in increased incidence of double COs (<link linkend="bib108">Nabeshima et al., 2004</link>)<!--:PMID 15579685-->. This apparent contradiction can be explained by the proposal that the SC functions in the process of CO interference (<link linkend="sec5.4">Section 5.4</link>). Although the mechanism by which interference is transmitted along chromosomes is not understood, <link linkend="bib84">Libuda et al. (2013)</link><!--: PMID 24107990--> found that each CO event is associated with a local extension of the axial element, suggesting that this structural alteration may play a role in impeding the formation of further COs. CO numbers are also increased when the structure of chromosomes is altered by reducing the dose of components of the condensin I complex, although in this case the extra COs are not associated with a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41080;class=Protein" role="_blank">COSA-1</ulink> marked cytologically differentiated site (<link linkend="bib167">Tsai et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18198337-->; <link linkend="bib99">Mets and Meyer, 2009</link><!--:PMID 19781752-->; <link linkend="bib182">Yokoo et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22464324-->.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec5.6">
<title>Window of opportunity for CO formation</title>
<para>DSB formation and repair are initiated in the transition zone; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> foci continue to accumulate through mid-pachytene, suggesting that both the initiation and cessation of DSB formation are controlled. DSB formation has been proposed to be subject to feedback regulation; once all chromosome pairs have a CO-eligible intermediate, DSB formation ceases (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>). In addition, it is clear that as nuclei transition into late pachytene, there is a shift in repair mechanism utilization; even if DSBs are formed in late pachytene germ cells (e.g., by gamma irradiation), these nuclei are incapable of committing to CO formation (<link linkend="bib182">Yokoo et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22464324-->. Further, during early and mid-pachytene, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41010;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-50</ulink> is required for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> loading at DSB sites; after the late pachytene transition, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41010;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-50</ulink> is no longer required for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> loading (<link linkend="bib56">Hayashi et al., 2007</link>)<!--:PMID 17983271-->. Finally, access to the homolog as a repair template is also shut down at the transition from mid- to late pachytene (<link linkend="bib135">Rosu et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 22144627-->, presumably reflecting reversion to preferential use of the sister chromatid as a repair partner. This transition to sister repair is accompanied by an ability of DNA damage to trigger localized separation of the chromosome axes, a feature that is antagonized by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11330;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-3</ulink> at earlier stages (<link linkend="bib34">Couteau and Zetka, 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 21397846-->. Ultimately, this transition in DNA repair mode may allow for residual DSBs to be repaired and the nucleus to escape apoptosis induced by the DNA damage checkpoint. The transition zone to mid-pachytene region can thus be considered the window of opportunity for the formation of DSBs and CO-designated events.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec6">
<title>Bivalent differentiation</title>
<para>Following the formation of CO-fated recombination intermediates, meiotic chromosomes undergo two major structural changes in preparation for the meiotic divisions: the disassembly of the SC, which occurs in an asymmetric fashion around the CO site; and condensation, a process that causes a dramatic reduction in chromosome size (for detailed reviews see <link linkend="bib147">Schvarzstein et al., 2010</link><!--:PMID 201233904-->; <link linkend="bib177">Wood et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20442714-->. Together, these lead to the formation of diakinesis bivalents, highly condensed pairs of homologous chromosomes held together by sister chromatid cohesion and COs. Bivalents contain two functional domains: a short arm where sister chromatid cohesion will be released during the first meiotic division, and a long arm where sister chromatids will remain attached until the onset of the second meiotic division (<link linkend="bib5">Albertson and Thomson, 1993</link><!--:PMID 8143084-->; <link linkend="bib4">Albertson et al., 1997</link>)<!--:PMID 21413226-->.</para>
<sect2 id="sec6.1">
<title>CO-triggered chromosome remodeling</title>
<para>The creation of bivalents with two differentiated functional domains starts in late pachytene with the redistribution of SC and axis-associated proteins that is triggered by CO-fated recombination intermediates (<link linkend="bib107">Nabeshima et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15738262-->; <link linkend="bib19">de Carvalho et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18923084-->; <link linkend="bib93">Martinez-Perez et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18923085-->; <link linkend="bib3">Agostinho et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23901331--> (<link linkend="figure6">Figure 6</link>). At this stage <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15580;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAB-1</ulink> are depleted from the region of the chromosomes between the CO site and the closest telomere, forming the short arm of the bivalent, while the SYP proteins and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43850;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZHP-3</ulink> are depleted from the region between the CO and the farthest telomere, forming the long arm (<link linkend="bib107">Nabeshima et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15738262-->; <link linkend="bib156">Smolikov et al., 2007b</link><!--:PMID 17565948-->; <link linkend="bib14">Bhalla et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18949042-->; <link linkend="bib19">de Carvalho et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18923084-->; <link linkend="bib93">Martinez-Perez et al., 2008</link>)<!--:PMID 18923085-->. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35852;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-3</ulink>/4-containing cohesin complexes are also largely removed from the long arm of each bivalent by late diakinesis and become restricted to the short arm by prometaphase I (<link linkend="bib150">Severson and Meyer, 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25171895-->. The short arm region undergoes a further change in protein composition in the two most proximal oocytes in which SYP proteins are removed and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24761;class=Protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink> kinase is recruited (<link linkend="bib68">Kaitna et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12015116-->; <link linkend="bib130">Rogers et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 11940606-->; <link linkend="bib107">Nabeshima et al., 2005</link>)<!--:PMID 15738262-->. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24761;class=Protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink> recruitment to diakinesis bivalents is required for homolog segregation during the first meiotic division (<link linkend="bib68">Kaitna et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12015116-->; <link linkend="bib130">Rogers et al., 2002</link>)<!--:PMID 11940606-->. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> is phosphorylated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24761;class=Protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink> in vitro (<link linkend="bib130">Rogers et al., 2002</link>)<!--:PMID 11940606-->, suggesting that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> phosphorylation may be important for cohesion release in vivo. In fact, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> staining in the short arm of bivalents becomes weaker during late diakinesis and prometaphase (<link linkend="bib130">Rogers et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 11940606-->; <link linkend="bib19">de Carvalho et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18923084-->; <link linkend="bib55">Harper et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22018922-->; <link linkend="bib150">Severson and Meyer, 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25171895-->, and this reduction in <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> staining requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24761;class=Protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib150">Severson and Meyer, 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25171895-->. By metaphase I, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> staining is greatly reduced in the short arm of bivalents (<link linkend="bib19">de Carvalho et al., 2008</link>)<!--:PMID 18923084-->, but use of a different anti-REC-8 antibody shows clearly detectable <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> staining in the short arm of most metaphase I bivalents (<link linkend="bib114">Pasierbek et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11390355-->; <link linkend="bib130">Rogers et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 11940606-->;; <link linkend="bib31">Cortes et al., 2015</link>)<!--:PMID 25848744-->. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35852;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-3</ulink>/4 cohesin complexes that remain bound on the short arm of metaphase I chromosomes must be removed at anaphase onset. A likely candidate for this activity is the conserved protease separase, which is required for proper meiotic chromosome segregation (<link linkend="bib154">Siomos et al., 2001</link>)<!--:PMID 11728305-->. Interestingly, separase is not required for the late prophase removal of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35852;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-3</ulink>/4 cohesin described above (<link linkend="bib150">Severson and Meyer, 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25171895-->, suggesting that distinct mechanisms mediate cohesin removal during <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> meiosis. Phosphorylation of kleisin subunits is required for their cleavage by separase in yeast mitotic and meiotic cells (reviewed in <link linkend="bib52">Haarhuis et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25313959-->, and it has been proposed that AIR-2-dependent phosphorylation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> complexes may render them sensitive to separase (<link linkend="bib130">Rogers et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 11940606-->; <link linkend="bib19">de Carvalho et al., 2008</link>)<!--:PMID 18923084-->. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24761;class=Protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink> activity in the long arms of diakinesis bivalents is antagonized by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01319;class=Protein" role="_blank">GSP-2</ulink> (protein phosphatase 1), whose depletion leads to the premature separation of sister chromatids during anaphase I (<link linkend="bib68">Kaitna et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12015116-->; <link linkend="bib130">Rogers et al., 2002</link>)<!--:PMID 11940606-->. Similarly, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink>/2 and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15580;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAB-1</ulink> prevent the inappropriate recruitment of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24761;class=Protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink> to the long arm of the bivalents, and their absence causes untimely removal of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> and premature release of sister chromatid cohesion during the first meiotic division (<link linkend="bib19">de Carvalho et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18923084-->; <link linkend="bib93">Martinez-Perez et al., 2008</link>)<!--:PMID 18923085-->. Since the ability of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15580;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAB-1</ulink> to antagonize <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24761;class=Protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink> localization depends on the presence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01319;class=Protein" role="_blank">GSP-2</ulink>, and since <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15580;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAB-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01319;class=Protein" role="_blank">GSP-2</ulink> physically interact, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15580;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAB-1</ulink> likely acts by recruiting <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01319;class=Protein" role="_blank">GSP-2</ulink> to chromosomes (<link linkend="bib19">de Carvalho et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18923084-->; <link linkend="bib168">Tzur et al., 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 22927794-->.</para>
<mediaobject id="figure6" xreflabel="Figure 6">
<imageobject>
<imagedata entityref="fig6" width="4.8in" align="center"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Figure 6</phrase>
</textobject> &fig6legend;</mediaobject>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec6.2">
<title>Chromosome condensation</title>
<para>Concomitant with the changes in protein composition described above, the overall structure of chromosomes is modified by a process of chromatin compaction that starts in late pachytene and continues until the onset of the first meiotic division. This process is mediated by condensin complexes, which are structurally similar to cohesin, containing a core of two SMC proteins that associate with additional factors to modify the topology of chromosomes (reviewed in <link linkend="bib177">Wood et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20442714-->. The condensin II complex (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18083;class=Protein" role="_blank">MIX-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03287;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMC-4</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24117;class=Protein" role="_blank">HCP-6</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11156;class=Protein" role="_blank">CAPG-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30620;class=Protein" role="_blank">KLE-2</ulink>) associates with chromosomes in diplotene and is required for the compaction and resolution of chromosomes during diplotene and diakinesis, demonstrating that condensin II is essential for the remodeling of chromosomes during late meiotic prophase (<link linkend="bib53">Hagstrom et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 11914278-->; <link linkend="bib21">Chan et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15557118-->; <link linkend="bib35">Csankovszki et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19119011-->; <link linkend="bib99">Mets and Meyer, 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19781752-->. In diakinesis oocytes, condensin II decorates chromatin on the long and short arms of the bivalents. On the other hand, depletion of condensin I (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18083;class=Protein" role="_blank">MIX-1</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE03287;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMC-4</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE08398;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-26</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31734;class=Protein" role="_blank">DPY-28</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE09790;class=Protein" role="_blank">CAPG-1</ulink>) does not induce gross defects in the condensation or individualization of meiotic chromosomes during late prophase, and condensin I components are only observed associated with chromosomes on the short arm of the most proximal oocyte, loading only after nuclear envelope breakdown (<link linkend="bib167">Tsai et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18198337-->; <link linkend="bib35">Csankovszki et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19119011-->; <link linkend="bib101">Meyer, 2010</link><!--:PMID 20381335-->; <link linkend="bib29">Collette et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22025633-->; also see X-chromosome dosage compensation). During the meiotic divisions, depletion of condensin I components induces mild defects that are only evident during the second meiotic division (<link linkend="bib35">Csankovszki et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19119011-->, while depletion of condensin II induces dramatic defects in both meiotic divisions, including chromatin bridges between separating chromosomes in anaphase I and II (<link linkend="bib21">Chan et al., 2004</link><!--:PMID 15557118-->; <link linkend="bib35">Csankovszki et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19119011-->. Thus, the reshaping of chromosomes by condensin during late prophase is an essential aspect of meiosis.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec7">
<title>Surveillance mechanisms during prophase I</title>
<para>The formation of COs during prophase I of meiosis is essential to promote the accurate segregation of chromosomes into the gametes. Therefore, multiple processes that promote the formation of COs, including the establishment of the SC and the progression of recombination, are closely monitored. Failures of those processes lead to a meiotic progression delay for the correction of errors and/or the induction of apoptosis to eliminate meiocytes where errors persist.</para>
<sect2 id="sec7.1">
<title>Monitoring of SC assembly</title>
<para>The assembly of the SC plays a central role in mediating meiotic progression. The absence of synapsis on one or more chromosomes causes nuclei to delay exit from zygotene, resulting in a prolongation of chromosome movement and chromosome clustering (<link linkend="bib87">MacQueen et al., 2002</link><!--:PMID 12231631-->; <link linkend="bib122">Phillips et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 16360035-->; <link linkend="bib18">Carlton et al., 2006</link><!--:PMID 16462941-->; <link linkend="bib120">Phillips and Dernburg, 2006</link><!--:PMID 17141157-->; <link linkend="bib117">Penkner et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913286-->; <link linkend="bib141">Sato et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913287-->; <link linkend="bib11">Baudrimont et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 21124819-->. This delay requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink>: <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002032;class=Gene" role="_blank">htp-1</ulink>; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006376;class=Gene" role="_blank">syp-2</ulink></emphasis> double mutants have no zygotene arrest, leading to the proposal that <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink> participates in the generation of an inhibitory signal that blocks exit from zygotene until the SC is installed between all homologous pairs (<link linkend="bib94">Martinez-Perez and Villeneuve, 2005</link>)<!--:PMID 16291646-->. This inhibitory signal appears to involve a soluble pool of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink>, since a mutant version of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink> that fails to associate with axial elements still supports zygotene arrest in SC-deficient mutants (<link linkend="bib153">Silva et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25455309-->. SC assembly appears to directly antagonize the inhibitory signal that blocks early meiotic progression, as improper SC assembly between sister chromatids in <emphasis role="italic">syp-3(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088873;class=Variation" role="_blank">me42</ulink>)</emphasis> mutants results in normal meiotic progression (<link linkend="bib156">Smolikov et al., 2007b</link>)<!--:PMID 17565948-->.</para>
<para><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27297;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHK-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink> protein kinases have essential roles in organizing and monitoring features of chromosome end mobilization (<link linkend="bib55">Harper et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22018922-->; <link linkend="bib77">Labella et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 22018921-->. Coincident with chromosome movements in leptotene/zygotene, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> shows prominent phosphorylation at several residues in its nuclear amino-terminus that are dependent on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27297;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHK-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib117">Penkner et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19913286-->; <link linkend="bib55">Harper et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22018922-->; <link linkend="bib77">Labella et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 22018921-->. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> serine-12 phosphorylation is restricted to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> molecules concentrated at PCs, whereas <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> phosphorylated at other residues is found throughout the entire nuclear envelope (<link linkend="bib117">Penkner et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19913286-->. Although PC mobilization still takes place when <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> is rendered non-phosphorylatable, synapsis proceeds at a slower rate. In addition, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> phosphorylation is required to sustain <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink> recruitment to PC attachments in the absence of synapsis; this suggests that phosphorylation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> can prolong the time window of chromosome movement (<link linkend="bib176">Woglar et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23505384-->. The interdependency of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> phosphorylation by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink> recruitment by phospho-SUN-1 therefore establishes a positive feedback loop to sustain chromosome end-led mobility for as long as necessary to complete synapsis.</para>
<para>In addition to prolonging PC-mediated chromosome movement, the presence of unsynapsed PCs also triggers apoptosis during oocyte meiosis. Induction of this apoptosis by unpaired PCs requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01547;class=Protein" role="_blank">PCH-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib13">Bhalla and Dernburg, 2005</link>)<!--:PMID 16339446-->. Synapsis at PCs is monitored with the help of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27781;class=Protein" role="_blank">MES-4</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE30503;class=Protein" role="_blank">MET-1</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27781;class=Protein" role="_blank">MES-4</ulink> alone for the X chromosome) (<link linkend="bib80">Lamelza and Bhalla, 2012</link>)<!--:PMID 23166523-->.</para>
<para>In males (chromosomally XO), the single X chromosome remains partnerless during meiosis and thus needs to be shielded from the mechanisms that recognize asynapsed chromosomes and induce delays in meiotic progression (<link linkend="bib67">Jaramillo-Lambert et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20008570-->. The single X chromosome in males assumes a condensed state and is enriched for repressive chromatin modifiers that are important for shielding the single X from the checkpoint machinery (<link linkend="bib22">Checchi and Engebrecht, 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 21909284-->. Transient pseudosynapsis of X chromosome sister chromatids has been observed and has been proposed to mask the X from being recognized as partnerless (<link linkend="bib23">Checchi et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 24939994-->. Furthermore, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> aggregates at the single X chromosome in males are not phosphorylated by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink>, despite its localization to the X PC (<link linkend="bib176">Woglar et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23505384-->.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec7.2">
<title>Monitoring of recombination progression</title>
<para>Successful completion of meiosis requires formation of COs between each chromosome pair; this in turn requires formation of at least one DSB per homolog pair. However, DSBs also represent possible sources of damage to the genome, and thus, <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has multiple mechanisms to monitor formation of DSBs and downstream recombination intermediates in order to limit the numbers of DSBs that form, to assure that sufficient DSBs are generated to ensure CO formation, and to prevent germ cells with persistent DNA damage from proceeding to the oocyte meiotic divisions.</para>
<para>A growing body of evidence from multiple organisms suggests that CO intermediates function as a rheostat for the DSB machinery, maintaining DSB formation when levels are low and turning it off when DSBs are high (<link linkend="bib81">Lange et al., 2011</link><!--:PMID 22002603-->; <link linkend="bib51">Gray et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23902647-->; <link linkend="bib69">Kauppi et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23599345-->; <link linkend="bib166">Thacker et al., 2014</link><!--:PMID 24717437-->; <link linkend="bib47">Garcia et al., 2015</link>)<!--:PMID 25539084-->. In <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis>, evidence for such a feedback system comes from analysis of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> and from <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05571;class=Protein" role="_blank">DSB-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44432;class=Protein" role="_blank">DSB-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib136">Rosu et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23950729-->; <link linkend="bib162">Stamper et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23990794-->, two proteins that are required for efficient DSB formation and that localize to chromosomes during early meiotic prophase concomitant with DSB formation. Similar to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> phosphorylation, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05571;class=Protein" role="_blank">DSB-1</ulink>/2 chromatin loading depends on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27297;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHK-2</ulink> (<link linkend="bib136">Rosu et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23950729-->; <link linkend="bib162">Stamper et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23990794-->. In synapsis- or recombination-defective mutants, the zone of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> phosphorylation and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05571;class=Protein" role="_blank">DSB-1</ulink>/2 localization is extended (<link linkend="bib162">Stamper et al., 2013</link><!--:PMID 23990794-->; <link linkend="bib176">Woglar et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23505384-->, suggesting the presence of a checkpoint-like feedback system that monitors formation of CO intermediates and retains nuclei in a DSB permissive state until enough CO-fated events are formed. Failure to form a CO intermediate between the X chromosomes (as seen in <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001864;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-5</ulink></emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001867;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-8</ulink></emphasis> mutants) results in delayed meiotic progression, suggesting that this feedback system is capable of detecting the absence of crossing over (or a CO-fated intermediate) on a single chromosome pair (<link linkend="bib98">Meneely et al., 2012</link><!--:PMID 22267496-->; <link linkend="bib162">Stamper et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23990794-->. (<link linkend="bib23">Checchi et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 24939994--> found that the <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49311;class=Protein" role="_blank">ATM-1</ulink> protein kinase plays a conserved role in limiting DSB formation, as mutants defective in <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000227;class=Gene" role="_blank">atm-1</ulink></emphasis> have elevated levels of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> foci; however, whether <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49311;class=Protein" role="_blank">ATM-1</ulink> activation is part of the above-described feedback mechanism or represents a distinct mechanism for limiting DSB numbers remains an open question.</para>
<para>During oogenesis, cells with unrepaired recombination intermediates are subjected to apoptosis dependent on the DNA damage sensors <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29376;class=Protein" role="_blank">MRT-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33217;class=Protein" role="_blank">HPR-9</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE20999;class=Protein" role="_blank">HUS-1</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29805;class=Protein" role="_blank">CEP-1</ulink>, the p53 homolog (<link linkend="bib48">Gartner et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 10882129-->; <link linkend="bib144">Schumacher et al., 2001</link>)<!--:PMID 11696333-->; (also see <ulink url="http://www.wormbook.org/chapters/www_germlinesurvival/germlinesurvival.html">Germline survival and apoptosis</ulink>). Mutants with high levels of resected single stranded DNA, such as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004297;class=Gene" role="_blank">rad-51</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012767;class=Gene" role="_blank">fcd-2</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000264;class=Gene" role="_blank">brc-1</ulink>,</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020316;class=Gene" role="_blank">brc-2</ulink></emphasis>, elicit massive apoptosis (<link linkend="bib48">Gartner et al., 2000</link><!--:PMID 10882129-->; <link linkend="bib92">Martin et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15798199-->; <link linkend="bib2">Adamo et al., 2008</link><!--:PMID 18219312-->; <link linkend="bib1">Adamo et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20598602-->. Interestingly, the pro-CO factors MSH-4, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26678;class=Protein" role="_blank">MSH-5</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE43850;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZHP-3</ulink> are required for the induction of apoptosis irrespective of DNA damage checkpoint activation, as evaluated by the transcriptional activation of <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001170;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="bib152">Silva et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23832114-->. The ability of unrepaired meiotic DSBs to trigger DNA damage-checkpoint-mediated apoptosis also provides a means to cull nuclei that had entered meiotic prophase with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBPhenotype:0001882;class=Phenotype" role="_blank">aneuploidy</ulink> accumulated during the preceding mitotic divisions (<link linkend="bib163">Stevens et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 24239117-->.</para>
<para>In males, where apoptosis is not triggered, many features of damage sensing and signaling nevertheless are activated and thereby contribute to faithful processing of recombination intermediates (<link linkend="bib67">Jaramillo-Lambert et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20008570-->.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sec7.3">
<title>Proteins that promote normal prophase I progression</title>
<para>After meiotic entry (which is covered in Germline proliferation and its control) oocytes remain in G2 throughout their progression along the gonad. Progression through prophase I must be coordinated with the cell cycle and oocyte growth for proper gamete development. <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009173;class=Gene" role="_blank">prom-1</ulink></emphasis> mutants enter meiosis and express axis and SC proteins. However, the processes of pairing and synapsis are defective: few nuclei display the asymmetrical chromatin distribution characteristic of the transition zone (leptotene/zygotene), loading of axis and SC proteins is delayed, and the synapsis that eventually does occur is often between nonhomologous chromosomes (<link linkend="bib65">Jantsch et al., 2007</link>)<!--:PMID 17914060-->. One known function of the SCFprom-1 ubiquitin ligase is the degradation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33761;class=Protein" role="_blank">CYE-1</ulink>, which plays a role in the germline proliferative zone (<link linkend="bib43">Fox et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 21558371-->. It is therefore possible <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009173;class=Gene" role="_blank">prom-1</ulink></emphasis> connects meiotic events to cell cycle progression.</para>
<para>ERK/MAP kinase <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01583;class=Protein" role="_blank">MPK-1</ulink> is required for progression to late pachytene; cells lacking <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01583;class=Protein" role="_blank">MPK-1</ulink> never enter a diplotene-like state (<link linkend="bib25">Church et al., 1995</link><!--:PMID 7671816-->; <link linkend="bib79">Lackner and Kim, 1998</link>)<!--:PMID 9725833-->. This is consistent with accumulation of the phosphorylated&mdash;hence activated&mdash;form of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01583;class=Protein" role="_blank">MPK-1</ulink> in mid-pachytene (<link linkend="bib82">Lee et al., 2007</link>)<!--:PMID 18073423-->. The transition from homolog-directed DSB repair to sister-directed repair, with the accompanying loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41010;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-50</ulink> dependence for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> loading (<link linkend="sec5.6">Section 5.6</link>), depends on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01583;class=Protein" role="_blank">MPK-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib56">Hayashi et al., 2007</link>)<!--:PMID 17983271-->. A key determinant of the length of prophase during <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> oogenesis is the translational repressor <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27062;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-41</ulink>, which coordinates oocyte growth with meiotic maturation. In <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003026;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-41</ulink></emphasis> mutants pachytene cells prematurely cellularize, diplotene does not occur, and oocytes prematurely enter M phase. This premature M phase entry is elicited in part by translational derepression of a <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00315;class=Protein" role="_blank">CDK-1</ulink> inhibitor (<link linkend="bib160">Spike et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 25261698-->. For further reading on oocyte maturation and oocyte release from prophase arrest, see Control of oocyte meiotic maturation and fertilization as well as <link linkend="bib73">Kim et al., 2013</link><!--PMID 22872481-->.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec8">
<title>Chromosome segregation during the meiotic divisions</title>
<para>Proper segregation of chromosomes at meiosis I requires orientation of homologs toward opposite spindle poles and the localized release of sister chromatid cohesion from the short arms of the bivalents at anaphase onset (see <link linkend="sec6.1">Section 6.1</link>). During metaphase I, outer kinetochore components are seen forming two opposing cup-like structures that encase each half of the bivalent (<link linkend="bib63">Howe et al., 2001</link><!--:PMID 11402066-->; <link linkend="bib104">Monen et al., 2005</link>)<!--:PMID 16273096-->. This organization promotes the mono-orientation of sister chromatids on the spindle, since sister chromatids of the long arm of the bivalent are encased within the same cup-like structure and thus behave as a single unit. Mono-orientation of sister chromatids in metaphase I also requires normal sister chromatid cohesion, as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004333;class=Gene" role="_blank">rec-8</ulink></emphasis> mutants show premature separation of sisters at anaphase I (<link linkend="bib149">Severson et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19574299-->.</para>
<para>During oogenesis, meiotic chromosome segregation takes place in the context of a barrel-shaped acentriolar spindle that needs to be correctly positioned, in close association with the cortex, within the large volume of the fertilized embryo (<link linkend="bib5">Albertson and Thomson, 1993</link>)<!--:PMID 8143084-->. Proper spindle assembly in oocytes requires <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32479;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEI-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11320;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEI-2</ulink>, the components of the microtubule severing complex Katanin (<link linkend="bib90">Mains et al., 1990</link><!--:PMID 2249759-->; <link linkend="bib26">Clark-Maguire and Mains, 1994</link><!--:PMID 8150281-->; <link linkend="bib161">Srayko et al., 2000</link>)<!--:PMID 10809666-->, the kinesin <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07978;class=Protein" role="_blank">KLP-18</ulink> (<link linkend="bib148">Segbert et al., 2003</link>)<!--:PMID 12937278-->, and the calponin homology-domain protein <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15710;class=Protein" role="_blank">ASPM-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib170">van der Voet et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19219036-->; <link linkend="bib30">Connolly et al., 2014</link>)<!--:PMID 24554763-->. Correct positioning of the meiotic spindle in oocytes is a two-step process that involves translocation of the spindle to the cortex, which occurs before metaphase I, followed by a 90&deg; rotation that renders the spindle perpendicular to the cortex before the onset of anaphase I (reviewed in <link linkend="bib42">Fabritius et al., 2011</link>)<!--:PMID 20708397-->. Spindle translocation requires kinesin-1, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32479;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEI-1</ulink>, and microtubules (<link linkend="bib180">Yang et al., 2003</link><!--:PMID 12885567-->; <link linkend="bib179">Yang et al., 2005</link>)<!--:PMID 15883196-->, while spindle rotation is promoted by the anaphase promoting complex, dynein, and a complex formed by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15710;class=Protein" role="_blank">ASPM-1</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE13902;class=Protein" role="_blank">CMD-1</ulink> (<link linkend="bib179">Yang et al., 2005</link><!--:PMID 15883196-->; <link linkend="bib41">Ellefson and McNally, 2009</link><!--:PMID 19357192-->; <link linkend="bib170">van der Voet et al., 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19219036-->.</para>
<para>Detailed imaging of microtubules and kinetochores during meiosis I shows that bivalents are surrounded by robust microtubule bundles running along their sides, and that the mid-bivalent region is surrounded by a ring-like structure containing the chromosome passenger complex and the chromokinesin <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE16631;class=Protein" role="_blank">KLP-19</ulink> (<link linkend="bib174">Wignall and Villeneuve, 2009</link>)<!--:PMID 19525937-->. This suggests that lateral associations with microtubules (rather than canonical end-on kinetochore attachments) facilitate chromosome movements prior to anaphase. Although kinetochores are required for proper chromosome orientation during congression, potentially helping to align chromosomes within the lateral bundles, the migration of chromosomes during anaphase I is kinetochore independent (<link linkend="bib40">Dumont et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20729837-->. Instead, lateral microtubule associations remain intact during anaphase to facilitate segregation (<link linkend="bib105a">Muscat, et.al. 2015</link><!--: PMID 26026148-->). At anaphase onset, the mid-bivalent ring structure containing <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE16631;class=Protein" role="_blank">KLP-19</ulink> is removed from chromosomes and is left behind in the center of the spindle (<link linkend="bib40">Dumont et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20729837-->, allowing minus-end forces to drive poleward movement along lateral bundles (Muscat, et.al. 2015<!--: PMID 26026148-->). Moreover, spindle elongation also facilitates separation, potentially stimulated by another ring component, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37546;class=Protein" role="_blank">CLS-2</ulink>/CLASP (<link linkend="bib40">Dumont et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20729837-->. Kinetochores are disassembled shortly after the onset of anaphase I, and are reassembled by metaphase II. In meiosis II, each sister chromatid is encased in a cup-like kinetochore, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE16631;class=Protein" role="_blank">KLP-19</ulink> and the chromosome passenger complex localize to a ring-like structure that encircles the region of remaining contact between the two sister chromatids (<link linkend="bib174">Wignall and Villeneuve, 2009</link><!--:PMID 19525937-->; <link linkend="bib40">Dumont et al., 2010</link>)<!--:PMID 20729837-->.</para>
<para>The processes that mediate meiotic chromosome segregation differ between oogenesis and spermatogenesis (<link linkend="bib5">Albertson and Thomson, 1993</link><!--:PMID 8143084-->; <link linkend="bib151">Shakes et al., 2009</link><!--:PMID 19696886-->; <link linkend="bib174">Wignall and Villeneuve, 2009</link><!--:PMID 19525937-->; <link linkend="bib145">Schvarzstein et al., 2013</link>)<!--:PMID 23401519-->. In contrast to oocyte meiotic spindles, spermatocyte meiotic spindles assume a more traditional configuration. They have centrioles at their poles and the metaphase spindles have high microtubule density adjacent to kinetochore domains at the ends of the bivalents, indicative of end-on attachments between microtubules and kinetochores. Furthermore, anaphase separation of chromosomes in spermatocytes is driven by separation of spindle poles. Finally, completion of the meiotic divisions produces markedly different outcomes in spermatogenesis, where four functional haploid gametes are produced, and oogenesis, where one haploid gamete and two degenerate polar bodies are formed (also see Control of oocyte meiotic maturation and fertilization). Interestingly, the asymmetry of oocyte meiosis can partially correct for pre-existing trisomies, since in triplo-X animals the extra X chromosome is preferentially extruded into the first polar body, thus reducing the incidence of aneuploid progeny (<link linkend="bib31">Cortes et al., 2015</link>)<!--:PMID 25848744-->.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec9">
<title>Summary</title>
<para><emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> has proven to be a very productive organism for the study of meiosis. The excellent cytology, coupled with the ease of isolation of meiotic mutants, has contributed to our understanding of the complex series of events necessary to produce haploid gametes. However, understanding the molecular mechanisms that regulate homolog pairing, meiotic recombination, the changes in structure that chromosomes undergo during meiotic prophase, the process of chromosome segregation, and the quality control of meiosis remain important goals for future studies. The recent development of efficient transgenic tools, combined with super-resolution microscopy, long-term in vivo imaging of meiotic chromosomes, rapid methods to map recombination events, and the use of proteomic approaches means that <emphasis role="italic">C. elegans</emphasis> will remain an excellent model organism to address these questions over the coming years.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec10">
<title>Acknowledgements</title>
<para>We thank Barbara Meyer, Anne Villeneuve, and David Greenstein for critically reading the manuscript and members of the Jantsch, Martinez-Perez, and Yanowitz labs for comments and discussions. We are grateful to Patricia Hamminger, Sophia Millonigg, Alexander Woglar, and Sarah Testori for figure preparation. The authors labs were funded by the FWF (VJ), an MRC core funded grant (E M-P), NIH (JLY/VJ &amp; KJH), and the March of Dimes (JLY).</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec11">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Table 1. List of meiotic genes discussed in this chapter</emphasis></title>
<para>Genes are organized in alphabetical order and numbers in brackets indicate the section(s) within the main text where the functions of a given protein are discussed.</para>
<table id="table1" frame="all" rules="all" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" width="75">
<title/>
<tgroup cols="5">
<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/>
<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/>
<colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
<colspec colnum="4" colname="col4"/>
<colspec colnum="5" colname="col5"/>
<thead>
<row valign="bottom" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Gene Name</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Ortholog/Homolog</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Molecular Function (known or inferred)</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Subcellular Localization (if known)</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="bold">Meiotic Role</emphasis></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000099;class=Gene" role="_blank">air-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">Aurora/ IPL Kinase</entry>
<entry align="center">Kinase</entry>
<entry align="center">Recruited to the short arm of diakinesis bivalents</entry>
<entry align="center">Loss impairs chromosome segregation at meiosis I; phosphorylates <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> in vitro. (<link linkend="sec6.1">Section 6.1</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008107;class=Gene" role="_blank">aspm-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">ASPM</entry>
<entry align="center">Interaction with calmodulin and microtubules</entry>
<entry align="center">Meiotic spindles</entry>
<entry align="center">Required for proper spindle assembly in oocytes and to promote spindle rotation in a complex with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE13902;class=Protein" role="_blank">CMD-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE18951;class=Protein" role="_blank">LIN-5</ulink>. (<link linkend="sec8">Section 8</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000264;class=Gene" role="_blank">brc-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">BRCA1</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Required for intersister DSB repair (<link linkend="sec5.2.4">Section 5.2.4</link>); mutation results in high levels of resected ssDNA and massive germline apoptosis (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020316;class=Gene" role="_blank">brc-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">BRCA2</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Facilitates nuclear entry of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink>, loading of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> on ssDNA, and D loop formation (<link linkend="sec5.2.2">Section 5.2.2</link>). Mutation results in high levels of resected ssDNA and massive germline apoptosis (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009254;class=Gene" role="_blank">capg-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">hCAP-G</entry>
<entry align="center">Condensin I complex</entry>
<entry align="center">Nuclear localization in mitotic and meiotic prophase nuclei. Associates with short arm of bivalents during late diakinesis and metaphase I, and between sister chromatids at metaphase II</entry>
<entry align="center">Heterozygous null mutants show altered distribution of DSBs and COs, increased CO frequencies, and increased pachytene axis length (<link linkend="sec5.3">Section 5.3</link>). Required for chromosome segregation (<link linkend="sec6.2">Section 6.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00010093;class=Gene" role="_blank">capg-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">hCAP-G2</entry>
<entry align="center">Condensin II complex</entry>
<entry align="center">Decorates chromatin in diakinesis oocytes and during metaphase I and II</entry>
<entry align="center">Required for chromosome condensation and segregation. (<link linkend="sec6.2">Section 6.2</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004048;class=Gene" role="_blank">cep-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">p53</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA binding, transciptional activation</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">DNA damage sensing, involved in DNA damage-induced apoptosis in the germ line. (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000499;class=Gene" role="_blank">chk-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">CHK2</entry>
<entry align="center">Kinase</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Master regulator of early prophase events. Required for loading of autosomal PC proteins (ZIMs); required for formation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> aggregates (<link linkend="sec3.2">Section 3.2</link>). Required for homolog pairing and normal loading of SC in early prophase (<link linkend="sec4.3.1">Section 4.3.1</link>). Required for N-terminal phosphorylation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> shortly after meiotic entry (<link linkend="sec7.1">Section 7.1</link>). Required for DSB formation and loading of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE05571;class=Protein" role="_blank">DSB-1</ulink>/2 (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000592;class=Gene" role="_blank">coh-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">Rad21L/Rec8</entry>
<entry align="center">Meiosis-specific kleisin subunit of cohesin complex</entry>
<entry align="center">Chromosome axes</entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35852;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27409;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-4</ulink> are highly identical and functionally redundant. Loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35852;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-3</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27409;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-4</ulink> impairs CO formation and SC assembly. Loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35852;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27409;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-4</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> causes gross defects in sister chromatid cohesion and prevents assembly of axial elements. (<link linkend="sec4.1">Section 4.1</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021560;class=Gene" role="_blank">coh-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000592;class=Gene" role="_blank">coh-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000592;class=Gene" role="_blank">coh-3</ulink></emphasis> (above).</entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000592;class=Gene" role="_blank">coh-3</ulink></emphasis> (above).</entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000592;class=Gene" role="_blank">coh-3</ulink></emphasis> (above).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008082;class=Gene" role="_blank">com-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">CtlP/Sae2</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair; resection of DSBs</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Promotes processing of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49824;class=Protein" role="_blank">SPO-11</ulink> DSBs to facilitate <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> loading; suppresses NHEJ. (<link linkend="sec5.2.1">Section 5.2.1</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00022172;class=Gene" role="_blank">cosa-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">CTND1</entry>
<entry align="center">CO designation</entry>
<entry align="center">Late pachytene&mdash;one focus per chromosome pair (presumed to mark CO position)</entry>
<entry align="center">Designates recombination intermediates for CO formation; required for CO formation. (<link linkend="sec5.2.3">Section 5.2.3</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020068;class=Gene" role="_blank">cra-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">NAA25</entry>
<entry align="center">N(alpha)-acetyl-transferase</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes to meiotic nuclei throughout prophase</entry>
<entry align="center">Required to promote normal loading of SC proteins (<link linkend="sec4.3.1">Section 4.3.1</link>) and for regulation of histone acetylation and DSB formation (<link linkend="sec5.1">Section 5.1</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000871;class=Gene" role="_blank">cye-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">CCNE1</entry>
<entry align="center">E-type cyclin</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Promotes mitotic proliferation in the distal germ line. Negatively regulated in meiotic cells by <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41801;class=Protein" role="_blank">PROM-1</ulink> ubiquitin ligase. (<link linkend="sec7.3">Section 7.3</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001085;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-26</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">hCAP-H</entry>
<entry align="center">Condensin I complex</entry>
<entry align="center">Nuclear localization in mitotic and meiotic prophase nuclei. Associates with short arm of metaphase I bivalents and between sister chromatids at metaphase II</entry>
<entry align="center">Heterozygous null mutants show altered distribution of DSBs and COs, increased CO frequencies, and increased pachytene axis length (<link linkend="sec5.3">Section 5.3</link>). Required for chromosome segregation (<link linkend="sec6.2">Section 6.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001087;class=Gene" role="_blank">dpy-28</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">hCAP-D2</entry>
<entry align="center">Condensin I complex</entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic">dpy-</emphasis>26 (above).</entry>
<entry align="center">Heterozygotes same as <emphasis role="italic">dpy-</emphasis>26 (above). Homozygous mutants of hypomorph allele show changes in distribution of DSBs and COs without altering CO frequency (<link linkend="sec5.3">Section 5.3</link>). Required for chromosome segregation (<link linkend="sec6.2">Section 6.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008580;class=Gene" role="_blank">dsb-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes to chromatin in transition zone and early pachytene nuclei</entry>
<entry align="center">Involved in DSB formation; regulates competence for DSB formation (<link linkend="sec5.1">Section 5.1</link>). Localizes to chromosomes, dependent on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27297;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHK-2</ulink>. Localization prolonged in synapsis or recombination mutants; suggests a role in maintenance of DSB-permissive state (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00194892;class=Gene" role="_blank">dsb-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008580;class=Gene" role="_blank">dsb-1</ulink></emphasis> (above).</entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008580;class=Gene" role="_blank">dsb-1</ulink></emphasis> (above). Loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE44432;class=Protein" role="_blank">DSB-2</ulink> from chromosomes may correlate with switch from homolog to sister repair (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001170;class=Gene" role="_blank">egl-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Positive regulation of apoptosis</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Positive regulator of apoptosis. (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009731;class=Gene" role="_blank">exo-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">exo1</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair; exonuclease</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Involved in resection of meiotic DSBs. (<link linkend="sec5.2.1">Section 5.2.1</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00012767;class=Gene" role="_blank">fcd-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">FANCD2</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Mutations result in high levels of resected ssDNA and massive germline apoptosis. (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001748;class=Gene" role="_blank">gsp-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">PP1CA</entry>
<entry align="center">Protein Phosphatase I</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Antagonizes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24761;class=Protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink> recruitment to chromosomes and physically interacts with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE15580;class=Protein" role="_blank">LAB-1</ulink>; loss leads to premature sister chromatid separation at Anaphase I. (<link linkend="sec6.1">Section 6.1</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00011819;class=Gene" role="_blank">hal-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Localized to the nucleoplasm in all germline nuclei.</entry>
<entry align="center">Promotes homolog pairing, prevents inappropriate loading of SYP proteins; required for DSB formation; required for mechanism that couples cessation of chromosome movement with SC assembly. (<link linkend="sec4.3.1">Section 4.3.1</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001833;class=Gene" role="_blank">hcp-6</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">hCAP-D3</entry>
<entry align="center">Condensin II complex</entry>
<entry align="center">Associates with chromatin from diplotene, persisting during metaphase I and II</entry>
<entry align="center">Required for chromosome condensation and segregation. (<link linkend="sec6.2">Section 6.2</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021905;class=Gene" role="_blank">helq-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">HELQ</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair; helicase</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Promotes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> turnover (removal of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> from D loops); redundant with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE00094;class=Protein" role="_blank">RFS-1</ulink>. (<link linkend="sec5.2.2">Section 5.2.2</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001862;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">HORMAD1; Hop1</entry>
<entry align="center">HORMA-domain protein; Component of chromosome axis</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes to axial elements throughout meiotic prophase</entry>
<entry align="center">HORMA domain flanked by short N- and C- termini; required for homolog recognition. Promotes use of homolog as DSB repair template; absence leads to dramatic reduction in SC. Required to prevent premature centriole disengagement in spermatocyte meiosis II (<link linkend="sec4.2">Section 4.2</link>.) Non-null mutations can affect chromosome axis integrity and regulation of meiotic recombination (<link linkend="sec5.5">Section 5.5</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001864;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-5</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">promotion of DSB formation</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes to autosomes from mitotic region through late pachytene</entry>
<entry align="center">Required for normal DSB formation on <emphasis role="italic">X</emphasis> chromosomes. mutation reduces DSB levels 4-fold, but only <emphasis role="italic">X</emphasis> typically lacks CO. Required for normal distribution of COs genome-wide (<link linkend="sec5.1">Section 5.1</link>, <link linkend="sec5.3">Section 5.3</link>, <link linkend="sec5.4">Section 5.4</link>). In absence, chromosome clustering/mobility extended and meiotic progression delayed (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001865;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-6</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">BLM; RecQ</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair; Holliday junction resolvase</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Resolvase activity (in conjunction with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24855;class=Protein" role="_blank">XPF-1</ulink>). Thought to enforce crossover-biased resolution of CO-designated intermediates (<link linkend="sec5.2.5">Section 5.2.5</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001867;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-8</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">X chromosome pairing and synapsis</entry>
<entry align="center">Binds X pairing center</entry>
<entry align="center">Required for homolog alignment and synapsis of <emphasis role="italic">X.</emphasis> Recruitment site for polo-like kinases <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink> (<link linkend="sec3.2">Section 3.2</link>, <link linkend="sec4.3">Section 4.3</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001874;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-17</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Promotion of DSB formation</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes to chromatin throughout the germ line</entry>
<entry align="center">Mutants accumulate aberrant histone modifications and display impaired DSB formation. Required for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE09062;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-5</ulink> localization to chromosomes. (<link linkend="sec5.1">Section 5.1</link>, <link linkend="sec5.3">Section 5.3</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00011415;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-18</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">SLX4</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair; Holliday junction resolution</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Scaffold for resolvases. (<link linkend="sec5.2.5">Section 5.2.5</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00022390;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-19</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Involved in homolog recognition, defects in <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00022390;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-19</ulink></emphasis> mutants worsen with age. (<link linkend="sec3.3">Section 3.3</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001997;class=Gene" role="_blank">hpr-9</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">RAD9</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA damage sensing; 9-1-1 complex</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">DNA damage sensing, involved in DNA damage-induced apoptosis in the germ line. (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002032;class=Gene" role="_blank">htp-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">HORMAD1; Hop1 (yeast)</entry>
<entry align="center">HORMA-domain protein; Component of chromosome axis</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes to axial elements throughout meiotic prophase, but becomes restricted to the long arms of bivalents during late pachytene. Large pool also present as nuclear soluble protein.</entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37734;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-2</ulink> (below), except <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink> is required for homolog recognition, to prevent non-homologous synapsis, and for CO formation. Promotes use of homolog as DSB repair template (<link linkend="sec4.2">Section 4.2</link>). Thought to help generate inhibitory signal that blocks zygotene exit until all homologous pairs have SC installed (<link linkend="sec7.1">Section 7.1</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002033;class=Gene" role="_blank">htp-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">HORMAD1; Hop1 (yeast)</entry>
<entry align="center">HORMA-domain protein; Component of chromosome axis</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes to axial elements throughout meiotic prophase, but becomes restricted to the long arms of bivalents during late pachytene.</entry>
<entry align="center">HORMA domain flanked by short N- and C- termini. <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37734;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-2</ulink> are 82% identical; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37734;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-2</ulink> is largely redundant with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink>. Together <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37734;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-2</ulink> are required for regulated cohesion release during meiotic divisions (<link linkend="sec6.1">Section 6.1</link>) and to prevent premature centriole disengagement during meiosis II in spermatogenesis (<link linkend="sec4.2">Section 4.2</link>). Loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37734;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-2</ulink> does not affect pairing or CO formation (<link linkend="sec4.2">Section 4.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002034;class=Gene" role="_blank">htp-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">HORMAD1; Hop1 (yeast)</entry>
<entry align="center">HORMA-domain protein; Component of chromosome axis</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes to nuclei in the mitotic compartment of the germ line. Localizes to axial elements throughout meiotic prophase</entry>
<entry align="center">HORMA domain flanked by short N-terminus and long C-terminus. Component of meiotic chromosome axis, required for efficient DSB induction. Required for loading of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE07625;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-3</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31692;class=Protein" role="_blank">HTP-1</ulink>/2, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> cohesin, for SC assembly, and for acquisition of posttranslational modifications on axis-associated chromatin. (<link linkend="sec4.2">Section 4.2</link>, <link linkend="sec4.3">Section 4.3</link>). Promotes DSB formation (<link linkend="sec5.1">Section 5.1</link>). Antagonizes separation of axial elements in early-mid pachytene (<link linkend="sec5.6">Section 5.6</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002042;class=Gene" role="_blank">hus-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">HUS1</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA damage sensing; 9-1-1 complex</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes to chromatin following DNA damage</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA damage sensing, involved in DNA damage-induced apoptosis in the germ line. (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016202;class=Gene" role="_blank">kle-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">hCAP-H2</entry>
<entry align="center">Condensin II complex</entry>
<entry align="center">Decorates chromatin in diakinesis oocytes and during metaphase I and II</entry>
<entry align="center">Heterozygous null mutants show altered distribution of DSBs and COs, increased CO frequencies, and increased pachytene axis length (<link linkend="sec5.3">Section 5.3</link>). Required for chromosome condensation and segregation. (<link linkend="sec6.2">Section 6.2</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002228;class=Gene" role="_blank">klp-18</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Kinesin</entry>
<entry align="center">Meiotic spindles; higher concentration at spindle poles</entry>
<entry align="center">Required for assembly of acentrosomal spindles in oocytes. (<link linkend="sec8">Section 8</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002229;class=Gene" role="_blank">klp-19</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Chromokinesin</entry>
<entry align="center">Forms ring-like structure around mid-bivalent region in meiosis I, and around region of remaining contact between sister chromatids in meiosis I</entry>
<entry align="center">Mediates anti-poleward chromosome movement via lateral microtubules. (<link linkend="sec8">Section 8</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00007278;class=Gene" role="_blank">lab-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Targets <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01319;class=Protein" role="_blank">GSP-2</ulink> to chromosomes</entry>
<entry align="center">Associates with axial elements and becomes restricted to the long arms of diakinesis bivalents</entry>
<entry align="center">Axial element component. Targets phosphatase 1 (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE01319;class=Protein" role="_blank">GSP-2</ulink>) to chromosomes and antagonizes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE24761;class=Protein" role="_blank">AIR-2</ulink> recruitment (<link linkend="sec6.1">Section 6.1</link>). Required for full SC assembly and for normal sister chromatid cohesion (<link linkend="sec4.1">Section 4.1</link>, <link linkend="sec4.3.1">Section 4.3.1</link>). Regulates release of sister chromatid cohesion during the first meiotic division (<link linkend="sec6.1">Section 6.1</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003026;class=Gene" role="_blank">lin-41</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Translational repressor</entry>
<entry align="center">Present, mostly in cytoplasm, from mid pachytene until oocyte maturation</entry>
<entry align="center">Coordinates oocyte growth with meiotic maturation. Required to prevent premature entrance into M phase. (<link linkend="sec7.3">Section 7.3</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003183;class=Gene" role="_blank">mei-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">KATNAL1</entry>
<entry align="center">Microtubule severing</entry>
<entry align="center">Spindles and chromosomes during the meiotic divisions</entry>
<entry align="center">With <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11320;class=Protein" role="_blank">MEI-2</ulink> forms the katanin microtubule severing complex. Required for proper assembly and positioning of meiotic spindle in oocytes. (<link linkend="sec8">Section 8</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003184;class=Gene" role="_blank">mei-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Microtubule severing</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes in the cytoplasm of late diakinesis oocytes and to spindles and chromatin during meiotic divisions</entry>
<entry align="center">Same as for <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003183;class=Gene" role="_blank">mei-1</ulink></emphasis> (above).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003222;class=Gene" role="_blank">mes-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">WHSC1; SEDB1</entry>
<entry align="center">Histone methyltransferase</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes to autosomes in mitotic region, late pachytene, and oocytes</entry>
<entry align="center">Involved in monitoring synapsis of autosomes and X chromosomes. (<link linkend="sec7.1">Section 7.1</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003367;class=Gene" role="_blank">mix-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">SMC2</entry>
<entry align="center">Condensin I and II complexes</entry>
<entry align="center">Associates with chromatin from diplotene (condensin II), and with the short arm of metaphase I bivalents and between sister chomatids during metaphase II (condensin I)</entry>
<entry align="center">Heterozygous null mutants show altered distribution of DSBs and COs, increased CO frequencies, and increased pachytene axis length (<link linkend="sec5.3">Section 5.3</link>). Required for chromosome condensation and segregation (<link linkend="sec6.2">Section 6.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016603;class=Gene" role="_blank">met-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">SETD2</entry>
<entry align="center">Histone methyltransferase</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Involved in monitoring synapsis of autosomes. (<link linkend="sec7.1">Section 7.1</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00019883;class=Gene" role="_blank">met-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">SETDB1</entry>
<entry align="center">Histone methyltransferase</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Shields univalent <emphasis role="italic">X</emphasis> in males from synapsis checkpoint. (<link linkend="sec7.1">Section 7.1</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003401;class=Gene" role="_blank">mpk-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">ERK</entry>
<entry align="center">MAP kinase</entry>
<entry align="center">Phosphorylated form (active) present in mid pachytene</entry>
<entry align="center">Required for progression to late pachytene; mutants never enter diplotene-like state. Regulates transition in mode of DSB repair. (<link linkend="sec7.3">Section 7.3</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003405;class=Gene" role="_blank">mre-11</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">MRE11A</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair. Nuclease; forms complex with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41010;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-50</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Required for efficient formation of meiotic DSBs and for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> loading to <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE49824;class=Protein" role="_blank">SPO-11</ulink> DSBs (<link linkend="sec5.1">Section 5.1</link>, <link linkend="sec5.2.1">Section 5.2.1</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003406;class=Gene" role="_blank">mrg-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">Chromo-domain protein</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes to autosomes</entry>
<entry align="center">Plays a role in non-pairing center mediated homolog alignment. (<link linkend="sec3.2">Section 3.2</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003420;class=Gene" role="_blank">msh-4</ulink> (<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001872;class=Gene" role="_blank">him-14</ulink>)</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">MSH4</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair; CO designation</entry>
<entry align="center">Early pachytene - multiple foci per chromosome. Late pachytene, one focus per chromosome (presumed to mark CO position)</entry>
<entry align="center">Forms a heterodimer with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26678;class=Protein" role="_blank">MSH-5</ulink>. Stabilizes CO intermediates to promote CO outcomes (<link linkend="sec5.2.3">Section 5.2.3</link>). Required for induction of apoptosis (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003421;class=Gene" role="_blank">msh-5</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">MSH5</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair; CO designation</entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003420;class=Gene" role="_blank">msh-4</ulink></emphasis> (above).</entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003420;class=Gene" role="_blank">msh-4</ulink></emphasis> (above).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016602;class=Gene" role="_blank">mus-81</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">MUS81</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair; Holliday junction resolvase</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Resolvase activity (in conjunction with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11216;class=Protein" role="_blank">SLX-1</ulink>). (<link linkend="sec5.2.5">Section 5.2.5</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008641;class=Gene" role="_blank">pch-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">TRIP13</entry>
<entry align="center">AAA-ATPase</entry>
<entry align="center">Forms foci in germline nuclei before transition zone, and SC-like tracks during pachytene</entry>
<entry align="center">Restricts SC assembly: SC assembly accelerated in mutants (<link linkend="sec4.3.1">Section 4.3.1</link>). Required for induction of apoptosis when synapsis fails (<link linkend="sec7.1">Section 7.1</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004042;class=Gene" role="_blank">plk-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">PLK1</entry>
<entry align="center">Polo-like kinase</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes to pairing centers, specially in absence of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">Can partially replace meiotic functions of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink> in promoting pairing and SC assembly. (<link linkend="sec3.2">Section 3.2</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004043;class=Gene" role="_blank">plk-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">PLK1</entry>
<entry align="center">Polo-like kinase</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes to pairing centers in early pachytene and to the SC in mid pachytene</entry>
<entry align="center">Induces nuclear envelope reorganization; <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32088;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink> relocate into aggregates at clustered PC ends of chromosomes. Required for N-terminal phosphorylation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> shortly after meiotic entry (<link linkend="sec3.2">Section 3.2</link>). Involved in feedback loop to sustain chromosome end-led mobility until completion of synapsis (<link linkend="sec7.1">Section 7.1</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009173;class=Gene" role="_blank">prom-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">FBXO47</entry>
<entry align="center">F-box protein</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Required for homolog pairing, normal assembly of SC, DSB repair; involved in degradation of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE33761;class=Protein" role="_blank">CYE-1</ulink>. (<link linkend="sec7.3">Section 7.3</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003417;class=Gene" role="_blank">mrt-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">RAD1</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA damage sensing; 9-1-1 complex</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">DNA damage sensing, involved in DNA damage-induced apoptosis in the germ line. (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004296;class=Gene" role="_blank">rad-50</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004296;class=Gene" role="_blank">RAD50</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair; forms complex with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE37459;class=Protein" role="_blank">MRE-11</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Required for formation and repair of meiotic DSBs (<link linkend="sec5.1">Section 5.1</link>, <link linkend="sec5.2.1">Section 5.2.1</link>). Required for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> loading to DSBs (and interhomolog CO formation) (<link linkend="sec5.2.1">Section 5.2.1</link>), but only in early to mid-pachytene; in late pachytene, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41010;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-50</ulink> is not required for repair (which is preferentially targeted to sister) (<link linkend="sec5.6">Section 5.6</link>, <link linkend="sec7.3">Section 7.3</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004297;class=Gene" role="_blank">rad-51</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">Rad51; DMC1</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair; catalyzes strand invasion</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes to sites of DSBs</entry>
<entry align="center">Promotes DNA strand invasion (<link linkend="sec5.2.1">Section 5.2.1</link>, <link linkend="sec5.2.2">Section 5.2.2</link>, <link linkend="sec5.6">Section 5.6</link>). Mutation results in high levels of resected ssDNA and massive germline apoptosis (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004298;class=Gene" role="_blank">rad-54</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">Rad54</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair; DEAD-like helicase family</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Promotes removal of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> from recombination intermediates (<link linkend="sec5.2.2">Section 5.2.2</link>). Mutation traps DSBR intermediates as <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> filaments (<link linkend="sec5.3">Section 5.3</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004332;class=Gene" role="_blank">rec-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Required for normal distribution of COs (but not frequency) (<link linkend="sec5.3">Section 5.3</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004333;class=Gene" role="_blank">rec-8</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">Rec8</entry>
<entry align="center">Meiosis specific kleisin subunit of cohesin complex</entry>
<entry align="center">Chromosome axes</entry>
<entry align="center">Required for CO formation and to prevent SC formation between sister chromatids (<link linkend="sec4.1">Section 4.1</link>). Loss of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE35852;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-3</ulink>, and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27409;class=Protein" role="_blank">COH-4</ulink> impairs axial element assembly and causes gross defects in sister chromatid cohesion (<link linkend="sec4.1">Section 4.1</link>). Regulated <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> removal during late prophase and metaphase I required for two step-release of cohesion (<link linkend="sec6.1">Section 6.1</link>). Required for mono-orientation of sister chromatids on the first meiotic spindle (<link linkend="sec8">Section 8</link>). Required to prevent premature centriole disengagement during meiosis II in spermatogenesis (<link linkend="sec4.2">Section 4.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004342;class=Gene" role="_blank">rfs-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">RAD51C</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair; interacts with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> paralog; Promotes <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink> turnover (removal of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE29064;class=Protein" role="_blank">RAD-51</ulink>); redundant with <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00021905;class=Gene" role="_blank">helq-1</ulink></emphasis> (<link linkend="sec5.2.2">Section 5.2.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00017546;class=Gene" role="_blank">rpa-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">RPA1</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair; single-strand binding protein</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Binds to ssDNA at DSB sites in <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00020316;class=Gene" role="_blank">brc-2</ulink></emphasis> mutants; may also bind in WT. (<link linkend="sec5.2.2">Section 5.2.2</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00009124;class=Gene" role="_blank">rtel-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">RTEL1</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair; DNA helicase</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Anti-recombinase: disrupts D loops in vitro, promotes alternative forms of repair (most likely SDSA; shunts a subset of DSBR intermediates into NCO repair) (<link linkend="sec5.2.2">Section 5.2.2</link>, <link linkend="sec5.3">Section 5.3</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic">scc-2</emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">SCC2</entry>
<entry align="center">Cohesin loader</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Mutants fail to load to cohesin and to assemble axial elements and the SC. (<link linkend="sec4.1">Section 4.1</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004738;class=Gene" role="_blank">scc-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">SCC3</entry>
<entry align="center">Cohesin component</entry>
<entry align="center">Chromosome axes</entry>
<entry align="center">Common to all cohesin complexes. Required for loading of axial element and SC components. (<link linkend="sec4.1">Section 4.1</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00018909;class=Gene" role="_blank">slx-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Resolvase activity (in conjunction with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32609;class=Protein" role="_blank">MUS-81</ulink>) (<link linkend="sec5.2.5">Section 5.2.5</link>). Inhibits CO formation in the central gene clusters of autosomes (<link linkend="sec5.3">Section 5.3</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001860;class=Gene" role="_blank">smc-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Chromosome axes</entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004738;class=Gene" role="_blank">scc-3</ulink></emphasis> (above).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004873;class=Gene" role="_blank">smc-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Chromosome axes</entry>
<entry align="center">Common to all cohesin complexes. Hypomorph allele causes reduction in axis-associated cohesin (<link linkend="sec4.1">Section 4.1</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004874;class=Gene" role="_blank">smc-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">SMC4</entry>
<entry align="center">Condensin I and II complexes</entry>
<entry align="center">Associates with chromatin from diplotene (condensin II), and with the short arm of metaphase I bivalents and between sister chomatids during metaphase II (condensin I)</entry>
<entry align="center">Heterozygous null mutants show altered distribution of DSBs and COs, increased CO frequencies, and increased pachytene axis length (<link linkend="sec5.3">Section 5.3</link>). Required for chromosome condensation and segregation (<link linkend="sec6.2">Section 6.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016151;class=Gene" role="_blank">smc-5</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">SMC5</entry>
<entry align="center">Forms complex with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE46466;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMC-6</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Involved in intersister DSB repair and/or interhomolog NCO repair. (<link linkend="sec5.2.4">Section 5.2.4</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00010056;class=Gene" role="_blank">smc-6</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">SMC6</entry>
<entry align="center">Forms complex with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27096;class=Protein" role="_blank">SMC-5</ulink></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00010056;class=Gene" role="_blank">smc-6</ulink></emphasis> (above).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004954;class=Gene" role="_blank">spd-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Mitochondrial</entry>
<entry align="center">Required for normal chromosome movements during meiosis; mutation results in non-homologous synapsis. (<link linkend="sec3.3">Section 3.3</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004985;class=Gene" role="_blank">spo-11</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">SPO11</entry>
<entry align="center">Formation of meiotic DSBs</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Catalyzes formation of meiotic double-strand breaks (<link linkend="sec3.2">Section 3.2</link>, <link linkend="sec5.1">Section 5.1</link>, <link linkend="sec5.4">Section 5.4</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006311;class=Gene" role="_blank">sun-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">SUN-domain family</entry>
<entry align="center">Transmembrane protein, interaction with KASH-domain proteins</entry>
<entry align="center">Nuclear envelope, forms aggregates in transition zone nuclei</entry>
<entry align="center">Binds lamins and KASH domain proteins forming aggregates in transition zone nuclei at sites of chromosome attachment. Required for homolog pairing and recombination (<link linkend="sec3.2">Section 3.2</link>). Shows <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27297;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHK-2</ulink> and <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink> - dependent phosphorylation at N terminus during leptotene-zygotene. Phospho-SUN-1 required for normal rate of SC assembly (slower in absence) and to sustain <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink> recruitment to chromosome ends (<link linkend="sec7.1">Section 7.1</link>, <link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>). Phospho <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> persists into pachytene in absence of DSBs or CO intermediates (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006375;class=Gene" role="_blank">syp-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Synaptonemal complex central region component</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes along chromosomes during prophase I</entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006376;class=Gene" role="_blank">syp-2</ulink></emphasis> (below). Additionally, partial depletion alters CO distribution (<link linkend="sec5.5">Section 5.5</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006376;class=Gene" role="_blank">syp-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Synaptonemal complex central region component</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes along chromosomes during prophase I</entry>
<entry align="center">Structural component of synaptonemal complex required for loading of other SYPs and for CO formation. Stabilizes interhomolog interactions during pachytene; promotes interhomolog DSB repair and normal meiotic progression (<link linkend="sec4.3">Section 4.3</link>, <link linkend="sec7.1">Section 7.1</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006377;class=Gene" role="_blank">syp-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Synaptonemal complex central region component</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes along chromosomes during prophase I</entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006376;class=Gene" role="_blank">syp-2</ulink></emphasis> (above). Also may interact directly with axis components (<link linkend="sec4.3">Section 4.3</link>). Allele <emphasis role="italic">syp-3(<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBVar00088873;class=Variation" role="_blank">me42</ulink>)</emphasis> leads to SC assembly between sisters (<link linkend="sec7.1">Section 7.1</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00019247;class=Gene" role="_blank">syp-4</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Synaptonemal complex central region component</entry>
<entry align="center">Localizes along chromosomes during prophase I</entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006376;class=Gene" role="_blank">syp-2</ulink></emphasis> (above). Interacts with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE41238;class=Protein" role="_blank">SYP-3</ulink>, spans into center of SC (<link linkend="sec4.3">Section 4.3</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006571;class=Gene" role="_blank">tim-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">TIMELESS</entry>
<entry align="center">Cohesin loading</entry>
<entry align="center">Nuclear localization in mitotic compartment of the germ line and in diplotene and diakinesis oocytes</entry>
<entry align="center">Required for loading of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE45697;class=Protein" role="_blank">REC-8</ulink> cohesin complexes. (<link linkend="sec4.1">Section 4.1</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006840;class=Gene" role="_blank">unc-116</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">Kinesin 1</entry>
<entry align="center">Kinesin</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Required for translocation of the oocyte spindle to the cortex of the embryo. (<link linkend="sec8">Section 8</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001514;class=Gene" role="_blank">xnd-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">AT-hook containing protein</entry>
<entry align="center">localizes to autosomes from mitotic region through late pachytene</entry>
<entry align="center">Required for subset of DSBs (mostly on <emphasis role="italic">X</emphasis>) (<link linkend="sec5.1">Section 5.1</link>). Mutants accumulate aberrant histone modifications, and result in impaired DSB formation. Required for <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE09062;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-5</ulink> localization to chromosomes (<link linkend="sec5.3">Section 5.3</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00008140;class=Gene" role="_blank">xpf-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">ERCC4</entry>
<entry align="center">DNA repair; Nucleotide excision repair</entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Resolvase activity (in conjunction with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE31724;class=Protein" role="_blank">HIM-6</ulink>). (<link linkend="sec5.2.5">Section 5.2.5</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006976;class=Gene" role="_blank">zhp-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">RNF212; Zip3 (yeast)</entry>
<entry align="center">RING finger protein; possible SUMO ligase</entry>
<entry align="center">Early pachytene - broadly distributed along SC. End of pachytene, diplotene - one focus per chromosome pair (presumed to mark CO position)</entry>
<entry align="center">Required for CO formation, role in stabilizing CO-fated intermediates (<link linkend="sec5.2.3">Section 5.2.3</link>). Also required for induction of apoptosis irrespective of DNA damage checkpoint activation (<link linkend="sec7.2">Section 7.2</link>).</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00011597;class=Gene" role="_blank">zim-1</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Zinc-finger protein</entry>
<entry align="center">Pairing center of chromosomes <emphasis role="italic">II</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">III</emphasis> in early prophase nuclei</entry>
<entry align="center">Required for homolog alignment and synapsis of <emphasis role="italic">II</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">III.</emphasis> Binds to PC ends only from leptotene to early pachytene. Localization depends on <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE27297;class=Protein" role="_blank">CHK-2</ulink>. Recruitment site for polo-like kinases <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE22877;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-2</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE26649;class=Protein" role="_blank">PLK-1</ulink>. (<link linkend="sec3.2">Section 3.2</link>)</entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00011600;class=Gene" role="_blank">zim-2</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Zinc-finger protein</entry>
<entry align="center">Pairing center of chromosome <emphasis role="italic">V</emphasis> in early prophase nuclei</entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00011597;class=Gene" role="_blank">zim-1</ulink></emphasis> (above) except is required for homolog alignment and synapsis of <emphasis role="italic">V.</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00011601;class=Gene" role="_blank">zim-3</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center"></entry>
<entry align="center">Zinc-finger protein</entry>
<entry align="center">Pairing center of chromosomes <emphasis role="italic">I</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">IV</emphasis> in early prophase nuclei</entry>
<entry align="center">Same as <emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00011597;class=Gene" role="_blank">zim-1</ulink></emphasis> (above) except is required for homolog alignment and synapsis of <emphasis role="italic">I</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">IV.</emphasis></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top" rowsep="1">
<entry align="center"><emphasis role="italic"><ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006997;class=Gene" role="_blank">zyg-12</ulink></emphasis></entry>
<entry align="center">KASH-domain family</entry>
<entry align="center">Interacts with <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink> in nuclear envelope-spanning protein complex</entry>
<entry align="center">Nuclear envelope, forms aggregates in transition zone nuclei</entry>
<entry align="center">Connects nucleus to cytoskeleton (via dynein). Binds <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink>. Required for homolog pairing and recombination (<link linkend="sec3.2">Section 3.2</link>). Recruits Dynein motor complex to cytoplasmic side of <ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE11288;class=Protein" role="_blank">SUN-1</ulink>/<ulink url="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WP:CE32088;class=Protein" role="_blank">ZYG-12</ulink> aggregates in leptotene/zygotene; facilitates proper synapsis (<link linkend="sec3.3">Section 3.3</link>).</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="sec12">
<title>References</title>
<para/>
&meiosis_ref;
</sect1>
</article>